<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main Document Type//EN"
"http://infomotions.com/alex/dtd/tei2.dtd">
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Josephine Donovan's Black Soil in electronic form (part two)</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Originally Prepared by </resp>
					<name>Erin Lee Kellerhals</name>
				</respStmt>
				<principal>Matthew L. Jockers, Stanford University Department of English</principal>
				<sponsor>
					<name>Stanford University</name>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Stanford, California 94305</addrLine>
					</address>
				</sponsor>
				<funder>
					<name>Stanford Humanities Lab</name>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Stanford University, Stanford, California 94305</addrLine>
					</address>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Distributed by The Irish-American West Project of the Stanford Humanities Lab</name>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Stanford, California 94503</addrLine>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<p>This e-text is freely available for non-commercial purposes</p>
				</availability>
				<date>2004</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>Josephine Donovan. Black Soil. Boston, Massachusetts: The Stratford Company, 1930<note type="abstract">Black Soil is Josephine Donovan's story of the arrival of European immigrants in northwestern Iowa, particulary that of an Irish farming family who faces the challenges of settling the area.  The title refers to the farmland of this area. </note>
                                <name type="region">Midwest</name>
                                <name type="country">United States</name>
                                <name type="city">Northwestern Iowa farmer's town</name>
                                <name type="state">Iowa</name>
                                <name type="setting">Rural</name>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>This text was prepared for use in the Irish-American West project of the Stanford Humanities Lab at Stanford University. The two principal goals of this project are (A) to bring the wealth of western Irish-American literary and historical writing to the Internet in a scholarly project and (B) to counter the existing eastern bias in Irish-American scholarship, by providing an online collection of primary source material and scholarly articles devoted to exploring the works of western Irish-Americans.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p>Suspected errors in the text are marked with a "[sic]" but not corrected.</p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p>Hyphens that occur at the ends of lines have been removed, except in cases where it is possible the author intended the hyphen.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<titlePage>
				<docTitle>
					<titlePart type="main">BLACK SOIL</titlePart>
				</docTitle>
				<byline>BY</byline>
				<docAuthor>
				<name type="first">JOSEPHINE</name>
				<name type="last">DONOVAN</name>
				</docAuthor>
				<docImprint>
					<publisher>B Y THE STRATFORD COMPANY Publishers</publisher>
					<pubPlace>PRINTED IN THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA PRINTED BY THE ALPINE PRESS, INC., BOSTON, MASS.</pubPlace>
					<docDate>C O P Y R I G H T  1 9 3 0  </docDate>
				</docImprint>
			</titlePage>
			<div type="other">
				<p>This edition printed for the members of the Catholic Book Club. </p>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXI">
				<p>WILD GOOSE lay somewhere in the grass as Danny, followed by Sheila, "put for home" and told Nell of the meeting.</p>
				<p>"An Indian big as Pop, and I bet yuh there's hundreds more of 'em hiding around here; and I had to do all the talking. Sheila just stood there like a gawk."Nell made the sign of the cross. "Between us and harm," she repeated, "between us and harm." She disregarded Danny and scrutinized Sheila, fearing lest she find any perceptible harm done by that dangerous con­tact.</p>
				<p>The children were warned to stay close by the door. Danny was dispatched for Johann, and when he came he added more gloom to the already terrorized family.</p>
				<p>"Indian can come," he said bitterly. "Indian can come and kill, kill." With a gesture he indicated the en­ tire community. "Die quick better'n die slow."</p><p>"A shame it is for you, John," Nell reproved, her voice quaking a little. "A big, able-bodied fellow like you to be talking like that. If we all gave up what would ever become of the children or of the country or of any thing else? Stay around here now, close, until we get the lay of the land. Other Indians may be hovering around. Tim will be along in a few days." She went to the bed­ room and returned with jeans and a shirt of Tim's. "Here," she said, "is the change I had ready for Tim. Whip off them clothes and I'll wash and patch them <pb n="174 BLACK SOIL "/>up." Johann, she knew, had other clothes which he was saving.</p>
				<p>Obediently Johann repaired to the granary and re ­turned with his bundle of clothes. Nell bowed over the tub and lathered the clothes with a bar of homemade soap. Johann sat nearby with the children.</p>
				<p>"Do you know that you're the only full-grown man around here for miles? You and Lou, Max's man. What with Max bedfast and the rest here and there trying to earn a dollar." Johann made no comment. Nell swung her body in unison with the rubbing. "Hear from Emma lately?" Johann shook his head. "Have you been practising up on the English reading? I have a few books that might ease your mind a bit." He did not hear.</p>
				<p>"Run, Margaret, and bring out <emph>David Copperfield</emph> for John. David had his troubles, too, and he came out all right."When Margaret brought the tattered, fingered book, it was the children and not Johann who were aroused. <emph>"David Copperfield. David Copperfield.</emph> Come on, Sheila, and read about David." They overpowered Margaret for possession of the book.</p>
				<p>"Young ones!" Nell ceased rubbing, raised red, swollen hands from the strong suds and dried them on her apron. She rescued the book, adjusted its loose pages, and handed it to Johann. "It's torn a little, but there's not a word missing. Go off in the shade now, and read a while."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 175"/>Johann roused himself, took the book, and dutifully walked toward the grove. "Oh, John, I like it best when he's a little boy and people are mean to him." Thisfrom Kitty Ann. And Margaret: "Didn't you cry, though, when Dora died?" "He was foolish," Danny added. "I would have married Agnes in the first place."</p><p>"Danny, don't have matrimony bothering you now, but hear Margaret there with her Catechism. The Com­munion class will be going in a month and our lady'll be a fine numbskull. Kitty, keep your eye peeled around. Watch everywhere. Sheila, get your History and be studying." Nell wrung Johann's clothes from the suds. Her muscular arms were taut. As she shook up his garments and hung them on the line, she looked after the retreating Johann. She compared his chivalry and ap­pearance on arriving in the country with his present sullenness and tatters. Hope had gone out from a young boy--hope was gone. "This country is enough to drive the hope and joy out of anybody except someone hard and calloused like myself. And sometimes I feel it had me, too . . ." The same scene confronted her: blue summer sky, barren prairie, shiny hoppers, Indians lurking close like snakes in the grass.</p>
				<p>Tim's homecoming brought its usual cheer. "The Indians are too busy across the line to bother with set­tlers," he said. "This young buck is probably someone just passing through." He told how everyone in the surrounding towns was excited about the fall election. The Dutch had a candidate of their own now for Representative,<pb n="176 BLACK SOIL"/>and the Germans were parading with signs: <emph>Down with the Dutch.</emph> "I am going to stop at home a while longer this time." At this information the children, delighted, mobbed him. They clung to his hands and swung their weight from his long legs. He was pa­tient with them and continued, "I'm going with the oxen to the county seat tomorrow. I'm in hopes of get­ ting a little loan there."</p><p>"I go to town with you," Johann announced, "and get a birth gift for the little one." "Don't bother with that, John, but go along for the trip. It will do you good. Buyyourself something and get as much enjoyment out of the day as you can," was Nell's advice.</p>
				<p>Johann accompanied Tim on his trip next day. It was noon when they reached the town. To all outward appearances the little cluster of drab shanties baking in the sun had little semblance to a capital; yet here, without trees or setting, squatted down on the prairie, was a county seat. A winding, black-rutted road bordered by frame buildings, their boarded battlements proclaiming the dealers' names and wares: Old Nic's Place, a saloon owned by Nic Hill, who lived in the rear; a bank with a modest sign: Loans; a General Store which held all the necessities of life, from copper-toed boots to ginger snaps. Frail and impermanent as this town appeared, its buildings scarcely able to withstand a strong gust of wind, here were experienced daily the most crucial tests of human sympathy, endurance, and avarice.</p>
				<p>People came to this town to try to borrow money at any rate of interest on their land, with which to buy food and shaker flannel. Incidentally, they asked for <pb n="BLACK SOIL 177 "/>their mail; their kinsmen were impatient with their re­peated requests for help, and seldom wrote. In the Gen­eral Store, women looked hungrily at the dried apricots behind glass cases; while over at the loan office their husbands gravely signed away milch cows or sewing ma­chines.</p>
				<p>Johann had trouble in selecting a birth gift for the baby. He thought seriously while he scanned the shelves. Nothing there for a baby of Nell Connor's. He thought of a fine necklace he had, an heirloom of his mother. He would give that to the baby.</p>
				<p>"Treat the whole family," the clerk was saying. "Take along a jug of whiskey. Good for the baby, good for the mother, good for snake bites. Always keep a little in the house." His tone was confidential now. "Have you had breaking fever yet? No? Well, whiskey will cure 'ager.' "Johann bought some whiskey.</p>
				<p>Not quite sure that he had spent his money profitably, he put his jug in the wagon and climbed up to the seat. In his search for a suitable gift he was impressed by the sordidness of the town, and he was anxious to get out of it. Tim soon took his place beside him; and their wagon and a few others struck out their diverse ways, while the loan men sat about like cats who fed on canaries, speculating as to where foreclosures would be easy.</p>
				<p>The county seat sank once more into the lap of the prairie, and the horizon above it took on again a fixity. Tim, after a few swigs at the jug, grew loquacious. His experience with the loan shark became a jocular one. Over and over it was repeated, with increasing mirth.     <pb n="178 BLACK SOIL "/>"Yes sir, yes sir," he reiterated, bringing his hand down heavily on Johann's knee. "Yes sir, when I said that I had a good farm and fine machinery, the hawk nosed loan man handed over that money meeker than a kitten."Johann smiled grimly. He was reminded of the heavily fed bodies of his father's friends, who no doubt would have to be drowned in spirits before they would become affected by them.</p>
				<p>Tim became jubilant. He orated and sang and orated again. Finally his hilarity waned . . .  He grew pensive-- unusual for Tim. Johann was depressed.</p>
				<p>When they arrived at his shanty, Johann asked Tim to stop for a moment. Racing inside he searched out his mother's necklace and brought it with him to the Connors' home.</p>
				<p>"I can't take this treasure for the baby," Nell pro­tested, as she opened thesatin-lined jewel case. "You keep it. It was your mother's. It is too valuable, toogood . . ." "No, no," Johann answered, his eyes growing moist. "Nothing is too good. . . ." "Well, I'll keep it for you, John."Later when he presented the jug of whiskey with the clerk's recommendations, she smiled and said, "We'll have a party and have the neighbors in. It will cheer them up a bit. You must come over, too, John." "I will come," he answered.</p>
				<p>The Connors had the party the next week. On the afternoon preceding the night, Pete Schwartz stopped <pb n="BLACK SOIL 179 "/>at Johann's enroute from town. He had a letter for Jo­hann, and after delivering it he loitered about the place. Pete wished to ascertain, if possible, the size of the jug that was to be drained that evening; and furthermore, if opportunity permitted, he planned to tell Johann to make the next treat a keg of beer.</p>
				<p>Johann read his letter in the shade of the house, and after a careful rereading of the fine script he raised his eyes, hoping to find solace somewhere about him. The sky was blue and guileless, the prairie brown and barren, the sun mercilessly hot. He looked at Pete--perhaps <emph>he </emph>could tell him what to do. The complacent smile on the boy's leathery face he interpreted as leering curiosity. Johann hastened to his shack and barred the door.</p>
				<p>What could he do? What should he answer? Emma was growing tired of waiting, and Emil was pressing his attentions more and more. She complained that all the other girls her age were married and had babies already. He must tell her again how people were starving. He must explain more fully, He must--but how? Hadn't he told her all that already? His head brushed the rope which dangled from the scantling--there was one escape.</p>
				<p>He dashed away from the rope, away from the shanty, out to the buffalo wallow, and took his usual seat. He gave no thought to supper. The sunset was tinging the world with yellow. He watched its changes in detail, as one who views a loved thing for the last time. He recalled his first night on the prairie, its won­der, its beauty, its charm. His flaming hopes and ambitions now reduced to ashes. Everything was false, was wrong, in the world! Herman loved Sheila . . . He loved Emma . . . and now she would never come. It  <pb n="180 BLACK SOIL "/>would never be. Just as well! She didn't belong here. It was over. She could stay where there was plenty to eat. She was an old-country girl. Placidly, the moon anchored itself over Connors' corner tree. The prairie took on its witching shadows--shadows that seemed to listen to his thoughts, cowardly thoughts that he did not want, could not want.</p>
				<p>The new country had deceived him, trapped him. He had burned all his incense to false gods. Even now false gods stalked through the darkness, grasping. Why not end it all? . . . Why not the rafter and the swinging rope? There was no one to grieve. The little community formed an impregnable wall of defense around him.  They also shared his misfortunes--all of them--Nell Connor . . . yes, he had promised Nell Connor that he would attend a party tonight. What use now! What for parties? There was nothing, nothing. Nothing in the old country, nothing in this country. There must be a place for him in some country. Was there perhaps another? Here this would go on forever. He could not endure it any longer. Seeing the sun rise each day on a world of desolation, coursing its way through a guileless sky, unmindful of the greed and hunger in its path. Night, in its mockery, hiding the tortures of the day. "Not right, not right." Hungry people . . . Prairie chickens, tame and inactive, their bodies fat from the slimy bodies of hoppers . . . Coyotes, in their turn, with sleek, shiny coats.</p>
				<p>It was not to any impatience in himself, or to Emma's exigencies, but to the prairie that Johann attributed his loss. It was the <emph>prairie!</emph> When he thought of his delivery from the place, he <pb n="BLACK SOIL 181 "/>experienced a sense of relief. Life here would go on the same. Always there would be the Connors, staying, trusting in God; the Emmas, demanding; yes, the Emils; the loan sharks--thieves; always himself, the fool--no good in Germany--a greenhorn here; always that es­cape. . . . Was it calling? No, that was Danny.</p>
				<p>"Mom said to come right over. We're having the party now." Johann followed Danny, who bounded ahead like a rabbit. "Look out, John," he called back over his shoulder, "don't let them big devil's darning needles light on yuh. They'll sew your ears shut." Mechanically, Johann struck at the glistening dragon flies that darted about him.</p>
				<p>That was lively music coming to him from the lighted house. Tim had the flute, and someone he did not know had the fiddle. Mrs. Connor was moving about briskly, like one who had not forgotten the dancing of her girlhood. Just so, Johann recalled, the officers in the army had celebrated when the enemy was near.</p>
				<p>In an adjoining room, Sheila was hearing the children with their prayers: "There are four corners on my bed. . . ."The fiddler, "a stranger going through the country," changed the tempo of the dance. After a jig he was play­ing a waltz--<emph>Auf Wiedersehen</emph>. Young and old re­sponded by drawing their feet toward their ankles. Max's girls, three of them, and the wife of Max were there. Mary was home with her father. It was an occa­sion for Lou Hoppe, the hired man, to swing the pretty <pb n="182 BLACK SOIL "/>Lena about. Katto and her boys were there, joining in the dance, in laughter and in argument. Some of the Hollanders were there. They did not dance but were content to watch the rest. One tall boy in wooden shoes stood outside and watched Annie, the youngest daughter of Max, through the window as she ranged about in the crowd, putting herself in the way of a partner. When Sheila and Herman collected the younger crowd in the yard for games, the tall Hollander left the window and joined in the play.</p>
				<p>Johann stood hesitatingly for a moment before the door. This would go on, on--he slunk back into the dusk. Turning, he ran as if pursued toward the shanty, to the solace of the dangling rope. <pb n="183"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXII">
				<p>PETE DUNN produced a bottle of vinegar bitters and passed it around; he tuned up the fiddle again and began a polka. There was promise of a very merry evening. Max's Lena and the hired man stole off into the night for a mutual kiss. Grasshopper plagues and their aftermaths? There was a moon . . . and a future.</p>
				<p>"Come, Danny," Nell appeared in the doorway. "Come, run and get John. Tell him I'm having a hard time saving a nip for him, and we need him bye and bye to fill a quadrille."</p><p>"Ah, Mom, I was over there once; and he came over. Let Sheila go now. I've just got out of being 'it' and I want to play." "I'll go meself," Nell said, using Tim's expression. "Come along, Katto, and we'll march John back here." "I go," Katto consented. The sound of music and play followed the women as they went on to their neighbor's quarter section.</p>
				<p>Johann was not sitting on the stone, but one glance in the moonlighted cabin showed his dangling body. The women paused, but only long enough to realize fully what their eyes beheld. There was no hesitation in the face of duty. "Quick, Katto, a knife! Where's his butcher knife? We may save him."They got him down--they never remembered just how--but Nell's knowledge of resuscitation was meagre  <pb n="184 BLACK SOIL "/>and her strength, moreover, was failing her. Katto hur­ried across the field calling loudly for help. The dancers did not hear; those at play did not heed--it was only Katto, shouting and carrying on.</p>
				<p>Quite out of breath, the pudgy figure filled the lighted doorway. "Hey! Greenhorn is dead!" One hand clutched Tim's shoulder, the other fastened itself in Dutch Fred's long whiskers. She would make them heed. "By Gutt, I am not making fun. The greenhorn hung himself up by the neck. Come, dumb fools, and help Nell Connor put the breath in him again."Tim and Dutch Fred disengaged themselves from Katto's frenzied grip and ran toward Johann's. The fiddler had jumped down from his station on the table, and was already at the door. Soon the entire party unseeingly tramped on each other's attenuating shadows, hurrying to the scene. Katto trotted along silently.</p>
				<p>Tim reached the shanty first. "Any hope of bringing him to?" he asked of Nell in the doorway. "He's gone," she answered. Katto broke the quiet of the eerie room by bringing down imprecations upon the girl in Germany. Tearing Emma's picture from its frame, she nailed it on the door, making it serve as head to the enormous grasshopper of Herman's drawing; vowing that such a countenance would scare away the hoppers.</p>
				<p>Pete Dunn, "the stranger passing through the country," was greatly moved by the tragic story of the un­ happy German boy. 'I'll take him to town in my wagon," he said; but Tim protested. "No, we'll take care of him; we'll wake him right here in this house--it's more like home to him."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 185"/>To this all agreed. Then Jake Van den Hull, spokes ­man for a group of Hollanders, said; "We make the coffin."</p><p>"I got candles from my brother in Dubuque," Max's wife spoke up. She had been crying and controlled her voice with difficulty. "I go get them. Johann he will not have a poor man's wake."Many of the guests remained. It seemed to Nell, who went to her home to administer to baby Alice, that people were stirring about the Connor premises and wandering back and forth on the prairie until long after midnight. After Alice was asleep, she took the lamp to the loft room and searched out two heavy silver candle­ sticks, heirlooms in the Powers family, and carried them with her when she went in the early hours of the morning to take up her vigil with Katto, the wife of Max, Tim, Van den Hull, and Dutch Fred, who were staying throughout the night.</p>
				<p>When Nell crossed the field, the rumbling of distant wagons was the only sound in the calm of the night. There were no dark figures stalking now. Nell knew that she was alone; yet she felt a presence.</p>
				<p>"Poor John, may the Lord have mercy upon his soul. Too bad he took his own life. He's had his Purgatory on earth . . . This prairie is worse than Purgatory. May the Lord receive his poor soul!"As she lingered a moment on the step of the cabin for the cool, refreshing breeze to ease the fatigue in her eyes, a star shot across the sky, carrying in its wake a trail of light.</p>
				<p>"A soul just went to Heaven," she announced from   <pb n="186 BLACK SOIL "/>the doorway. "It passed right over the big stone where John used to sit and watch the sky."There was no comment. The wife of Max, who was passing her knotted fingers over the beads of her rosary meekly raised her eyes.</p>
				<p>Later in the morning, when Nell returned to take up the duties in her own house, there were tired lines in her face; and her hair, loosed from its coil, hung down her back. "I declare the house seems strange to me," she said as she bathed her face in cold water and began rattling stove lids. "I've been through so much yesterday, and it isn't over yet. A funeral now. Poor John. I wonder if there's anything I left undone for that boy. Poor lad. May his soul rest in peace."The neighborhood--Germans, Luxemburgers, Hol­landers--turned out; and with the very simplest of rites Johann was laid to rest beside Bennie and the others. Accounts of his death were sent to Emma and his father. Emma did not reply; but his father wrote a scathing letter in which he accused Connor and people like him of coaxing young men into the country and then starving them.</p>
				<p>"The back of me head to that fellow," Tim re­ marked. "He's nothing but a bigheaded and big-bellied tyrant. We shouldn't have written at all, at all."</p><p>"'Twas our duty, Tim, whatever; and if I had it to do over again I would have written to him long ago and implored him to send money and Emma to that poor boy." <pb n="187"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXIII">
				<p> WHENEVER anyone hangs himself in a house, or gets killed there, that house is haunted." So Danny told the younger Connors. "The ghost never leaves the place. It wants revenge."The children, with Herman Schwartz, were sitting before the Connors' door one evening. Tim had gone away again. They were lonely, and appreciated Her­ man's company.</p>
				<p>Herman and Danny had been speaking of many things. They had spoken of their future; Herman was going to be an artist, and Danny had said; "Some day I'm going to leave the prairie, too." The conversation had shifted to Johann--the Connors had been told to forget his death, to cease speaking of it--but Herman had begun it, so the tragedy was quite thoroughly re ­viewed again. This led up to Danny's telling about the ghost of Johann.</p>
				<p>Robert Emmet cuddled up close to Margaret as Danny argued; "And I can prove it, too. His ghost is there. I'll call it and it will answer."Sheila glanced sideways at Danny. His look challenged her--she said nothing. Herman looked at Sheila and smiled his wise smile. Danny stepped out from the group and ceremoniously traced a circle around himself on the ground. He wildly ran his fingers through his brown hair. Danny's hair was always tousled and usually very long. Only at rare intervals was it trimmed. <pb n="188 BLACK SOIL "/>It stood on end now--there was nothing unusual about that!</p>
				<p>His audience was waiting, eager to become excited. Danny squinted his eyes, drew his body up erect as he imagined conjurers did, gave a shift to his jeans, adjusted his homemade suspenders, whirled about three times, and cupped his hands around his mouth.</p>
				<p>An anatomist watching him in this ceremony would have been conscious of joints--hinge joints, elbow joints. <emph>"Johann,"</emph> he called out. <emph>"Johann,"</emph> came a hollow reply from the empty prairie. "Are you green where you are now, Johann?" "Are now Johann?" "Good thing if you are." "You are . . ." "See." Danny swung around. "Didn't I tell yuh?" Danny's jaw seemed loose jointed as he grinned. His dark blue eyes flashed; they appeared black.</p>
				<p>Robert Emmet was completely under the spell, but Kitty Ann spoke out boldly: "He didn't answer yuh, Danny. He just mocked yuh." "Well, maybe he's in a place where they only allow him to mock. You must remember he hung himself."</p><p>"Oh, I know something that will scare better as that," Herman boasted. "I saw that Injun that's been around here. I saw him today." The Indian around here yet? The children sat erect as he related as casually as was possible for fidgety Her­ man: "I was hiding in grass never thinking of nothing. I <pb n="BLACK SOIL 189 "/>was holding snare over gopher hole. That Injun just got up from grass near me. I never knew he was there. He had gopher in his snare. I follow him. I stay down in grass, but he walk along just like anyone. Pete he see him lots o' times. I want to see what he does. And he goes to crick, start a fire there, roast that gopher and eat it."</p><p>"Oh," the children said in chorus. "Eat a gopher?" It was Danny's turn to be incredulous. "Eat it," Herman repeated, drawing his legs up under him importantly. As the children saw Nell coming from the cowyard, they cried out: "The Indian is around here yet, and Her ­man saw him eat a gopher."Nell placed her pail of foamy milk up in the wagon box. "Where is he, Herman?" she asked in alarm as she joined the group.</p>
				<p>Encouraged, Herman was unusually voluble. "First I see him not so far from Johann's, then I see him by the crick. Pete he say he cut off his hair and hit himself with it until there was no more hair. We see him lots of times."Nell moved close to Herman. "Why didn't you tell us he was around here? We never see him." "We think you know it. We see him lots of times." "Where was Pete when he saw him lash himself with his hair? Did he say anything to Pete?"</p><p>"Pete he was hunting some meat. Pete was hungry for meat, and our meat was all. We have nothing for the gun, so Pete dig a hole and hide in there. You know, prairie chickens always come to look what for black pile   <pb n="190 BLACK SOIL "/>of dirt is doing there, and Pete he grabs them by the legs. You know how, Danny--you do it, too."</p><p>"Yes, we know how to catch chickens, but was it while Pete was in the 'hide' that he saw the Indian? Was it far from here?"</p><p>"Oh, not so far. Over by the crick. Pete he was in the hole and he saw Injun come to the crick and make as though he was going to take a drink. After he look into the water once he don't drink no water, he takes out a knife, cuts off his braids of hair and whips, just whips his self. Pete say maybe he's mad over himself that he is Injun."</p><p>"I hope he keeps his distance," was Nell's comment. "Maybe he'll steal my candlesticks from John's shanty. They're there since the wake. I wouldn't want to lose them. Most of my people were laid out with those can­dlesticks at their head. Run over and get them, some of you."</p><p>"I go," Herman volunteered; "I and Sheila." "All right," Nell said, rising, "and Danny, come before it's too dark and help me finish up the chores. That Indian's mind may not be right. We'll have to re ­port his hanging around. Lashing himself with his hair! I never heard of the like, East or West." Then, seeing alarm in the children's faces, she added: "Oh, he is prob­ably harmless. Be going in now and getting ready for bed."Sheila was taller than Herman. As she walked beside him, her two heavy braids of hair tapped against her shoulders, and her smooth ankles slipped through the <pb n="BLACK SOIL 191 "/>grass. Her dark eyes were fixed beyond Herman, al­ though she listened to his prattle.</p>
				<p>"And we got such a book at home with white pages in it, and I make your picture there, Sheila, but it does not look like you." Herman had a roundness of body: his head was round, his face, his eyes. Only when he smiled and squinted could one notice any acuteness of feature or of perception. Herman was no neater than other boys of his community, but his grime was uniform and added somewhat to his general roundness of physiognomy. Tim often said: "Herman's layers are even."The two children did not linger in Johann's shanty. Each grabbed a candlestick and hastened toward the door, but there they stood too terrified to move. A figure, a man, coming suddenly out of the twilight, was before them.</p>
				<p>"I take now," he said, calmly grasping Sheila in his arms. "The Injun!" Herman cried out. "She not your squaw. She Sun-in-the-Hair."Sheila struggled in his arms. She could not see his face, but his voice was that of the Indian on the prairie. Recalling Mom's warnings and horrors: "Herman, help me!" She used her fists, to no avail.</p>
				<p>The Indian seemed to be enjoying the situation as he had on the former meeting. "In a trap, but not wounded," he said as he attempted to carry her away bodily.</p>
				<p>For just an instant Herman was incapable of action. The recalling of Johann's death in the shanty, and now this struggle before him, were too tense for his slow per­ception.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="192 BLACK SOIL"/>"Herman!"Sheila's appeal aroused him to action. Sheila was being carried away by the Injun! Herman raised the can­dlestick with both hands and from his point of vantage on the cabin steps brought the piece of silver down heavily on the assailant's head. The Indian swayed and fell. Sheila was free.</p>
				<p>For an instant the children stood, too excited to move. Herman wished to drag Sheila away, but instead she bowed over the recumbent figure. "Oh, it's the sameone." "Same one?" "Yes, and his hair is cut. Now he's dead." "Yes, and now they make me dead, too," Herman said in tears. "I run, I run away. I run away now. In­juns might get me. Soldiers might get me. I run away."Both children ran, first toward Connors'; then Her­ man stopped suddenly, swung around, and dragged Sheila a few rods toward his own home. Each still carried a candlestick, and Herman held fast to Sheila's wrist. Sheila pulled her hand away. "Come on--tell Mom," she commanded. "I don't want to go to your house."</p><p>"I don't, neither," Herman answered, still clinging to Sheila. Herman was trembling. "Leave go my hand," Sheila said, "or I'll hit you with the candlestick. I'm going home. What if he ain't dead? He'll get after us."Herman loosened his. viselike grip on Sheila's wrist. "I go away, Sheila. I go now. I all time want for to be artist. I go now for to be artist. I go first to my uncle in Dakota. Injuns will not find me. When they get tired of <pb n="BLACK SOIL 193 "/>looking for me, I will be, oh, fine artist, and I will grow, oh, such big whiskers and come back and we'll get married." "Oh, Herman . . ." Herman had started west. "Goodbye, Sheila. I go for to be artist," came to her from the darkness.</p>
				<p>It was Danny who brought the news of the attempted abduction to Nell. He had met Sheila on the edge of the grove.</p>
				<p>"Glory be to God," Nell said, holding Sheila se­curely in her arms. "Tell me one thing: are you all right?"Danny was already on Ned's back to summon Katto and son, Pete. They appeared in a short time, also on horseback, Pete with the butcher knife and Katto dangling a pitchfork. Nell, with the clothesline in her hand, joined them. All cautiously made their way to­ wards the ill-fated shanty.</p>
				<p>In case of encounter, Katto was ready, weapon in hand. It was not called into action. The Indian lay as he had fallen.</p>
				<p>"We'd better bind him, hand and foot, in the name of God," Nell advised, "in case he comes to. There's a pulse, Katto. Herman need not have run away."Nell knotted the rope firmly. "Oh, don't think on Herman now," Katto said lightly. "He'll come back once when he gets hunger. Let him hide. We got enough dead ones around here these days. This one is dead, I think."But the Indian was not dead. As Nell leaned over him, he stirred and moaned. "Thank God, he's not  <pb n="194 BLACK SOIL "/>dead," she said. "I wouldn't want Herman to be a murderer protecting Sheila."Danny spoke up. "It's the same Indian, Mom. Got his hair cut, and wearing a sash."The Indian, quite unconscious, and bleeding from a scalp wound, was placed in Johann's bed. Nell applied cold compresses to his head. Why, if he should die . . ! Pete, who had been summoned to Max's for Lou, re­ turned with only the wife of Max.</p>
				<p>"I come," Max's wife said with emotion. "Max he will not leave Lou come; he does not want it that any ­thing shall happen Lou--Lou must work the place. He says he don't care if I come, so I come right away with Pete. You got much trouble, Mrs. Connor, here; I stay now, and Katto will stay. You got such a little baby yet. . . ."</p><p>"The baby'll be all right; they can come for me when she cries. I'll stay by this villain. Why, if he should die . . . !" She whispered: "Think of the revenge." She changed the compresses, cringing a little at the con ­tact with coarse hair. <emph>Indian</emph>.</p>
				<p>Pete was dismissed with the order to ride over for Dutch Fred. Danny was sent home; the wife of Max, accompanying him, said: "I can do nothing here now, so I will see how that little baby is once. You got Katto with you; I will watch out for that baby."It was a long night for Nell Connor. Katto snored in her chair. The pitchfork fell from her hand. Nell felt quite alone, cut off from life, in a world where she had never been before. It was strange. . . . Before her was an unconscious Indian, bound hand and foot. ... It <pb n="BLACK SOIL 195"/>was ridiculous somehow. . . . She guarding the In­dian, Katto guarding her. It was a nightmare, surely, so strange, so impossible. Yet, here was Johann's little house ... his intimate possessions--his pipe on the ledge of a two-by-four, his thoughts ... his despair. And, too, the little shelf that Bennie Hurd had so crudely constructed. . . . The Hurds--Bennie; all were with her here . . . but she was alone. Tim, the man whom she had married in a period so remote that it was a dream world, a memory--was peddling ware to secure food. . . . Hardware that was made back there in Northampton ... the cutlery with, the wicked eyes that had caught the sunlight each morning as she went to school with other little girls in clean aprons and freshly-made curls . . . they had squinted back at the cutlery's eyes, but it seemed superior standing there so tall when they were so very tiny. ... At times when she drove to school with her father in the carriage when he was going to make a call on old Mrs. Leeney who was bedfast, she had got even with the cutlery: she could roll past it, and it was forced to stand still forever . . . now it was packing hardware and sending it here for Tim to sell. ... Had there ever really been a North­ampton, a cutlery, an opera house? . . . Jenny Lind coming to sing ... the town turning out to hear her.  . . . Nell walking up the steps, one hand in her father's big hand, one hand clasping her mother's. . . . Did those things ever happen really? . . Her mother . . . Did her mother know that her daughter had come to the West? ... did she know what the West was? . . . Did the dead know? . . . Nell hoped that they did not know all. . . . Did her mother know of that   <pb n="196 BLACK SOIL "/>houseful of small children? . . . She hoped so. . . Nell's children . . . little souls, little minds, little hearts, little bodies for whose wellbeing she was responsible ... they were being tended now by a strange, kind woman whose life was valued not at all . . . a strange world. . . . Night sounds. . . . Why did young wolves yelp so sharply? ... If their cries were not so penetrating . . . and owls, would they never cease! . . . "Who-ho-ho-hoo. . . " Owls and Schwartzes' hounds. . . .Which were the owl sounds? . . . Were the baying hounds attacking young wolves? . . . Did owls never grow weary? . . . Grasshoppers hurling their bodies against the small window pane like spirits tossing handfuls of putty. . . . Katto's discord ­ant snoring--the raucous gyrating of train wheels moving westward, intermingled with the purr of the old millrace near the box factory. ... Nell felt a kinship with the Indian, bound, insensible to real life. . . . Living . . . dreaming in a world that could not possibly be reality. . . . The young wolves were not yelping now; the owls, too, were still. Where had Herman gone? . . . Dutch Fred would be coming soon, . . . Nell was bound to the strange prairie; she was part of it, influencing other lives, becoming affected by others. This was the West. The East, Bay State, was irrevocable, never to be lived again save for snatches in the Limbo between sleeping and waking; or when Reality, en­ grossed in the business of devising afflictions, would al­ low memory to slip in unnoticed and sprinkle a mitigating hyssop. Reality--jailer, faithful to his post --was back again.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 197"/>  Johann's lamp wick was poorly trimmed; it sputtered as it disclosed an injured Indian. He had tried to carry Sheila away! Why did she change those applications so painstakingly? Her spirit rebelled, but her hands worked automatically, wringing out the cloths and placing them on forehead and head. Sheila was unharmed! Sheila was safe! God was good.</p>
				<p>At dawn she brought fresh water, washed the blood from the Indian's face, and resumed her vigil. She thought she saw a sign of consciousness--or was it merely a flicker of the daylight that was dancing on counterpane, on his face, everywhere? His eyelids raised, and she caught the bewildered eye of a young man upon her. She stood over him. He tried to raise a hand--Nell untied his hands. He raised one feebly, indicating a drink. She gave him water and continued looking down at him.</p>
				<p>He was handsome, yes, but his beauty was not of the chiseled Indian type; it was rather one of imperfections. His upper lip was too full and his nose was broad, but the skin was smooth and tan. His race was forgotten. He was injured, a foolish boy, perhaps, but injured. There was a childish curl to his upper lip, and his chin was pointed like Danny's. Nell untied his feet. "He wouldn't harm us," she decided, "his eyes are too meek." And she roused Katto to see the improvement in the patient. <pb n="198"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXIV">
				<p>DUTCH FRED nursed the Indian for a few days, leaving him only to tend his stock. The neigh­borhood decided that the lad should be arrested and taken away; but to this Dutch Fred would not agree.</p>
				<p>"You talk with him once," he told Nell, who was most concerned about his speedy removal. Dutch Fred was serious; he nodded his head. "You find out. I am sorry for such a boy. He got funny things in his head."</p><p>"He's not right," Nell replied. "All the more reason he should be looked after. He may kill us all. An Indian is bad enough in his right senses--"</p><p>"Oh, no, not that way. I don't mean crazy," Dutch Fred interrupted. "I don't know how you say it, but he got such funny thoughts in his head. I cannot the Injun thoughts very well. Now I! can the English thoughts right away when you and Tim come; they are like the German thoughts; but the Injun thoughts I cannot very well." The settler stroked his long beard and lowered his eyelids. "His grandmother is white woman. And he don't want to fight white mans."</p><p>"What about grabbing Sheila to carry her off? What has he to say to that?"</p><p>"He won't do that no more. He all time is sorry now. He say that was the Injun in him. He will be white man now."</p><p>"You never can tell what he'll be. Some of them are <pb n="BLACK SOIL 199 "/>pretty  crafty."  But Nell could not convince Dutch Fred of the Indian's treachery.</p>
				<p>"I like that boy," he went on. "No need for scare. I all time do right by you. I don't want you to have trouble. Here is some salve. He will come here and you must put it on his head, so that bad stuff don't go to the brain. This salve is good salve. I put it on horses' shoulders."Nell knew that Dutch Fred was sincere, but she feared the Indian. She hoped that he would disappear.</p>
				<p>One morning he stood before her door, smiling. "Food? You want food?" Nell asked.</p>
				<p>"No. No food. Wild Goose knows here is Kind Woman and Sun-in-the-Hair. You--Kind Woman," he said, and turned away.</p>
				<p>His scalp wound required dressing, so Nell called to him and applied the salve.</p>
				<p>Few words were exchanged, as Nell used every art of which she had ever heard, so that he would get well and be off out of sight. She had no personal fear of him now, still his presence made her uneasy, since he so boldly admired Sheila.</p>
				<p>Sheila herself retained her usual passivity during this ordeal, never speaking her thoughts, hardly giving the impression that she had an opinion on the matter. She smiled, she frowned, she listened, she obeyed. She did not show less interest in her books, but she appeared less keen. She planned her salary with Nell, she agreed that some money should be saved for herself and that the rest should be borrowed and used by the Connors-- they would pay interest.</p>
				<p>Nell bided her time, waiting for the Indian to disappear.   <pb n="200 BLACK SOIL "/>He was like the snow in winter, the grasshoppers, and other plagues; he would disappear in time. She thanked God that one of her dreams was about to be realized--Sheila would be a teacher! This thought made her jubilant, and forgetting immediate cares she added addition after addition to her air castle. Sheila would be teaching this winter; and surely next year there would be a crop.</p>
				<p>"We'll have a top buggy some day," she would say, "and a team of grays, and we'll drive all over the country and visit the towns that Pop is visiting now. People will say: 'There go the Connors "</p><p>"And I'll be driving," Danny added. "And we'll all be going to meet Sheila, who will be coming back from school in the East."</p><p>"Grasshoppers won't put the sun out all the days," Robert Emmet added, knowing that the realization of their wonderful chariot depended on just that.</p>
				<p>"They'll leave us, please God, before another har­vest." And as Nell, pulse throbbing, dreaded to think of what they would do if the hoppers did not leave, she started their conversation in another channel with: "Wonder what Pop'll have for us the next time he comes."Wild Goose often slipped into the group as they sat out in the evening.  They did not fear him any more. He sat apart from the white family, his knees drawn up under his chin, his hands clasped about his legs. Dutch Fred had shaved his head in the region of the scar, and had trimmed his hair in much the fashion of a settler.</p>
				<p>One night Kitty Ann stole boldly over near the silent  <pb n="BLACK SOIL 201 "/>spectator.  "You wouldn't steal white childrer, would you? You wouldn't scalp me and make my curls all bloody, would you?"</p><p>"No," he answered, "Wild Goose harms no one. Wild Goose is no wolf." He moved near the group, not rising but propelling his body along the ground with his feet.</p>
				<p>He spoke at length, and as he related his story in his deep, musical voice, he looked beyond his listeners, his eyes fixed on the distance as if he saw there in panorama that which he was relating.</p>
				<p>His grandmother had been a white woman. She was loved by a chief and lived in happiness with his people. When old, she became ill. His grandfather carried her back to her people to see "good medicine man." She recovered and asked to be taken back to the Indians, but her people said never would they let her go back. In the spring she began to fail again and spoke often of her husband and children--Wild Goose, especially, was beloved by her. . , . One morning when the trees were shooting forth green leaves and spring scents filled the air, she could remain no longer; she disappeared, trav­eling east instead of west, to elude her people. She picked up with movers headed west who were afraid of Indians. She promised them a safe trip, and they carried her as far as Big Muddy. "One night, I remember, I was raised from my bed. Someone kissed me, with tears on her face. It was my grandmother."</p><p>"Did she live long after coming back?" Nell asked while all the children were leaning forward to hear more.</p>
				<p>"No, she didn't live long after that, but she was   <pb n="202 BLACK SOIL "/>happy to die in the sight of the hills, and with her children. She asked that her body be interred, and it was as she wished. Old chief soon followed."</p><p>"And your mother?" "My mother I do not know. She died when I was like the papoose," pointing to Alice. "My mother was In­dian. I was cared for by my grandmother. I went away to Mission School. I did not care for school. When I returned to my own people, I was not happy. I could not be a brave, for I would not war against the pale ­faces. I went from home. I walk away from the reservation. I cross the river. I come here. I am--" he said, turning his face to Nell, the white spot shaven on his head uncanny in the darkness of his hair, "I am--Wild Goose does not know what he is. With Indian he is not Indian. With White he is not White. I belong nowhere." He smiled, reconciled, boyishly shrugging his shoulders. "I am Wild Goose."Followed a silence, a harsh silence. There was some­ thing about the Indian boy as he related his life that was poignantly sad. His tale, coupled with the musical quality of his voice, surrounded him with a charm that was felt even by the smaller children.</p>
				<p>Nell's words and tone were flat. "I'm glad you're a Christian. You pray, don't you? I suppose you know your prayers?"</p><p>"I pray, and the Great Spirit is pleased with my prayers. My prayer is of the white people. It leads me to the white people." Looking happily at Sheila, he con­tinued: "Her eye does not tell me, but in my heart and with my eye I know that a paleface will be my squaw."</p><p>"The Lord save us!" Nell said under her breath,   <pb n="BLACK SOIL 203"/>her old fear returning; but he was speaking now of something else, in response to the children's repeated: "You won't carry white childer away."</p><p>"No, the Great Spirit is not pleased with such, and punishes. Wild Goose will not carry away a paleface. But he will pray to the Great White Spirit, and will learn how to take a paleface in the white man's way."Danny, not quite so overcome with mixed emotion as the others were, spoke out rudely: "If you want a white girl, why don't yuh go over to Steindlers and ask one of them girls? They're crazy to get married to anyone. They can't find a soul for Mary. Maybe one of them will marry you."Wild Goose did not respond. Instead, he looked at Danny with the same smile that was so humiliating at their first meeting on the prairie.</p>
				<p>Danny stood up and turned defensively toward Sheila. "Sheila is going to be a teacher and go away off back East to school. Maybe she'll never get married, and surely not--"</p><p>"Danny," Nell broke in, alarmed. "Be careful what you say. Go on in out of here and hear Margaret with her Catechism."Danny arose and said half under his breath but distinct enough so that all heard: "That's humbug about his being at Mission School. And I wonder if all that other--" Nell was grateful to hear the slam of the door. She turned toward Wild Goose with a gracious smile.</p>
				<p>"I guess we'll be going in now," in a tone of dis­missal. She shook up drowsy children.   <pb n="204 BLACK SOIL"/>"No, no," they chorused, "we want to hear Wild Goose."</p><p>"Some other time. Go in now and I'll go down to see if that stray hatcher and her chicks got settled for the night. The coyotes are getting terribly bold."</p><p>"Sheila! Sheila, put Ellen to bed and then be combing the snarls from your hair." Wild Goose disappeared without ceremony. Sheila jumped, aroused from reverie.</p>
				<p>Nell protected the hen and chicks against possible prowlers, then stood watching into the night. 'Twas a strange world! Poor Tim perhaps on his way home. Poor Herman, just a little child off there in the world trying to be an artist. Poor Johann! She would always treasure that necklace he gave Alice. May the Lord rest his soul! Poor Danny, worried because Wild Goose saw beauty in Sheila. She must warn Danny not to provoke him to wrath. "Lord knows what he'd do. Poor fellow seems torn in two between the two races."She stumbled over a prostrate body and would have fallen headlong were the recumbent figure not so nimble. He recovered his feet and averted her fall. It was Wild Goose.</p>
				<p>"See," he pointed, much pleased. "See! The moon cannot take the sun from her hair."Nell's feeling was at first one of repulsion. How dare an Indian!--how dare anyone! lie in the grass and watch Sheila brush her hair? With the light of the lamp upon it, her hair was truly golden; and this Indian, as well as anyone else who had eyes, could not help but admire. She must bide her time and be patient with this annoyance.</p>
				<p>As she walked toward the house, a terrible foreboding <pb n="BLACK SOIL 205 "/>seized her. What if he attempted to carry Sheila off? Was there ever going to be an end to miseries? She'd have Sheila sleep with her, and if anyone dared to alarm her--"between us and harm"--she'd kill him.</p>
				<p>At the door she heard Danny's voice, impatient. "Now I'll ask yuh the ones you missed last night. Is God good to us?' "Margaret answered tearfully: " 'God is good to us; He gives us many blessings because He loves us. "</p><p>"Is God merciful?'" "'God <emph>is</emph> merciful . . .' I know He <emph>is</emph>, but I don't know why."</p><p>"God is merciful, children. That's enough for to ­night. Now, we must always remember He's merciful, even when we can't tell why."<pb n="206 "/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXV">
				<p>THE next day Katto came to the Connors' carrying herself with an attempt at dignity. Her prodigiously plump figure was crammed into a tight basque and skirt; her chin proper was raised somewhat from her accessory chin; and her head slightly elevated caused the pug nose to become decidedly more pug. She produced a grimy letter and handed it to Nell with a hand none too clean, flopping herself into the proffered chair.</p>
				<p>"From Herman," she said. As Nell read the fine Spencerian script with its lavish scrolls and shadings, Katto opened the most constrain­ing buttons of her basque, removed her calico sunbonnet, and raised her voluminous skirt from her bare feet. With the return of comfort her loftiness dwindled.</p>
				<p>"Read it once for me," she said. "Pete he say that Herman's going to see ocean."</p><p>"Yes, he's a bullwhacker and on his way to the Pacific. Think of it! I can't imagine shy little Herman in a job like that." Nell turned the page and read it again aloud: " 'I walk by the bulls and prod them with a stick. Me and many other boys with a long row of wagons. We will go till we get to the ocean . . .' "</p><p>"He gives no address," Nell said, disappointed. "I'd like to write or have Sheila write and tell him how Wild Goose has recovered. Perhaps he worries about it."</p><p>"Ach, he don't think on that no more. He wants for to be artist. Always, always, he want for to be artist. <pb n="BLACK SOIL 207 "/>Now he will go to ocean. Now he will be artist Katto spoke with disdain for any contrary opinion.</p>
				<p>"I'm afraid he's gone to the wrong ocean. He should have gone east. There's no one to teach him out there."</p><p>"Always teacher, teacher with you. He don't need teacher. If Herman got the drawings in his head they can get into his fingers without all time teacher, teach."</p><p>"Well, I hope so, Katto. Herman has talent," Nell concluded, as she folded the letter and returned it. "Schwartz will be glad to hear from him."As Katto stuffed the letter into her bosom, she leaned back in her chair. "Yes, Schwartz. I will be glad, too, when Schwartz and my Nick comes back. By Gutt, Nell, it's hard work there with just the boys and me. We cut some slough grass last week for fire."</p><p>"I'm doing a little baking now, on cattle chips the children gathered. We get so tired of twisting hay. When Tim comes again/though, we must put up a little hay."</p><p>"Pete he says that Injun's around here yet. He needs another crack once before he'll go. I tell him so, too, if I was you. He don't come near my house." Katto was grabbing at the grasshoppers which alighted on her, and when she succeeded in catching one she pulled off its legs and head and cast it down. "That one won't live no more-- But if you're afraid to tell that Injun I'll tell him once."</p><p>"No, no, Katto. Don't say anything. I've been handling him with gloves on. We're here alone with the children and we'll let well enough alone, in the name of God. He'll soon be clearing out."They discussed relative merits of ducks and turkeys,   <pb n="208 BLACK SOIL "/>and the conversation shifted to bits of gossip. Nell evidently had not been hearing the news, and Katto grew voluble as she narrated.</p>
				<p>"Jake Van den Hull's wife has gone back to Bella again. She should stay in Bella. She's one from high tone Dutch."</p><p>"And who's with the children?" "His mother she come. And did you know then that there's trouble at Max's again? The hired man he quit and he wants that he and Lena shall go away. Max he say, 'Lou, if you quit me, you shall not have Lena.' Lou he say, 1 quit you and I shall have Lena.' So it goes. . . . His Katie tell my Pete."Nell leaned forward. "Bully for Lou to have some gumption. Max's wife should see to it that they are married now, and then let them off."</p><p>"Oh, Max's wife she is for Lena, but you know,  Mrs. Connor, that she can do nothing. Her man is so crazy with his meanness and that there sickness in his leg he says he will follow them if they go far as the Mississipp' and then he will throw her in. By Gutt, I guess if he had two good legs once no one could live near him."</p><p>"Max is not as bad as he appears. He just likes to bully people."</p><p>"Oh, no, Mrs. Connor, people that know him once in Dubuque they shake their heads over him. Did you know that Bill Breidbarth's wife got the consumting? They read it in the almanac; it say there just the same as she got it. They got no money for to send away for the cure, so I guess maybe she won't live much longer. I guess there'll be enough of Low Germans anyhow left <pb n="BLACK SOIL 209"/>if she does die." Katto smiled wickedly, expecting a reprimand, and she got it.</p>
				<p>"Shame on you, Katto, you with your good health. There's seven children there, and a drinking man."</p><p>"I aint [sic] so soft like as you are, Mrs. Connor, and I think it is best that way. Of course we got to have some foolish ones." She reached for the discarded bonnet.</p>
				<p>"Don't go yet. What's your hurry? I just die for someone to talk to," Nell said.</p>
				<p>"I must go. With those boys maybe I ain't got no house when I get home; and I heard some hens caxing in the trees as I come down. I must get their eggs before it is dark."Nell stood up and the two women faced each other. "Well," Nell said, "things are pretty bad, Katto, but I suppose they could be worse."Katto viciously decapitated an unfortunate hopper and dashed it on the ground. "By Gutt, we ain't dead with the hunger yet."She perched her bonnet on her head, leaving the strings untied, and waddled off, having lost every trace of her attempted superciliousness. Once out on the prai­rie, her gait resumed what Tim called "a sling trot," and she disappeared near her own grove, there to take care of the place and the boys, to prepare meals from scanty rations, to do the chores, and to search out the hens that were "caxing" in the grove.</p>
				<p>At the supper table, Nell told the children some of the news of the neighborhood and added: "We should thank God that He leaves us our health and our senses." As they recited the prayer after meals in chorus: "We give Thee thanks, O Almighty God, for these and all <pb n="210 BLACK SOIL "/>Thy blessings . . ." Max's girl, Lena, stood in the doorway.</p>
				<p>"Hide me! Hide me!" she begged, her breath short from her recent haste. A shaft of sunset light falling across her threw an attenuated silhouette into the room.</p>
				<p>Nell looked in amazement at the girl. Never before had she seen such terror in one so young. Lena's thin face was ashen white, and her eyes dark as coals. . . .  The  face receded,  and Nell was conscious only of black eyes, pleading, terror-stricken.</p>
				<p>"He said he'd kill me and he <emph>will</emph>!"  This aroused Nell.  The imminent danger became apparent as she saw Max's sulky speeding across the prairie. She recalled Katto's recent information.</p>
				<p>"Go up in the loft--come on," she said, leading the way. "He can't climb." "Mary is with him, and she'll climb. Don't put me in a trap."Nell looked about the house. There was the oven, but the stove was warm. The trundle bed, sagging so that an occupant could not make a perceptible bulge, suggested itself as a hiding place. Nell doubled back the covers. "Here, come on, hop in here and I'll put the baby in with you."Lena curled up her slim body and the bed sank. When Nell bent to remove the sleeping Alice, the child's helplessness reproached her. She couldn't take that inno­cent child and place her in danger. She must choose someone who had, at least, the use of his feet. "Kitty Ann, would you go to bed and play you're sick to help Lena?"<pb n="BLACK SOIL 211"/>The child answered in tears: "No, I don't want to be sick. I'm well."Bewildered, Nell looked about for a solution. Was there no one who could understand? Must she always be alone?</p>
				<p>"Let me, Mom," volunteered Danny eagerly, "and if that old Max comes near me I'll pull the red whiskers off'n him. And if he tries to drag me out, I'll jump up and step on his sore leg."Nell, convinced that she had a dependable ally, tucked Danny into the small bed. It was not until years after ­ward, however, that she could smile at that ludicrous picture: Danny a sick boy, with such roguery in his eyes that he must keep them closed; a face tanned and torn, eager for excitement; a body relaxed and comfortable after having done full justice to a supper of mush and milk.</p>
				<p>The unusualness of this excitement caused the younger Connors to cry, adding more tumult; but Mar­garet and Kitty Ann smiled in anticipation of some ­thing--they knew not what.</p>
				<p>"Clear out of the house, every one of you," Nell commanded.</p>
				<p>Sheila hung back. Nell recalled Sheila's previous lack of tact when questioned by the Indian on the prairie.</p>
				<p>"Take them toward Schwartzes'," she said. "Run now, and if questioned remember not a word. Out with you." Robert Emmet, quit your pipering. Margaret, Sheila, take Ellen by the hand. If Max comes near you, remember, run--run and say boo to no one."The sulky was close to the grove now. Nell at <pb n="212 BLACK SOIL "/>tempted no further advice to her accomplices, but made useless trips from table to stove, lifting dishes and pans and setting them down again.</p>
				<p>She prayed: "Oh, Holy Ghost, enlighten me." Max, a wild lion, growling oaths and threats, was there before her at the door. He was attempting to climb down. Nell hastened to aid Mary in the herculean task of sustaining him. Max shook Nell off, threw one leg over the back of the sulky, and sat hesitant, dreading to move the diseased member.</p>
				<p>"What ails you, Max, coming out this way on your leg?" Nell asked.</p>
				<p>His only answer was a grimace, the result of a spasm of pain.</p>
				<p>"What's amiss?" Nell asked Mary casually. "We will tell you once when we find Lena," Max answered uncivilly. To Mary: "Go once and find Lena. Go first to barn and granary."Mary went toward the barn. "Is Lena gone?" Nell asked as if surprised. "Well, well. Trouble never comes single. I've got a boy here that isn't himself, either. Wish Tim would be along."Nell prattled unconvincingly. She felt a pity for Max. His big frame trembled with pain. His day was done. He who had ruled by brute force alone was now forced to surrender. He could threaten to shoot, but if he did he would be taken away to die in jail, and he knew it.</p>
				<p>"I'll be going in to Danny," Nell explained, as she went into the house.</p>
				<p>"It's Mary you'll have to contend with now," she whispered.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 213"/>Lena heard in despair--Mary was her father's de­pendence. Mary not only feared her father but she was jealous and bitter toward Lena.</p>
				<p>Danny assured her: "I'll fix Mary." "Why Danny, what's happened to you?" Danny evidently had climbed out of bed, procured the cornstarch which she had secreted for a chafing baby, and applied it liberally to his face.</p>
				<p>As Mary entered the house Nell stroked the sick boy, thereby rearranging the extravagant makeup.</p>
				<p>Mary's stocky figure climbed the ladder and descended. She was sullen.</p>
				<p>"Come here, Mary. Don't let him see you." Nell indicated the pale Danny. "It might be catching. It's queer he's acting. Out of his head like."Mary drew quite near. Danny looked up at her, then grabbed a corner of the quilt and began chewing it ravenously. "Gr-r-r, wang, wang, wang," he uttered, looking furtively the while at Mary.</p>
				<p>Mary drew back. "I guess he thinks he is a cat," she said, "eating meat. Out of his head."</p><p>"Do you think your mother would know of some­ thing to do?" Nell asked disconsolately. "Do you sup­ pose he would spring out and hurt the other children?"</p><p>"He might," Mary answered, as she looked about the house perfunctorily, keeping one eye on the mad Danny.</p>
				<p>"Stay awhile," Nell begged as Mary, through with her search, stood a moment in the doorway before re ­turning to the sulky.</p>
				<p>"No, I must go. I can't find Lena." "Maybe she struck off toward Shelbourne." "No, Annie say she come this way."<pb n="214 BLACK SOIL   "/>"Perhaps it was Sheila she saw." "Maybe 'twas."</p><p>"If she comes, I'll tell her," Nell went on, but Mary, preoccupied, had left the house. She must tell her father that she had failed!</p>
				<p>"Lena, is not here," she said. "They got a sick one here, Danny. He won't live, I think. We go. Maybe it's catchin'."</p><p>"I get sheriff," Max answered. They were gone. The broad, sagging sulky disap­peared.</p>
				<p>Danny was already afoot, but Lena remained curled up even after Nell had withdrawn the covers. After a talk with her, Nell went out and sat on the platform of the pump.</p>
				<p>What could she do for Lena? The young couple in their perfidy of getting away had not thought of propriety. With fear and threats hanging over their heads, they had not been capable of estimating values. Lou seemed a decent sort of fellow, but a perfect stranger to everyone in the neighborhood. Yes, they must be married before they go away.</p>
				<p>Father Luermann was in Casper Center. "This is Saturday," Nell reasoned. "He'll be there for Mass to ­morrow." Yes, it was four weeks ago that Tim had taken in Mass there on his way home.</p>
				<p>She'd go to Casper Center with Lena and get Lou, who was waiting there with a team. They could be married and start out. How could she go? Little Alice could not be left--she was feeling none the best as it was. She would take little Alice and Danny with her. Danny could drive the oxen. Was it safe to take Danny <pb n="BLACK SOIL 215 "/>off the place, with herself and Tim gone? And Wild Goose! Lord save us, why Wild Goose was still hanging about! She pondered on the fox--goose--oats problem. Katto? No. There must be no excitement in the neighborhood. She stood up. There was no other way. She would take Wild Goose with her.</p>
				<p>The prairie was in its nightly hush when Buck and Spec were swung out on the trail. In the wagon, Nell, holding wee Alice, shared the seat with Wild Goose. Lena sat crouched in the back, her head bowed lest it appear above the wagon box. She held the unlighted lantern.</p>
				<p>The consciousness of being pursued which obsessed the women was evidently unfelt by Wild Goose and the tortoise-paced oxen. The Indian boy sat listlessly. Nell urged and beseeched the oxen to hasten their gait, but they remained immune to the fever of flight.</p>
				<p>They picked a circuitous trail to Casper Center to evade the agents of Max; it was unfamiliar and seemed interminable. If they could have hidden in the protecting cloak of darkness, they might have been more at ease; but it was light--the stars and moon, shining brightly, traveled with them into the town.</p>
				<p>After what seemed like days, Wild Goose brought Buck and Spec to a halt before the livery barn. Lou was bunking there. He joined them, and they drove over to a small white house next door to the largest building in the town--the church. Nell alighted and knocked at the door.</p>
				<p>"Who's there?" a voice called out, and Nell's heart beat gratefully. Father Leurmann was at home!</p>
				<p>"It's me, Mrs. Tim Connor. I have a couple here   216 BLACK SOIL leaving the neighborhood. Marry them, Father, in the name of God."Before the priest had opened the door, the young couple--Lou carrying Alice sleeping as soundly as if she were in her crib--joined Nell.</p>
				<p>Nell whispered to Lou: "It's customary, you know, to give him a trifle. You have it. It's your duty. He gets hardly enough to keep body and soul together."Lou nodded. "I'll have to have another witness," the priest said, surveying the crowd.</p>
				<p>"We have an Indian outside," Nell spoke up. Then, seeing the look of surprise on his face, she added: "Not a real Indian. He has some White in him--I'm thinking tonight a great deal."She snatched the baby from the embarrassed groom. "It's my child, Father, the youngest of six besides an adopted one."</p><p>"God bless you," the priest commented. "You're a good woman."Little time was spent in formal preparation--a license was not required in the county at this time.</p>
				<p>Wild Goose, summoned, took his place as witness beside Nell Connor. His face was sphinx-like. Whether he grasped the significance of his role or not, no one knew.</p>
				<p>Lena and Lou were married. "I have no treat or banquet for you, but I'll give you my blessing," the priest concluded; and he made a gen­erous sign of the Cross on the motley group.</p>
				<p>At the livery barn, Nell saw Lena placed in a carriage and driven away. As the sound of the spirited hoofs <pb n="BLACK SOIL 217 "/>died in the distance, she was seized with a sense of deso­lation and physical weariness. The shanties of the town were black and forbidding. There was no sign of life. Wild Goose lighted the lantern and stood by the wagon. "If I only knew someone to whom I could go and get a cup of hot tea," she wished furtively. "I feel so--faint."The boy answered nothing. Nell climbed into the wagon. They retraced their way, again taking the route south of the slough to avoid any encounters with the frenzied Max.</p>
				<p>"I'm not so afraid of him, but he might put a bullet in one of us," Nell reasoned.</p>
				<p>Enroute home she realized that she and poor helpless Alice were alone with an Indian. She thought of her first night on the prairie, how she had mistaken the goo-gooings of the prairie chickens for Indian signals. A wave of that1 terrible horror returned to her as she reviewed the night. She tried to reassure herself by recall­ing Ben's experiences: "I trust an Indian further than lots of white men." Tim's, too. Tim was not afraid of Indians. "Treat 'em decent and they'll let you alone." But Tim was always so trusting. He couldn't think evil of anyone.</p>
				<p>She looked sideways at the boy. His face was thin; the scar on his head discernible. It was, no doubt, to be near this boy that his white grandmother had made a long journey back to the <emph>red</emph> people years ago. Perhaps she had passed near this very trail!</p>
				<p>"Stars are not so bright. They're sort of hidden." She tried to break the tenseness of a night so soundless that even her thoughts seemed clattering things.     <pb n="218 BLACK SOIL "/>"Stars, no; but Wild Goose knows that stars will go farther away. Wild Goose knows there's heap fire."Nell looked about her. The air was a little hazy. "There's always fire nowadays," she answered. "I can smell it nights when there is wind. Everyone is smudg­ing the prairie to kill off the grasshoppers. I hope to the good Lord that they'll succeed in getting rid of 'em."There was no answer; only a tense, palpitating silence.</p>
				<p>Nell bowed her head lower over the sleeping Alice, and swayed with the motion of the wagon.</p>
				<p>The oxen stopped with a jolt. Nell would have fallen forward had not Wild Goose held a restraining arm.</p>
				<p>She rubbed her eyes. Dawn! Not dawn! "It's fire!" Surrounded by clouds of smoke, Buck and Spec, off the trail and in grass to their bellies, bawled dismally.</p>
				<p>"Maybe they'd go on the trail. Did you get lost? Lord save us! What'll we do?"</p><p>"Wild Goose leaves trail, goes to slough so Kind Woman and papoose will not burn."So saying, he leaped over the wheel, quieted the oxen by turning them away from the oncoming smoke, and led them on toward the slough in a more diagonal course.</p>
				<p>Nell pulled the shawl about Alice to protect her from the pungent smoke, and shut her eyes. "The children and Tim! May the Lord protect them, tool7' When she heard the stamping of the oxen in the slough and the slashing of water on the wheels, she opened her eyes and looked into an ocean of fire.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 219"/> It was a bad fire. The fierce, singing kind whose billows of blaze overlapped each other in their haste to destroy. As it drew nearer, its tune became the roar of mad animals frothing smoke and lapping, lapping red tongues. On it came! Jaws snapped and bit. At the edge of the slough the flames leaped higher and hurled sparks toward the wagon.</p>
				<p>Something in Wild Goose found a challenge in the frenzy of the fire. He left his place of safety near the wagon, tore off his shirt, and bounded to the water's edge. Like a demon he lashed the fire, uttering wild, un­ canny shrieks, running into its midst to be scorched and singed, and returning to plunge into the water.</p>
				<p>It was wild, barbaric! His movements were in accord with the spirit of the fire.</p>
				<p>Nell sat fascinated, tensely pressing her feet against the box of the wagon, "Wonder if he's lost his senses, or is it a custom of Indians to torture themselves like that!" The boy's lithe body bounded into the smoke-- for an instant it would be lost--and soon again Nell could see the dark silhouette against the ruddy back ­ground.</p>
				<p>The flames receded; the billows rushed on. In their wake they left smoke and darkened prairie.</p>
				<p>Wild Goose returned to the wagon. Without a word he led the oxen from the slough and resumed his seat.</p>
				<p>"Where's your shirt? Did you burn your shirt en­tirely?" Wild Goose smiled as though in reminiscence. "You're all blistered! Foolish boy, to burn yourself like that." <pb n="220 BLACK SOIL "/>"Wild Goose can bear pain. Wild Goose will be a man." To this Nell had no comment.</p>
				<p>They drove on through a sea of charred prairie. Occasionally a smoking tuft of grass would shoot into blaze like a skyrocket and as quickly die down again.</p>
				<p>Nell was crying now. What if it had got the children! "Wild Goose, can't they hurry any faster? If we only had Jack and Jule! Do you think Danny could handle the firebreak? What if they did not waken in time!"Dawn scattered a faint tinge of light. The oxen were spectral, moving, scarcely moving. Daylight grew bolder and flooded the black prairie.</p>
				<p>Nell's eyes ached; her sight was not keen. Would the prairie ever cease to be black?</p>
				<p>A pack of dogs rushed at the oxen. Schwartz's dogs! They were in the neighborhood of home.</p>
				<p>"Look, Wild Goose, look! Isn't that a fresh fire ­break? Is it?" She strained her eyes toward a band of lustrous black.</p>
				<p>"Heap fire not jump fresh firebreak," the Indian boy answered in his solemn way. Thank God I The children were safe. <pb n="221"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXVI">
				<p>THE house was spectral, quiet. Nell placed Alice in the cradle. Robert Emmet and Ellen were in their trundle-bed. Thank God, Danny had had sense enough to sleep downstairs. There he was in the big bed, with Kitty Ann by his side. Margaret and Sheila were breathing deeply in the other room. They were all there, safe and sound, and Lena was married and gone. Their many escapes proved the goodness and mercy of God. Nell moved the sprawling Kitty Ann over and lay down beside her.</p>
				<p>Later in the morning Danny sat up in bed, his hair and eyebrows black with soot.</p>
				<p>Nell was on her feet in an instant. "Lord save us, Danny, were you in the fire?"</p><p>"Oh, Mom, there was a terrible fire. We were all in bed and Max's wife came over and said that Max got so mad when they couldn't find Lena last night that he smashed the lantern on the cart wheel and lit the prairie. Mary told her mother about me. She thought I was sick, so she came over. And Katto was out plowing our fire­ break; She had Pete with her. Our break was all over ­grown with grass--and Mom, she was mad at Pop. She said he should have stayed back East with the Yankees and never brought you here or nothing. She said he was no good except for making jokes and singing, and that didn't get money."One by one the other children awoke and sat up in bed to listen to the night's excitement.     <pb n="222 BLACK SOIL "/>"'N Max's wife said Pop was as kind as a woman and that she would like a man like that. Katto said that one who goes tramping and lets his family burn because they got no good firebreak--"</p><p>"Danny! Danny! Now don't be repeating such. . . , You're safe and you have a good father."</p><p>"And, oh Mom, the fire leaped over in places and we tramped it out and Katto kept plowing all the time.</p>
				<p>"God bless Katto," Nell repeated, tightening her belts about her, preparing for another day and what it would bring forth. "Van den Hull's wife left here be ­cause there was nothing going on! . . ."</p><p>"And Max's wife is coming here tonight," Danny continued, "so don't be afraid when she comes. She asked about Lena, and I told her, Mom, because I knew she was on our side."</p><p>"You did right. And did you sleep through it all?" Nell asked Sheila, who with Margaret was perched on the foot of the big bed. "I never heard a thing." "Nor you, Margaret?" "I heard noises, but I knew Danny was awoke."Nell said nothing more, and was soon out in the kitchen rattling stove lids. Barley coffee and fried mush were very acceptable to a weary and hungry body.</p>
				<p>"I saw big prairie fire, too," Robert Emmet began. "Bigger than your head, too, and I plowed firebreak, too." "When, Emmet, when?" the others chorused, smiling in anticipation. "Oh, one time I did."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 223"/>Nell had decided to be more civil to poor Wild Goose after his gallantry on her secret trip, but for days the boy avoided the house. After recalling his barbaric dance on the edge of the slough, he was ashamed and disgusted with himself. He was not White, but Indian, he thought ruefully. It was with something like relief that one day he saw his small pony, Scar Neck, being led by another Indian on horseback, on the horizon. It was, he knew, a summons back to his father.</p>
				<p>That evening, leaving his companion and the horses out in the shadows, he joined the Connors before their door. He told them about his father's lands and his home. "Better than the house of white men. I will go to my father, but I will come back,'' he said significantly. "There is one who will be glad to see Wild Goose come back."Nell, content in knowing that he was going, was not greatly concerned with his return.</p>
				<p>"Which way will you go? Won't you get lost?" the younger children asked. "Wild Goose will cross Big Muddy at Floyd's Bluff." "What's Floyd's Bluff?"</p><p>"There is where Indian is buried on a living horse. Wild Goose will pass Center Lake. There in the water an Indian girl sings. Wild Goose will listen." "Why is she there?" "Big Chief want the girl to be his squaw. She loved young brave. She threw herself into this lake and there she sings. Some day when Wild Goose leads his squaw to his father's house, he will pass Center Lake and he will say: 'My squaw loves Wild Goose.'"<pb n="224 BLACK SOIL"/>"What does she sing? What does she sing?" "She sings: 'Do not take a squaw who does not want to be your squaw.' It is a sad song." "How does she live in the water?" "Shucks!" Danny said, jumping up--angered, no doubt, that he, too, was feeling the spell of the musical voiced narrator.</p>
				<p>"Let him alone, Danny, Danny," Nell said softly. "Let him go in peace now."Not a farewell was spoken. Before the circle of listen­ers were fully aware of it their guest had risen, taken a step or two backwards, and was swallowed in the night. The sound of horses' hoofs died away in the distance.</p>
				<p>"I declare I'm glad he's gone off with himself. He actually gave me the shivers with his solemn stories," Nell said, relieved.</p>
				<p>"He's a good Indian. Never scalped us or nothin'," Kitty Ann added.</p>
				<p>Emmet said sadly: "Will he come back again tomor­row?" "Huh, by tomorrow he won't even be to his home," Danny answered curtly.</p>
				<p>Later on that night, as Nell tucked in Kitty Ann, the child remarked thoughtfully: "Wild Goose liked Sheila, didn't he, Mom?" "I guess so." "She won't marry him, will she?" "Lord save us, no, child. What put such a notion into your head?"</p><p>"Well, it sounded like he wants to marry her and take <pb n="BLACK SOIL 225 "/>her past that lake where the Indian girl sings. He did like Sheila, Mom."</p><p>"Anyone can't help but like her. The teachers like her. Didn't Ben like her? Herman? And even old Max told his girls that they were a pack of crows compared to Connors' Sheila."</p><p>"Mom, do you like Sheila better than Danny and me and Emmet and Ellen and Margaret and the baby?" "No, Kitty dear, I love you all the same. Every one of you. Every bit the same." "Does Pop, too?" "Pop does, too."Wild Goose was forgotten next morning, for Tim was home. And there was somuch to tell him. The fire impressed him; his lips twitched and his eyes grew glassy. "Old Nero," was his only comment on Max's re­venge.</p>
				<p>Tim, as usual, had some groceries. "I have a bag of flour and a bit of tea here," he said.</p>
				<p>Nell eagerly reached for the tea. "It's only a few drawings I begged off of old Goebel in Walton. He set the finest cup of tea before me that mortal could wish. So overcome was I with the aroma of it, I couldn't taste it. I felt guilty, having it there by myself."</p><p>"'Not like your tea, Tim?' Goebel asked me." "I told him that I wished I could take it home so me wife could have some. 'She hasn't had anything,' I said, 'but the smell of the canister for months.' "</p><p>"'Drink it down, Tim,' he said, 'and I'll send your    <pb n="226 BLACK SOIL "/>wife a few drawings. And there it is. Keep it now for yourself. I'll be getting some again."But Nell made two cups of tea, and Tim didn't re­ fuse when one was placed before him. The pot was rinsed and drained for a second serving. Tim had brought crackers, too, and as Nell ate she felt well provided for, indeed. <pb n="227"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXVII">
				<p>TIM was to stay at home now until after election. As usual he was to serve as a judge and carry the results to the county seat.</p>
				<p>As election time approached and harvest in fortunate localities was over, men of the neighborhood returned with money in their pockets. Schwartz came back. Son Nick stayed on to pick corn, but Schwartz was also one of the judges of election.</p>
				<p>Election day dawned clear and bright. As Tim and Schwartz walked to Center School, five miles away, the grass was spongy underfoot. The sods of recently ploughed land were whitish-gray rectangles of frost. Weeds and brush towered sticklike above the wilted grasses.</p>
				<p>They discussed the summer. Schwartz had received eighteen dollars per month as a harvest hand five counties to the east. Tim had traveled to nearly all the sur­rounding towns in his search for buyers of ware.</p>
				<p>Non-infested areas of Iowa were living a normal life, they agreed. Prices were good and hopes were high. People could hardly believe that such want was at their doors.</p>
				<p>Schwartz swiped his nose with a forefinger. "When I tell 'em how bad we got it, Tim, they think I lie."</p><p>"I know, I know. I got so I didn't tell our circum­ stances. They were less suspicious of me. There's talk of relief from the State," Tim went on. "Both candidates   <pb n="228 BLACK SOIL "/>promise it. If we get the hay-twister in, he'll speak up for us."</p><p>"You mean Jim? Yes, I am for Jim. He is a good one, I think."</p><p>"A voter beat us," Tim remarked as they neared Center School. A carriage was before the door.</p>
				<p>"Not one from this township," Schwartz said, drolly.</p>
				<p>"Perhaps someone with instructions. We'll see." "Voting here?" the stranger called from the carriage, and, as the men nodded, he jumped spryly down, un­ earthed a keg from under the lap robe and rolled it out on the ground.</p>
				<p>"And cigars, too," he added, presenting them with a box. "Compliments of our next representative, Nate Young."Brisk and agile, he was back in the buggy again. "Now, gentlemen, we expect you to do your best for Nate. Pass it around aplenty. Get 'em all tight if need be."</p><p>"We don't want that stuff here," Tim remarked, as Schwartz glowered at him and tried to halt his speech.</p>
				<p>"That's for you and Nate to settle," the man called back as he disappeared, no doubt to visit the next place of voting.</p>
				<p>"Tim," Schwartz spoke up, "for a smart man, you are the biggest damn fool I ever see. Won't take--huh --what people want to give for nothing. You do the figuring here today and I'll tap the keg and see that be­ fore a man gets a drink of beer he votes first for Jim Long. Now go on, do the business."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 229"/>  Boyd, another judge of election, appeared soon. He was no lover of beer, but the cigars were very acceptable.</p>
				<p>At midnight, when Tim and Boyd had finished counting ballots, Schwartz was sleeping soundly on the recitation bench. They roused him and he struck off with Tim in a cold, drizzling rain. Jim Long had carried the township by a large majority. In voting for Jim, many had to scratch their ballots and as a consequence had lost their votes. Going through the pelting rain, protecting his books under his coat, Tim smiled as he recalled scenes and arguments of the day.</p>
				<p>Nell was sitting up, waiting. She had a fire and something to eat. As Tim did justice to his late supper he told what they had found in the count. "One man wrote: 'I want for Haytwister.' Poor devils! Some had just lately learned to write their names, so they added them to the ballots for good measure. I'd like to know who was the fairy-of-a-man that brought us the day's treats."When Tim, driving Buck and Spec, struck off to the county seat with the election returns, it was still misty and there was a raw wind.</p>
				<p>When he arrived in the morning's light, acquaintances called: "Here comes Connor, bearing the German town­ ship favorites."Tim was in his element. There were jokes and story telling, and treats of cigars and hot toddies from friends of successful candidates. The hay-twister's election was unquestioned. Tim returned home, assured that there would be some provision made for the winter. With Jim's election, <pb n="230 BLACK SOIL "/>relief was in sight. He knew the people must get help from somewhere.</p>
				<p>The defeated Nate Young, who had counted on a ballot for every drink and every cigar given out, was in ­censed. Immediately he began to use his influence against relief measures. "Sufferers are exaggerating. Times are not hard, but people want things handed to them."When Jim Long presented his bill in the House ask­ing for help, before action was taken a non-interested committee was sent to investigate conditions. The report disclosed pitiful circumstances of famine, and want un­ heard of. They had seen men with heads and feet wrapped in gunnysacks, and in clothing made of quilts, stacking hay to twist for a winter's fuel.</p>
				<p>The House voted an appropriation of $50,000 for use in devastated areas. The cry for help was answered throughout the state. Carloads of clothing, flour, leather for tapping boots, and other necessities were sent. Grass ­hopper bees became a fad. But in the distribution of the charities some few received more than their just dues; others received nothing at all. The Connors were among the latter.</p>
				<p>The cars were practically empty when Tim arrived.  Still he stood there, fingering the coupon presented him: "-------------Iowa, 18. I,, do solemnly swear, so help me God, that I have not flour or other provisions sufficient to last my family one <emph>week</emph>, and that I have no means on hand or at my command to procure subsistence for my family."Tim hesitated. "I have a few provisions on hand--enough for a week," he said finally. "I can't take that oath."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 231"/>"Make way then," he was told, "for others who have more belly than conscience."Tim perforce moved aside, and returned home with an empty wagon.</p>
				<p>Later, a carload of flour was received. It was stored in a schoolhouse to be kept in reserve until cold weather, when it was to be rationed out. Practically all of the flour disappeared the first night.</p>
				<p>Pete Weiss, whom Tim had accompanied to the county seat on several occasions, came to Tim again, in tears--he was among those accused of theft of flour. "You come with me. I pay you; I pay--"Tim was incensed at the charge. "Indeed 'n' I'll de ­fend you, pay or no pay. The ones accusing him are per ­haps guilty themselves," he told Nell, "imposing on a poor devil like Pete because he can't speak for himself."Accordingly Tim accompanied Pete, and the court freed him of the charge.</p>
				<p>On their return, Pete said: "I pay you ... I got not much money but I got some of that flour. I give you flour, heh?"Tim was dumbfounded. "No, I'll take money. Five dollars. <emph>Five</emph>, do you hear? Don't you come to Tim Connor again. Now clear out."Although Tim was crestfallen at Pete's duplicity, he said that it was worth his humiliation to hear Nell laugh at him. It was one of her best taunts during the winter. "A fine reputation you'll have, defending criminals," she said. "Better defend that old man that was here yes­terday trying to sell children's clothes he had taken from the car. I asked him if he didn't have children that they   <pb n="232 BLACK SOIL "/>fit. He said that he had no children at all. Places like that is where much of the clothing went."</p><p>"Well, some childer got what they needed, I hope," Tim said disconsolately, "and I guess I'll take to the road again. Me feet are on the ground." So he got an ­other shipment of cutlery--on time--and hoped to trade it for merchandise at the stores.</p>
				<p>During his absence Nell and Katto visited Johann's deserted shanty with the purpose of disposing of his be­ longings. The youngest Connors, eager for any new di­ version, followed but stayed outside the door. Danny had said that the shanty was haunted and they had be­lieved. The November sunshine was inviting this morn­ing, so they gathered rose haws and opened milkweed "pods."Johann's shanty was in much the same condition as he had left it; it bore no evidence of Wild Goose's ten­ancy. Dead grasshoppers crunched under foot.</p>
				<p>"By Gutt, love letters!" Katto ejaculated, as foraging in a valise, a shower of envelopes littered the floor. "My Pete and my Ditz will make fun over those. I take them home."</p><p>"We'll burn the letters, Katto." "Are you afraid once of the dead ones?" Katto asked, looking sharply at Nell Connor's face.</p>
				<p>"The dead won't hurt you. Here, see here, these things." Nell had a box on her lap. She unearthed pictures. Johann in curls in the various stages of childhood, a man in military costume. . . .  "I bet this is his father. He looks like a Sittin' Bull. See. . . ." There were a lady's handkerchief, a card of pink celluloid rosettes, a blue ribbon. . . .</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 233"/>Katto misinterpreted the look on Nell's face. "Dead ones;--they can be mean once, too. I call him greenhorn when he was living. He may greenhorn me once, too. . . . I better not talk on him."</p><p>"Nonsense, Katto." Nell looked at her companion, so fearless of the living but in awe of the dead. "There are  lots of clothes here. We'll divide 'em. There are uniforms, even. All our boys can be German soldiers."</p><p>"I don't think I take any. My boys can go in their skin first. I know a man one time he wore clothes of a dead man, and one time when there was a storm he went to the door and, by Gutt, he got the thunder right in the face. That dead man he don't want him to have those clothes."</p><p>"Nonsense, nonsense, woman dear. Gather up some of these clothes and be glad you have them. The guns we'll put in one of the boxes in our granary. Some time they can be used if necessary . . . your boys might blow each other's heads off with them, now. Danny, bring the wagon over and we'll move this stuff into the granary."</p><p>"And the ghost can have the shanty?" Katto asked roguishly. "And the ghost can have the shanty."The day of the first snowfall, Tim came into the yard riding a horse and leading a second. He had Jack and Jule! The liveryman, not very hopeful of his business, had asked Tim to keep the team during the winter for their food. Tim had readily consented.</p>
				<p>The return of Jack and Jule was a good omen. Their presence restored hopes and spirits.</p>
				<p>"Can we sell them again?" the children asked.    <pb n="234 BLACK SOIL "/>"No, we can't sell them. They are not ours."When winter prevented Tim from continuing his peddling, he aided Nell in preparing Sheila for the teacher's examination which was at hand. How fortu­nate they were to have Jack and Jule to make that long, cold trip to the county seat! <pb n="235"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXVIII">
				<p>"SHEILA, Sheila." The glare from the lamp in Nell Connor's hand fell across the girl's face. "Sheila, Sheila."Sheila tried to open her eyes but succeeded only in closing them tighter, her face taking on a grimace. In the interval between sleeping and waking, she reasoned vaguely that she was not sick, nor could she recall a bad dream in which she might have called for help--why was Mom over her, with that light?</p>
				<p>Nell's hand was on her shoulder. "Get up, Sheila. Get up to go and take the examination." Holding the lamp so that its direct glare would be obstructed by her body, Nell deftly rolled back the warm quilts. "Hop out now," coaxingly, as a wave of frigid air swept over Sheila. "It's turned colder and snowed more during the night. You'll have to bundle up well. Leave on your old petticoat inside the good one." Nell and the light moved away.</p>
				<p>Sheila jumped out of bed, and with bare feet scarcely touching the cold floor she followed the light into the warm kitchen. Her clothes were there: dress hanging limply on a chair near the oven door, new stays rolled and in their box, shoes, "strong shoes," toeing in on the zinc mat.</p>
				<p>Nell was padding about in a pair of Norway socks which Tim had brought her. They were soft and soothing  <pb n="236 BLACK SOIL "/>to her varicose veins. She moved with a subdued force which stimulated those about her to action.</p>
				<p>Sheila, hunched up on a chair, her knees drawn up under her chin, reflexively reached for a black wool stocking.</p>
				<p>Nell put a generous lump of butter into the spider of warmed-over potatoes. As she chopped them, the shawl on her shoulders flapped and her coil of hair wound without a pin on the top of her head swayed like an un­ steady chimney.</p>
				<p>"If the roads aren't drifted too much you'll get there in plenty time. Don't be afraid, now, to put down what you think. You're as well qualified as any of 'em," she encouraged, and added as an afterthought: "If any ad­vanced pupils come this winter--which I doubt, for where would they come from?--Tim and myself can keep you ahead of 'em nights."Sheila, her loosened hair hanging over her face and shoulders, was absorbed in the unaccustomed task of ad­justing stays. She tugged at the laces with no result and answered nothing.</p>
				<p>"Here, turn around. Let me give you a hand with that," Nell left off setting the table and assisted the girl. "You'll get some shape with this," she said, pulling the laces tightly as Sheila's pliant body took on hips and bosom. "Now tell me when it's too tight." At a protest from Sheila--."Must be tight, you know."Nell stood off a bit. "My old basque fits you tiptop now. That head of yours!" With the lamplight upon it, and disheveled, it shone like ripe grass. "We'll braid it up tight first of all," she suggested, "and then pin it up on your head. I'll go and get my few pins."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 237"/>  When Nell carried away the lamp, Sheila was in darkness. She watched the rectangles of red from the draft of the stove shiver on the floor.</p>
				<p>As Nell arranged the girl's hair she warned her: "Feel of your stack during the day and keep it pinned. Don't have it streaming down your neck like old Mrs. Probst, who has only nails to fasten hers." She ran the comb through Sheila's bangs, which she had cut recently. "I declare, I like the bangs on you." So engrossed was she in the job of making a lovely, grownup lady out of Sheila that thoughts of the momentous affair of the day were tentatively put aside.</p>
				<p>"Sheila, your hair is like braided straw. I never plaited my hair. I wore it in row upon row of curls until I was married. Your hair is much longer and heavier than mine ever was. Back East now I could keep yours lovely." (Nell's graying hair still curled kindly about her face and neck.)The kitchen door suddenly creaked open and Tim, his face red and eyes watery, emerged from a puff of frosty air. "Ha-hah," he greeted Sheila. "The frost this morning will take the cockalene out of your eye." Find­ing the girl unresponsive, he continued with a wink: "Quite a pedagogue. Say, Sheila, could you be after tell­ing a fellow how many <emph>'a'</emph>s' there are in <emph>separate </emph>this mornin'? To my recollection there was only one in it last night."Sheila bit her lower lip and industriously set the table. The knives and forks had once been silver plated; the dishes were unmatched, a transparent saucer holding a thick, cracked cup.</p>
				<p>The girl felt sick and afraid. She resented Tim's festive   <pb n="238 BLACK SOIL "/>manner. He was, moreover, dressed up. A pair of Johann's trousers was pulled on over his old jeans; his beard was trimmed; and a boiled shirt almost completely hid the hickory one beneath.</p>
				<p>Tim was quiet at breakfast, while Nell urged Sheila to eat her serving of egg and potatoes. When more than a share of cream was poured into the girl's coffee, a lump rose in her throat; she couldn't swallow.</p>
				<p>"Head ache or anything?" Nell asked solicitously. Tim, chewing audibly, supplemented: "Eat up, now. It's a long day we have before us." Less seriously; "It's too dainty the lady is to eat. Good thing the county superintendent isn't a man, I'm a-thinkin', or I'd be coming back without me girl."Sheila, seventeen, very much a child and somewhat a woman, felt a tenderness heretofore unexperienced to­ward these two--Mom and Pop. She realized that they in their goodness of heart were doing the very best they could for her in their present circumstances. They had prepared her, encouraged her, to teach school. Neighbor girls were bound out as hired help. Never need she work hard while there were Mom and Pop. With this appreciation a sadness came over her. No, all of Mom's dreams for her would not be realized. For the present she would dismiss this premonition and try to pass; oh, she would try so hard to pass! She would be painstaking in her writing and not forget and make a capital <emph>I</emph> like a capital <emph>J</emph> . . . why were they so much alike!</p>
				<p>Tim had risen and had kicked in his chair. He put on his coat, cap and scarf and carried the warm brick from the oven to the sled. Nell bundled up Sheila, putting her own black fascinator over the girl's hood, crossing <pb n="BLACK SOIL 239 "/>it under her chin and tying it in the back. Her shawl also was placed over Sheila's and fastened securely with a safety pin. She pressed something cold into Sheila's hand--two nickels and a dime--with the direction; "You can go out at noon with the others and get your ­self a hot bite to eat. Tim, I suppose, will be about town. Tie this in your handkerchief and put it in the pocket of your petticoat. Stop at Boyd's coming back, too, if you're cold."Sheila stood on the threshold. Nell held the lamp high. The air was sharp, cutting as knives. The lamp made a yellow fan on the black outside and disclosed Jack and Jule and the bobsled with the top box. The seat was in the bottom, resting in hay. Tim stood in the sled, holding the reins in one hand and a corner of a quilt which was to be used as a robe in the other. The horses' breath sent white, ghostly spirals into the night. Tim, the horses with their glossy eyes, all things were conspirators. The frozen mud on the wagon, the red runners on the sled, the money in her handkerchief, the new clothing . . . <emph>everything</emph> was plotting with her seventeen years to compel her to leave Nell's wing and to face the outside.</p>
				<p>"Oh, it's black and cold," she said, drawing closer to Nell. The horses, stamping, were impatient to be off.</p>
				<p>"Hurry on, Sheila," Tim coaxed. "Don't you know the blackest hour is just before the dawn?"Somehow her feet carried her body to the sled and found the brick placed for them. The red fan of light disappeared from the door. The horses lunged into the unknown.</p>
				<p>The dignity and novelty of ladyhood which she had   <pb n="240 BLACK SOIL "/>experienced yesterday were gone. Then she had tilted the mirror in their dresser, better to view the long skirt and the curves of her body in a corset. Now she struck at the hard, uncomfortable stays with her mittened fist. She felt wretched and shackled.</p>
				<p>Tim was silent, standing with feet wide apart, tug­ging at the reins as the horses floundered in deep drifts.</p>
				<p>It was a strange, cold world in which Sheila traveled. There was no sky, no prairie. A ghostlike moon ap­peared and sailed along in the darkness. A wind moaned feebly and whipped light, powdery snow about, raising it from its snug drifts of night. A coyote's cry resounded, then another; these died away in the emptiness of the world. They were speeding through Sheila's herding grounds, but she saw no landmarks, only a stretch of homelessness and night.</p>
				<p>"Cold?" Tim shouted, bending toward her. Chills coursed up her back. "Yes, a little," she an­swered. "Soon be at the halfway house."Sheila had been anticipating this stop at Boyd's, the halfway house, for many weeks. The house, a log cabin, was a novelty in this region. Boyd had not adopted the temporary sod shelter or the pine shanty of the prairie settler, but instead had hauled logs from the Sioux River to erect this home. It was built in a thicket of willows on Mill Creek, and had a snugness which the prairie homes lacked. His family was hospitable, his lo­cation midway between two towns, so he was the host on many occasions.</p>
				<p>Tim drew up the team a few feet from the window and uttered a long drawn-out "Whoa-o!" A head immediately <pb n="BLACK SOIL 241 "/>appeared in the doorway. In an instant, Boyd greeted them and led Sheila into the house. "Be with you in a minute," he called back to Tim.</p>
				<p>Sheila walked with difficulty. Her feet had lost all sense of feeling. Mechanically she moved them and found herself in a large kitchen where a lamp hung from the ceiling. A small woman unfastened some of her wraps and placed her in a chair. "Better not go to the stove for a while," she cau­tioned.</p>
				<p>When the men opened the door, the hanging lamp swayed gently and the green cottonwood shoots which had sprouted down from the logs stirred. A canary in a white cage chirped sleepily and began hopping about from swing to perch.</p>
				<p>"Take off the rest of your wraps now and walk about," the little, dark-eyed woman directed, hardly looking at Sheila, so intent was she on getting something to eat on the table.</p>
				<p>Tim declined eating. "We just want to warm up a bit," he explained. "No one has food to give away."Boyd insisted, and the travelers were refreshed with warm coffee and corn cakes.</p>
				<p>Boyd, a hearty man with a political turn of mind, liked company. Tim, also, enjoyed talking and was loath to leave, but he said that they must hurry away so that Sheila would not start her examination with the handicap of being late. Mrs. Boyd, though less effusive, was kind and dutiful. She bundled Sheila into her shawls, wrapped the reheated brick, and invited them to stop on their way back.</p>
				<p>At the door Sheila cast a last, lingering look around   <pb n="242 BLACK SOIL "/>the comfortable room whose ceiling was a summer can­opy of green twigs. The lively little bird, caged but happy, was hopping about from perch to swing, from swing to perch, singing of a future day of freedom.</p>
				<p>As they continued their way, daylight unrolled a white, pellucid landscape before them. The light revealed more strikingly the emptiness of the white earth. Uniform brown groves, clogged with snow, made a feeble attempt at sheltering clusters of buildings. That was all there was against the horizon--these rectangles of man made groves.</p>
				<p>A bar of yellow rimmed the east. "Sun's coming," Tim shouted, pointing. Sheila nodded. "Soon be there now."Sheila felt sick. She imagined she had forgotten every­ thing she had ever learned. <emph>What if she had!</emph> She began: "To him who in the love of Nature . . ." She knew <emph>that</emph>. "We, the people of the United States . . ." She had not forgotten everything. "Two pints make one quart, eight quarts make one peck. . . ."The sun had assumed its shape as a yellow disk and was gliding high into the heavens before they drove into the county seat. The windows of the square white court ­house were ablaze with sunlight, but on the streets nothing was astir.</p>
				<p>The county superintendent was a tall, thin woman no longer young, but to quote Tim, "She hadn't altogether given up hopes."Tim presented the applicant and left. Sheila was as ­signed a seat and given pen, ink, paper, and a list of questions.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 243"/>HISTORY1.   What do we owe Robert Fulton? Sheila thought: Do we owe Robert Fulton? Who is Robert Fulton? She had never heard of him. She was seized with panic. Her heart sank. She would not pass!</p>
				<p>Sheila had never written an examination in her life, and most of her information had been obtained infor­mally in the Connor home. The word <emph>owe</emph> was familiar enough. What do we owe on the wagon? What do we owe on the place? But what do we owe Robert Fulton? Robert Fulton!' Now Robert Emmet . . . "When my country takes her place. . . ."The man beside Sheila was writing in an easy, flow­ing style like the top line in a copybook. Dip, dip went his pen into the ink bottle at frequent intervals. How queer he looked! His skin was so white and his hair and  moustache so black. He looked delicate. And his boots were as shiny as Max's new stove.</p>
				<p>A girl behind her was writing, also scraping her pen and dipping it. They all knew what we owed Robert Fulton! Why had Mom and Pop not told her? Why hadn't Miss Inman told her? A wave of resentment surged through her. <emph>They knew and they had not told her.</emph>The county superintendent opened the draft on the stove. Oh, why must the room be so warm? Sheila's toes smarted and the soles of her feet pricked in the intense heat. If only she could remove her shoes and scrape the soles of her feet on the floor! Oh, those stays! Why had she found that big nest of eggs last summer? <emph>That</emph> had begun the saving for the stays. Why had she gone out sweeping the weeds for eggs? <pb n="244 BLACK SOIL "/>With her physical discomforts came the thought: The necessity of passing this examination. It seemed as though all her life Mom had been saying: "If Sheila passes." Well, Sheila would not pass, because they had not told her. Pop must take her home. How could she get out? She looked about. . . . All were intent upon their work. The county superintendent was out in the hall. Sheila made an effort to rise but instead put her head down on her arms and burst into tears.</p>
				<p>Something pressed her foot. She moved her foot, but in an instant it was pressed again. She risked one eye on the floor and saw the shiny black boot, which had not been entirely withdrawn.</p>
				<p>"Say," the delicate-looking man whispered, "what's the matter? Can't you answer any? Try 'em, they're easy. Put down something. Answer the ones you know.' Mom had said that, too--"Answer the ones you know." Still, Sheila could not raise her head.</p>
				<p>"Better hurry up now and quit that crying. The old lady'll be in and think you're a baby." Sheila drew out the handkerchief from the pocket of her petticoat and dried her face. As she opened her eyes her glance fell on the list again.</p>
				<p>"<emph>Barbara Frietchie</emph>. . ." Danny's oratorical voice: "Shoot if you must this old gray head. . ." Yes, Barbara Frietchie was familiar. She was an old friend. She could answer that one.</p>
				<p>Sheila dipped her pen and began her History. Arithmetic, Orthography, and Physiology followed. The as­pirants did not leave <emph>en masse</emph> for refreshment at noon, <pb n="BLACK SOIL 245 "/>so Sheila wrote continuously. She filled out an application blank and completed the remaining subjects: Gram­mar, Geography, Reading, and Didactics. The county superintendent "corrected" the papers as they were handed in. Sheila, when finished, untied the coins from her handkerchief and waited for Pop.</p>
				<p>Pop would show her the place where she could get something to eat. What if Pop didn't come! What if Pop had gone home! Would she stay here all night?</p>
				<p>There was no answer. The big, moonfaced clock on the wall ticked ominously. There was the closing of doors. Inrushing puffs of cold air. The winter afternoon was slipping into night.</p>
				<p>Oh, there was Pop! How welcome that tall, erect fig­ure in the doorway! Childlike, Sheila left her seat and rushed toward him. Tim jerked off his cap and removed his clumsy mittens. As usual there was a smile on his lips and a drop of moisture on the tip of his aquiline nose.</p>
				<p>The county superintendent approached him with a paper in her hand. "Your ward, or daughter, or what­ ever she is, is not yet eighteen years old. I cannot issue her a certificate," she announced officially.</p>
				<p>"Since when," Tim spoke up hotly, "is it a test of years and not of learning?" "Since October it is both, Mr. Connor. I'm sorry." "Sheila may be more than seventeen. We have no rec­ord of her birth. She came tous a good-sized girl. We gave her a birthday, Christmas day. She may be past eighteen for all I know." Tim was thoughtful for a while, then continued: "If I say she's eighteen, does it not exonerate you? We'd like the girl to teach pretty bad this winter. She's got a school and everything. I <emph>know</emph>
					<pb n="246 BLACK SOIL "/>she's eighteen. Now that's settled," he said pleasantly.</p>
				<p>Miss Butterfield folded her arms in disdain. "No," she said, "I must uphold the honor of my office. I would never stoop to anything so base as that. This county has suffered enough from dishonesty already."</p><p>"'It was not me intention at all to incriminate you or anyone else, but one thing you can do without loss to your honor or the county's--you can issue her a permit. A permit, as I understand, does not conform to the re­strictions of a certificate. It can be issued at the judgment of the county superintendent."Miss Butterfield, having triumphed once, drew her­ self up anew and said with an air of finality: "No, I have made it a practice during my years in office to issue no permits. They are issued too freely in adjoining counties."A twinkle flashed in Tim Connor's eye. People who had seen this amused look in court were always a bit fearful of it afterwards. He fingered the beak of his cap and wiped at the drop of moisture on his nose. He spoke thoughtfully. "Perhaps it was in Woodbury, then, that Jerome Loutch received the permit on which he taught in our district a while back. Your first term, I believe. Loutch was a good six footer, but I knew he was not qualified for teaching; so when he came for his money order--I happen to be secretary of the school board--I questioned him as to what grade certificate he held, and asked to see it. He confessed that he had none at all, so I told him to secure one as quickly as possible--"</p><p>"This, I'm sure, does not concern me at all, Mr. Connor," Miss Butterfield interrupted. "I have others waiting."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 247"/>  "Hold on, now, hold on. This does concern you. Perhaps more than you're aware. In a week Loutch comes to me with a permit signed by the county super­intendent, which was yourself, and says he to me honest enough: I'm not smart enough to teach. Your Danny knows more than I do, but the county superintendent gave me this. I electioneered for her. "</p><p>"I don't know the man." "Don't know Loutch? I don't see how anyone can hold a county office without knowing Jerome Loutch and the old man." Tim smiled again. "I happen to have the permit he taught on in me book, waiting for him to come back for his last month's wages; but, poor devil, he never came. Guess he thought he'd donate that much to the county. No doubt he knew that he was getting out on the skin of his teeth."Color surged over Miss Butterfield's face; it flooded her forehead and ears. Without a word she turned to her desk, signed a permit, and handed it to Tim Connor.</p>
				<p>Tim unfolded the document and read it carefully. "This will suffice," he said, "until she is a bit older. Come on, Sheila, we have a long road ahead of us."Quite happy to be in the sled again and bound for home, Sheila forgot her hunger. The evening was very cold. The sun was dogged, lodged, it seemed, in its southwestern position a little above the horizon. It gradually disappeared in a yellow blur, and a cold wind again took possession of the earth. Jack and Jule, eager to reach home, needed no urging.</p>
				<p>Sheila's memory of the day was a nightmare . . . a confusion of people and verbs and battles and tight clothing. There was a canary caged, too, which must be  <pb n="248 BLACK SOIL "/>freed sometime. It sang and hopped about, but it must be freed! It sang its song as she wrote the answers to her questions. The bars of that cage against which it beat its wings were stiff stays and sharp hairpins. She'd like to go some day and sneak in there and let that bird escape to build its nest in that clump of willows nearby.</p>
				<p>Mrs. Boyd would miss the bird, though. . . . Mom and the children would be eating supper at home now. . . . Mom, yes . . .  she would want to know the questions they had asked.</p>
				<p>Suddenly Sheila forced the fascinator from her mouth and pounded on Tim's knee with a mittened fist.</p>
				<p>Tim lowered his head. "Say," she said, "do we owe Robert Fulton? It was the first question: 'What do we owe Robert Fulton?' " "What?" Tim shouted, lowering his head the more. "What's that you say? 'What do we owe Robert Ful­ton?'"Sheila nodded, "What do we?" she asked. A roar of laughter was his only response. It echoed and reechoed over the silent waste of snow.</p>
				<p>Sheila wondered if he had been drinking too much during the day.</p>
				<p>He turned to the bewildered girl. "It's a long story,"  he said. "I'll tell you when we get home. Won't Mom crow, though? And Boyd--that will be a good one to tell Boyd, but we won't stop tonight." Chuckling, Tim stood erect, braced his feet, and swerved his team from an unbroken drift.</p>
				<p>Sheila huddled herself lower into the quilts. The sled runners were cutting sharply through the snow. The twilight hung like a sheer curtain through which hundreds <pb n="BLACK SOIL 249 "/>of stars multiplied and danced as she watched them. Her body ached. Her clothes were binding her without mercy. The coins in her mitten were cold. She closed her eyes--her lashes were frosty. The bobsled and team were moving through space now. She allowed her body to move with the sled. By keeping herself suspended thus between sky and prairie she would soon reach home, where there would be warmth and food and a welcome. <pb n="250"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXIX">
				<p>THE repetition of the questions, and in particular the debt owed Robert Fulton, did not amuse Nell as it had Tim. "A question like that is no question at all," she argued. Sheila had <emph>passed!</emph> That was an absorbing piece of news. Sheila had passed. Sheila would be a teacher now.</p>
				<p>With Sheila established in a school three miles from home, Nell's next chief concern was for her children's schooling. As she silently made innumerable trips from stove to table, to bedroom, she pondered on existing circumstances. ... If they did secure a teacher and did open the corner school, how could her children at­ tend? They had no warm clothing. Shoes. They had no shoes. One night as she lay sleepless, the cool air blowing across her open eyes, the deep breathing of her family isolating them from her world, she conceived a plan. Tim could teach, and instead of holding school in the building they could have it in their house. Fuel would be saved, and her children would not be perished in the cold.</p>
				<p>She elbowed Tim but could not waken him. He, per ­haps, would not consent, as the time of presenting it was not opportune. She pulled the covers about her and tried to sleep. Reaching out, she felt of Alice--one plump leg had evaded all security and was exposed. Nell took the child from its cradle and held it to her bosom. The little, cold leg pressed close to her warm <pb n="BLACK SOIL 251 "/>body. Nell prayed now. She could always pray fer­vently when she had a child at her heart.</p>
				<p>Next day Tim agreed to her plan. "I can try it at any rate." He went to see the director, and on to the county seat. He procured a certificate without much ceremony. The patrons were satisfied; in fact, pleased. There would be no strife among the clans now; and if children who perforce must race about in moccasins of carpet or wool ventured out into the snow, Nell would prevent them. Yes, they were quite happy to place their trouble ­some broods in the Connors' keeping. Tim would earn his money.</p>
				<p>Tim, with a second-class certificate, demanded five dollars a month more than Sheila, who received twenty five. Each day Tim took Sheila to school and built her a fire of lath and coal. Before he returned, neighbors were coming in sleds with his pupils. Children wrapped like bundles and bales of merchandise were handed to Nell Connor, who received them, unwound them, and held snow to a nipped nose or rubbed numb feet.</p>
				<p>The Connors' kitchen was enriched by the blackboard, the recitation bench, the chart, and the dictionary from the schoolhouse. As must be in such surroundings, school was rather informal. Robert Emmet and even Ellen joined classes, making the enrollment reach twenty-two.</p>
				<p>There was really very little study done. Who could study when Tim Connor was conducting a class? How could one concentrate on the Battle of Bull Run while Tim was telling how to outwit the spell of the wee people? . . . "You reach down without ever taking   <pb n="252 BLACK SOIL "/>your eyes off them, pull a handful of grass, and throw it over your left shoulder . . ."And again, the attention of the entire school might be called to something of note in a special recitation. "Childer, listen to this: <emph>The land of the free and the home of the brave.</emph> You don't understand what that means; but if you'd ever lived, as I have, in a country ruled by tyranny, you'd understand. Here in this land of ours, of course we have our troubles sent us as crosses from a hand on High; but if our present poverty was forced upon us by confiscation, I'd not be sitting here calmly, I'd ..."Nell, in the bedroom, cleared her throat several times. Tim didn't notice.</p>
				<p>What was he trying to tell those poor little German children who had come to learn how to read and write English? They weren't interested in Ireland's troubles.  . . . They had troubles enough of their own.</p>
				<p>"A sadder and a prouder country you never saw. So childer, you must thank God you're where you are to­ day and not under the heel of an oppressor. <emph>Sweet land of liberty</emph>. It is a sweet land of liberty. Let's all sing that song now."Nell chided Tim for his methods and informality. "You mustn't teach children those things." "The truth, Nell, can't they learn the truth?"</p><p>"Yes, but it's not your business here now to criticise England. You're paid to teach 'em."The children continued to listen to his voice. Younger ones learned how to parse, hearing the drill in more ad­vanced classes. Older ones seldom turned a page or <pb n="BLACK SOIL 253 "/>scratched a pencil on a slate when the primary class was on the recitation bench.</p>
				<p>"Fairies live in the Old Round Towers and do be out nights. One evening a hunchback was coming along, coming along ..."Often the kitchen rocked with laughter. Raucous, uncontrolled chuckles of adolescent boys mingled with the spontaneous mirth of younger children.</p>
				<p>Thus the school time was pleasant enough, but Nell dreaded the noon hour; not that she resented its added bedlam, but she saw that some children had little or nothing to eat. "How I'd like to stuff their stomachs like ticks," she often said, but she could not--her own family was on rations.</p>
				<p>Hendrika and Johnny Van den Hull had no lunch at all. There was no mother at Van den Hull's. She had gone away from the prairie to a place where there was something going on. "Where there is no mother, there's nothing," Nell concluded, "and the little grandmother may be sick." She gave the Van den Hulls something-- a cup of mush, a drink of milk. Others followed her example, and they ate their portions avidly.</p>
				<p>One day Hendrika and Johnny came with smiling faces. Hendrika had a basket, and Johnny hopped about whispering to the children. The little ones and the grandmother had not forgotten their friends. When Jake, the father, had received money from a relative and had bought flour and a few extras, they shared their good fortune. It was a real treat they brought-- <emph>Saint Nicholas</emph> cookies, one for everybody. Nell saved hers for Sheila, who was nothing but a child.     <pb n="254 BLACK SOIL "/>When the Connors' two wage earners had taught a month, many needed expenditures were made. They bought shoes, flour and groceries. Interest was met, and a small payment made on the team. Nell had sent for raisins, and what marvelous things can be created by an ingenious woman with an oven and raisins! Each day she had an extra for the children's lunch; and their round eyes often left their readers and centered on Nell as she bustled around the stove.</p>
				<p>Max's wife came over one day and volunteered to aid in fixing a little Christmas party for them. She would give each child a stick of candy. Other mothers cooperated, and the day before Christmas was a mem­orable one.</p>
				<p>Of course there were pieces and songs. Recitations were given in many dialects. Santa was Kriss Kringle, St. Nick, and Santy Claus.</p>
				<p>Margaret closed . . . "Silent Night, Holy Night . . . " Margaret--tremulous lips, sweet voice, slim white face, soft brown hair, clear blue eyes fixed beyond the bedroom door.</p>
				<p>"Christ our Saviour is born.  .  . ." Quiet in the kitchen, a subdued quiet. Children, en­ grossed in eating, wrapped pink tongues around their sticks of candy and noted perceptible losses. Dutch Fred squeezed rosy apples out of his pockets--one for each.</p>
				<p>Tim broke the stillness. "It's over, folks. Merry Christmas to ye all."Little children bundled into sleds. Early dusk. Dutch Fred's deep voice leading others as they hitched their teams and swept away: "O tannen Baum, O-O-O tannen Baum . . ."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 255"/>The Connors watched. Santa and reindeers! Christ Child would return to earth tonight! Would He come here to the prairie? It was cold and the full moon was lemon-colored and the world was white. Look! A bright star over Schwartz's grove!</p>
				<p>Ellen scolded next day: "I don't like Mrs. Santa Claus. She stole poor Mom's good bonnet ribbon and made me a doll dress out of it."</p><p>"Ellen, you're a goose," Danny began. "Danny!" Nell stood before him. "I declare, if you say a word to that child one way or another, I don't know what I'll do with you. Your good sense ought to be growing in proportion to your legs. Take that pail there and bring me in some water."The children danced about. It was Christmas and there was duck for dinner! Santa Claus had found them; and they knew that the Christ Child, too, had come to the prairie, although they had not seen Him. <pb n="256"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXX">
				<p>YES, sir, time is a river flowing on and on . . ." Tim spoke out one evening from where he sat by the stove smoking his pipe. "One day leads right into another. There is no break in time--east or west. Sheila, we'll soon be through leading our flocks out of the darkness of ignorance into the light of knowledge."Sheila, playing cat on a slate with Kitty Ann, did not answer.</p>
				<p>"Sheila, it's you and meself that have the responsible positions around here. We're moneyed people. If we didn't have so many places to put it we could carry it about in our pockets."Nell, in the adjoining room tucking in the younger children, also thought of time, the days passing. Before she rejoined the group in the kitchen, she knelt by her bed and thanked God. . . . January, that hard, cruel month with the thirty-one days, was over.</p>
				<p>In Connors' neighborhood it was easy to be poor. Almost all were very poor. No one had a luxury. "One poor devil was worse off than the next." Whenever Tim and Nell Connor spoke of the difficulties of their lot, they soon heard of others who were worse off. Just when the winter terms closed and wages perforce discontinued, diphtheria broke out in the township.</p>
				<p>Briedbarths, the family whose mother had consumption, now had black diphtheria! Liddie had it first and died in a few days. Everyone shunned the stricken home.</p>
				<p>BLACK SOIL 257People out of doors would not breathe deeply when the wind blew from Briedbarths'.</p>
				<p>Nell grieved for Liddie. "I welcomed that child into this world," she would go on. "I gave Liddie her first bath. There is no one to help bury her in decency." Finally she could be inactive no longer. "Someone must help! Of what use are lives if we can't risk them to save others. Go, Tim, and get Dutch Fred. He'll go over; he has no children. He has a kind heart. Have him call this way. I'll have a little dress ready."The overskirt of Nell's wedding dress was of white bombazine. She ripped a generous width and fashioned a dress that fit Ellen--Liddie was the one age of Ellen.</p>
				<p>When Dutch Fred came with a rough, little coffin under his arm, Nell went again to the bombazine skirt. She covered the box with another width, and lined it with her wedding veil.</p>
				<p>The young Connors were amazed. Never had they been allowed to even touch that veil! And now. . . . But something unusual in the solemnity of Nell's face kept them from remonstrating.</p>
				<p>As Nell worked, she advised Fred. "Tim'll send a doctor to the other children. And you'll stay there, won't you? The neighbors can look after your stock."</p><p>"I stay," he nodded. "And come within calling distance if you need us for anything. Give 'em plenty milk and keep 'em warm. Tim will report their circumstances. The county'll help 'em, I know."As Fred buttoned up his buffalo coat, after putting his long beard fondly inside, he started off."    <pb n="258 BLACK SOIL "/>Nell called after him: "May the Lord reward you, Fred, and keep you from catching it."Dutch Fred buried Liddie, and nursed the stricken family. The less fearful neighbors brought milk frozen and wrapped in paper or cloth, left it at a safe distance from the house, and ran. Fred religiously followed the doctor's orders: he tied a stocking around each throat,  and gave a teaspoonful of kerosene every two hours.</p>
				<p>They lived. The epidemic spread, but decreased in virulency. Katto saved her boys with onions. She poulticed them with onions and fed only onion soup. Some neighbors, not wishing to give Katto and her remedy full credit, argued that Schwartzes did not have it so bad; but Katto insisted that it was "black dipteery"--she could see the black in their faces.</p>
				<p>The Connors prayed that they would be spared, and Nell's faith gave hope to all. "Pray, children, pray. Pray to your gardian [sic] angel."</p><p>"My guardian angel won't let me get it," Margaret said, convinced. "My guardian angel won't let me get it," Kitty Ann repeated, " 'cause she don't want to catch it her own self." "Kitty, Kitty Ann, child, such talk," Nell reprimanded. "Don't be bold now."The Connors were spared the diphtheria; and with the advent of spring, fear of the epidemic passed away.</p>
				<p>Again settlers mustered up hopes, and the desire to gamble with the black soil stirred their blood. The state apportioned out seed. Stricken lands were exempted from taxes. "Seed early!" all were advised.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 259"/> Would there be a harvest? The roulette was spun! They could but await results. Grasshoppers were still a menace, but their numbers were greatly reduced. Favorable winds had carried many away the previous year before they had deposited their eggs; prairie fires had helped to diminish them.</p>
				<p>Summer showed promise of a partial crop. The Con­nors lost much of their barley and oats, but had a fine stand of wheat. Schwartz had a fair patch of corn. It was not for long, however, that the settlers were ex­ultant, for a third combatant entered for possession of the crop--the mortgage!</p>
				<p>They realized that a mortgage had strong propensi­ties. Grasshoppers came and went, hail and blizzards visited and passed on, but the mortgage stayed. It did not mellow with age; indeed, it daily grew more savage, more vigilant, more remorseless.</p>
				<p>Foreclosures were the order of the day. Shiny carriages, when seen on the horizon, filled Nell with awe. What if they were coming to foreclose <emph>them</emph>? What if they should demand the wheat for interest? The ham­mer would fall on them!</p>
				<p>Steindler's section of land was free from mortgage; moreover, Max had cash in a tin box under his bed. Everyone thereabouts knew of his surplus, yet no one would ask for a loan. Max was humored as a child, and as his malady grew worse he became more tyrannical. Opiates only would calm him.</p>
				<p>One day when Tim and Schwartz had been called to Steindler's to assist in his care--he was without sufficient sedative--a shiny carriage appeared in the neigh­borhood.    <pb n="260 BLACK SOIL "/>Nell was lulling Alice to sleep, Danny and Captain were off with the cattle, the young ones were in the grove, and Sheila was pulling the wild mustard from the wheat.</p>
				<p>Sheila saw the strange carriage enter Schwartzes' yard. A few minutes later it drew up with a flourish at Connors' wheat field.</p>
				<p>The girl--her brown feet moving carefully amongst the wheat, golden-red hair flecked with mustard pollen, face flushed with the heat of the day--bent her supple body, plucked stalks of mustard, and added them to the pile on her arm whose yellow blooms framed her face. The summer sunlight! A field of ripe wheat! A golden girl!</p>
				<p>"Gawd, that's a sight," the man in the carriage mumbled. <emph>Wild Mustard</emph>! He called to the girl: "Wild Mustard, come out here."Sheila made her way carefully out of the field. "Good day, my beauty," the visitor said kindly, as he leaned over the buggy wheel.</p>
				<p>Sheila dropped her eyes. Added color surged over her face and neck . . . a mortgage man was not so formid­able as she had imagined.</p>
				<p>"Dutch or German? How shall I twist my tongue?" "English. Talk English," Sheila answered, her eyes risking a look at the team, whose skins were moist and shone like satin under the bright fly nets.</p>
				<p>"Thank God for that!" the stranger answered good naturedly. "A man coming into these parts must have not only an interpreter but a shotgun. Woman over there next got after me with a pitchfork when I wanted to talk a little business with her. She told me the <pb n="BLACK SOIL 261 "/>various parts of my body that she would feed to the hogs. She looked like she might do it all right, so I put out."</p><p>"She would have," Sheila answered calmly. The man took a list from his pocket. "What about Tim Connor? Is a man safe there? Gawd, that was an awful woman."Sheila dropped the armful of wild mustard. Her throat ached from pollen. "Foreclosing?" she asked timidly. "No" he answered, "Selling lightning rods! This his wheat? Fine crop of wheat. He should have money enough to protect his home and you, my beauty."</p><p>"Pop  can't  buy,"   Sheila   answered.   "He  has  no money." "Oh, can't he, my beauty? Come for a little ride. No? Then, climb in here and we'll talk it over." Conde­scendingly, he reached for her hand.</p>
				<p>Sheila drew back instinctively, like a colt from harness The stranger was kind, his smile broad, his mous­tache oiled, his boots shiny. Still she was apprehensive of that look in his dark eyes; she had an impulse to run.</p>
				<p>"Your folks now, Connors--" he began, as he jumped from the buggy with the reins over one arm. Sheila backed away from him. He restrained her, holding her arm. "Oh, Wild Mustard," he said, amused. "Don't you ever want a lover?"Yes, Sheila had been dreaming much of lovers; but this man was not a lover. He was a stranger! She tried to free herself. She was not quick enough. No, you don't Wild Mustard--" He had her in his arms.    <pb n="262 BLACK SOIL "/>"Sic 'em Cap! Sic 'em!" Sheila heard Danny behind her. Cap came bounding over the grass and jumped at her assailant. Long, flapping coat tails were the most alluring things in the world. Cap tore away a mouthful and came back again, but the man had taken refuge in his buggy. With an oath he picked up the reins and drove toward the house.</p>
				<p>Nell met him in the yard. The man removed his coat and said nothing of his last encounter. He began: "I had a very unpleasant stay at your neighbor's house. I hope this little call will be more pleasant. It will be." He tied his team to a tree.</p>
				<p>Nell, arms folded, stood before him. Bully for Katto if she ran him off. May the Lord continue to give her courage! What was the man saying to her?</p>
				<p>"And I met your daughter--she's a beaut--in the field and I think with a little coaxing that she would be willing to come and work for me. And I'm sure you'll think it Is a very good plan all around. You see--I need the hired girl--you need the money." Ingratiatingly: "We can help each other in such hard times."Nell, apparently calm, looked at the man. Her gray blue eyes flashed like steel. "A good bit of water has gone under the bridge since I've seen the likes of you. If Tim was here he'd knock you down. If you have a man's business here, state it. Otherwise, be moving on." The man was a bit chagrined. People were poor as Job's cats. Did they still have honor? And such pride! He had taken the wrong method, he realized that. He drew a paper from his pocket. "I have something of interest to progressive farmers," he began.</p>
				<p>Danny, with Captain at his heels, had reached the <pb n="BLACK SOIL 263 "/>yard. The boy's eyes narrowed as they saw a paper in the man's hands. The horses pricked their ears at the dog.</p>
				<p>"S-s-s--<emph>sic</emph> 'em," Danny said softly. Captain jumped at the tassels of the fly nets; and, in one accord, both horses jerked their heads, broke the hitching strap, and were away on the prairie.</p>
				<p>Danny dodged behind the granary, holding the dog. When the enraged man followed his team, in an effort to catch them, Danny again released Captain; and dog and man and team disappeared in a fog of dust.</p>
				<p>Day after day passed and the lightning rod man did not return. Nor did the loan man visit them to press his claim. The crops were harvested; and Connors had flour for the winter. <pb n="264"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXXI">
				<p>THE next spring there was little occasion to speak much of hoppers. The plague was practically over. Prosperity hovered in sight once more.</p>
				<p>The railroad now became the chief topic of conver­sation. There was a new road venturing west, and many counties were offering a right of way. Jerome county was exulting in the report that it had received the rail­ road when word came that the line had swerved south, and that negotiations were being made with the Central Railroad to jointly build a track to the Missouri River.</p>
				<p>Tim Connor, neglecting his fields, had spent much time in securing signatures for the right of way. This last report filled him with chagrin. "It do beat all. ..."</p><p>"Something may come up yet," Nell consoled. "I'll set no hopes on it. ... Of course, there will be other roads later on."</p><p>"I suppose so, if we live long enough to see them." While Tim renewed his energy putting in his tardy crop, Nell, also reconciled to the caprices of fortune, re­joiced in the more immediate sources of joy. It was spring of the year for Nell. She went about her daily duties which included now: kitchen, chicken coop and garden. She sang. Snatches of songs. A little of this and a little of that. Crumbs of happiness.</p>
				<p>She often stood in the yard and watched the bobbing heads of Jack and Jule as they pulled the seeder. The cultivated land was black, but the prairie grass was green, and light and shadows already had begun their <pb n="BLACK SOIL 265 "/>play across its wide sweep. Sticky yellow leaves curled out on the cottonwoods so that they resembled huge bouquets. The cactus, resting unscathed on the top of the overturned kraut barrel, showed no sign of blossom, but was taking on a more delicate green.</p>
				<p>There was Steindler's knoll, beyond which Sheila dis­appeared each morning. Teaching. Coming home each evening with the younger brood of children to eat her out of house and home.</p>
				<p>Danny, loose-jointed, long slim hands, husky voice, less a torment but retaining the twinkle in his eye . . . the spit of his father. He'd soon be demanding another school.</p>
				<p>Margaret, more sensitive than ever, losing her freckles, secretly envious of Sheila, writing down little notions on bits of wrapping paper. "Poems," Tim called them; but poor child, they had no rhyme to them at all.</p>
				<p>Kitty Ann, outgrowing her stumpiness, boasting that she could whip any boy her age, both Margaret's de­ fender and persecutor, having feet that could improvise a dance to any tune her ear could catch.</p>
				<p>Robert Emmet, a lovely child with a fine-shaped head, round blue eyes contemplating visions of Danny's world. A little outcast--classed with the older ones with whom he could not belong, because he had outgrown the younger ones. Ellen and Alice had a monopoly on Tim's knee, but occasionally Emmet drew near, sat astride Tim's boot, and called out: "Ride a cock horse."</p><p>"You're pretty big, Emmet. Hop off, now, that's the man, and we'll give wee Alice a ride."Poor Emmet must be seen to a little more. They  were  fine, healthy  children . .  . but how <pb n="266 BLACK SOIL "/>would they rank with eastern cousins? Nell often pondered thus as she worked in the garden.</p>
				<p>There was one section of this garden patch to which she gave special care. Daily she carried water to a few twigs. Fruit! Max's wife had sent away for currants and high-bush berries and had given her a few shoots. There were also three young maples and an elm which had been donated by a mover. The nurturing of these twigs was a delight. They were from the East. Would they grow? Would they thrive here in this prairie? . . . If eastern vegetation flourished here, why not transplanted chil­dren?</p>
				<p>One day leaves curled out on the sticklike saplings and bushes. They were growing! Thank God. She knew that they would grow. Now if discouraging thoughts came in the future she would think of the success of this bit of garden ... it would be a trysting place with hope. It must be given a chance, however, and not be rooted or scratched out. She made a fence of sticks to discourage the chickens; and spoke often of fencing the yard.</p>
				<p>One spring evening as the Connor family was sitting outside the door listening to unrestrained prattling children and rustling cottonwood leaves, Nell complained anew of the freedom of the young hogs.</p>
				<p>"The hogs do no harm," Tim argued. "They have everything rooted up," Nell answered with irritation in her voice. "I can't have a sign of a flower. I declare, if they go down there and break my few young bushes, I'll break their backs. Now, Tim, that's fair warning. Max's always had a fence, and even <pb n="BLACK SOIL 267 "/>Katto has now. You could just get a little extra barbed wire. You'll be fencing fields soon."</p><p>"I have no time now to fence the yard. Maybe later on. Crop's behind as it is with that railroad bubble, and I'll have to do some fencing. Herd Law is being carried out this spring--"</p><p>"You get the wire and I'll fence it." "I'll not get the wire and have you fence it." This fence argument was dismissed, for a team had turned in from the trail.</p>
				<p>"Max must be worse and Mary's after me," Nell speculated, standing up and slipping her feet into her old shoes. "If he's bad, Tim, you must come, too. I don't mind sickness, but this may be death. He can't last much longer. The poison'll soon reach his heart."Tim's eyes were fixed on the team. They didn't step like Max's team! He walked with Nell to greet the guests, whoever they might be.</p>
				<p>"Awful to say," Nell prattled, as she fixed her hair ­pins more securely in her hair, "but Max's wife'll have peace when he's gone,--not but what his death will be hard on her in her delicate condition and all. He's a bad head to her . . . handles all the money. Everything must be brought to his bed.--That's not Max's team. Could it be the mortgage, Tim?" Nell looked at her husband anxiously.</p>
				<p>Tim swallowed--his Adam's apple expanding in his throat--and walked toward the strangers.</p>
				<p>A man and a boy were in the buggy. In the dusk the man's long, dark sideburns gave his face a sinister look.</p>
				<p>"Allen is my name. Tim Connor?"    <pb n="268 BLACK SOIL "/>"It is, sir," Tim answered solemnly. "I'm out for a right of way for the railroad. How are you standing?"</p><p>"Right on me two feet, and you're welcome." The stranger laughed, a hearty laugh in which there was a little of the diplomat. The Connor children heard it and were glad.</p>
				<p>"You're the man we're after," Allen said, climbing down and shaking Tim's hand. "Old Ben, one of the road gang, sent me here to you--he dug a well for you once."He knew Ben, the stranger did! Followed an evening, a momentous evening in the life of Tim Connor and his family. The horses, "dandy pacers," were cared for in the wreck of a stable.</p>
				<p>"Safe enough, for the steeds," Tim said jokingly, "for if the thing does collapse there won't be much danger. There's nothing much to fall."\"The road'll get you plenty cheap lumber for a new barn," Allen answered suavely.</p>
				<p>Nell set out a lunch: mush which had been simmering in a black kettle on the back of the stove, and milk.</p>
				<p>All the Connor family stood around the table. The strange boy, Edgar, about Danny's age or a little older, had dark, pensive eyes. Unabashed by the scrutiny he was receiving, he in turn searched out details about the room: the table above which was a row of blue eyes, a lamp sputtering in the night air. His father, noisily dis­posing of bowl after bowl of mush, and with milk running down his beard, talked. He talked of everything: <pb n="BLACK SOIL 269 "/>people, money, politics--and concluded each with the outburst: "That's mush, that is!"And Nell, pleased, asked: "Won't you have some more?" "A little, please."After the meal, Tim and Allen sat in front of the house. Allen passed cigars, and they smoked and talked. The number about them dwindled as tired children stumbled into bed.</p>
				<p>Nell lit the lantern and called Danny, saying: "Here, take the boy down and show him his bed. I've fixed one in the wheat bin."Danny took the lantern and whispered: "What'll I say to him, Mom?" "Oh, don't act like a greenhorn. Ask him if he isn't tired after his long trip, or something like that."Danny approached the boy and together they went to the granary, Danny broke the stillness in an unnat­ural voice, "I presume you're quite tired after your long journey."Edgar didn't answer for a moment. He jerked off his shirt and hung it on a nail in a two-by-four. "I'm not so all-fired tired, but I'm sleepier than the devil."Bewildered, Danny found his way back to the house, listened to the voices of the men for a while, and then went off to his bed in the loft. <emph>I'm not so all-fired tired, but I'm sleepier than the devil.</emph>The house grew dark. Nell withdrew from the door­ way and was soon asleep. The men remained talking on the step.</p>
				<p>Birds were twittering when Tim came into the room.   <pb n="270 BLACK SOIL "/>He called: "Nell, Nell," and shook her by the shoulder. His heart was glad. It was good news he was bringing to the woman who had shared with him so many grief's. "Nell, Nell, the road's coming through, and a town on our land! A railroad and a town coming to us, Nell."Tim was asleep in an instant. It was Nell's turn to stay awake. She lay wide eyed, thinking, until Alice awakened, placed a chubby fist on the rung of the cradle, and joined the clamor of the hungry young birds.</p>
				<p>The road coming and a town! Tim explained more fully next morning. "Allen was sent out from Buffalo to supervise the building of the road. Crary, the former superintendent, got fired--he ignored our right of way, and then couldn't make terms with the Central further south. Now Allen is intending to push a road right through on its own hook. Right through Jerome county. Right through Low German township. And Ben told him of us and asked him to put a town on our land. It could be a mile further east be right, but the railroad has the saying of it--that's between ourselves. I tell you, that Allen is a fine man."Allen made Connors' his headquarters for a few days, and Tim accompanied him to settlers on the west who would aid in pushing things through. The Hollanders were promised a town of their own ten miles from the one on Connors' land.</p>
				<p>While Tim was away, Danny worked in the field. It was Margaret who took Edgar about the prairie and made him acquainted with her world. Edgar was pleased with her discoveries. He was anxious to be of some use about the farm, too, but Danny ignored him.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 271"/>One noon he met Danny at the well as he was watering his team. "I presume you're tired after your long morning," he said roguishly.</p>
				<p>Danny answered: "Not so all-fired tired, but I'm hungrier than the devil."Both boys laughed. They were good friends after that. Edgar learned much of the life of a farm boy, and Danny in turn heard of school life in Buffalo.</p>
				<p>"I'm going East some day," Danny said solemnly after one of Edgar's recitals. "I'm going to get a farm and live somewhere in the West," Edgar answered.</p>
				<p>Although Edgar enjoyed all the Connor children, it was obvious that Margaret was his favorite. Unlike other boys of Danny's acquaintance, who no doubt would have concealed this admiration, Edgar was very frank about it. As they sat talking on the platform of the well one evening, he said: "Gosh, Margaret's awful pretty."Danny, taken by surprise that anyone should see in freckled-faced Margaret a sign of beauty, looked at his sister for the first time with the eyes of another. Margaret, her bare feet swinging from the back of the wagon box, was intently reading a book of Edgar's, her chin cupped in her hand, her dark eyebrows drawn in con­centration, her frowsy brown hair framing her slim face.</p>
				<p>"You're the first one that ever remarked her. Everyone goes wild about Sheila." "Sheila's pretty, but she's coarse, awful coarse. Don't you think so?" Edgar said,imprinting the outlines of a   <pb n="272 BLACK SOIL "/>well-made boot heel in the soft ground. "My father and I guessed that she did not belong to you folks, before we were told."What was this world coming to? thought Danny Connor. A train! A town! And now this boy from back East speaking like that! <emph>Margaret pretty! Sheila coarse!</emph>"Coarse?" Danny repeated--Mom had said that Katto was coarse. "Sheila's not coarse. She's a lady." Fire flashed from his eyes. A paleness disfigured his face. His jaw was rigid.</p>
				<p>Edgar, though only one year older than Danny, felt very much his senior for the moment. "Well, don't you see? It's because I like Margaret best," he dismissed it.</p>
				<p>Danny didn't see, nor did he care to see. Mom knew Sheila best and Mom had said that she was a lady. Why, even Indians liked Sheila. Coarse. . .</p>
				<p>Edgar thought it best not to mention Danny's sisters to him again; but he wrote a little verse to Margaret. Margaret, in turn, wrote one for him. Tim, upon hearing of the lad's poetic tendencies, nicknamed him Edgar Allan Poe.</p>
				<p>Comments and raillery on the mutual admiration and common interest of Edgar and Margaret were the cause of much bolted food, until one day Tim "put a stop to it."</p><p>"When I was young," Tim began, "I craved to write verses; and every attempt I made me brothers laughed at me. I'm sorry now I didn't go ahead in spite of 'em. See here. We'll let these childer alone. A poem, to me--" Tim stood erect and his deep-set blue eyes were fixed on something distant in the fields--"a poem, to me, is <pb n="BLACK SOIL 273 "/>music ... it is more . . . it is a bit of Divinity cap­tured for just a fleeting second and released again. Let the childer alone." He pulled out his chair. "We'll have no more tormenting whatever."All were silenced, even Mr. Allen himself. "Pop always pets Margaret," Danny complained af­terwards to Kitty Ann. "And Mom always pets Sheila," Kitty Ann added. "No one ever pets me." <pb n="274"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXXII">
				<p>IT was Saturday evening, a few days after the Allens had gone on negotiating farther west, when Ben, the well-digger, drove into Connors' yard. "Ben!" all shouted; but the younger ones drew away from him. Robert Emmet stood abashed at his greeting: "Let me see if I can show you the Black Hills."He recognized each one of them and had an extra word of greeting for Alice, "the grasshopper baby," whom he had never seen. He had business, he said, with Nell and Tim.</p>
				<p>"We're laying out a few more towns soon now," he began, as the family sat in front of the house, "and right away you must have buildings here. The depot, of course, the road will build, and it will be permanent. Other buildings such as grog house, eating house and the like, will move away with us. There's chances here right now for the right kind of men. Get someone in here with a store and post-office. A saloon, too, and a lumber yard. I'd like to see you in the lumber yard, Tim--that's where the money is. Road's hauling lumber and the carpenters are moving with it. Put up a big barn here so they'll know where the town is for miles around." Ben looked about at the cluster of frail buildings, black in the dusk. "You need a barn and a house, too."Tim unfolded his long legs and said nothing. Ben leaned more closely, raising a horny hand. "You got to do it, Tim. Road expects some help in boosting a town. Others would be right glad of the chance."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 275"/>"Let others try it," Tim snapped. "You're foolish, man. Think of your wife and children. It's your one opportunity, and the road will be back of you. Settlers are following us, needing houses. Crops are good."Tim did not comment. "I asked Allen to plant the town here, Tim, because I remembered all of you here; and I wondered about you, too, when I heard of the hoppers. I never once thought that you'd leave, and I was right."Tim could not reply. "How did that lovesick German come out who was counting his cornstalks?" Ben changed his mood. "Hung himself," broke in the children in chorus, as the parents hesitated.</p>
				<p>Ben turned to the children. "Well, he was the kind that would do such a thing. Not ready to meet the old world as it turns around. And the artist with the pro­ fane mother? Family stuck, did they?"They told of Herman, recounted the details of Johann's death, and the coming of Wild Goose. "And he was a good Indian; didn't scalp our heads or nothing. The place where you got scalped is bigger now."Ben smiled and rubbed his hand over his bald head he had only a fringe of gray hair now. "And Herman is a cowboy and he's coming home soon for a visit," they added.</p>
				<p>"So Sheila hasn't been carried off yet. Well, all in all, you've weathered it pretty well considering ..." Ben said thoughtfully. "You've been here hoping and pray­ing for better things and now you won't grasp the opportunity when it comes." He stood for a few minutes   <pb n="276 BLACK SOIL "/>staring at the tops of the trees and at the stars; then he moved out of the group. From the edge of the grove he asked: "Who got Johann's land?"</p><p>"Max got that," Tim answered. "It stayed idle for a while. Then it was put up for the taxes. When Max heard of the railroad coming he paid the taxes and got the land."</p><p>"I'll bet yuh. That's the kind of a man that would take a chance and help himself while he aided the rail ­road." "Why is Ben mad at us? Doesn't he like us any more?" the children asked.</p>
				<p>No one replied. After a silence, Nell began: "I believe, Tim, in the name of God, we should consider what Ben says. He's for our good." "Easy to talk, woman, when we have neither credit nor money."</p><p>"Well, others along the road had neither credit nor money, and they made out. Ben knows our circum­ stances well enough, and he wouldn't insist if he didn't know it was the thing to do. I believe the man is disgusted with us."</p><p>"Disgusted he'll be, then." "Well, we prayed so much, Tim, for success here and for a decent living for our children, and now maybe our prayers are being answered. I'm willing to take a chance. We can't be any poorer than we are. I think it's what we're to do. The hand of God seems to be behind it all-- Allen coming and Ben directing him here and all." "It's truly provoking you are at times. But I'll not quarrel with you over it."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 277"/>Danny spoke up. "Well, if the town's on our land, Pop, won't they have to buy the land? That'll be some money. And if the buildings go up why can't you sell them the lumber? That'll be money, won't it? Maybe Ben'll go in with you, Pop. Since he's got money, and if it will make as much as he says. . ."Tim looked sideways at his son. He was no longer a little child to be hushed up, but a long boy sprawling on the ground saying something in a husky voice that was provokingly sensible.</p>
				<p>"If I make a little," Tim answered, "they'll be after me like hounds. Me harvester note is due this month, and something must be done on the mortgage." "Pay up the things with the money, Pop, and maybe you'll get credit then."</p><p>"That's the eye," a voice sounded from the yard, and Ben joined them again. He took his place once more be ­fore the door. "Right smart son you got there, Tim, and you don't know it." He leaned forward facing Tim, his fringe of hair white in the moonlight. "Tim, you're a fine man and an honest man. Now would it be fair for you to let your wife's wishes and your son's plans go without at least a trial? That would not be honest, Tim, and I know you to be honest, too blame honest for your own good."Tim smiled at that. Cynically: "We'll see, Ben, we'll see." "We <emph>will</emph> see. And I do have a little, too, as Danny said, and into the pot it'll go to show you where my faith is." And Ben raised sleepy Robert Emmet so that he rested comfortably in his arms.</p>
				<p>As a climax to the auspicious evening, a black horse   <pb n="278 BLACK SOIL "/>from which streamed colored ribbons stopped before Connors' door. Its rider, likewise bedecked, drew out a revolver and shot once into the air.</p>
				<p>The Connors were invited to a Low German wed­ding! "It's Heinie Keister's and Clara Hebbing's wedding," Nell guessed. "Yes, that's Clara's brother on the horse," Tim agreed as he waved, thereby accepting the invitation. "They'll have a big time," Nell went on. "It's two years now since we had a real wedding here. It does my heart good to see 'em celebrating again. Low German weddings mean prosperity."Indications of a good harvest! The railroad! A town! The neighborhood was completely revolutionized. This section of the country, despite the ill fortune of past years, was determined to show other districts who were really progressive "when given half a chance."Allen called for volunteers to hasten the road through. People responded, giving teams and extra help.</p>
				<p>As settlers plowed their corn and saw the grain ripen, their thoughts were on the town, on the road, and they felt the elation and excitement which accompanies un ­usual progress.</p>
				<p>Tim began building his barn, and the townsmen their store buildings. . . . What would the town be called?</p>
				<p>Anyone interested was asked to propose a name; and a committee consisting of Connor, Allen, Schwartz, Van den Hull, and Dutch Fred was to judge. In all forty names were suggested--<emph>Connorstown</emph> being the choice of many. Tim didn't want that name "Connorstown"; <pb n="BLACK SOIL 279 "/>instead, he favored Casvales. This name was suggested by an ingenious railroad hand who had combined the first letter of the surnames of the committee and the new tradesmen in the town. Casvales: Connor--Allen-- Schwartz--Van den Hull--Altman (the hotelkeeper) --Lustfield (the saloonkeeper)--Engelke (the store­ keeper)--Schuknecht (Dutch Fred).</p>
				<p>"Wouldn't Casvale be more euphonious?" Allen asked blandly after all had been settled. Tim shook his head at him. "We've voted now. And Dutch Fred, the old standby, must not be omitted." "It's your town," Allen said, laughing. "So it is," Tim answered, and the committee nodded agreement.</p>
				<p>While the railroad was still miles away, Casvales appeared in white lettering on a diminutive red depot.</p>
				<p>Max Steindler raged at the method used in selecting a name. Did he not own six hundred and forty acres of land, besides Johann's one hundred and sixty, bordering the town? Was he not an early settler?</p>
				<p>Dutch Fred called to see him, and Max raved at this grievance. The visitor bowed over the bed, his long beard commingled with Max's, and consoled him: "The last s is for Steindler. Didn't you know that?" Max was satisfied.</p>
				<p>When Dutch Fred was chided by Schwartz for giving away his s, he answered: "Oh, Max he won't live long. That don't hurt. Max he can have that s until he dies once. Then I take it back again."Accustomed now to having strangers come into the yard at any hour of the day, the Connors were not startled when a cowboy swooped in from the trail. It   <pb n="280 BLACK SOIL "/>was Herman Schwartz, they knew, but he bore little resemblance to the former Herman. He had the same quiz­zical smile, but the restless expression in his eye had changed to a brazen look. The bull whackery had left its mark. He alighted easily, held the check strap, and shook hands with a sort of swagger.</p>
				<p>Sheila was shy. Herman, noting this, grew bolder and patronizing. "I told you I'd come back for you, Sheila. Pretty as ever. . . ." He winked at Tim as though they shared some secret. "Saw lots of 'em that look like you, but you got them beat."Nell rescued her. "Sheila is a teacher now, Herman." "Teacher? Glad she is. Cowpunchers don't stoop to nobodies." "Herman, you're joking." Nell could hardly be con­ vinced that he was serious. "Be your own self again," she begged. "Don't you paint and draw any more?" "Naw," with a guffaw. Looking around, he said: "It's the same old shiftless dump."</p><p>"Going to stay here long?" Tim broke in. "Lots of work here." "Yes, guess I'll dig and grade a while to bring in the road; but by winter I'll be off again. I'd die around here." "We don't want to be the cause of your death," Tim said, laughing. Herman was in the saddle again.</p>
				<p>"Going over to see Max's girls. I'll show them once what a cow punch looks like. S'long," and he was off, his small buckskin pony kicking up the dust on the trail.</p>
				<p>A sadness came over Nell Connor as she walked back to the house.  Does the country make the man, or the <pb n="BLACK SOIL 281 "/>man make the country?  There was gentle, stammering Herman, an artist--a hard-looking man now, a braggadocio, talking lightly to Sheila as her equal, yes, as her superior. How gratifying it was to see Sheila resent his boldness!</p>
				<p>"I thought cowboys were different," Danny said dis­gustedly. "He, I believe, is one dressed up for the occasion," Tim said, amused. "Ben was a cowboy once and he wasn't like Her ­man." "Herman's young yet; he'll learn," Tim answered.</p>
				<p>The community, while rejoicing in unprecedented bustle--the railroad moving nearer each day, a town, a post-office, an abundant harvest--was made to pause for a short time to bury Max. Max, the master of his house, lay dead in the darkened parlor. It was strange that in that house of death voices were raised and lowered at will. A tension was released. There was sorrow, a sor­row permeated with a subdued peace.</p>
				<p>Nell and Tim were with him during his last hours, Nell comforting his wife in an adjoining room, Tim sitting by the sick bed. It was at dawn, and after such a long silence that Tim thought the sick man would speak no more, Max said: "Box."Tim drew out the indicated box from under the bed and opened it, thinking that perhaps Max wished to make a will.</p>
				<p>Max indicated a roll of bills and a document--the deed to Johann's land. "Give to Sheila," he said. "I--   <pb n="282 BLACK SOIL "/>I know the father, and the mother is Indian. The name is there--Sheila's." That was all.</p>
				<p>In a short time the bushy-haired man was at peace. Not until then did Tim realize the significance of Max's words. Sheila an Indian! Ben had hinted that long ago, but he had not understood. Tim looked down at the deed in his hands. The roll of bills! "I know the father." Tim understood. The red-haired Max was her father! There was the name: "Shaylah vin." Indian! The very name the child had given on her arrival. It had sounded like Sheila Winnie. There was no surname. . . poor Sheila had quite a heritage.</p>
				<p>As Tim performed the duties of a neighbor in a house of death, he thought that if he had to choose between Sheila's parents he would choose the unknown Indian. But one cannot select parents. Neither should he censure the dead.</p>
				<p>As the settlement again resumed its varied interests, Tim was troubled with the secret of Sheila's legacy and parentage. The truth, he knew, must be made known to a few at least. He dreaded telling it, and to Nell most of all. But one day while they were alone in the kitchen, he told her of the inheritance and the paternity--he did not mention the mother.</p>
				<p>Nell steadied herself against the table. Her throat grew dry. Sharp pains darted through her swollen ankles. "Tim, you're fooling," she said finally, searching his face. "Surely that old grizzly bear . . . the father of such a mild, sweet girl. Well, it had to be someone. Sheila, no doubt, is like her mother, whoever she may <pb n="BLACK SOIL 283 "/>be. ... I'd like to know the mother. . . . His coloring of the hair--" "There he was all these years," Tim interposed, "living in lashins and lavins; and Sheila and ourselves--" "Well, it was God's will, Tim, that's all I have to say." "The land'll come in handy for her," Tim com­forted.</p>
				<p>But the quarter section of land meant little to Nell. She had lost her respect for land. In the past years the more land people had the poorer they were. She tried, however, to forget about Max and to consider the land as a means of sending Sheila to school. Yes, Sheila could go back East to school now. And Nell saw Sheila bearing a standard and carrying all the other Connors in her wake. "Poor Sheila," she said, "with such a father. And he settling right beside us ... the world is small after all. And isn't it strange, Tim, it's Johann's land? Poor fellow! Well, 'tis a queer world. And did Max tell you all that the night he died? And think of his wife--poor woman." <pb n="284"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXXIII">
				<p>MIDSUMMER found the town of Casvales in a whir of industry. Stores and homes, both permanent and temporary, were being erected in the stubble where Connor lately had grown barley.</p>
				<p>Sand for plaster was being hauled from a pit in Sioux county. In the Connor yard the skeleton of a pine barn shouldered above the grove. As Ben had ordained, it indicated the location of the town for miles around.</p>
				<p>Harvest was at its height; there was a heavy yield. Commingled with whirring harvesters were pounding of nails, sawing of boards, intermittent whistles of the distant locomotive, shouting of men, laughter of Ellen and Alice in the pile of shavings, slamming of the new screen door, pumping of water, rattling of dishes, and the discordant bawling of Bluey, whose calf was lost on the prairie. Above this pageant of prosperity the summer sun glowed, and a south breeze stirred its golden light until it shimmered before the eye.</p>
				<p>Nell, her graying hair smoothed back from her full, high forehead and rolled in a tight knot, her wrapper open at the throat and gathered about the waist with a checkered apron, her eyes clear and alert, cooked for carpenters, harvesters, and children. Her heart was grate­ful for the scene before her.  Her rugged constitution gloried in accepting a share of the ceaseless industry; only her limbs rebelled and grew numb in the long hours of duty. Evenings, however, brought a respite. While the men smoked and relaxed, Nell went off to <pb n="BLACK SOIL 285"/>bed, where she fell asleep immediately, often not to waken until duties of a new day began once more.</p>
				<p>One warm afternoon as Nell prepared an early sup ­per, she anticipated a long, restful evening, as Tim and the men were going over to see the progress made on the road; but supper dishes were scarcely put away when Max's Annie drove into the yard and summoned Nell to the bedside of her mother--her hour was at hand. Nell left immediately; Tim, Danny, and Margaret ac­ companied the men who drove away in the wagon, wagering and speculating as to whether or no the road would reach the town in a month. Kitty Ann and Robert Emmet were out looking for Bluey's calf. Sheila was alone with Ellen and Alice. She put the little girls to bed and sat down on the doorstep.</p>
				<p>Sheila was tired, too tired, she told them, to go over and see the road. In her heart she knew that she cared little for the road. In a month a train would pull into the town, and there would be a celebration. The rail­ road would run through her land, the land which Pop had bought from Max with money received from her real parents--so Pop had  said. Who were her real parents, anyway? Whoever they were, they had entered her life again and had given her property from which she would procure an income. The Connors would send her to school now. Why should her real parents, so long dead, rise from their graves and ally themselves with Mom? Why should they interfere? Why should everyone, everything, unite to restrict and confine her more and more as she grew older? Now when she wanted freedom, more freedom!</p>
				<p>She looked into the bright night for answer. The air   <pb n="286 BLACK SOIL "/>was heavy with dew: stars were clear and distant. Kitty Ann's and Robert Emmet's arguments grew louder as they neared the house.</p>
				<p>"I didn't go over near Johann's shanty," Robert Emmet made excuse. "I saw--maybe banshees there." "Oh, Emmet, Pop's only fooling 'bout banshees. Besides, fairies 're only in Ireland."</p><p>"I heard 'em though; but maybe it's a girl singing there like Wild Goose said. You know, about the girl in the lake one time." "Oh, them's all lies. Danny said so."From the direction in which the children were com­ing, Sheila heard the bleating of the calf. She stood, released her braids of hair which duty had required her to fasten up on her head before supper, and opened the collar of her dress. The cool air eased the stifling in her throat occasioned by the thought of the future. Why did Mom insist that she teach school and go away to school, when there was a big world here to roam . . . and a lover somewhere waiting!</p>
				<p>"Go to bed, children," she said, "and I'll go and look for the calf." She stood for an instant listening. ... Only the sounds of evening: a mourning dove in the willows, the prolonged bellow of Bluey, a cricket, the children quar­reling over the wash basin: "I was washing my feet, and you . . ."Sheila passed the gaping, silent barn, the thatched shed where mud swallows chirped sleepily and pigs gave an occasional grunt, through barley stubble where pine buildings shone spectral, put to the wild hay land.</p>
				<p>It was moonlight on the prairie. The moonlight was <pb n="BLACK SOIL 287 "/>more than mere light; it was the essence of the air. It flooded the earth.</p>
				<p>Sheila raised her skirts from the heavy dew and breathed deeply of the night, pausing, listening, waiting. There was no sound. The moonlight enveloped her, cutting her off from the earth; the Connors, teach­ing, books, lumber yard, railroad, seemed far away indeed. In this wild, unbroken land she was <emph>free</emph>! She extended a hand, hoping to restrain the old life. It must not again overpower her! Raising her face to the light, she anticipated, she longed for--she knew not what. Her heart beat wildly.</p>
				<p>The white air shifted slightly and a figure stood be­ fore her. The sheen of dew was on his black hair, and his eyes--his eyes had caught hers and were holding them. A faint smile broke the tenseness of his look. He folded his arms. "Sun-in-the-Hair. You are waiting."And Sheila, knowing him to be an answer to all the unspoken wishes and desires of her life, advanced a step. He moved; and she was enfolded in arms hard as iron. "Sun-in-the-Hair."Sheila's heart answered: "My deliverer, I will follow." Her lips said: "I--I was waiting--looking--" Disengaging herself: "Did you hear a little calf bleat­ing?" At mention of the prosaic calf a flood of duty and remorse swept over her. Mom! Her advice! Her warnings! Oh, what have I done! Her heart answered: "I don't care--I don't care."Wild Goose was speaking, saying something about the little calf. He turned.</p>
				<p>After the white air had swallowed him, Sheila stood waiting. She knew that she should remain there, but   <pb n="288 BLACK SOIL "/>remorse had cut away the moonlighted world. The in ­discretion of her surrender assumed gigantic proportions; it overpowered her. She turned and ran towards Connors' house. As her skirts swished through the stubble, she imagined that she was being pursued. She hastened her steps. Out of breath, she reached the yard, to find a horse there. Herman, too; he came to meet her.</p>
				<p>"Gosh, Sheila, ain't this moonlight? You ought to have seen the moonlight on the Pacific Ocean." Herman was less overbearing than on his previous visit.</p>
				<p>Sheila sank down on the doorstep. "They're all gone away over to the railroad," she answered irrelevantly. "But it's you I came to see," Herman said, taking a seat beside her. "But you won't look at a fellow."Sheila leaned her head against the door. "I'll talk to you some other time. I'm tired, too tired tonight, Herman."Seeing her physically spent, he commented: "Huh, they make you work like hell here, don't they? Can't even talk to a fellow. Now I want to talk to you about things. You and me were always good friends when we were young, weren't we?"<emph>Wild Goose will be coming with that calf! Wild Goose!</emph>"Go now, Herman," she begged, "and come some other time. Please go, Herman. I'm--go on' Herman." Herman, with feigned gallantry, whisked off on his horse; Wild Goose stepped from behind the barn with the calf across his shoulders.</p>
				<p>Sheila raised her face, but failed in her attempt at the explanation she thought due.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 289"/>He answered: "Calf needs milk." With his assurance and presence, peace of mind returned to her. "Bluey is my cow," she told him, as they released the calf. And she led her guest to the doorstep before which so many air castles had been builded, shattered, and builded again.</p>
				<p>They spoke little; but much was said in their silence. Thoughtless crickets chirped.  Unknowing bullfrogs, croaked. The dove in the willows ceased to mourn.</p>
				<p>At the rumble of the wagon, Sheila and Wild Goose rose to their feet. Wild Goose caught Sheila in his arms. When he attempted to release her, she clung to him. "Take me away now," she begged. "Take me with you."Wild Goose did not reply immediately. He pursed his lips into her hair, then raised his eyes to the sky.</p>
				<p>On just such starlit nights he had roamed the prairie of Dakota and had prayed to the Great Spirit to show him how to win Sun-in-the-Hair in the white man's way. And the Great Spirit had heard his prayer. He would never carry away a white girl! And Kind Woman must not grieve. In a measure he sensed Nell's depth of feeling on that trip to Casper Center a few years before. Kind Woman had said: "Lena and Lou must go before the priest." As in panorama, that night in all its solemnity and significance passed before his eyes.</p>
				<p>He raised his lips from Sheila's hair, and spoke as though to the stars: "Kind Woman must not grieve. We will go first before a white father. Kind Woman--" "Mom, you mean? She won't let me go!" Sheila argued, sobbing. "If I tell her she won't let me go."   <pb n="290 BLACK SOIL "/>The voice of Wild Goose was calm and convincing. "Kind Woman will not say no. Wild Goose will tell her now--"The wagon was drawing near. "She's not with them; she's over to Max's. They're coming! Go, Wild Goose, go!"</p><p>"Wild Goose will go. You tell him, your father, then. You tell him before themoon dies tonight." "Go now. I'll--I'll tell him," she said hesitantly. But Wild Goose was authoritative. "Before this moon dies tonight."Sheila went to her room, where Kitty Ann lay ensconced on a patch quilt, her white arms encircling her head. Was that Kitty Ann? <emph>Yes, that was Kitty Ann</emph>. As she placed the child in her proper one-third of the bed, she dreaded the talk with Pop. It was well that Mom was not there; Mom would not understand. But with this dread, the joy of life, sweet life, throbbed in her subconscious self. Wild Goose was master. There could be no difficulties. The small bedroom was strange. The pictures: <emph>Waiting for the Tide at Venice</emph>, Mom's Uncle Henry--what were they? Shadowy survivals of a childhood that was gone, a life that was over.</p>
				<p>Margaret rushed in excitedly. "Road's clear up to Mill creek! They're putting in a bridge there! Think of it, Sheila! By threshing time we can see them working! Danny's going to be waterboy next week!"That was Margaret! Yes, Margaret, another Connor. A girl almost as tall as Sheila herself, slender, vivacious, with blue eyes flashing, red lips parted, and a braid of brown hair switching her back. Yes, that was Margaret.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 291"/>"But don't tell Mom," Margaret was still speaking: "But Danny's going to drive the engine into town that day. Of course the engineer will be right beside him. Ben did it. He asked Mr. Allen. Sheila, Edgar was there tonight, and I got another book. He sent clear to Buffalo for it so I could read it. Say, Sheila, what's the matter with you? You look so different. Are you sick or something?"</p><p>"No, I'm not sick. Get down on your knees and pray for me while I talk to Pop. Pray, Margaret--you can pray better than I. I'll tell you why later on; but pray now, Margaret, on your knees."Alarmed, Margaret obeyed. Seeing her kneeling beside the bed, Sheila went out and closed the bedroom door.</p>
				<p>Tim was sitting on a chair in the kitchen, taking off his boots.</p>
				<p>How could she tell him? Wild Goose was an Indian. She glanced out the door. What if the moon had set and she had not obeyed! "See ye found the calf." Tim was patting the sole of a boot as he emptied its chaff into the cob box. "Yes." Tim looked up quickly. "Trouble, Sheila? Anything wrong? Any word from Max's?"</p><p>"No." Why should Sheila now be overpowered with a flood of reminiscences? Never before had she been so aware of Pop's liberality, his understanding. He had never failed her. She recalled many of the sacrifices that he had made for her. How vividly she could remember the day of her arrival years before! Pop had poured out   <pb n="292 BLACK SOIL "/>the kerosene from that lamp so that Mom might cleanse her hair.</p>
				<p>She could not speak. She stood by the table and with a forefinger diligently traced a pattern in the new oil­ cloth which had been bought on the arrival of carpenters.</p>
				<p>"Not wanting to go off with Herman, are yuh?" Tim said as a joke. "No--not Herman." "Who? Has any of the carpenters been throwing sheep's eyes?" "No--it's Wild Goose." "Wild Goose! Sure, he hasn't been here the past year." "He was here tonight."Tim stood before her. The clock ticked, ticked; the lamp wick responded to a whiff of wind and made a quivering in the light and shadows of the room.</p>
				<p>"Do you like Wild Goose pretty well?" Tim laid a hand on her shoulder. He raised her face. Sheila flung herself into his arms, sobbing. "I-- guess, I love him, Pop. I want to go with him any ­where--to the end of the earth."Tim was staring at the floor, staring and holding his breath--another girl had said those same words. "We won't stand between you and your happineses [sic], Sheila, but it will be hard on Nell."Encouraged, the girl went on. "I don't care for teach­ing and schooling. Your young ones can have my land --and I know I love him better than Mom or anybody . . . and Pop, I would have gone away with him tonight <pb n="BLACK SOIL 293 "/>if he would take me. He wants you and Mom to know of it and for us to marry before a priest."</p><p>"Thank God, child, some one of you had sense. That would have killed Nell, and you know it. Nell has placed great stock in you. We'll see, Sheila, I'll have a talk with the young fellow. Over to Johann's shanty, I suppose. I wish he'd come and go like a white man . . . I'll tell him so."</p><p>"You won't send him away!" Sheila withdrew from Tim's arms. Dark fires which had been smoldering in her eyes flashed now. "No, Sheila. Nell and meself'll stand by you. Say nothing of it for the present."Danny, tall and loose-jointed, ambled into the house, slamming the screen door with a generous swing. At his step Tim turned to wind the clock. "I'll be glad when we get a house where I won't have to sleep in a cupola," the boy complained. "I'm going out in the barn soon as the roof's on."Tim, in response, wound the old clock, and it gy­rated noisily. Sheila poked at the ashes in the stove and laid cobs for the morning fire.</p>
				<p>Danny, ignoring the ladder stairway, swung himself into the loft by his arms.</p>
				<p>"Sheila," he called down, "you should have seen Herman. He's not a cowboy tonight; he's a jimdandy. He was over there at Beavers' when we passed, talking to Louisa, He can have Louisa Beaver. He thought all he had to do was to come back and take you. You had better not have anything to do with him. Train men don't like him. You should hear him brag; you'd think   <pb n="294 BLACK SOIL "/>he discovered the Rocky Mountains." Shoes dropped on the floor. "Bet you if he saw that young Indian now he'd run faster than ever, and hide a few more years."</p><p>"Oh, dry up, Danny," Tim commented. "Give us a rest with your Herman. Get some sleep now, or you will be a mile behind the binder tomorrow. Can't expect to be a waterboy next week if that shocking isn't done." <pb n="295"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXXIV   ">
				<p>THE next morning Pete Schwartz stopped at Connors' and told them that the wife of Max had a son.</p>
				<p>On hearing this, Tim hitched Ned to the sulky and dispatched Kitty Ann for Nell. Max's wife had daughters there to look after her, he reasoned, and Nell was needed at home; there were things that must be told her soon. Tim had not slept during the night. At times he was tempted to seek out Wild Goose in the deserted shanty, but he finally decided that it would be better, perhaps, to bide his time.</p>
				<p>Kitty Ann braced her sturdy legs against the lattice bottomed sulky and urged Ned toward Max's. She an­ticipated something extraordinary, she hardly knew what. But births were often accompanied by unusual events. Now, when Pop was born in Ireland the year of The Big Wind, the waves of the ocean flopped right up on the land and left fish there. When Alice was born, the land was brown with grasshoppers. And her own birth, she felt, was especially favored. She associated it with the legend told among pioneer women, how on one occasion a young mother, alone to greet her child, was visited by the Mother of God, who, mindful of Bethlehem, came and administered to her.</p>
				<p>There was nearly always mystery connected with new babies, she concluded, as she brought the reins down sharply on old Ned's back. But Ned was as un­ feeling as he was sightless. He had one gait and no more.   <pb n="296 BLACK SOIL "/>This Kitty Ann knew, but she continued to urge him by standing and slapping him with the reins.</p>
				<p>There was nothing unusual in Max's yard. In the house, Mom was dressing Max's son--he wasn't much to see; he was red and scrawny. Katto was there, sitting close by, "jawing Mom." "What for your Sheila don't make up to my Her­ man?"Nell gently inserted a very small fist into a flannel sleeve, and answered: "Oh, Katto, they're too young to be serious. They both have a great life ahead of 'em before they think of getting married. We're figuring on sending Sheila East to school in the fall."Mary Steindler interposed from the kitchen where she was kneading bread: "You say Sheila shall go to school. Sheila does not like school. You are boss over Sheila, I guess."</p><p>"Gosh, she's homely," thought Kitty Ann. "And fatter than Mom!" Kitty Ann was standing between the two rooms, leaning against the jamb, one bare foot atop the other.</p>
				<p>Mary had been more sullen since her father's death, while Annie and Katie were buoyant and gay in their new freedom. These two were on their way to town this morning, so Kitty Ann could not talk to them.</p>
				<p>"Oh, Sheila will like it when she gets acquainted; it's just homesickness she's afraid of," Nell ignored Mary's thrust.</p>
				<p>Katto leaned back in her chair. "Well, Herman he is a smart one, too, but, by Gutt, he don't have to go to Massachusey to get his brains. He don't want to be artist any more, but he has a good time."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 297"/>  Max's wife smiled on the group, her tanned skin leathery on the bleached pillow case. She called Kitty Ann to her and whispered: "Tell Mary once I say that she shall give you orange."Katto, with lowered voice, spoke again to Nell. Their argument apparently was at an end. "Max is dead and now he got a boy."</p><p>"Yes, Katto; it's a queer world, whatever." Nell wrapped the baby in a shawl and placed it beside its mother. "I'll be going now," she said to Mrs. Steindler. "If you want me send over and I'll come." Max's wife could not speak. Tears rushed from her eyes and down her furrowed cheeks.</p>
				<p>Kitty Ann was circling around Mary in the kitchen. Mary was kneading the bread with vengeance, and her coil of red hair nodded as if to say: "You won't get an orange. You're afraid to ask for it." Kitty Ann accepted the challenge. "Mary," she said. Mary's broad back did not turn. The coil of red hair nodded wickedly. "Mary--your mother said--I could have an orange." Mary did not heed.</p>
				<p>Katto's round figure filled the doorway.  "Mary," she said, "your mother say that you shall give Kitty an orange." "Well, can't you wait once till I get my hands from dough?" Mary answered in ill humor. "Come along, Kitty Ann," Nell called, "we'll be going." Mary continued to knead vigorously.</p>
				<p>Max's wife called meekly from the bedroom. There­ upon Katto went to the cupboard, unearthed an orange,   <pb n="298 BLACK SOIL "/>and handed it to Kitty Ann. "Mary," she said ironically, "too bad, by Gutt, that some man don't know how you like to mix bread."After Nell and Kitty Ann had started out in the road cart, Kitty Ann made a "hollow" in her calico lap and deposited the orange peel as she ate the juicy center. "Poor Mary, I wish she could take a trip and visit somewhere when her mother is better," Nell said thoughtfully. "Who would ask her to visit?--I wouldn't," Kitty Ann commented. "Child, have you eaten all the orange? Why didn't you save a quarter for the others?"</p><p>"I'll take them some peelings," Kitty Ann answered. She scooped a piece automatically now, making parallel furrows with her two permanent frontals. "Don't take them anything, then. Say nothing to them at all about it."Kitty Ann scooped all the peel and tossed it over her head--all except one small piece which she secreted in the pocket of her apron. She wouldn't tell them she had had an orange. No. But as soon as all were with her she would accidentally find this bit of peel and say: "What is this?  Oh, yes..."While Nell lightly swung her feet over the sulky wheel and alighted, Tim, on a pretext of getting a drink of water, came into the yard. Together they viewed progress made on the barn; then with a significant nod Tim drew Nell behind the haystack. He didn't speak at once. His eyelids quivered, and beads of sweat stood on his face.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 299"/>"For God's sake, what's wrong, Tim? Out with it. I felt as though something was up when you sent for me." "It's Sheila, Nell. It's really two things" "No one's harmed her, have they?" "No--Nell, no." "Well, then, tell me anything." Nell looked rather defiantly at her husband.</p>
				<p>It was hard for Tim. He shifted his weight, pulled a straw of bluejoint from the haystack and chewed it thoughtfully. "I always felt this day would come." "Out with it." "First, Nell, I'll tell you that her mother was an Indian." "Max told you that, did he?" "He did; and I've carried the secret around with me since." Nell turned pale. She closed her eyes for an instant. "I'd never think that, Tim. That's what Max had to humble me--but he won't humble me . . ." "People boast of Indian blood," Tim consoled. "You remember Cutlers in Springfield, don't you?"</p><p>"Yes, I remember Cutlers in Springfield. The other thing, Tim. It's not that Herman's coming here . . . Sheila doesn't care about Herman." "Wild Goose--" "Go on, Tim, I'm prepared for anything now." "Wild Goose is here again--and she tells me she wants to go away with him. Wouldn't that chestfounder you?"Nell swayed a little and steadied herself against the haystack. Tim went on: "She told me last night. She loves   <pb n="300 BLACK SOIL "/>him, she says, and met him here last night. I told her nothing of her mother; but promised her we'd do as we always have--stand by her." "Wild Goose!--That savage!--Sheila!--" "Don't go too hard on him, Nell. Sheila would have gone away with him--" "Glory be to God ..." "--but he refused to take her. I guess of the two he has the more character."</p><p>"You talk of character, Tim, in one so young. She's so young, you see, so young." Nell turned away. The white barn swam before her eyes; the house came to ­ward her. On entering the kitchen she leaned against the wall.</p>
				<p>Margaret was peeling potatoes, and Sheila was scrubbing the floor. Nell's eyes lingered on Sheila, her perfectly formed shoulders and hips. <emph>Carrying the heavies  burden</emph>. <emph>The coldest place in the tent</emph>. Aloud she said: "Margaret, how many times have I told you not to take such a thick skin?" Her voice was strident and at the breaking point. The girls turned flushed faces in her direction.</p>
				<p>Nell reached the bedroom, latched the door, and threw herself down on the bed. Alice and Ellen clamored for admittance, but were unheeded. Nell lay quiet, her eyes unseeingly fixed on the wall with the broken plaster. In her calm she realized that in this as in all other things she must be reconciled to His indomitable will. Her spirit of fight was of no avail; she must accept fate. Her recent flash of anger went out like the lightning of a storm. She got up from her bed with a feeling akin to that experienced after the birth of her children <pb n="BLACK SOIL 301"/>here in this room--she had been down in the valley for a while, but now she was up in the heights again.</p>
				<p>She unlatched the door to Alice, who wore a wig of shavings and an apron of leaves. "It's God's will."Realizing that she had not given her family a pleasant greeting, she called to the girls in the kitchen: "Children I see you got along fine without me. You must go over and see the new baby--cute little fellow, small and dark like Mrs. Max."  Poor Sheila.   He's her half brother and she doesn't even know it. She must be told some things! . . . but when? Nell bathed her face, combed her hair changed her wrapper, and rattled up some custard pies for the men's dinner. <pb n="302"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXXV ">
				<p>"HE'S a fine specimen of an Indian lad," Tim began, as he reported his conversation with Wild Goose. Nell, waiting in one of the stalls of the new barn for Tim's return from his visit to Johann's shanty, raised a haggard face. "I told him--as we planned-- that we did not disapprove of him," Tim went on, "but that Sheila was very young; they should wait-- say a year."</p><p>"And what did he say to that?" Nell asked. Nell had aged since morning; there was a droop in the corner of her eyes. She spoke hoarsely. "And what did he say to that?"</p><p>"He's proud. He drew himself up and told how his blood was of chiefs and our own white people. And how his grandmother worshipped our Great Spirit. How she had loved the Indians and had come back to die among them. 'So, too,' he said, 'Sheila would love them.' I like the fellow." Tim was pleased. "He seems upright enough. He's going away now, but he's coming back again next year when the grain is yellow. I told him that I would then tell him something that might please him."Nell was in tears. "If she would only get kindness at his hands!" "Don't worry about that, Nell. He seems honorable. He'll be kind." "But his idea of kindness is not ours." "Perhaps it will suit her." Tim, quite satisfied, drew out his pipe and joined a group of carpenters for a chat.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 303"/>Nell, not convinced, decided to see the lad at once. So she met him in the field as he was approaching the house. "You'll be good to her?" she asked, raising a tearstained face to the young Indian.</p>
				<p>Wild Goose stood erect, folded his arms, and smiled. It was an indulgent smile. "Kind Woman," he said, "you have many children. You have much care. Sun-in-the-Hair will be safe with me." Nell had no answer.</p>
				<p>Nell and Tim soon shared the secret of Sheila's parentage with Ben. Ben, sitting on Connors' doorstep as they confiden­tially told the story, drew a match across the sole of his boot, squinted faded blue eyes, lighted his pipe and tossed the smouldering match toward a tuft of grass. "I always expected that--the Indian strain. The red hair fooled me a little. Didn't expect she had more than a quarter; but I recognized it first time I set eyes on her. I'll look up this Wild Goose when I go West again. Might as well let her off with him."But Nell was determined, despite all opposition, to send Sheila East to school for one year. "She'll meet people there," she argued, "and maybe forget all about this mysterious fellow."</p><p>"Would that be fair, for us to put her in the way of marrying a white man, he not knowing her race?" Tim questioned. "Whom will she marry, if not an Indian?" "And the fellow has some White in him," Ben helped out. "God made them and He matched them, is my way of thinking." And Tim puffed his pipe nervously.</p>
				<p>Ben nodded in agreement, but Nell was unsatisfied.   <pb n="304 BLACK SOIL "/>"They were raised different. He's wild . . . the Lord only knows what he eats." "He's had Christian training, and has property." "And some schooling," Tim seconded. "And he's stood the test of honor better than herself."Nell couldn't argue; neither could she be convinced. She could only try to resign herself, while a dull ache throbbed in her heart. "Better not leave her out of our hands till we have him or some other responsible person to look after her."</p><p>"Tim, was there ever a man more aggravating? As though ..." Nell could not finish. She moved away from the men. Tim and Ben smoked on in silence.</p>
				<p>Wild Goose stayed but a few days longer. He left as mysteriously as he came, and his name was seldom men­tioned. Johann's shanty was moved near the group of buildings forming Casvales. The building which had first served the Hurds as a granary, later to be occupied by Johann and lastly by Wild Goose, was converted into a blacksmith and cobbling shop.</p>
				<p>"Webber's going to be able to shoe anything from a buffalo to a grasshopper, but it's Lustfield who is going to put the skates on," Tim started the joke around.</p>
				<p>The young Connors found many interests in this new shop. Horseshoeing! Cobbling! Each day brought something novel. Wonderful things were coming to pass at their very door. The barn, having received its coat of shingles, now scintillated in the sun and sloped down conveniently from horse barn to cow shed, calf shed, pig shed. It was a tower! A palace! Ireland even could never boast of such. What a place to climb! And from <pb n="BLACK SOIL 305 "/>the calf shed Kitty Ann could touch the branches of a cottonwood. When the tree grew larger she would try to swing on its branches as Mom had swung on beeches! What a fascination in mangers, alley way, trap door, grain chute! All the children wished that they might live in the big, clean barn; but only Danny was allowed the privilege of sleeping there. Beside this imposing creation, the old black hatcher-of-a-house squatted and clucked unheeded.</p>
				<p>The road was making progress. The advance guard-- men with horses and scrapers--was already in sight, throwing up a black ridge in the level field. Followed the laying of ties at proper intervals, the setting of rails, the driving of spikes; and the engine hauling supplies and equipment moved nearer and nearer.</p>
				<p>School claimed the children before the town was reached. Sheila, relieved that Nell would not send her off to school, gladly resumed her teaching; though apparently happy, she was quiet and more withdrawn from the Connors than before.</p>
				<p>Danny was taking a man's place in the community-- threshing, driving a team on the road, hauling lumber. Tim had many interests. "A jack of all trades and a master of non" he commented thereon. What with the threshing and the care of the stock, he had a lumber office; on one window was printed, <emph>Lumber</emph>; on the other, <emph>Lawyer.</emph>Nell had only Alice at home with her now. Alice did not give much trouble; she contentedly built barns and stores of clean pine blocks. As Nell went about her work sometimes she limped a little to ease her more pain­ful limb, but mostly she moved with a light, quick step.    <pb n="306 BLACK SOIL "/>The railroad coming to her door was symbolical to Nell. It was like the hand of God reaching out connecting them with the culture and civilization of the East. The railroad was making amends now! How cru­elly it had deposited them at its terminus, years before, and had turned around and gone back East! She antici­pated some satisfaction now in not viewing the train at all until it entered formally into the town.</p>
				<p>As this celebration drew near, great were the preparations. The entire community was to view the train pull­ing into the town of Casvales. An immense bowery was laid; seats of planks were arranged, and a grandstand for speeches and for the band. Tim was asked to augment a Sioux City band with his flute.</p>
				<p>Men worked all the night before; and when the first bars of pink shot from the eastern horizon, wagons loaded with men, women and children were arriving. By the time the sun peeped over Schwartzes' grove it viewed an unusual, variegated blot on the tramped stubble: flags, white pine, people, teams, wagons, the long ridge of black earth.</p>
				<p>The Connor children were awake and out in the crowd without a thought of breakfast. The band had arrived!</p>
				<p>Tim, flute in hand, hastened from the house and as quickly returned. "Come on, Nell," he called; "come out here now, where you can see the train. It's coming, Nell!"Nell stood before him. "Tim," she said, "I don't want you to touch a drop of anything today. You shouldn't, Tim, if all the men in the world ask you. It <pb n="BLACK SOIL 307 "/>wouldn't be right. . . . And you know you can't stand anything." "I won't," Tim answered solemnly, "if you come out close enough to see the train. Promise me this now--I must be off."</p><p>"I'll go out, Tim; but I'll stand here for the present, to get the first glimpse from our own doorway as I al­ ways said I would. I'll dress up and go out in the crowd later on; but I have a baking here to do, and Alice is in bed yet."A cornet sounded. Tim hurried from the house. Nell slid two long pans of bread into the oven. A prolonged whistle sounded through the house. The old black hatcher stirred irritably as the reverberations jarred its feathers.</p>
				<p>Nell put the lid on the stove, closed the drafts, took Alice in her arms, and went to the doorstep. A train decorated with bunting was crawling like a gay caterpillar through Schwartzes' hayland. Now it was entering Connors' stubble! The band struck up <emph>America</emph>--it was entering the town!</p>
				<p>Nell, carrying Alice, joined the crowd. Margaret found her and pulled her closer to the train. "See Danny, Mom?"Glory be to God! There was Danny, wearing a train­ man's cap and a bunting sash, in the engineer's box! His slim face was set, his chin firm.. He looked neither to right nor left, but kept his eyes fixed on the track ahead and held firmly to the throttle of the engine.</p>
				<p>People cheered and tossed hats into the air. There were hymns, too. While the children joined with the band in <emph>My Country, 'Tis of Thee</emph>, old Germans moved   <pb n="308 BLACK SOIL "/>together and added: Grosser Gott, wit loben Dich. . . ."Nell, holding tightly to the bewildered Alice, raised her apron to her eyes and cried with joy. There was Danny, driving a train into their land! . . . Their town! . . . The last time that she had seen a train. . . . "We knew Danny all the time," her children shouted as they pressed against her. "What's the matter, Mom? Oh, Mom's crying." "Children, the last time I saw a train it was leaving us, and I thought I'd die with the lonesome--" "And now it's come to us," Margaret said happily, using Nell's own words. "Come on, Mom." Kitty Ann was tugging at her arm. "What is it, child?" "Pop said for you to come. They want you in the picture."As Nell moved with the children to be photo­ graphed, she thought: "I'll send one back East . . . but what will they think of my old wrapper, and Alice, poor child, in her nightgown!"Once in the crowd she exchanged greetings with many: those with small children she invited to the house. The younger Breidbarths broke away from the hands of their elders and clung to her.</p>
				<p>The first ceremony was the christening of the town. No preparation had been made for this ritual, as it had only now been suggested by Jim Long. Lustfield do­nated a bottle of wine. "Where's a pretty girl, now, for sponsor?" they asked.</p>
				<p>"I'll find a girl," Nell volunteered. With Van den Hulls she had noticed a Dutch girl in <pb n="BLACK SOIL 309 "/>native costume. Evidently just landed. A white cap partly covered the yellowest hair that she had ever seen. Her fair skin was tinted with color; she was alert, animated. Just the girl!</p>
				<p>Jack Van den Hull acted as interpreter, telling the bewildered girl details of the ceremony which she had been chosen to enact. She nodded as he explained. In her face was fear and timidity, yet there was the acquiescence found in the look of many immigrants. "I don't know what it all means, but I'm willing."The girl religiously took the bottle, braced a wooden shoe against a railroad tie, leaned over, broke the bottle on a rail, and pronounced thickly: <emph>Casvales</emph>, While the shimmering golden fluid dried in the sun, the band played once more, and people shouted wildly.</p>
				<p>Katto and others resented this honor shown the Dutch. "Dutch," Katto said bitterly. "You think, by Gutt, we got no Germans here. Dutch they got a town over farther. This is not their town."Nell, knowing that Danny's place of prominence was no doubt included in her grievance, was nonplussed. "What harm, Katto, what harm?" she said. But later, when she heard that Katto's son, Pete, had caught the greasy pig, she was pleased, Things were evened up now. There must be no hard feelings on this great day.</p>
				<p>There were other contests, and dancing, and excessive drinking. "Settin' 'em up" was the order of the day. Old prejudices and traditions were apparently forgotten. Strange, shy people smiled ingenuously at each other.</p>
				<p>It was a motley crowd. No uniformity of dress. Hickory shirts and jeans. Green-black wedding suits. A few   <pb n="310 BLACK SOIL "/>swaggering young men in boughten clothes. Roadhands shaved for the occasion. Swarthy peddlers in sweaty coats. The speaker of the day, Jim Long, in a high hat and swallow-tailed coat--few recognized him. Silk dresses enlarged by bright new gores. Flashy calicoes. Immigrant women in shawls, full skirts, and light aprons. The Dutch in wooden shoes--little boys in full trousers fastened to the waist with large white buttons. Nell Connor in a faded wrapper. Alice in a nightgown.</p>
				<p>Nell, while greeting distinguished guests from the county seat, thought of her bread in the oven. Excusing herself, she picked up Alice and hurried to the house. The crust of the bread was burned black, but that could be scraped off. The fire was out. Lord save us, it was eleven o'clock and not a sign of dinner, or a tap of work done! The children had eaten no breakfast. Chiding her ­self, she rekindled the fire and put a cake into the oven. She dressed Alice and made up the beds. None too soon. The women were arriving with their babies.</p>
				<p>At noon clans became conspicuous as people gathered in their respective groups to eat. When the Connor children came trooping in, all talking at once, Nell hushed them. The beds were filled with babies! Luxemberger slept peacefully beside High German, German beside Dutch. Max's son occupied Alice's cradle.</p>
				<p>Kitty Ann complained: "We can't even talk, and other people are having picnics with chicken 'n' every­ thing."Nell felt a little guilty. "We'll have our chicken and our picnic some other day to make up for this," she told them. "Eat up your bread and milk now, and I have a cake for you, cooling."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 311"/>They were surprised to see Tim coming--Tim and Danny had been invited by the railroad officials to eat at the hotel. "I gave me place to young Peck down from the county seat. He had no place to eat," Tim explained. "Danny is enough to represent the family."</p><p>"Come here, Tim," Nell called him into the bed­ room where the children were sleeping. There was some ­thing prophetic in the rows of soft babies, their hands outstretched over their heads, their satiny skins, their plump curved legs, their chunky bodies. "The railroad and the town are not for me nor for you, Tim, but for them, them and for ours outside."Tim drew closer. "Look at their fists doubled up ready for each other! Them Hollander babies are the color of skimmed milk. Max's son is the brunette of the crowd. Please God, may they never know what it is to be cut off from a railroad." "And civilization," Nell added.</p>
				<p>"Here's a bottle of wine Lustfield sent to the women folks," Tim said, unearthing a flask. "Give 'em some if they want it; the men are getting more than their share."After dinner women coming to reclaim their children stayed on in the shade of the house. The sun shone in­ tensely on the stubble and town. Children sought out the grove. One woman whom Nell had not noticed before sank weakly onto the doorstep. Her baby was very young. "How old?" Nell asked. "Two weeks," she replied, smiling with colorless lips.</p>
				<p>"Two weeks!" Nell repeated. "Here, lie right down on this lounge and I'll give you a little wine. Stop right <pb n="312 BLACK SOIL "/>here till your husband comes after you." Nell still wore the wrapper of the morning.</p>
				<p>By mid-afternoon, resolutions of peace and good fellowship were numbed by beer. Quarreling began. The music ceased. The band left. There was only the clamor of voices: threats, epithets.</p>
				<p>"Oh, Mom! Breidbarth is fighting someone and his children are crying," the young Connors reported.</p>
				<p>Nell went over to the bowery, where Emil, the eldest Breidbarth boy, and Lizzie Abel were sitting. "Emil," Nell called, "come now and get your father and load up the children and start for home."Emil loved to dance with Lizzie, yet he was fond of Nell Connor. He lowered his big, blonde head, but raised his clear, gray eyes. "I want for to dance once more the schottish." "You better not wait, Emil. Go along with him, Liz­zie," Nell added, as Emil obeyed reluctantly.</p>
				<p>Nell returned to her house to meet the father of the very young infant. He was a shy, husky man; and Nell was pleased to see that he had not drunk too much. They left for home, the young mother holding the babe perched upon the high wagon seat.</p>
				<p>As the sun lowered, women hitched the teams, lifted tired children into the wagons, coaxed their men from the bar, and helped them to wagon seats; then picking up the reins they drove home, the rumbling of their wagons echoing to each other across the level land.</p>
				<p>On the long ridge of black earth, two rails glistening like lines of fire pointed first to the east and then to the setting sun. A small train engine in tattered bunting shrieked a prolonged Godspeed. <pb n="313"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXXVI">
				<p>SPRING came again to the prairie, but the hues and tints of its illimitable green were defined by sharp corners--barbed wire had made a checker board of the country. It was settlers now who determined where should be a square of bluish-green oats, or a rectangle of greenish-blue hayland. Along the railroad track lush grass and flowers, after their recent upheaval, again found footing in the moist "dump"; but the pebbly ridge defied vegetation and traced a white scar across the green. In Casvales, heavy boots and calloused heels ground paths to store, to depot, to Connors' yard.</p>
				<p>The sight of growing grain was to Nell a constant reminder that there would be a day soon when that harvest would be yellow, and Sheila would perhaps be carried away. Although she said nothing of this, she had a feeling that each day brought her nearer to the death of something dear. She went on with her work. Yes, she was grateful to God for their prosperity. She cooked, she baked, she sewed, she spoke to the children: "Margaret, hear Kitty Ann with her Catechism. Alice, child, don't suck that thumb." <emph>Sheila is an Indian and must, I suppose, marry one! The coldest place in the tent! The heaviest burden! "Emmet, get me a basket of shavings. That's the man." Perhaps Wild Goose won't return! Would Sheila forget him? Should she tell Sheila her parentage now? When must neighbors be told? "Ellen, bring me in a few fresh eggs." Wild Goose will return! I feel it!     </emph>
					<pb n="314 BLACK SOIL "/>After the grain turned from grass to stalk, Sheila went daily to the field, tenderly held a stalk across her palm, and speculated as to when it would head . . . fill out . . . turn yellow!</p>
				<p>While the older Connors were enacting this silent drama, the young ones, lately freed from school, daily watched the trains, the neighbors hauling lumber, the unfurling of a tender yellow bloom on the cactus, the erection of the little church, and the new house.</p>
				<p>Early summer saw the framework of Connors' new house hoist itself over the trees as a rival to the pretentious barn. Nell had visualized this house for many years--a replica of Judge De Wayne's in Springfield. In the drafting of plans, however, the eastern gables were forced to compromise with the plain ells of the <pb n="BLACK SOIL 315 "/>prairie; and, in consequence, the Connors had a spacious ten-room house whose front was assuming more each day the expression of a face, the bay window serving as mouth.</p>
				<p>Nell spoke much of Sheila's room. "Why plan so on Sheila's room?" Tim questioned. "Maybe we won't have Sheila after we have the house." But Nell continued to plan on Sheila's room. She wished to convince herself that Sheila's going off was in the future, if at all.</p>
				<p>Ben appeared one evening, and his casual relating of momentous news brought Nell face to face with the present; and she realized that in this as in all other things she must try to reconcile herself to the will of God. Sheila would be going! Ben had visited Wild Goose in his home where he was living alone since his father's death. He was coming, as he had said, when his harvest was cut and shocked.</p>
				<p>The well-digger had made other inquiries on his trip and had learned the meaning of Sheila's name. "Shayla vin" he said, "means <emph>reddish girl</emph>. That's all anyone could make out of it."Tears of pity rushed to Nell's eyes, tears of com ­passion for Sheila's deserted young Indian mother, who had nothing by which to place a name upon her child other than the coloring of its hair.</p>
				<p>"And you should have nothing against Wild Goose," Ben continued. "Some half-breeds have the best of both races in 'em. And others again--" "Are not so blessed," Tim finished for him.</p>
				<p>As the young Connors gathered around the doorstep, Ben related other bits of news. He had given up railroading, <pb n="316 BLACK SOIL "/>he told them, and was going to settle in Casvales and help run the lumber yard. "I'm tired of roving," he made excuse as he put an arm around Robert Emmet, who was snuggling close. Ben was tired, and he looked very old. His body had shriveled since he dug Connors' well, and his fringe of hair was white and sparse. "I'll help your Poppy here make a little money to school this young army. And Allen is moving his family from Buffalo to Sioux City. The West has won him. His boy, Edgar, is going to attend the new acad­emy at Upham. Now that school would be a fine place for Danny. He could come home every few weeks."Nell could not assent; she could say nothing. Her heart was too full. She was grateful to Ben the well digger, but she could hear no more just now. She arose and walked away. As she entered the grove, the big white house with its rectangular eyes glared at her accusingly. Ingratitude? Here all about her were evidences of the realization of hopes. How dare she, Nell Connor, dread the yellowing harvest, a bountiful har vest! No, she would rise to meet that harvest as she had risen to greet each day and what it held for her, all these years. <pb n="317"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XXXVII">
				<p>IT was four weeks later, and Sheila was moving out of sight of the Connors, away from their town, the big barn, the new house. Wild Goose and his spirited team were carrying her farther and farther away. At the back of the covered wagon Bluey was tied, followed by her two heifers. Nell could still see them from the doorstep.</p>
				<p>Sheila and Wild Goose had made an impressive picture that morning as they stood before Father Leurmann in the unfinished church. Indeed, even Katto and Max's wife could not refrain from commenting on their beauty. Wild Goose, erect, in velvet trousers and scarlet shirt; Sheila, demure as usual, her hair in two long braids bound by a band of beads--the gift of Wild Goose. They were a beautiful pair. Now they were gone.</p>
				<p>Nell's own children broke from the line which they had formed in watching the disappearing wagon, and were climbing to points of vantage on the barn. "She's waving, Mom," they shouted.</p>
				<p>Nell snatched the white cloth from the table, ran outside the grove, and swung it high over her head. She saw Sheila waving from the rear of the covered wagon, its gray shirring forming a broad halo around her head.</p>
				<p>Nell sank down wearily on the doorstep. Alice stood before her, inserted her thumb in her mouth, and buried her face in the spacious lap.</p>
				<p>Danny, on the apex of the barn, called out: "Good­ bye, Sheila."    <pb n="318 BLACK SOIL "/>Margaret from her station on the cow shed, Kitty Ann from the calf shed, Robert Emmet from the hog shed, and Ellen, swinging from a board which carried rainwater from the series of sheds to a barrel, echoed] in turn: "Goodbye, goodbye . . ." The wagon was lost to Nell's view. Her eyes were filled with tears. Unheeded they rolled down her face. With the knowledge of a great void in her heart came the thought: she had failed in her guidance of Sheila. Else why should Sheila, a lovely young girl, leave com­forts and go off to the unknown with a strange man? Well, if she had failed she knew that she had done her best. And Tim saw only satisfaction in Sheila's decision. But Tim couldn't understand. . . . Where was Tim? He should be in the field! And Danny and the others should get down from that barn! There was so much to be done. . . .</p>
				<p>She looked at Danny, but his sphinx-like attitude arrested her call. Oblivious to the chatter of his brother and sisters, he was standing silently facing the east. Nell recalled his often repeated aspiration: "Edgar can work the land. When I'm a man I'm going East and study how to relieve pain and how to cure women like Mrs. Breidbarth. . . ."Nell stood up and raised Alice to her arms. Her pulse quickened. She wiped at her tears with the back of her hand. As the circulation stirred in her swollen ankles, she winced with pain. Only for an instant. She squared her shoulders.</p>
				<p>From Danny she looked at the others. They, too, had fine, erect bodies and alert minds. Thank God, they now had enough to eat.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 319"/>Their future, however, would be more than a struggle for bread. It would be a series of achievements and heart ­aches in the realization of individual ambitions. If she could only place her body between them and life! . . .</p>
				<p>She saw her children like sturdy stalks of corn, well rooted in black soil, each carrying a golden tassel, going on and on and . . . disappearing off there at the horizon.</p>
				<p>Stretched before her, too, was her own future: days upon days of loving service. Anxious moments. Com­ forting moments. And if she failed! . . . Well, she would have done her best.</p>
				<p>But God is good. Danny will be going to the academy at Upham this fall. He must have a suit of boughten clothes. And Margaret . . . perhaps the railroad will be built clear to Upham before Margaret starts.</p>
				<p>There were footsteps. Tim was standing at her side. With a swoop he took the sleeping Alice in his arms. Relieved, Nell shifted her weight and leaned against his shoulder.</p>
				<p>A train was crawling through their field. It stopped near the cluster of small buildings, unloaded some white lumber and moved on to the west.</p>
				<p>It was cool on the doorstep. Shade from the tall cottonwoods filled the yard. Flowerbeds bordered with whitewashed stones. The white fence. The barn. A new house. And on a pedestal--the cactus which bloomed only once every hundred years, showing a delicate yellow blossom.</p>
				<p>Nell was conscious of music--not clearly defined. But a harmonious rhythm: creaking cottonwood leaves, <pb n="320 BLACK SOIL "/>Alice's even breathing, Tim's crooning lullaby, bare feet descending shingled roofs. . . .</p>
				<p>The Connor children of various heights pressed around their parents. But Tim and Nell stayed on the doorstep of the old house and watched the summer sun ­shine flood their stubble with a maze of golden light.</p>
				<p>THE END </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
