<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main Document Type//EN"
"http://infomotions.com/alex/dtd/tei2.dtd">
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Josephine Donovan's Black Soil in electronic form</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Originally Prepared by </resp>
					<name>Erin Lee Kellerhals</name>
				</respStmt>
				<principal>Matthew L. Jockers, Stanford University Department of English</principal>
				<sponsor>
					<name>Stanford University</name>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Stanford, California 94305</addrLine>
					</address>
				</sponsor>
				<funder>
					<name>Stanford Humanities Lab</name>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Stanford University, Stanford, California 94305</addrLine>
					</address>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Distributed by The Irish-American West Project of the Stanford Humanities Lab</name>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Stanford, California 94503</addrLine>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<p>This e-text is freely available for non-commercial purposes</p>
				</availability>
				<date>2004</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>Josephine Donovan. Black Soil. Boston, Massachusetts: The Stratford Company, 1930<note type="abstract">Black Soil is Josephine Donovan's story of the arrival of European immigrants in northwestern Iowa, particulary that of an Irish farming family who faces the challenges of settling the area.  The title refers to the farmland of this area. </note>
                                <name type="region">Midwest</name>
                                <name type="country">United States</name>
                                <name type="city">Northwestern Iowa farmer's town</name>
                                <name type="state">Iowa</name>
                                <name type="setting">Rural</name>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>This text was prepared for use in the Irish-American West project of the Stanford Humanities Lab at Stanford University. The two principal goals of this project are (A) to bring the wealth of western Irish-American literary and historical writing to the Internet in a scholarly project and (B) to counter the existing eastern bias in Irish-American scholarship, by providing an online collection of primary source material and scholarly articles devoted to exploring the works of western Irish-Americans.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p>Suspected errors in the text are marked with a "[sic]" but not corrected.</p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p>Hyphens that occur at the ends of lines have been removed, except in cases where it is possible the author intended the hyphen.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<titlePage>
				<docTitle>
					<titlePart type="main">BLACK SOIL</titlePart>
				</docTitle>
				<byline>BY</byline>
				<docAuthor>
				<name type="first">JOSEPHINE</name>
				<name type="last">DONOVAN</name>
				</docAuthor>
				<docImprint>
					<publisher>B Y THE STRATFORD COMPANY Publishers</publisher>
					<pubPlace>PRINTED IN THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA PRINTED BY THE ALPINE PRESS, INC., BOSTON, MASS.</pubPlace>
					<docDate>C O P Y R I G H T  1 9 3 0  </docDate>
				</docImprint>
			</titlePage>
			<div type="other">
				<p>This edition printed for the members of the Catholic Book Club. </p>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body><pb n="no page number"/>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER I ">
				<p>DIRECTION? . . . There was no direction. The prairie stretched to the end of the world. Nell Connor, seated on a high wagon, swayed with the motion of the ox team and closed her eyes. Would there be, perhaps, some change in this scene when she looked again? No, No change. She became insensible to the prattle of Tim and the children, and listened to Dutch Fred as he directed his oxen. "Geee. Haw! Haw Ha!" On, on toward an elusive horizon. Did that driver with the long, bushy beard and kind gray eyes really know of a destination? Where was he taking the Connor family? Why had Tim selected land so far, far from any signs of life? It was hours, days, since the rail road terminal the last connection with civilization--had been swallowed in those palpitating grasses.</p>
				<p>"Look, childer," Tim was calling to Danny and Margaret from where he stood behind the wagon seat, "See the wild turkeys!"Flocks of big fowl keeping off at a distance, their long necks and topknots resembling flowers.</p>
				<p>The wind blew fitfully against the slow-moving wagon. It whistled mournfully around Connors' household furniture, jerked Nell's lavender poke bonnet, billowed her full skirt. She wound her skirts more securely around her ankles, tied her bonnet tightly and held her head down.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="2 BLACK SOIL"/>Margaret, toddling about, found her way under the seat and pulled at Nell's skirt. The child raised a travel stained face, "Let's doe home, Mom, Let's doe home."For answer Nell raised the child to her lap.</p>
				<p>Home! Home on a shady New England street must be a memory now. Somewhere here among these grasses would be home. Where? . . . Her eyes could not measure the expanse of land. A loneliness seized her. The fear that had haunted her on the train, as every revolution of the wheels carried them farther west, took possession of her again and made determination give way to bodily fatigue. Besides, wagon seats are not built for comfort.</p>
				<p>Margaret, from her place of vantage on Nell's lap, was surveying the country. "Oh!" she cried, her cheeks pink, her blue eyes flashing. "Fowers! Fowers? Everyfing is fowers!"Nell looked from the child's glorified face to the prairie. Stretches apparently all blue and patches of pink beckoned to them. They were making a road through flowers--tramping them down--rolling over them going along and crushing down more. It <emph>was</emph> a world of flowers!</p>
				<p>"See, a good house?" Dutch Fred pointed with his goad at an unpainted frame house squatted down on the grass. Surrounding it were sheds thatched with dry brown hay. They passed no other habitations except occasional sod houses, like clods of black earth, which gave no signs of life. Yet stovepipes, sticking through the grassy roofs, proved that there the business of living was carried on.</p>
				<p>When the oxen stamped into a deep slough and the wagon lunged in after them, Nell grew rigid. Clinging<pb n="BLACK SOIL 3"/>to the seat and holding the baby tightly, she peeped over the side of the wagon box and saw only a bed of clear water over which tall grasses were blowing and nodding in the wind. When the dripping wagon was drawn safely to dry grass, the staunch, dependable power of the oxen convinced her. As they slashed through other sloughs, she sat as serenely as the wild ducks that nested on top of the muskrat houses which looked like conical piles of drift in the water. With Tim and the children she marveled at the countless number of yellow-headed blackbirds that circled above them, and admired the dove coloring of the silent, humped-up blue heron stationed on the water's edge.</p>
				<p>"Your land come soon now," Dutch Fred announced, as he surreptitiously spat tobacco juice against the wagon wheel.</p>
				<p>At this, Nell's tall husband stood erect and searched the landscape. Nell, too, watched the horizon.</p>
				<p>Land coming! Where?</p>
				<p>She wearied of the futile search. The sheen of sun and grass hurt her eyes. Why did the wagon not advance toward the land? She looked at the driver he was silent, listless. Margaret, asleep, rested a heavy head on her arm. The Oxen swayed; the rims of the wagon wheels shone as they glided sinuously through the grass.</p>
				<p>"There it is!" Tim shouted.</p>
				<p>In the midst of the green ahead there was a white speck like the sail of a boat far out at sea. It drew nearer . . . larger. It was a house. Dutch Fred soon stopped the oxen and climbed from the wagon.  The chain jingled as it loosened around the tongue and the oxen reached for mouthfuls of grass.  After walking<pb n="4 BLACK SOIL"/>around a rod or so, he came to a piece of wood stuck in the ground,"Here your land is!" Boyishly Tim leaned over the seat, put his hands on Nell's shoulders and made oration: "This is the finest one hundred and sixty in the West and cost just five dollars an acre," Then half to himself, "I hope, please God, we'll never regret the move."</p><p>"I know we shan't," Nell assured him. She cried then and could say no more. Their own fields, her husband's emotion and her aching back all added to her feeling.</p>
				<p>Dutch Fred peered into her face with beaming eyes. "You must not cry, your man get strong, you get rich."Nell could not answer, but she laid her hand on his calloused palm.</p>
				<p>"Nobody lives near us, Pop," Danny said petulantly. "Who'll play with me?"</p><p>"Don't worry about that, me bye," Tim answered pleasantly. "We'll hunt out the fairies. There must be hundreds of 'em hidden under these flowers."</p><p>"You got a cellar," Dutch Fred announced. The pile of black earth near the building indicated this. In comparison, the boards of the house were chalky white. Where was the roof? There were only two sides boarded.</p>
				<p>"Mine Gott! It is not ready! It is not done!" Wild eyed, Dutch Fred looked at the silent family. "We won't unload," he said, shaking his head. "You come with me to mine soddy. It is not big, but you can come."As Nell stood in the unfinished house, a square patch of blue sky formed a roof. She untied the lavender poke bonnet. "Let's stay here, Tim!"<pb n="BLACK SOIL 5"/>Tim nodded. "It's good the carpenter made you a well already." Dutch Fred led the way to a hole in the ground about three feet deep. "You think you stay? Then I unload, and come back in the morning."Tim drew out a round wallet. "I want to pay you now for the trip from the railroad."Dutch Fred smiled, but as he began to speak his voice quivered and his eyes watered. He grasped Tim's  wrist with both of his hands. "No, no money, Teem. I am glad you come once. We need one like you. I go now."</p><p>"How far?" Nell asked. "Seven mile. I am your nearest neighbor."As the smiling settler started off east, Nell wanted to run after him and call out, "Take us back! Take us back!" The oxen moved on. . . .</p>
				<p>Tim dipped up a drink for the children. "Fine tastin' water," he commented. Nell stood beside the packing boxes, her hand on her mother's sewing machine. She looked to the east--and grass; to the west--grass and sky.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="6"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER II">
				<p>THE prairie was creeping out from under a fog. Sinuously it moved. Having freed its head, it ex tended a long neck, raised Herculean shoulders, then lay motionless. Released fog slowly, reluctantly lifted and revealed a portion of the prairie's flat back. Dawn, a phantom trailing a web of pearly light, sifted in, peered about, and disclosed a shanty. On the doorstep of the shanty stood Nell Connor with her face raised to welcome the day.</p>
				<p>The daylight played about her. It touched the jagged fringe on her gray shawl; it toyed with the sheen in her braid of brown hair; it glistened on the blisters of her face and hands.</p>
				<p>"It's light," she said aloud. "It's light, thank God." Turning in the direction of the county seat, she peered into the receding fog from which her husband and the ox team must surely emerge soon.</p>
				<p>Nell Connor had on many occasions during the past anxiously awaited Tim's safe return. Today, she had no fear of fog. She was filled with anxiety for the success of his trip. <emph>Would the bank loan him more money? </emph>Money to compensate for the loss of their wheat by: fire a few days before, a loan with which to pay interest on the mortgage and buy flour for the winter.</p>
				<p>
					<emph>Winter. </emph>Nell looked toward the northeast, but the receding fog revealed only prairie; prairie whose general appearance<pb n="BLACK SOIL 7"/>had not changed since Dutch Fred had deposited the Connor family and their packing boxes beside two boarded walls.</p>
				<p>That incomplete shanty, however, had evolved into a tight, comfortable home, luxuriating in two rooms and a loft. A third child, Kitty Ann, had joined the forces of young Danny and Margaret in their world of flowers, and was already able to carry fistfuls of bloom to her admiring mother. The Connors had a start in stock, a few chickens, a quarter section of land, a healthy mortgage and two crop failures.</p>
				<p>"Not so much a failure of crops as a failure to harvest the crops," Tim Connor had expressed it. The first year, having arrived too late to do much breaking, they sowed sod corn and oats. It was a dry season, but the belated crop flourished miraculously. Near harvest time, however, it was laid flat by a wind; and then, lest it dare raise its head again, an ensuing hailstorm had fairly beaten it into the ground.</p>
				<p>This, the second crop, had been wheat. Escaping previous catastrophes, it had greened, ripened, was harvested, and in its setting of four golden cones had assumed the dignity of monuments--monuments to toil, to patience and to the goodness of God. Then had come the fire, Tim away with the threshing crew.</p>
				<p>The scene returned to Nell in the morning light as the stretch of charred stubble and the pile of black straw came into view. She saw in retrospect flames reaching to the smoking sky, striking out at her as she lashed them with wet gunny sacks.  The red tongues winding venomously around the setting of wheat.  The locking of the terrorized children in the house.  The starting of the<pb n="8 BLACK SOIL"/>backfires that saved them and the buildings.</p>
				<p>"What harm about the wheat? Let the wheat go! Ye're safe, thank God," had been Tim's mollifying comment when he and the other threshers had arrived. "There's always wheat," he had repeated as he looked at his sleeping children as if he counted them, and tenderly applied badger oil to Nell's blistered face and hands.</p>
				<p>As Nell reviewed this recent terrible experience in this wild land, she felt a greater appreciation of Tim's kindly qualities. With this realization came the resolve not to write East for help if he did not receive the necessary loan from the bank.  Never again would her kinsmen have occasion to attribute their lack of success to Tim's shiftlessness. They would not learn of this defeat. She would not write. She was tired of their I-told-you so letters, recalling advice given, and comments made at the time of her departure.</p>
				<p>"Tim Connor, that light-hearted devil-may-care, carrying off his young family to the wild West on a high adventure."</p><p>"He a farmer?" There had been many jokes afloat, too.</p>
				<p>"Say, did you hear about Tim Connor going to a lawless country to practice law? What're you going to live on, Tim?".</p>
				<p>Tim, as usual, had taken it good naturedly. "I intend to charm the buffalo with me flute, and lead the Indian choir on Sundays and holy days."Friends had tried to dissuade him, but he had answered doggedly: "I'm going out West."In those days, only Nell had sympathized with Tim<pb n="BLACK SOIL 9"/>in his ambition. She told him that she was willing to go to the end of the earth with him despite the persuasions of her aunt and uncle.</p>
				<p>They had come to the end of the earth indeed. And the ill-luck which had accompanied them had been attributed to Tim's mismanagement. "Well," Nell reasoned bitterly, "a close-fisted plodder like Uncle Henry himself couldn't get on if God was against him."Why, that was blasphemy! Oh, she didn't mean that. No. God was good! God was good! They must wait . . . But, what if Tim didn't get the money? What then?</p>
				<p>Well, God is good! And as she tried to dwell on the goodness of God, Tim's saying returned glibly to her, "God is good. It's a free country. . . . If you haven't shoes, you can go barefoot."Nell jerked her shawl about her. She repulsed that sickening feeling of despair. She must fight against such thoughts. Was she going to lose her soul, too, in this godforsaken country? Were her children to be as heathen as the Indians, with such a mother?</p>
				<p>If Tim would only come soon.  He must surely come soon with good news.</p>
				<p>Nell Connor pulled her nightgown down over her bare feet, and sat down on the cold step. Toward the east the familiar unchanged landscape opened up. Though looking at it, she thought only of their present needs. What was ever to become of the children? Bowing her head she prayed that the banker would loan Tim the money for the interest--and perhaps a little extra for flour. Vaguely she heard the awakening prairie:  high, piercing<pb n="10 BLACK SOIL "/>
					slough-sounds answering the warbles of the grass, A newly active breeze pricked into motion the prairie which unrolled before her to the end of her vision, assuming now its elusive contrasts: here a flash of bluish green, there an irridescent silver and on all sides shifting, mysterious shadows, Mystery! What misery in its keeping?</p>
				<p>She shut her eyes away from it and rested her fore head on her knees. On her little step she felt as completely forsaken and at the mercy of the billowy prairie as if she were on a raft in mid-ocean. She allowed her thoughts to waver .with the motion of the grass, and she was lulled into a lethargy not knowing whether fear or hope or assurance or premonition engrossed her.</p>
				<p>When she raised her head the sun had risen. Shielding her eyes from the dazzle of the reeking grass, she scanned the horizon.</p>
				<p>Was that Tim in the distance? No. That was a covered wagon. She could see its gray canvas swaying like a sail. "Company! Someone coming!" she said aloud. Enlivened by the luxury of seeing someone, her abstractions for the moment forgotten: "Wonder what kind they'll be. Perhaps they'll be from back East. At any rate they'll stop."Hastening to the mirror of the walnut dresser, she wiped the oil from her face and hands and attempted to smooth her tawny, singed hair with a wet comb. Back and forth from door to bedroom she walked, watching, speculating. She put 0.n her good dress, a gray alpaca basque and skirt: the tight sleeves crushed her blistered arms, but she did not flinch. "Tim can help them select their land. Wonder if they have any cattle!"<pb n="BLACK SOIL 11"/>At the doorway she suddenly paused, baffled for the moment. Instead of the wagon gliding on with a slow regular beat, its horses were galloping. Horses galloping on a mover wagon!</p>
				<p>"Oh, it's a new life coming," she concluded. "They're hastening to a woman's care."She tied on an apron, brought in an armful of twisted slough grass, started the fire, and placed the copper bottomed teakettle to boil, mentally taking stock of what she had on hand for such an emergency. She re moved her baby from the big bed, got in readiness fresh linens, and from a cupboard unearthed a bottle containing a little olive oil. Stepping about swiftly, she was filled with a great exultation: she felt akin to the Dispenser of life; she was its custodian.</p>
				<p>The covered wagon, with axles rattling, halted at her door. The ill-matched skeletons of horses were puffing and lathered, their dilated nostrils round as their wild eyes, which rolled involuntarily. Nell drew back in horror of the driver, who sat hunched like a ground squirrel sleek and striped and cunning and gray.</p>
				<p>"She's gone," he piped out, sniffling. "My wife Mary's dead. She had a wasting sickness. 'Tis my punishment for the drink.'' Clinging to the spokes of the wheel he climbed down and approached Nell. "She wanted to get to a settler's to die; but we're too late. Mules would've brung us.'' He shuffled toward the door step.</p>
				<p>Nell was aroused from her [sic] stupefication by a little girl who had risen from under the seat and was also climbing down over the wheel. She had a profusion of<pb n="12 BLACK SOIL"/> red matted curls which hung unrestrainedly about her face. At intervals the uncontrolled sobs which follow prolonged crying shook her thin body. On reaching the ground, she lowered her head to her soiled plaid dress on which she wiped her nose.</p>
				<p>Nell's first impulse was to go to the rear of the wagon. "</p><p>"I'll wait till Tim comes," she decided and gave her attention to the girl.</p>
				<p>With the intuition of a child, the girl knew that Nell was to be trusted. She raised her round, dark eyes to her and said between sobs. "He says he'll leave me to the wolves on the prairie."</p><p>"Isn't he your father?" Nell questioned. </p><p>The girl shook her head. "Not my ma there, neither. 'Dopted."</p><p>"I'll get you some breakfast," Nell said irrelevantly, "and then you can play with my children."Mumbling, the man went off and lay down on the ground.</p>
				<p>A series of questions revealed that the child knew nothing of her true parentage. The dead woman whom she called "ma" had cared for her; but "pa" had not. Ma had wished to reach a settler's home before her death so that she could leave the child there. They had kept driving as she directed, but the fog had got them.</p>
				<p>Nell hardly knew what to make of the state of affairs. Her anticipated visit from the movers had revealed only more tragedy. As usual, she was helpless to allay it. Only tragedy and grief this country offered. And there was only Tim, goodhearted and impractical, upon whom to depend.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 13"/>When Tim Connor drove up in the low wagon, his height and leanness were accentuated. His wife watched him from the kitchen window, studying his face for news. He eyed the covered wagon with the team tied to the plow interestedly, turned his oxen loose, and stood before his wife in the doorway.</p>
				<p>"Company, I see,'' he shouted. He was smiling, but his eyes avoided Nell's. "My, but you're a fine stump of a girl," he addressed the strange child, touching her head lightly with his hat. "What's your name?"</p><p>"Shaylah," she answered timidly, "Shaylah Winnie Moore."</p><p>"So it's Sheila it is! Sheila Moore, a good name. Where's the rest of ye, and where are ye bound for?"Sheila looked up into his face. She saw a tall man with bushy brown beard, a long, sharp nose, and eyes the color of the sky under which she had traveled for many days. He was smiling at her; his voice was gentle.</p>
				<p>"Black Hills," she said, looking to Nell for help. So Nell told Tim about the work that lay before them: they must bury a woman, sober up a man and make him realize the responsibility of a child. The neighbors, distant at all times, were now farther away, threshing. There were only the Connors.</p>
				<p>Tim rubbed his hands together, lingering near the stove where the hay: was snapping. His teeth chattered, "That fog was a cold one last night," he said, avoiding the immediate issue, "I got over too far west. Wasn't far from home."Nell laid a hand on his shoulder. "That old ague acting up again? Everything all right?"<pb n="14 BLACK SOIL"/>Tim nodded. "You bet yuh." But Nell knew.  He hadn't got the money!  He hadn't  got it!  Her pulse hammered in her temples:  He hadn't  got it!  Aloud she said: "Come and have a swallow of hot coffee."After a hurriedly eaten breakfast, Tim tried to arouse the stranger but failed.  "We might as well let him sleep it off," he said as he searched out material for a coffin.</p>
				<p>Tim's carpentry was rough, but his efficiency was not to be questioned.  He ripped some of the clean boards from a partition in the unused granary and fashioned a rude box.</p>
				<p>Nell went to a black chest in the bedroom, drew out a satin-pieced quilt, and crushed it for a moment in her arms.  "Here, Tim," she said, "line it with this."Tim nodded without looking up. On a slight rise of land in the free range to the south of Connor's homestead, land agent maps showed a square marked "Cemetery."  Tradition claimed that a baby, whose parents afterward had returned to the East, had once been buried there.  There was no evidence of a former grave, however, on this sunny swell of land when Tim Connor turned over the tufted grass whose roots were matted deep into the ground.  The excavation, black and unfamiliar, piqued the curiosity of the wild things about.  Coyotes stealthily crept near; a prairie chicken advanced boldly and peered into the darkness of the cavern; a buzzard circled about and disappeared at the horizon, only to return, circling, circling.</p>
				<p>While Mr. Moore apparently lay in a drunken stupor, his wife Mary's funeral took place.  The cortege, led by<pb n="BLACK SOIL 15"/>Connor's unperturbed oxen, rolled past the squatty house with its thin coil of white smoke forcing itself vertically into a cloudless sky; past the small granary, blatant with its shingled roof; past the shed, hay thatched and plastered with the nests of mud-swallows; past the struggling cottonwood grove; past the slough well with its square wooden pump; out upon the shining prairie, quiescent and guileless as if it knew not death, the white buffalo skulls and branching antlers lay hidden in its grasses.</p>
				<p>When the wagon stopped beside the dark mound, Nell sent the children away. "Run off," she said, "and pick all the flowers you can carry."Sheila lingered. "Run along now," she repeated, "there's nice roses over that way," indicating a pink section of prairie.</p>
				<p>Nell, while engrossed in rendering arduous assistance at the grave, could give the strange child no thought; but later, as Sheila returned with her own children, their faces framed by armfuls of bloom, she wished that she might keep her. If Tim had only got that loanThe black mound turned pink as offerings--short stemmed, long stemmed, and pulled out by the roots--were laid upon it.</p>
				<p>Tim tossed his shovel into the wagon, then looked intently toward the west. Nell's eyes soon focussed [sic] there, too. There was a wagon on the trail. Sheila's father had hitched his jaded horses and was swinging his wreck of a wagon off toward the Sioux River.</p>
				<p>Nell, an arm about the cowering Sheila, wondered on the justice of fate.  It must be God's will, that's all.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="16 BLACK SOIL"/>This morning I prayed for help--for food for my children, and I received no answer but another mouth to feed. Aloud she said, "Well, Tim, there are worse things than hunger."Tim said nothing; but that evening as he fixed a makeshift bed in the loft he tried to hide with a bantering "Always room for one more," the immensity of his own misgivings.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="17"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n=" CHAPTER III">
				<p>IT was summer again, and the Iowa prairie was a study in green and gold and pink. Patches of ripening barley, oats and wheat were diminutive islands in the green sea. Corn waved green fronds and nodded golden tassels. Sweet Williams vied with the wild roses in flooding the unbroken lands. And the summer sun light, tempered by the ever-blowing south breeze, cast a sheen over the whole which dazzled the eye and gladdened the heart.</p>
				<p>The Connors had one hundred acres under cultivation. What with all the wild hay they wished to cut, they were assured a bountiful harvest. Interest would be paid, necessary machinery bought, and there would be food--food for all. The Lord was indeed providing. It was well. . . . During the winter Kitty Ann had been crowded from her cradle by a new brother, Robert Emmet; and the girl Sheila who had been thrust into their keeping was being cared for as their own.</p>
				<p>During the year that Sheila had been with the Connors, she had slipped into their lives as unobtrusively as if she had been there the ten years of her existence. She accepted their care, their chastisings and their love as unquestioningly as a stray kitten. She had always had enough to eat; it had never occurred to her whether Nell and Tim Connor had or not. During the past winter, oh, she had tired of corn mush and potatoes. And the way they cooked potatoes? They boiled them, then peeled them, then mashed them on their plates<pb n="18 BLACK SOIL "/>and flooded them with milk. While she secretly longed for the sweets that she had had in Wisconsin, she learned how to thank God for the potatoes and to ask Him for "a continuance of the same" food. She had enjoyed especially the variety in game and the baked eggs--prairie chickens', partridges' and plovers'--which they had gathered in their aprons after the old grass had been burned off in the spring. Now there were garden vegetables; and an occasional sheep sorrel pie sweetened with molasses. Sheila liked molasses; but the molasses, bought in jugs on the rare trips to town, didn't last long, And as for sugar--they had none.</p>
				<p>Although Sheila was often displeased with the food at the new home, she liked her attic bedroom. There was isolation in the loft. The low roof gave her the sense of protection which Danny had suggested one day.</p>
				<p>"Sheila, your room is like an old hatcher covering yuh. See, the roof is her wings and that one window is the old hen's eye."During the past year the low roof, had indeed shut out many fears. Daylight had always been pleasant in the loft; but when she had been a stranger there, the moonlight had played tricks on her by contorting the storage into grotesque heads and extending arms.</p>
				<p>At such times she had called below to Nell: "I'm afraid up here. There's big heads and funny faces trying to get me."Nell would climb up a few steps of the ladder. "There's nothing there, child. Say the prayer to your guardian angel and close your eyes tight. I'll stay here<pb n="BLACK SOIL 19"/>till you go to sleep and the first thing you know it will be morning."Thus Sheila soon forgot her fears. Even rain on the roof added to her sense of security. She defied hail, daring it to break through her roof. In time of dangerous winds she was called.</p>
				<p>"Sheila, hurry down. The roof may go." Or: "Come below, the chimney may fall."When distant prairie fires lighting her room awakened her, she listened to the voices below. If their tone was assuring, though tumbleweeds shot into the air like balls of fire, she fell asleep.</p>
				<p>One summer morning as she dreamily lay abed, she speculated on how she should spend the day. There would be the cattle to take out, as usual. If Danny would accompany her they would go far--perhaps over to Mill Creek and chase those baby deer or drown out gophers.  Danny, though three years her junior, was able to keep pace with her; but on every possible occasion she would "dodge out" of taking Margaret, and Kitty Ann.</p>
				<p>When the aroma of cooking food reached her attic room, she bounded from her bed, hastily put on her dress, and descended the ladder.  Her smooth tanned legs appeared below; there was a sudden leap from the fourth lowest rung to the middle of the kitchen floor, and she stood before Nell.</p>
				<p>Nell, with the plump baby in her arms, was preparing breakfast.  They exchanged no greetings; but Nell looked fondly at the girl as she burrowed her head of wavy red hair into Robert Emmet's chest.  The baby pulled her hair without mercy and crowed with delight,his rosebud mouth assuming in his excessive mirth the shape of a leaf.</p>
				<p>Nell, her hair tightly drawn away from her small ears, the thinness of her face augmented by her slightly high cheekbones and pointed chin, her small, close-knit body shapeless in a calico wrapper, wondered when Sheila's head of hair would look like it saw the tooth of a comb. How she had brushed and cared for that hair the past year, and how willfully [sic] it loosed itself arid became tangled! "Child, your back's buttoned wrong,'' and disengaging one hand she adjusted the dress. "You didn't wash your feet last night."The girl did not answer, but placed the cleaner foot atop the one which showed the greater neglect. "Wash yourself now and set the table," Nell commanded patiently as she withdrew the baby. After breakfast, Nell gave Danny the water pail and suggested that he accompany Sheila with the cattle, and together they could gather some wild straw berries. Tim had remarked on the great abundance of them, "over west." Immediately Margaret and Kitty Ann clamored to be allowed to go also.</p>
				<p>Sheila would have preferred to have no additional duties assigned her other than keeping the cows from the patches of cultivation, but she said nothing; she rarely expressed her likes or dislikes as did the young Connors.</p>
				<p>"Get your bonnets now, and keep them on,'' Nell said, marshaling them about. "Remember, keep them on. Sheila, I declare, is as brown as a berry: and Margaret, I can't tell you from a turkey egg. Your complexions will be ruined for life."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 21"/>Duly coiffured and admonished, the children set off. From the doorway Nell watched the four dark specks assume the motion of the grass as the enveloping blue sky rocked the prairie in its arms.</p>
				<p>The children, meanwhile, explored the area of which they unknowingly had become a part. Kitty Ann and Margaret held up savory-looking discoveries, asking of the elder two: "Will this deaden me? Will <emph>this </emph>deaden me?" Sheila held Kitty Ann by the hand: and Danny, who should have been caring for Margaret, found a chicken hawk's nest four blue eggs surrounded by a few sticks. Should he destroy it? The hawks had been carrying off Mom's chickens. . .  The eggs were so blue. . . .</p>
				<p>"Margaret's gone!" Sheila shouted. The hawk's nest was forgotten. Danny ran through the grass, shouting: "Margaret, Margaret, stand UP now. Answer, Margaret. Margaret, answer or you can't never come again."</p><p>"What if she is really lost this time?" Sheila asked fearfully, as dragging Kitty Ann along she came up with Danny. Young stock was often lost. Why not children? And Morn had warned them so!</p>
				<p>Danny pushed back his wreck of a straw hat, and with his calloused soles rubbed his shins, which were bleeding from his recent search through rose bushes and knife-edged grass. "I'll put for home and get Mom. Keep this place now," he warned Sheila. "Don't stir from this spot."As he started for home, Margaret arose from where she had been lying in a patch of flowers.  She had been listening to the murmur of the flowers as the wind<pb n="22 BLACK SOIL"/>blew through their petals.  Her freckled face was flushed with ecstasy, her blue eyes round with wonder, as she related what she had heard in her retreat.  "Flowers don't want to be picked: they want to be kissed."Kitty Ann, her bonnet off, her curls in damp ringlets, delighted at this time to wildly pull off colored blooms and allow the wind to blow them from her hands.  Thereupon Margaret brought down a righteous arm upon her sister's yellow head.</p>
				<p>"Oh, Margaret," Danny said disgustedly. "you ought to be licked.  I'm going home to tell Mom, and the next time you'll stay home."  He held her viciously by the wrist, and the four continued their way.</p>
				<p>On reaching the indicated strawberry patch, they ate as they filled the pail.  The berries were not very large, so the sun was high before they had finished. Then Danny encircled the cattle and headed them about.  All started for home behind the herd.</p>
				<p>They had not gone far when Kitty Ann cried to be carried.  No sooner had Sheila raised her to her arms than the child was prostrate in sleep, her arms relaxed about Sheila's neck, her dress torn, and her stumpy bare legs red from the stain of wild strawberry.  Danny carried the pail, held fast to Margaret, and shouted to the cattle.</p>
				<p>In the grass about the feet of the passing herd darted frenzied nesting meadow larks.  Then from stations on swaying grass and flower, they raised their heads to the blue sky, inflated their yellow throats, and poured forth a thanksgiving.</p>
				<p>Bird songs; wind whispering to the flowers; insects on the wing; subdued murmurs of moving grass; voices of children--a prairie diapason.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="23"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER IV">
				<p>Since the battered covered wagon carrying Sheila to the Connors had disappeared in the west, many other prairie schooners had passed, and paused at Tim Connor's door.  Lands east of the Mississippi were becoming too crowded for the real frontiersmen and they were moving farther on; Europeans, too, were being attracted by the cheap lands in the open prairie.</p>
				<p>There had been a good crop in northwestern Iowa; a boom was on.  Land agents from Fort Dodge and Sioux City with well-matched spirited teams and shiny carriages dashed about, selling and locating.  They chewed tobacco, swung a tasseled whip, and expatiated on the good crops, the motley of flowers, the level land and the black soil…"The garden spot of the world."But people whose eyes were accustomed to timber were skeptical. "No streams; no hills; no shade; no protection," they argued.</p>
				<p>"Who wants trees to wear their lives away grubbing them out?" the salesman answered disgustedly.  "Plant your own trees.  Place them where you want them.   Land like this will grow anything--even tropical foliage."When occasion demanded, the agent stopped his horses abruptly, removed a spade from beneath the seat and handed it to the prospect, commanding:  "Here;<pb n="24 BLACK SOIL"/>dig in and see what the soil is black, clear down to China."Yes, the soil was black and loamy, they admitted; but where would they obtain fuel?</p>
				<p>Oh, the good Lord and the buffalo had provided for that. There was that sea of waving grass that made the most wonderful fuel in the world. Then, too, the buffalo bones and the buffalo chips needed only the gathering.</p>
				<p>Some said timidly: "I'll try farther west--just a little farther around the Sioux." "If you value your life don't cross the Sioux . . Indians!" <emph>"Indians!"</emph> "Yes, Indians." Boom! Sell! Mortgage!</p>
				<p>A Dutch colony was being formed on the east bank of the Sioux River. To the south of Connors', German immigrants were settling in what was later known as Low German township. Luxemburgers and Austrians, too, were filtering in and staking out grounds for kinsmen to follow.</p>
				<p>The Dutch, arriving in amazingly large numbers, were decidedly clannish. Many came direct from Holland; others had belonged to a colony a little farther east. A few of their leaders were well educated. Reports of their perseverance and thrift were carried among the scattered settlers by land agents. "The Dutch are here. Real wooden-shoe Hollanders. Took up a whole county, swamps and all. . . . They ain't afraid of a little water. They know how to work. They'll show yuh how to pay for a farm in a few years."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 25"/>At this last Tim Connor smiled. "The devil they can. Let us see them do it."Nell, though starving for companionship, did not complain of the unfriendliness of the Dutch. Despite their isolation, she rejoiced that they were located between her children and the Indians, Their strength and solidarity gave her assurance: she knew that in time of need they would be a dependable ally, stubborn and unyielding as the prairie sod which they had come to break. "God bless the Hollanders," she said often. "At night now I don't have to be watching the west imagining every moving thing an Indian. I feel like there was a garrison of soldiers over there. God bless the Hollanders."The other groups of immigrants were from various parts of the German Empire. They were divided by innate prejudices and traditions and were bitterly antagonistic to each other. Unlike the Dutch, they had no trained leaders; and recognizing their handicap in not being able to speak English, they clustered around Connor as an advisor.</p>
				<p>Thus Tim became known as "Der Englishmann." Tim, a native of Ireland and a Fenian sympathizer, smiled grimly at the appellation. "The devil's own name. So it is."But Tim proved himself a friend. It was no easy task keeping harmony among peoples who had carried all the enmities of their nations across the water and allowed them to flourish in their new propinquity.</p>
				<p>It was not long, however, before Luxemburger, High German, and Low German knew that while Tim could aid them in business transactions and in settling disputes,<pb n="26 BLACK SOIL"/>they could advise him on farming. They refrained, nevertheless, from suggesting aids in the preparation of soil, details of machinery, and innumerable bits of knowledge upon which they, who had been peasants in Europe, were quite well informed.</p>
				<p>Tim had had no previous experience in farming. His father in Ireland had been a professor. Tim had come to America as a lad with ambitions to become a lawyer. His greatest possessions were a kind heart and a sense of humor. His jests, however, were often lost on his lately formed associates, but they were nearly always appreciated by Nell. Tim could meet with careless banter a difficult situation. There were no fears in the young Connors' lives when Tim was there. Nell sometimes wondered if Tim knew fear or worry.</p>
				<p>Nell was less adept at hiding her grief and worry from the children, "Put on your nice face, Mom," she was sometimes reminded when she brooded on conditions and saw the results of Tim's impracticability. Nell, her self, knew nothing of farming. She was a doctor's daughter and was left an orphan at an early age. When she was seventeen she spent a summer with an aunt and uncle at North Hadley. And there she met Tim Connor.</p>
				<p>Tim and several other young men who were studying law in Judge De Wayne's office in Springfield were up at North Hadley picking tobacco on the Judge's farm. They spent their evenings serenading the comely young ladies in the village. Nell immediately became interested in the Irish tenor who sang so persistently below her window. They became engaged. After their marriage they lived in Northampton, and Tim discontinued his study of law and worked for a cutler.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 27"/>A few years later, when they were out beyond the Mississippi engaged in the grim battle of living, there were yearnings, of course, for the old life. Nell religiously banished them and instead wove a future for her children, fashioned from the warp and woof of her old life and colored with the mystery of the new life on the prairie. These dreams of stark beauty and majesty carried her on like a sweep of prairie wind. And though her back grew broad and her hands became rough, she retained a dignity and a look of fragility which caused other settlers' wives to chide Tim for bringing such a woman to the West.</p>
				<p>Nell had never taken any especial interest in the medical environment in which she had been reared, but unconsciously she had become acquainted with practical remedies and had acquired an ability in meeting emergencies. It was through her efficiency in the sick that distant settlers first became acquainted with her. She took many midnight horseback rides, perched be hind some morose man with whom she could not con verse and to whom she could only cling as he, in his anxiety, urged his horse to a continuous gallop.</p>
				<p>The many dialects in use in the neighborhood were confusing to her, but all managed in one way or another to make themselves understood. Nell secretly longed for a woman with whom she could converse easily; she also wished for a near neighbor. Although northwestern Iowa was becoming settled, land all about the Connors' was still held by eastern speculators and was not on the market. When Tim spoke enthusiastically of the influx of people and the number of wagons passing, Nell answered less exultantly: Why do so many go by?  Why<pb n="28 BLACK SOIL"/>don't they stop near <emph>us? </emph>I'm so tired of the emptiness and loneliness. I want to hear stakes driven into the ground; I want to hear a constant clamor . . . voices."</p><p>"Well, if it's stakes you want, any one of us can go out and drive stakes."Ignoring his evasive reply, Nell continued: "But stakes mean it's sold--taken over, occupied. I know we're not alone on the frontier any more, but I want to <emph>see </emph>the houses and the smoke, and have people to talk to close by . . . someone to run in for a piece of an afternoon."</p><p>"They'll soon be here," Tim answered assuringly. "They're still clustering around streams; but they're bound to come. You wait and see."</p><p>"I've waited four years now, and no one has settled very near." "They're coming." <pb n="29"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER V">
				<p>THE next spring Tim's prophecy was fulfilled. The Connors had near neighbors. One morning when the grain was pushing up its tender green shoots in the black patches of cultivation, Tim hitched Buck and Spec to the breaking plow and went east to assist a new comer in erecting a sod house. Nell was jubilant at the prospect of having a neighbor only a mile away. She would have liked to accompany Tim and to welcome the newcomer, but she did not wish to leave little Ellen, the new baby of the house, who was croupy. Danny, Sheila, Margaret and Kitty: Ann, however, trailed after Tim to get acquainted with the Schwartzes.</p>
				<p>John Schwartz's family, consisting of himself, his wife and seven sons, drove no stakes in building their home; but after their arrival, the immediate neighbor hood was never lacking in clamor. They were originally from Germany, but had lived in Minnesota for a few years.</p>
				<p>The Connor children, on greeting them, stood in a row before the Schwartzes similarly grouped and ranging from Nick, a lad about sixteen years old, to Vil, a curly-headed baby. There were both blonds and brunettes in the Schwartz family, but this morning they looked alike, as they were covered with the dust and grime of travel. Immediately Nick and Ditz and Pete and Herman, the four oldest, individualized themselves: Nick by chewing tobacco and expectorating promiscuously; Ditz by his grimace--a new one to the Connors<pb n="30 BLACK SOIL"/>made by dragging down the lower eyelids with one hand and tilting the nose with the other; Pete by calling out to Sheila: "Hello, English redhead;" and Herman by his slate upon which he had drawn a miscellaneous display of animals and flowers. Herman, his eyes sparkling, stepped out from the Schwartz formation and held out his slate. The Connors warily gathered about him.</p>
				<p>"There's a cat," Danny said, timidly pointing to an exhibit. "There's a rose," Margaret volunteered. "Don't you like 'em, huh?" Herman asked Sheila, who had proffered no opinion. "Yes," she began to say, as Ditz grabbed the slate, spat upon it, and erased it upon the back of his jeans.</p>
				<p>The Connors huddled together as Herman patiently rescued the slate, withdrew to a safe distance, and began to reproduce his works of art.</p>
				<p>Schwartz, who had been speaking to Tim in intelligible English, came over to his sons and addressed them in German. He was a dark man with narrow slits of eyes from which he looked sideways. The Connors forgot their fear in watching him gesticulate. He had a crooked thumb!</p>
				<p>Katto Schwartz, unobserved before, appeared and joined in conversation. She was not formidable looking: fat, blond, and squatty, with a pug nose at variance with her square, stolid face. Her voice was guttural and raucous.</p>
				<p>Her husband informed her that Tim had said it was good luck to erect the sod house on the spot where they had stopped their covered wagon.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 31"/>"Ya," she turned to Tim. "Sleep in water. You want us to get our skin wet, eh?" She swung around, pointed to a barely perceptible rise of land. "No." Ironically: "On what you call a big hill there. My house shall be there.''Connor nodded. Schwartz acquiesced. She continued her generalship.  She handed baskets to the older boys and equipped herself with the dishpan, and all began carrying sods to the indicated elevation.</p>
				<p>Thus the Schwartzes became permanent. "Better run along home, childer," Tim directed; and his brood took to their heels, dragging Kitty Ann along, to tell Nell of the strange, interesting people.</p>
				<p>"They're Indians, Mom, I bet yuh they're Indians," Danny shouted, on reaching the house first. "Hardly, child," his mother answered. Nell was rip ping heavy black silk from an umbrella which Tim had won at the cattle show at Amherst, The material would make dresses for the two little girls. "No, Danny, why do you think that? They're cousins of the Brickners … don't you remember the Brickners, that stopped here with those pretty little twins?"</p><p>"Well, they act like Indians, anyhow." Nell looked questioningly at Sheila. "They're all boys," she said, unimpressed, and picked up baby Ellen, who was cooing in her cradle.</p>
				<p>Margaret, who had recently listened to the discourses of Sheila and Danny as they recited their Catechism, found in these neighbors the embodiment of a group newly-added in her world of fantasy. "They're devils," she said laconically.</p>
				<p>When Tim returned home, later on, he smiled and<pb n="32 BLACK SOIL"/>shook his head. To Nell's inquiries he answered: "Nice enough man, but a hector of a woman, and holy terrors of childer."Nell frowned uneasily. The black material was now washed, and pressed, and cut into two dresses. She was gathering a full skirt to a tiny waist. Her stitches were uneven. She ripped them. Tim had verified the children's impressions. These, then, were to be her children's companions. And she had hoped that they would be people whom they could emulate?</p>
				<p>For the moment she forgot her sewing, was unaware of Tim's presence. She looked out of the small window. Her children had nothing but the prairie, and it held nothing for them. Was it destitute, this green that ex tended away out there until it met the blue sky? Fruitful land. It was a fruitful land. Her eyes became lighted. She saw herself and other women bringing the heritage of the East and planting it in that prairie sod. Couldn't love and deprivation purify it? Could it not be fired with a love of the ideal so that in time it would blossom into a Spirit? A Spirit that would bear the culture of the East. A Spirit that would enter into the hearts of the children.</p>
				<p>Tim stood by, painstakingly scraping the bowl of his corncob pipe with his knife. He divined something of Nell's thoughts; but he knew that the Spirit set free here would be not of the East nor of faraway places. It would be a Spirit of <emph>this prairie</emph>, and it would enter into the hearts of its children! How could the young ones whose eyes daily saw a world of beauty bounded only by heaven became identical with those who tossed jackstones<pb n="BLACK SOIL 33"/>son scrubbed sidewalks! This new West would have children of its own.</p>
				<p>He said nothing to his wife. After he had left the house, Nell picked up the black silk dress. There was an ecstatic look on her face. "I wonder, can we save it for 'em? I pray we can. The schools will help."Connors were hardly accustomed to the proximity of the Schwartzes when Max Steindler arrived and bought a section of land adjoining Connors on the north. Steindler's arrival was heralded by rumors of money, and there was the hauling of much lumber. His large house, a barn and smaller buildings, were viewed for miles around. Tim met Max and described him as a blustering old fellow with a grayish-red beard and long hair. "Regular old Robinson Crusoe."Max Steindler's wife and six grown daughters, satellites governed by his whims and wishes, arrived after the buildings were completed. They immediately became known as the wife of Max and the daughters of Max.</p>
				<p>The first time that Nell saw the wife of Max was a few days after her arrival. Nell was sewing, making a dress for Sheila from one of her own full skirts, when there was a gentle knock at the door. Sheila opened the door to a timid little woman. Her hardy body was bent a trifle forward, and she shifted her weight on the door step. Her voice, too, was hesitant.</p>
				<p>"Is your mother home?" she asked. Nell answered in person.  "Yes, come right in.  You're Mrs. Steindler, aren't you?" she asked, shaking hands. "I'm Max's wife," the caller answered, smiling, showing square yellow teeth across which her narrow lips stretched tightly.  There was a twinkle in her bright<pb n="34 BLACK SOIL"/>brown eyes. Her face was small, its skin dried into a series of wrinkles. She rubbed her hands together; her hands were small, the joints knobbed.</p>
				<p>"No, thank you, Mrs. Connor," she said. "I can't come in. I come to tell you my Annie lost her shawl, I think on your land." Her voice grew lower. "If you find it once, don't bring it back when Max will see you. Max he don't know it's lost," She looked at Nell entreatingly.</p>
				<p>Nell assured her. "If we find it, we'll get it back as you suggest. You don't know how glad I am for near neighbors," she said, clasping the woman's hand again. "Come in a bit. I have no tea, but we can have a cup of hot coffee. It's a little chilly this morning."</p><p>"No, no, Mrs. Connor," Max's wife said, turning and reluctantly withdrawing her hand. At mention of food her thoughts had automatically reverted to her husband. "No, I must hurry home and make Max's dinner." She went down the step and turned about again, smiling her wide smile. "Some other time I come, thank you.'' She hurried away, her gait a trot, a measured trot.</p>
				<p>Standing in the doorway, Nell watched the movement of the small body with the narrow, stooped back until it disappeared.</p>
				<p>Danny found the missing shawl and wished to return it. He was rather curious about the family, and wanted to learn details of the wonderful buildings.</p>
				<p>"I'll go myself,'' Nell said. "Then I'll be sure that the shawl will be returned unbeknownst to that bear of a man, I must go and see them anyhow."Leaving Sheila to care for the children, she set off next morning for the Steindlers'. As she walked across the<pb n="BLACK SOIL 35"/>
					prairie, she experienced a sense of freedom from house hold cares. It was the first time that she had been out of the yard since Ellen was born, three months before. She looked about at the growing grain, which was still in the grass stage. Her way was a sea of green. A breeze whipped her along. Meadow larks accompanied her for great stretches and then disappeared: others took up the refrain. Violets and bluebells reached up to her from the grass. She stooped occasionally and gathered those most tempting. She hummed a little, sang snatches of old songs. The sun grew hot. Slipping her own shawl from her shoulders, she folded the truant shawl within.</p>
				<p>As Nell neared Max's farm, the pretentious buildings in the center of the six hundred and forty acres were glaringly white in the sun. The windows were fiery eyes which from their point of vantage oversaw the entire section which seemed to be astir. A drove of red cattle was being herded by two girls. Nell stopped and talked to them. They were Katie and Tilly. One had the flashing brown eyes of her mother, the sparkle, however, not smouldering [sic] but vivacious; the other, not less comely, had red hair and freckles. They were neither the youngest nor the oldest. Annie, the youngest, was snaring gophers, and the older ones were helping with the breaking.</p>
				<p>Nell already had discerned two of the elder. Walking on, she passed them handling a large team of horses and a breaking plow. So intent were they upon their task that they scarcely raised their heads as she spoke to them. Nell stood for a moment. She heard the wrenching of stubborn roots of grass like ligaments tearing in a human body, followed by smoother passages where the<pb n="36 BLACK SOIL"/>
					share cut into the soil with a murmur like that of gurgling blood. The full skirts and long-curtained bonnets of the girls blew in the spring breeze; their shoulders and arms curved, contorted and grew rigid as they clung each to a plow handle while the horses with lowered heads tautly stretched their traces.</p>
				<p>Nearer the house, Nell encountered another daughter who was also assisting with the breaking. She walked beside a yoke of oxen, directing them with a goad while a young hired man held the plow handles.</p>
				<p>The wife of Max met Nell at the door with a furtive smile and led her into the house.</p>
				<p>Max was sitting on a chair in the middle of the sunny kitchen, soaking one of his feet in a basin of water. The other foot, well stockinged, was resting on a second chair. Although he smiled at Nell as he spoke, he also cast her a malevolent look from his small gray eyes which added to the savageness of his general aspect, the long, foxy beard and hair. Nell felt his eyes upon her as she talked to his wife. She glanced at him again. He lowered his eyes . . . She felt that he was a coward.</p>
				<p>The wife of Max showed Nell about the house. They paused in the doorway of the parlor which was devoid of furniture and had the odor of fresh plaster.</p>
				<p>"Nice for your girls to have a parlor, isn't it?" Nell remarked.</p>
				<p>The woman answered: "Oh, I feel so bad for my gels. I got so many gels and none are married. My Mary got a chanst back in Dyersville, but we move away." The situation was truly tragical to her.</p>
				<p>Nell, at first, could not refrain from smiling. "Don't<pb n="BLACK SOIL 37"/>worry," she said. "There's lots of time. Schwartzes over there have seven boys."The wife of Max could not smile, "My gels," she went on, "they got it so hard here. That is why I want that they should marry quick."Nell became serious. "That plowing is pretty hard for a girl . . such young girls, I never saw the likes before."The man in the kitchen listened grimly as his wife continued in a low tone: "I want <emph>I </emph>should go for Lena today. She ain't so good,'' she said significantly, " but I must fix the water for my man's foot."At which the man in the kitchen called curtly: "Hot water."His wife ran to administer to him, and Nell addressed him affably: "Nice set of buildings here. Ever farm be fore?"Max wriggled the toes on his submerged hairy foot a while before responding. "Yes, I farm before. I am a farmer, but not such a farmer as your man. . . . He's in county seat today and his corn not planted. H e can't farm," he said convincingly. "Small children no good for farmer. Dumb wife who don't stay at home and tend to her own business no good for farmer."Nell faced the grizzled man and spoke up hotly, using the vernacular: "My man is in the county seat with a neighbor who wishes to insure his crop against hail. Someone had to help him . . . he can't talk a word of English." Her voice wavered, "I am a good wife and my man is good to me. Yes, he's good to me, and will never allow the children to work as I saw" The terrified expression on the face of her hostess checked her. "Come<pb n="38 BLACK SOIL"/>out and show me your new chicken coop before I go," she said, ignoring Max's chuckle.</p>
				<p>There were tears in Nell's eyes as she returned the shawl to Max's wife behind the Hen house. Max's wife was crying also.</p>
				<p>"My man don't want that anyone should tell him that the gels must not work so hard. He thinks I tell you that you should say that," she said apologetically. She looked at Nell appealingly. "My man don't like it that they are all gels. . . Oh, why for are they not boys?"</p><p>"I don't know," Nell answered. Nell walked through the prairie grass toward her home. She had lost the rapture of the morning, The scene at the neighbor's had depressed her; but one thought seemed most vitally disturbing, No one thinks that Tim is any good as a farmer. Even that old bear. What does <emph>he </emph>know about Tim?</p>
				<p>There were the Connors' buildings before her: the small house, weathered and unpainted; the tilted barn, with holes in the thatch where the hay: had rotted away; the cottonwood grove forming a green hedge.</p>
				<p>The door of the unpainted house swung open, Kitty Ann had sighted her and had given the alarm. Here they were, all coming to meet her, Sheila in the rear carrying Ellen. It was a race! Yes, Danny would win! Then Margaret!. . .  No, Kitty Ann had passed Margaret by. . . . Poor little Robert Emmet tripped and fell headlong into the grass.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="39"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER VI">
				<p>MILL CREEK township was organized the following year. At the adjournment of the meeting each man present, with one exception, was en trusted with one or more offices. As Butch Fred, the ex empted member, expressed it: "I am the peoples. All the rest be officers, Don't it?"Tim Connor was elected secretary of the school board and township trustee.</p>
				<p>The county had been raising bonds for school purposes for several years, but graft had eaten up the funds and no buildings had been erected. Mill Creek township levied a tax for the purpose of building a school. Materials were ordered and the work finally began.</p>
				<p>This, the first school in that part of the country, was known as "the corner school,'' since it was built on the intersection of north-south and east-west trails. The north-south trail was the direct route from the terminal of the railroad in the south to the lakes further north. The east-west trail was the former path of the buffalo, deepened by the streams of caravans going to seek their fortunes out West there just beyond the horizon. These trails, curving as they dodged deep sloughs, had a permanency although in the distance they were defined only by shadows.</p>
				<p>Tim lost no occasion to secure "a man that was bandy with a hammer" to hasten the completion of the school, but work progressed slowly owing to the scarcity of lumber, After the foundations, sides and roof were completed,<pb n="40 BLACK SOIL"/>shingles were delayed.  This meant that the building could not be equipped and ready for use until fall.</p>
				<p>The Connors meanwhile continued teaching the children at home, in a haphazard way preparing them for the systematic routine of school.  Sheila could not read when she came to the prairie.  Now she was able to work fractions, to spell quite readily, and to recite her Catechism.  Sheila did not love study, but Nell kept her at it assiduously, horrified that the girl had known nothing of "God, man or the devil."  Sheila was receptive and obedient, and she made progress.</p>
				<p>"Nell Connor is not a stepmother," the neighbors often remarked to each other.  It was true.  Nell loved Sheila, and cared for her more painstakingly than she did for her own.  Often she watched Sheila, analyzing her, wondering, admiring.  The prairie wind did not freckle her as it did the Connors.  It tanned her an even golden tan.  The scorching sun bleached her red hair until it was the shade of wild honey.  The care of that hair was an irksome trial to both Sheila and Nell.  It defied string and pin and persisted in hanging free about her shoulders.  Sheila's eyes were dark brown, her eye brows black and narrow, almost meeting over her narrow nose.  Her skin was smooth, conforming well to her supple body, which had lately taken on the curves of adolescence.  Nell was giving her tansy tea.</p>
				<p>In addition to the study at home, the pictures on the Connors' walls were factors in the education of the children.  Some of these in heavy frames and a few clipped from periodicals and newspapers suggested Bible stories, and tales of history.  All the older children could relate the stories of <emph>The Last Supper, The Landing of the Pilgrims,</emph>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 41"/>and <emph>The Trial of Robert Emmet;</emph> but only Danny could identify those referred to by Tim as "the rogues' gallery."  Danny would rattle off:  "There's Mom's Uncle Henry at Hadley; there's Abraham Lincoln what freed the slaves; there's Horace Greeley, the first man that Pop ever voted for in this country; there's Walt Whitman, the man that Mom don't like but Pop does.  He wrote that about the prairie grass--'The prairie grass dividing, its special odor breathing, I demand of it the spiritual. . . ' What's the rest o' that, Pop?"Each child had a favorite picture.  Margaret would stand transfixed before <emph>Waiting for the Tide at Venice, </emph>wondering when that boat would move; and little Robert Emmet associated himself in a vague way with the tall young man standing erect in the face of those stern, wigged puppets.</p>
				<p>Another source of enlightenment at the time was a mission church which was established at Casper Center by Father Leurmann.  Connor and his family attended Mass whenever possible.  Here Sheila was baptized and received the name:  Sheila Moore Connor.</p>
				<p>"You're Sheila Connor now," Nell said.  "You be long to us."Nell's bit of sentiment were embarrassing to Sheila. She did not know just how to receive them.  She remained quiet, but smiled.  Nell's announcement was no revelation to her . . . she had always been Sheila Con nor, hadn't she?  Reference had been seldom made to her true parentage, and then only when Nell was called upon by some curious but well-meaning mover to ac count for the disparity of years between her and Danny.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="42 BLACK SOIL"/>Sheila was now eligible to join a class of boys and girls for "special instruction,'' and during the summer she made her first Communion. On this occasion Nell allowed Tim to remain at home with the children, and she herself accompanied Sheila, driving the oxen twelve miles to be present at the solemn event.</p>
				<p>Sheila wore a new white dress, and her mass of curls were lustrous and intact, Nell having protected them during the long ride with a heavy scarf. A woman living near the church opened her house to the communicants and their mothers, and here Nell drew out her wedding veil from a box and draped it over Sheila's curls. While other women were adjusting wax wreaths, Nell un earthed from a damp paper a dainty spray of bluebells which she had gathered and woven into a chain the night before.</p>
				<p>When Nell saw Sheila in the procession, her eyes grew moist, She wondered, about the girl's mother. Sheila was not .only different from the Connors; she was different from the children around her. There was some thing truly distinctive about her. As she passed with her easy, graceful stride, her face like the others wore a look of rapture; but the deep, dark eyes held a mystery: which frightened Nell. For love her and do for her as she might, she feared that she could never wholly under stand her.</p>
				<p>When the children were grouped before the altar of the crude little church, Nell knelt and prayed. She asked God to guide her in raising Sheila and to protect the girl from all harm to soul and body. "I want to do the very best I can for her. Help me. Guide me."She kissed Sheila after the service, saying: "I hope <pb n="BLACK SOIL 43"/>you will always remain as pure and sweet as you are to day."On the way home Nell's thoughts reverted to the baby.  In her zeal for Sheila perhaps she had been negligent of her own. . . Ellen was such a wee baby.  She tried to hurry the oxen, but unmindful of exhortations or goad their pace remained unchanged.  Resigned, she spoke of school in the fall.  How fortunate they were now to have a school!  She had been planning somewhat on what they would wear.  There was a wine-colored silk that she had been saving.  Now she would make it over for Sheila.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="44"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER VII">
				<p>ONE sunny September morning, the first day of. school in Mill Creek township, the Connors rose very early. It was a momentous day. <emph>The children were starting to school! </emph>It was the beginning and it would lead . . . well, God knows where. While Nell prepared the breakfast, she allowed herself to dream and to hope. There was a vision of Sheila going back East to school--to Mt. Holyoke. Sheila would lead the way. The others would follow. Danny to Amherst--Nell checked herself guiltily as she realized there were so many, many present needs, and the future was so far away. But who could tell?</p>
				<p>After Tim went threshing, Nell arranged Sheila's hair in eighteen long curls, brushing each painstakingly around her finger. Sheila wore the wine-colored silk, The soft material clung to her supple young body, and Nell was pleased with her efforts. The beginning would be auspicious, and she would trust in God for its continuance. She must have a ribbon to tie some of those suds, Nell went to the bedroom and clipped a ribbon from a bonnet worn on her wedding trip to Boston one of the few treasures that she had kept intact--and tied it on the girl's hair.</p>
				<p>Danny had his hair shingled and wore a new gingham' suit. His face shone with soap and his eyes with anticipation, "Gosh! Going to school?" he ejaculated at intervals.</p>
				<p>Margaret allowed herself to be washed and her soft<pb n="BLACK SOIL 45"/>brown hair fixed in ringlets: then she cried, as she had no book. Danny had a second reader, and Sheila many books, including <emph>David Copperfield, </emph>which served as a reader. Nell took down the <emph>Almanac </emph>from its nail and gave it to Margaret to appease her. "Now you have a book, too," she said comfortingly. "We'll have new books after the threshing is done, Hurry on, children, and don't be late."Eighteen other children walked miles through the dewy prairie and assembled with the Connors at the corner school. Many of them had never been in a school building; nor had they, owing to the clannishness of different settlements, become acquainted with each other. Somewhat awestricken they huddled together--feudish impulses for the moment forgotten and gaped at the clean white walls, the twelve shiny double seats, the six bright windows, the patch of blackboard, the round bellied stove, and the teacher.</p>
				<p>The boys wore wool caps and hats of straw or felt whatever they happened to have pulled down with disregard for courtesy or lopped ears. Shirts and make shift pants of gingham or jeans extending to the ankle completed their attire. The younger boys still held the appeal of babyhood.</p>
				<p>The girls' tight waists and full skirts were made-overs of various materials: linsey-woolsey, muslin, calico, silk. Many of these had been garments worn by their elders when they came into the country. Their hair was tightly braided or hanging open for the day.</p>
				<p>All shifted about on their bare feet and stared at the strange man before them.</p>
				<p>Teacher, in an armchair, officially opened and closed<pb n="46 BLACK SOIL"/>the drawers of his table: then rose to the height of six feet, two inches; moved his basket of lunch to a more suitable corner of his desk; placed a sledgehammer fist upon the <emph>Webster's International Dictionary; </emph>looked down with beadlike eyes over an extravagant length of nose; and addressed the children.</p>
				<p>"I am your teacher," he began. "My name is Jerome Loutch. I hope in time to know your names and to learn you to read and write. I hope you all have books and slates.'' Here his oratory ceased and his voice struck a less formal. note. "You little fellows sit up here to gather," he said, leading two to the front seat. They moved reluctantly, looking anxiously at their elders. "You girls sit here. Larger ones in back."Walking among them, he paired them off. As most of the families represented were large and of corresponding ages, it came about that members of unfriendly cliques were placed side by side in double seats. A <emph>Breid-barth with a Schwartz!</emph>Margaret refused to occupy the seat indicated with the small girl in the front of the room. Instead she sat with Sheila and buried her face in the older girl's lap.</p>
				<p>"Won't you come up, Margaret?" Loutch encouraged. Margaret's body stiffened, and a shudder ran through her. "You'll sit up here tomorrow, won't you?" he said helplessly.</p>
				<p>The room was very quiet. All faces were turned. There was a stir in Sheila's lap. One moist blue eye appeared above the desk. The tone was unmistakable: "I ain't comin' morrow."BLACK SOIL 47The tension of the room was broken by Margaret's audacity. Ditz Schwartz immediately ventured: "My brother can't sit with Heinie Breidbarth--he's <emph>Low German."</emph>This statement was like fire to a series of bombs. "YOU mustn't, you mustn't . . . here now" Loutch began, as many of the children rose to their feet with protests.</p>
				<p>"I can't sit by Emmie Steinberg. She got the lice, my mother say." Then, <emph>sotto voce </emph>to a neighboring ally: "Luxemburgers got the lice."Epithets of <emph>Luxemburger </emph>and <emph>Plattdeutsch </emph>were hurled at each other, kicks and cuffs were exchanged. While Jerome Loutch stood scratching his thin pinkish hair and wondering just how much he could interfere without offense to patrons, the fruit basket was upset, and children carrying books and slates moved about the room. Loutch's position as teacher was rather hazardous at best, and he had been advised by. the county superintendent to teach as peacefully as possible. By no means was he to arouse the wrath of patrons. H e had not been warned of this strife. . . . This surely was an unusual state of affairs.</p>
				<p>During the confusion, Danny's seatmate, Emil Grothe, had not moved, In some subtle way it was known that the Connors didn't count. The Connors were not in the fight.</p>
				<p>For the moment, Danny was bewildered. This was not the kind of school that he had imagined. They needed no manners for school as Mom had said. He didn't seem to be learning much, but there were many interesting children around him. First of all, he was favored<pb n="48 BLACK SOIL"/>in his seat partner. Emil was lame: he had a shriveled foot. He had also a tubular pencil box, whose lid he had allowed Danny to crack off and on after he had moistened it generously with his tongue.</p>
				<p>Louisa Beaver, sitting behind Danny, had a long white mark on her upper lip. And Ernest Probst, across the aisle, scraped his cheek against his shoulder until it bled. Hank Webber had a scooped mouth. Then, too, Herman Schwartz was drawing Teacher on his slate.</p>
				<p>After the exchange of seats, there was a general quiet. Loutch ascended to his platform and called a. class. The room had adjusted itself and in so doing the authority of the school had shifted from Teacher to the majority party the High Germans, And Ditz Schwartz, the protagonist, who had six brothers, knew that he con trolled Loutch.</p>
				<p>When school was dismissed at four o'clock, difficulties brewing all day were settled by pitched battles wherein girls fought in defense of boys, brothers in defense of sisters. Teacher, carrying his empty basket, paused in the yard. "Children," he said, "the director will not allow this. Your parents will not allow this either. Now go home," Turning quickly, he set off to ward his boarding place.</p>
				<p>His admonition only stimulated the contestants and they responded by shouting challenges to him.</p>
				<p>The Connors, already on their way, looked back and witnessed the fray. Bennie Hurd was with them. Bennie was connected with Hollanders, and exempt like them selves. He was from New Jersey and had come to Iowa to live with an aunt and uncle who were childless and<pb n="BLACK SOIL 49"/>
					lonely.  He was different from the other boys.  His books were covered with calico, his face and hands were clean, and his clothes were "boughten."  His aunt and uncle  lived beyond the Connors, so he went part way with  them.  After he had left them to turn north, the Connors, very hungry, and anxious to tell their impressions of the day, quickened their pace.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="50"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER VIII">
				<p>OH, he'll get the upper hand of 'em in a few days," Tim said comfortingly as he and Nell discussed the discipline of the school that evening. Tim sensed his wife's great disappointment in the school for which she had been praying for years, "They'll learn Something and get on to the routine a bit," he said, climbing into bed. "I'm dog tired, . . . Another term the teacher may be better."Nell stood by the bed and looked out to where the fields were flooded with moonlight. She told Tim about Margaret, how she had acted and what she had said. "A11 evening she cried whenever school was mentioned."</p><p>"Poor young one," Tim said, then chuckled. "Did Margaret say that? Bully for her. Let her stop at home. She's young and has plenty of time for school."</p><p>"If we give in now maybe she'll never want to go," Nell said, tucking in her fifth born.</p>
				<p>"Margaret has a reasoning all her own," Tim argued. "Aren't you afraid you'll be making her headstrong, Tim? And what bad manners it was in her! I'm just mortified before all those children!"Tim adjusted his pillow with a thump of finality. "Don't expect too much of 'em, Nell. A child will be a child, whether its grandfather was a land agent or a highwayman,"Sheila and Danny attended school regularly. Nell watched the cows at intervals and kept them from the<pb n="BLACK SOIL 51"/>
					corn. Margaret remained at home and faithfully tended the baby while her mother was absent.</p>
				<p>Margaret cared little for sharing Kitty Ann's games. She preferred making expeditions to visit her friends on the prairie. She had a personal interest in, and speaking acquaintance with, every bird and flower.</p>
				<p>But Kitty Ann disregarded Margaret's favorites. With an air of utter abandon she chased butterflies, disturbed ant hills, and poked earth into gopher holes.</p>
				<p>It was little Robert Emmet whom Margaret enjoyed having with her on her excursions. He was an avid listener. She showed him the fairies with the golden hair who lived down near the slough. "See 'em nod, Emmet, nod 'yes, yes' all the time?"Robert Emmet, credulous, did not disagree as did Kitty Ann, He opened wider his round blue eyes, eager to span his ever-widening horizon, and clung with difficulty to Margaret's neck while his chubby legs grappled to find a footing on her curveless body.</p>
				<p>"See 'em, Emmet? See 'em bow their heads and wave to us?"</p><p>"I see, I see," he answered. "We can't go over there alone. The grass is too high. Sheila will take us some time," she promised, setting him heavily on the ground.</p>
				<p>The days of autumn sunshine grew shorter and the nights were chilly. Nell hoped that the cold would hold off until the threshing was done and their trip made to town. She was busy with the eternal patching and making things over to keep her brood covered. It would be easier after the trip to town, when new materials could be obtained.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="52 BLACK SOIL"/>There was nothing in the line of fruit for fall preserving. Nell wished she might have some of the fruit that no doubt was wasting back East. She dried corn, how ever, and other vegetables and tied them in sacks. In the cave was kraut, and a barrel of cucumbers in brine.</p>
				<p>They had had a good crop and a fine garden. She had helped with both. She had taken a man's place in haying and shocking., Work to her had become negligible what was heavy work if obstacles were on hand to be overcome?</p>
				<p>Tim had resented her help. . .he could manage. They had harvested without hiring help. Now there were only the threshing and the corn husking, and Tim could take his time to these.</p>
				<p>One crisp day of Indian summer, Nell sat outside the door in the afternoon. From this position she could watch the cattle as they grazed homeward, and also be near the toddling Ellen. It was warm and pleasant there, too.</p>
				<p>The pollen-laden south breeze blew against her face. It lacked its earlier delicate scents and was pungent. The choruses of bird and insect were gone, but blackbirds congregating on the cottonwoods produced a dismal, in terminable chatter.</p>
				<p>"Sign of a death in the family during the year," was  the superstition of such a visit of blackbirds. This thought saddened Nell for the moment, but she soon banished it as nonsense. Hadn't the birds visited them annually for two or three years without any such after math? Her family was entire, and a lovely family it was, healthy and bright and straight of limb, How she would like to dress them up and have, them parade the streets<pb n="BLACK SOIL 53"/>of Northampton, "Look! There are Tim Connor's and Nell Powers's children!" The family was entire, augmented, in fact the covered wagon conspiring with the prairie stork. Nell smiled at her own humor. "As Tim says, 'A fool laughing at my own folly.' "Baby Ellen in her meanderings had reached her knee. Nell gathered her into her arms and lulled her to sleep. "God keep her," she prayed as she looked down at the sleeping child. "Keep her. Keep all of them. Guard their minds, their hearts and their bodies. . . And I'll do my part," she added hopefully.</p>
				<p>But when the children came from school and related the day's excitement, her spirits sank.</p>
				<p>"This can't go on," she concluded. "We must look into it."She was still in a perturbed state of mind while she did the evening chores; and when Tim drove in from threshing she accosted him before he had climbed from the wagon.</p>
				<p>"Something must be done about the quarreling at school," she began. "That teacher can't cope with conditions at all. He's been giving two sets of recesses, one for each faction, and our brave Danny has been taking advantage of both. I was so in hopes that Loutch would come for his first month's wages and we could talk to him: but I suppose he'll wait now until both months are in. You'd better go and see him," she concluded, looking up at Tim.</p>
				<p>"Is that all's the matter?" Tim said, standing up stiffly. "From the look on your face I thought the devil himself was to pay. It's you that can sing the Molly Bawn about nothing at all."<pb n="54 BLACK SOIL "/>
					Yellow with chaff he crawled down over the wheel. Chaff was piled on his shoulders and in the creases of his felt hat. His eyes were bloodshot and unnatural with their powdered lashes. He had been threshing barley, and wore his shirt hanging outside his jeans like a smock.</p>
				<p>He drew himself up before his wife, his tall body gaunt in the flowing shirt. "Why don't you go up your self and see that simpleton?" he said. "I'll not be having the time." He tossed aside his hat and wiped his face with a grimy bandana. "Whew! the chaff in that wind was a fright. Danny, give a hand here."Danny unhitched the traces and unbuckled the girths of Jack and Jule. Their muscles quivered as Tim raised the heavy: harness from their sore shoulders. Danny led the horses to the trough, and Tim swung around. "Childer," he said, "what do you think of your Pop's white whiskers? Have a clean shirt for me, Nell, and a bit of warm water."Nell did not go to see Jerome Loutch. The term would soon be over. The factions meanwhile continued to quarrel, and to read four times a day.</p>
				<p>The primary class droned out <emph>cat </emph>as Loutch pointed to the picture. Once Danny was called to the blackboard alone. At his mother's suggestion he had questioned the  teacher on several occasions: "When are we going to have arithmetic?." The answer was always evasive; but one day he was startled as he was reading Bennie Hurd's  <emph>Arabian Nights </emph>to hear: "Danny, go to the board and do some sums." Reluctantly he put aside the book, went to the board, and placed the correct answers after the<pb n="BLACK SOIL 55"/>inscribed columns. Danny was studying his tables and long division at home, so addition was mere play; but the incident was important, as it was the only time Loutch had called a class in arithmetic. Bennie and Sheila had arithmetics [sic] from which they studied without school supervision. Often it was Bennie who helped Sheila when her dark eyebrows were brought together in a frown as the work seemed incomprehensible.</p>
				<p>Danny was friendly to Bennie, also. Bennie was an example of the children who lived, in that other world off there beyond the big slough, off farther than he had ever dared to venture. T o the other boys, Bennie was no prototype; he was ignored as the Connors were ignored. Bullying them was not so stimulating as humiliating a Luxemburger or a Low German.</p>
				<p>Herman Schwartz alone had a secret dislike for Bennie. Herman, though closely allied with the pugnacious element, was not an active member, He neither attacked the Low Germans nor defended his own. He spent his day drawing pictures on anything available. Already the schoolhouse walls were decorated with prairie sunsets; and the outbuildings were defaced with caricatures of Teacher. Loutch sought favor with the Schwartzes by allowing Herman to use his colored chalk at pleasure. He also agreed with Bennie that Herman had talent.</p>
				<p>Herman disregarded Bennie's praise, antagonized him whenever possible, and sought favor with Sheila by giving her the dainties from his lunch, These things Sheila accepted with utter indifference, but ate with relish, much to Danny's disgust.</p>
				<p>The equilibrium of the Connors' supper table was often disturbed by Danny's reference to Sheila's voraciousness.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="56 BLACK SOIL"/>
					"Sheila, you'd eat anything that Herman would give you. I'd be good and hungry before I'd eat what Katto baked. . . Even the threshers couldn't eat there, could they, Pop?"As Sheila said nothing, Nell rose to her defense. "Katto's all right, and Herman's different from the rest."Danny was about to speak again, but Tim's "dry up now" silenced him.</p>
				<p>Sheila was apparently unconvinced and unmoved. Though quiet, she would not forget Danny's insolence, and at some future time when the Connors had completely forgotten the incident she would slight Danny in some way and say softly, "That was for what you said about my eating Herman's lunches."</p><p>"In some ways Sheila is so different from us," Nell often said to Tim when they: were alone.</p>
				<p>"Yes, I notice it, too, since she's growing up; but you can't expect her to act like an Irishman, can you, when she isn't one?"</p><p>"No, I suppose that's it." Sheila continued to share Herman's lunch, work her arithmetic, and read four times a day. The wine-colored silk was torn and patched, Danny's suit was in tatters, and the flour was gone. All were anticipating Tim's and Nell's trip to town. <pb n="57 "/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER IX">
				<p>ONE morning toward the last of October, Tim announced that by noon the yearly threshing would be completed and he would be ready to start plowing up potatoes. This announcement was met with general applause. I t indicated that the long anticipated trip with the grist and the garden truck would be made next day.</p>
				<p>In the afternoon Tim, true to his word, having hauled the wagon to the truck patch, hitched Jack and Jule to the plow. The bright shares cut into the baked ground, deftly turned under the crisp stalks, and un earthed the smooth potatoes. The Connor children, buckets in hand, fell upon them like a flock of yellow legs.</p>
				<p>The air still held the warm, drowsy feeling of Indian summer. Light clouds floated leisurely overhead. The prairie  stubble, corn and grass--was dredged with yellow. Occasionally wedge-shaped flocks of geese and ducks flew high to the south and melted into blue sky and misty cloud.</p>
				<p>The children worked faithfully for a while. Sheila walked in the rear, as Nell suggested, and gathered potatoes overlooked by the more spirited. As she stooped, her hair, hanging over her shoulders, brushed the ground. When pails and baskets were filled, Danny climbed up on the hub of the wagon wheel and emptied them into the wagon box with a low, deep rumble.</p>
				<p>Emmet was the first deserter. Casting aside his tobacco<pb n="58 BLACK SOIL"/>pail, he watched a tumblebug in a prodigious under taking. Kitty Ann was tempted away by: the white butterflies which sailed dreamily around the heads of cabbage. The task became irksome to Margaret when bursting milkweed pods scattered their silky down.</p>
				<p>Nell worked in the garden with a broad, sharp knife. Bending with difficulty, she cut off cabbage. As the heads fell to the ground, shiny yellow drops oozed from their outer leaves. Danny deserted the potatoes to follow her, and with his jackknife cut wedge-shaped pieces of stump, which all the children ate regardless of their earthy hands.</p>
				<p>Keep moving, children," Nell admonished. "Don't you want us to get your shoes tomorrow? Dig out some of those carrots with your knife, Danny, but don't break off the tops."Tim had stopped at the end of a furrow, and with hands on his hips stood looking off to the south, where the fall growth of grass was thick and shoulder high.</p>
				<p>"Come here, childer," he called. When they had gathered around him, he pointed off to the dark brown flecks on the yellow, shimmering grass. The grass was lighted by the lowering rays of the sun and was stirred by the wind into soft, velvety ripples, endowed with life, moving ceaselessly, untiringly. Its brown flecks were running, running, racing, racing but never free.</p>
				<p>"Do you know what I see?" he asked. "I see big Brown bears but there their legs tie that. They Keep crawling along on their stomachs, but they can't get away."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 59"/>  Danny smiled. "Oh, I seen 'em lots of times. They're patches of ripe grass, Pop."</p><p>"Will they eat us?" Kitty Ann asked in alarm, raising a face the worse for carrots and black soil.</p>
				<p>"No," Margaret assured her, "their legs are tied." Rather bewildered, Emmet followed Danny and Sheila back to their work.</p>
				<p>Only Margaret stood by. "I wish I could see 'em better, Pop," she said, as Tim knew she would.</p>
				<p>He lifted her to his shoulder. "I know how they got there," she said ruminatively. Tim waited. A moment went by. Jack and Jule impatiently stamped their feet and swished their tails at the flies.</p>
				<p> "Don't you suppose it was seeds scattered down by the clouds?" Tim suggested cautiously. "Or was it the fairies?"</p><p>"Don't you know, Pop?" Margaret answered. "It was the queen of the fairies. The golden cups and saucers that the fairies picked up the dew in got stolen. They were robbed, robbed by Jessie James. So the fairy queen sent those bears to take care of 'em. And now they can't be robbed any more." Margaret laughed and hit her heels against Tim's chest.</p>
				<p>"The bears'll fix the Jameses all right," he encouraged.</p>
				<p>"And then" Margaret continued. The cry of baby Ellen reached the garden. "Margaret, run to the baby," Nell called. Margaret left off with her story, slid from her father's shoulder, ran to the cradle, and rocked it violently.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="60 BLACK SOIL "/>The sun sank lower; a chill came into the air, All the Connors repaired to the house and yard. Sheila worked on alone.</p>
				<p>Standing in the last glare of the sun she felt the urge and pull of an enfolding adolescence. It caressed her,  assured her. Life was sweet; life would be sweeter. She did not question who she really was nor why she was thrust into this family. She was fairly content with life now, but she saw in the glamour of the sunset tonight a prophecy that some day beyond that yellow horizon she would find the perfection, the fulfillment [sic] of a life that she now but vaguely felt.</p>
				<p>She thought of the new shoes that would be obtained on the morrow. These, and the new dress, she would display at school . . . especially to Bennie Hurd and perhaps, Herman Schwartz.</p>
				<p>As she dreamed, mechanically reaching for potatoes, the east was lighted as though the earth had instantaneously rotated, causing a sudden dawn. Familiar bars of fire tinged the sky, and smoke rose from the dark fringed border. Tim and Nell hurried outside the grove and watched the east. The children gathered tearfully around them.</p>
				<p>"Is prairie fire coming home?" "Will it get us, Pop? Danny said 'twould get us." While Nell herself looked at Tim before making reply, Danny spoke up: Naw, can't get us. Wind's from the north."</p><p>"It's headed toward Cherokee," Tim enlightened Them. "Hope it won't burn up the straw piles. Poor critters of cattle'll need them this winter."After supper a dull glow still covered the land. The<pb n="BLACK SOIL 61"/>Connors needed no lantern to complete their preparations. While Tim loaded the wagon with wheat and vegetables, Nell, Sheila, and Danny filled the poultry crates fastened to the rear of the wagon. Chickens drugged with sleep were pulled from trees and sheds; .the roosters were crated, and the pullets, set free, went blindly into the dusk. When the children were put to bed the only evidence of the fire was a hazy sky and the pungent odor of burned grass.</p>
				<p>Sheila, from her bed in the loft, heard Nell and Tim in their final discussion of the trip. The greatest item was shoes, shoes for all.</p>
				<p>Nell, sitting at the kitchen table with the list in her hand, said: "The baby will be easy to fit, and Sheila's I can fit on myself. If they are a little large for me they will fit Sheila."</p><p>"Better be sure they're big enough," Tim advised, as he trimmed his beard at the cracked mirror in the kitchen.</p>
				<p>"Well, come help me then, and let's measure their feet," Nell said, picking up a string.</p>
				<p>They stood first over Danny's and Robert Emmet's bed. Emmet's head was nestled against Danny's shoulder. A mere baby with little chubs of feet. Danny, breathing deeply, his thin face wan in repose, The month was firm, the chin pointed.</p>
				<p>"If that old ague will only stay away. from him this spring," Nell said prayerfully.</p>
				<p>"We'll get him a fine pair of copper-toed boots," Tim answered, as he measured a calloused foot and placed it beside its mate.</p>
				<p>The lamp in Nell's hand cast a glow over Margaret's<pb n="62 BLACK SOIL"/>and Kitty Ann's faces. Kitty, mischievous eyes closed, was doll-like with her mass of yellow curls. As she yielded her foot, a half-eaten carrot fell from her grimy hand.</p>
				<p>Margaret opened her eyes and closed them again tightly. Her shoulders and arms, protruding from her underwaist, were thin. Her dark fringe of eyelashes increased the pallor of her face. Her nose, as usual, harbored a horseshoe of brown freckles.</p>
				<p>"She's growing so tall, and you see Kitty isn't,'' Nell said.</p>
				<p>Tim wiggled her toes a little as he measured her. "Our freckled-faced Maggie has a bit of the poet in her."</p><p>"Lord save us, Tim. Not poet. Poets don't have good reputations." "Just said a little of the poet, Nell, the desirable qualities. How's that?" he answered, looking at her out of the corner of his eye. At which both smiled.</p>
				<p>"Tim," Nell paused, lamp in hand, "do you know what day it is?" "Yes,  Thursday, and we're going on a spree tomorrow." "Tim, you don't know. Think of the date." "Indeed'n I do now, me girl. How many years? Not more than--Danny's ten--well, we'll have to add on a little."</p><p>"Tim, such talk. It's eleven years. Eleven years ago today, you and I went arm in arm out of my uncle's door and through the gate."</p><p>"Yes, and now come on. Tonight, eleven years after, I will go out of our own door  our own, not<pb n="BLACK SOIL 63"/>counting the bit of a mortgage that's against it. But as they say in court, 'We have some equity in it.' "Arm in arm they stood in the doorway. "Not having a gate we can reproduce the scene no farther," said Tim.</p>
				<p>They were silent for a while, their thoughts racing back and forth like shuttles over the past years and resting on the scene before them the prairie, with its majestic sweep of land lighted by an unusual ruddy light.</p>
				<p>
					<emph>Eleven years! </emph> Here was fulfillment [sic] . . . the sturdy little feet that were measured for shoes, and the where withal to buy the shoes. The loaded wagon, assuming immense proportions, testified to this. The doomed roosters, wakeful in their propinquity, agreed.</p>
				<p>"Let's celebrate tomorrow," Tim spoke out. "What kind of a wedding is eleven years? Not a wooden wedding, is it?"</p><p>"I don't know what it is . . nothing, I guess." "I'll tell you. It's a slough-grass anniversary. Now that's something we can produce."</p><p>"Wouldn't that be funny?" Nell answered, entering into Tim's jovial mood. "Slough-grass anniversary." "Yes," Tim went on, "and we have a yard here that could entertain the whole of Massachusetts and York state, too, and all your clan from Boston could come and we'd feed 'em rose haws, creamed rose haws, garnished with seeds and wigglers, How's that, Nellie?"</p><p>"Oh, quit your nonsense and come on in, Tim. We'll have to be up early in the morning." <pb n="64"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER X">
				<p>THE Connors were astir early. Sheila woke to the thump, thump of Tim's boots on the kitchen floor. Nell was rattling stove lids; there was the aroma of barley coffee. Crated chickens squawked complainingly, and the privileged chanticleer left behind answered with a rising: "Ka, ka, ka, ka--what is it all about?"A faint pink rimmed the eastern horizon, Recalling the day's duties, Sheila flung herself out of bed. This time tomorrow she would have a slate pencil. Hers must have a flag on it and must <emph>not be broken.</emph>When she descended into the kitchen., Nell was tying on a black hood. Instructions which she had heard at. intervals for two months were again repeated. "Don't let anything happen to the children; but if something does happen, send Danny for Katto. We're all out of meal, but you can get along. Boil potatoes, and give 'em plenty of milk. Be careful of fire don't put in too much hay with the draft open, Keep Ellen dry and warm. She took a little cold yesterday. Don't let the I children off in the tall grass." With this last which had not been included before: "On the top shelf of the cup board there's a little brown sugar for the baby's milk," Nell fastened her broshay shawl and climbed into the wagon. "Goodbye now. We'll be back by nightfall."By the time the younger children were dressed and Danny was ready to take out the cattle, the sun was hid den in a hazy gray sky. Danny rode to the house on Ned's back, and the children congregated around him.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 65"/>(Ned was old and almost blind; he had been left behind by movers.)"Look!" Danny pointed at myriads of ducks and geese flying swiftly to the south. "Well, must be movin," he broke off importantly. He adjusted the gunny sack which served as a saddle, straightened his wiry, slim body, dug his heels into Ned's ribs, and gal loped off behind the herd.</p>
				<p>In the afternoon when Danny drove in the cattle, all went to meet him. It was cool out of doors; but they wanted to be free from the house which loneliness had pervaded. The children were conscious of its emptiness without Mom, who had been there always. Now a certain responsibility, owing to the unusualness of the day, was shared by all, down to baby Ellen.</p>
				<p>"Let's do the chores. There's going to be a storm or something," Danny called against the brisk wind which had lately risen.</p>
				<p>"It's too early," Sheila answered, as she shifted the heavy Ellen to her other hip. "What'll Pop say?"</p><p>"Well, I don't want to be out in no storm. I'm about frozen now." This from Danny, whose face was red with cold. "Let's do the other chores and then milk, Let's get extra hay in to burn. We must cover that pile of potatoes, too."Sheila complied, and by the time they had finished milking it was snowing. The wind was blowing fiercely, tossing the snow madly about.</p>
				<p>"Didn't I tell yuh?" Danny asked proudly, showing his permanent frontals which loomed large in line with his just appearing bicuspids. "The geese and ducks knew it. Funny we can't tell better."<pb n="66 BLACK SOIL"/>The children drank the warm milk and watched for Pop and Mom until sudden darkness covered the window pane. When the wind swooped around the house and drove the snow against the roof, Danny jumped from his chair.</p>
				<p>"It's a regular blizzard,'' he announced like a veteran, "and the stock will be buried. I've tied Ned and I'm going to untie him and I'll turn the cattle loose."They opened the door, and the wind swung it from their hands. They stood in a semicircle, just inside. A duck and a drake quacked assuringly on the doorstep. The premature night was not black but white. Only at intervals could they see the barn and cowshed.</p>
				<p>Danny put on his cap and an old coat and boots of Tim's.</p>
				<p>"Ain't you afraid, Danny?" Sheila asked in alarm. "Mom wouldn't want you to go."</p><p>"I ain't afraid much, You see, everything will be buried 'fore morning.''Still he hesitated on the sill. The wind chilled the house and tossed things about. The children drew back their semicircle.</p>
				<p>Suddenly Danny set his chin, bent his head, and stepped into the storm. The children waited. He re turned in a short time.</p>
				<p>"A knife, Sheila. I need a butcher knife. Ned's rope's so frozen I can't untie it." Again he disappeared and again returned.</p>
				<p>"Pop and Mom ought to be comin','' he remarked. "They'll have a terrible trip." "Oh, Pop won't get lost," Sheila comforted.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 67"/>"But that wagon in the snow. . . . Snow's gettin' terrible deep, and driftin'." At Danny's apparent alarm, the younger children cried with anxiety. "Why don't you put them young ones to bed?" he asked.</p>
				<p>They lighted the lamp, although they were low on kerosene. Danny fed the fire. Then all prayed in secret and aloud, Kitty Ann reiterating in tears: "Dod, bring Pop and Mom home from the bad storm, and don't let my new shoes get all snowy."When there was apparent quiet in the bedroom ad joining, Danny looked up at Sheila, who was sitting with him beside the fire, and remarked convincingly: "I bet yuh Pop and Mom are dead."</p><p>"Why, Danny, Pop always comes home. Maybe they stopped at somebody's house."</p><p>"They wouldn't stop at no house." There was a wail from the bedroom. Kitty Ann had overheard. "Oh, Danny said Pop and Mom are dead." Sheila went to her. "They'll come during the night."</p><p>"O oh. Mom and Pop'll come during the night." " 'N bring me tandy?" Emmet was awake also. "Yes." "O-oh, <emph>candy!" </emph>in chorus. "And shoes for all of us." This from Sheila. "Shoes for me?" "Yes." "Sooz for me?" "Yes, go to sleep now."</p><p>"O-oh, Pop and Mom are coming home, Pop and Mom ain't dead at all."<pb n="68 BLACK SOIL"/> "Go to bed, Danny," Sheila said as she reentered the kitchen and saw him slouched dejectedly in the chair.</p>
				<p>Danny was not thinking of rest. Knowing that his parents could not combat the storm, he was convinced that they were dead. And they had always returned be fore. He stood up, toyed a little with the lamp screw, .and announced solemnly: "If they are dead I'll help you raise the children, Sheila." He then left the kitchen and took his place beside Emmet.</p>
				<p>Sheila slept in the big bed, and rocked the cradle when Ellen began crying. The wind caught up the child's wail, repeated it, echoed it, and sent it moaning through the stovepipe. The roof sent down bass cracking chords. The little house, beating out the tempo, rocked in the hold of the wind. In momentary lulls they heard Ellen's difficult breathing. There was the tapping, tapping of a dangling clothesline against the corner of the house. Its tattoo was melancholy, ominous. Sheila wrapped her feet in her petticoat, curled up and prayed. She prayed all her English prayers and then attempted the German prayers heard recently recited in concert at church.</p>
				<p>Danny: alone was awake when Ellen began to gasp  for breath. Having slept near Ellen the eighteen months of her life, he recognized symptoms of croup. Jumping out of bed like a released spring, he groped to the cradle and grabbed up the child. Turning her over on her face, he ran his finger as gently as he could down her throat and produced vomiting, The relieved child cried raucously.</p>
				<p>"Sheila! for God's sake get up and start the fire. Ellen has croup awful bad," he called, "Sheila. <emph>Sheila!"</emph>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 69"/>Danny was in tears himself, his teeth chattering with cold and anxiety.</p>
				<p>Sheila, her head entirely covered to shut out the noises of the storm, was hard to arouse. Finally Danny succeeded in waking her, and they lighted the lamp and built a fire. Danny drew a chair to the stove and wrapped a quilt about himself and Ellen, holding her to the warmth there. When the baby's breathing became nor mal and she slept again, his thoughts went to his parents, lost out there in that night of storm. The fears of the evening returned to him. They: were dead or they would have come. He brushed away his tears with the back of his hand and sat up in his chair. He wouldn't be a baby there were enough babies around. He would meet it like a man. And, as the wind continued to blow against the house, merciful sleep came to Danny and he bowed his head over Ellen's face.</p>
				<p>While the young Connors slept, Tim and Nell spent a sleepless night in the crude hotel at Shelbourne. While Tim praised the horses for their sagacity in refusing to start out in the storm, Nell's lips moved inaudibly.</p>
				<p>The next morning the Connor children woke to find themselves entirely submerged, It was morning and Mom and Pop had not come! Sheila now was ready to share Danny's opinion, and in her inexperienced way she wondered what would become of them all. The youngest shrieked as their bare feet came in contact with the snow which had found its way in through every crevice. Before the door was a large drift. The house had not been banked or prepared for winter.</p>
				<p>Having breakfasted on milk and potatoes, they united their strength in opening the door. They were welcomed<pb n="70 BLACK SOIL"/>by the two ducks, which were entirely cut off from the outside world by a huge drift as tall as the house. The sun was shining. The storm was over: but they were completely snowed in.</p>
				<p>Danny made a successful exit from the window of the loft, shovelled [sic] a channel back close to the house, and reported no signs of the stock.</p>
				<p>It was a memorable day in the lives of the Connor children. Food gave out. There was no milk for Ellen. Hay was brought in through the tunnel.</p>
				<p>In the afternoon Danny ventured as far as the Schwartzes'. He returned with milk. Schwartzes had no flour and were waiting to get some from the Connors. Katto assured him that his parents were all right and would show up soon.</p>
				<p>As the sun was sending its last red glow over the sub merged prairie, Ned, foraging in a cornfield, suddenly pricked up his ears, turned his head and sent out a welcoming whinny. It was answered by Jack and Jule, ejecting huge funnels of steam from their nostrils. A white vehicle moved slowly, clumsily around the big drift and stopped before a mound from whose apex a peeping chimney emitted a wispish curl of gray smoke. <pb n="71"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XI">
				<p>SHEILA and Danny were very anxious to return to school for the winter term. Jerome Loutch was still employed as teacher the director, Emil Webber, with whom he boarded, saw no reason for dismissing him. Any teacher is better than none at all, Nel1 reasoned, as she bundled up the children and sent them off.</p>
				<p>The winter, which had set in <emph>so </emph>early, continued to hold sway. There was no respite. Fresh snow fell every few days, completely obliterating newly-made paths and roads. The snow changed the contour of the prairie, each storm adding new embellishments, ephemeral and fantastic. Instead of its usual regularity, the landscape was broken by ranges and valleys, peaks and low foothills, each with its vegetation of flutes and filigree, On top of the crusted mounds the children ran to school like pigmies.</p>
				<p>The attendance was not large. The Schwartzes were there, Bennie Hurd, and a few others. The Low Ger mans who lived farther away had not ventured out. Excitement was at low ebb. Bennie had a book satchel of black walnuts which he had received from his former home in the East. He gave each pupil a few, but he was most generous with Sheila.</p>
				<p>Snug in his copper toes, Danny displayed his two new slate pencils and; oblivious to the glances of envy cast him by Ditz Schwartz, opened his new reader and began to study: with a will.</p>
				<p>
					<emph>"You </emph>say <emph>I am a rogue? I say I am not a rogue."</emph>
					<pb n="72 BLACK SOIL"/>The word <emph>rogue</emph>, a new word: what was it? Danny made a trip to the teacher's desk, his boots squeaking rhythmically, with his finger under the word.</p>
				<p>"Rog-u," pronounced Jerome Loutch. Danny returned to his seat and earnestly repeated: <emph>"You say</emph>
					<emph>I am a rog-u? I say I am not a rog-u." </emph>What did that mean? He must ask Pop.</p>
				<p>At noon Herman and Ditz Schwartz, who lived close by, ran home and soon returned with two young pup pies. Vitchy, their mongrel, was caring for a family of eight, which was seven more than Schwartz would al low them to keep. The boys saw an opportunity for a good trade.</p>
				<p>Ditz alluringly held out to Danny a black puppy with a white spot on his nose. "I trade him for one pencil."The puppy looked up at Danny and raised one silky ear.</p>
				<p>"I'll take 'um," Danny answered. In another corner Herman was exchanging a brown puppy for the remainder of Bennie's black walnuts; and having secured the prized nuts immediately presented them to Sheila, much to the chagrin of his brother Schwartzes. "Dumb," they: hissed. Herman flashed his beady eyes, made a grimace, and proceeded to draw Danny's puppy for him on his new slate.</p>
				<p>"I'll call mine Captain," Danny whispered.  "What's yours?"  "Oh, maybe--Shep," Bennie answered, secreting the dog in the satchel where he had carried the nuts.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 73"/>At the last recess Herman Schwartz, after a turn in the air, reentered the schoolroom and packed away his book.</p>
				<p>"I go home," he announced laconically, "there's blizzard.'' Thereupon all the children began bundling into wraps. Jerome Loutch likewise was winding a scarf about his neck.</p>
				<p>A little fresh snow was falling, but the loose snow was being picked up and blown about by a brisk wind. The Connors and Bennie struck out against the gale. As they went on, the storm became more furious; and at the point where they were to separate, the snow was blinding. The three paused for a moment, their backs temporarily to the gale.</p>
				<p>A rift in the storm revealed Bennie, with his store overcoat buttoned tightly under his chin and the satchel containing the puppy swinging from his shoulder. His cheeks were red, his eyes watery.</p>
				<p>"Think you can make it?" Danny asked. "Better come along with us. 'Tain't so far."Bennie hesitated, kicking one foot against the other. "I'd like to go home and make him a little doghouse tonight," he answered.</p>
				<p>The wind whipped away his words. Something of the mother in Sheila prompted her to insist on his coming, but she said nothing.</p>
				<p>"See yuh tomorrow," Danny called as they parted. The Connors continued west; Bennie turned off to the north.</p>
				<p>Danny, held his puppy inside his coat with one hand. With the other he clung to Sheila, at the same time staying<pb n="74 BLACK SOIL"/>a little in the rear so that he should be shielded some what from the wind.</p>
				<p>The snow beat against their weather eyes, which they  had left unwrapped; cold penetrated their clothing, their skin, and entered into the marrow of their bones.</p>
				<p>Danny began to cry, his tears freezing immediately and blinding him.  "I'm cold, Sheila.  My feet.  My hands, Oh-h-h, I'm cold."Sheila answered:  I'm cold, too, Danny; we're nearly home.  Pray that God will help us."  Her voice and Danny's piping cries mingled with the moaning wind. "You pray, Sheila, I'm too cold."Exhausted and chilled, they dragged on, but no object, no landmark came into sight.</p>
				<p>Suddenly Sheila stopped.  "Oh-h-h Danny, Danny," she cried, "We're lost! I don't know where we are.  Help me, Danny.  Show me the way, and I'll carry the puppy."They bent close to each other, their voices mocking and unnatural.  Danny stepped from behind Sheila and lowered the scarf from his face.  Sniffing the air like a hound, he swung his head around. "We're not facing the wind.  We gotta keep facing it." Changing their course toward the blast, they stumbled on, falling, pulling each other out of drifts until Danny's face was pricked.  His scarf was caught and held. "Malget's fence!"  There was no doubt of it, for there  was not another rod of fence in the neighborhood.</p>
				<p>"Gosh, we're out of our way," Danny said. They concluded that by keeping to the right of the fence until they came to the corner post, and then by<pb n="BLACK SOIL 75"/>going directly west again they would come to their grove if the wind had not changed meanwhile.</p>
				<p>They advanced, Sheila keeping one hand on the fence in spite of constant jabs.</p>
				<p>Exhausted and chilled, they would have preferred to lie down in the soft white snow, and be warm.  They thought of home at this time.  Ellen in the highchair, the stove, the odors of food, Mom, Pop.  They were jerked from their musings by the corner post.  They felt the bracings and recognized the turn.</p>
				<p>They knew that now they must locate the west and strike out boldly.  Still they clung to the post, as the only raft in that ocean of snow.  A few times they ventured out only to return and cling there again.  Finally Danny said:  "I'm going," and holding to him, Sheila followed. They had not proceeded far before they heard a whistle.</p>
				<p>"Pop's whistle," Danny shouted. "The wind," Sheila answered. A resounding whistle pierced the wall of snow.</p>
				<p>"Pop's whistle," Danny reiterated.  "Let's go toward it." "Might be just something in the storm, and if we turn we'll get lost." They stopped and listened. The whistle came again, unmistakable, and they hurried toward it.  Soon they were in Tim Connor's arms. "Your mother has the old bell," Tim told them.  "We must listen for it."Soon it came, soft and alluring as the trickle of water. Tones--swelling, dying, strangled, only to be born again.</p>
				<p>Sheila, leaning on Tim's arm, wondered about<pb n="76 BLACK SOIL"/>Bennie. Bennie, bright and clean in boughten clothes, happily carrying off the soft brown puppy into the storm.</p>
				<p>As Danny set down his own chilled dog before the fire he shared Sheila's misgivings. "I bet yuh Bennie never made it," he prophesied.</p>
				<p>Next morning dawned calm and bright. Tim Connor was shoveling a path from his door when Mr. Hurd's cap appeared over a bank of snow.</p>
				<p>"Our Bennie here?"<emph>"Bennie?" </emph>Bennie had not made it.</p>
				<p>By ten o'clock a searching party was organized, branching out in all directions. Tim returned late in the afternoon, his beard white with frost, icicles streaming from eyelashes and nose. T o the children he gave an evasive answer: to his wife he said nothing.</p>
				<p>Nell Connor looked at Danny, romping with his nuisance of a puppy, and offered a voiceless and sincere prayer of thanks. God was indeed good to them. God was good.</p>
				<p>After the children were in bed, Tim went to the door. "Wind is picking up again," he muttered. "Wolves howling over west. I'll look over west tomorrow." "I heard the wind all evening," Nell answered. "It's a requiem, that's what it is."After many futile trips the search for Bennie was tentatively abandoned. Later snows effaced all clues and folded the victim the more securely in an enveloping shroud.</p>
				<p>"The childer can stop at home the rest of the winter,"<pb n="BLACK SOIL 77"/>Tim suggested to his wife. "Not much use sending 'em. Danny may develop into a 'rog-u', who knows?"</p><p>"They'd better stay out of the cold, in the name of God," Nell agreed. Just one day Sheila returned, to bring home their books.</p>
				<p>It was a lonely day. Few children were at school. At unprecedented intervals Jerome Loutch ate prodigiously of his bread and drippings, The Schwartzes quarreled over their lunch, each striving to get the lower slice of bread, which was the more soaked with molasses. Her man was not there, Bennie's desk was empty. Sheila did not apply herself to study, but looked instead out of the window at the white waste of snow. There was no life only the fluttering of snowbirds against the pane. The sun was making its circuit just the same as when Bennie was alive. In the forenoon it fell across her desk, reached as far as the stove, touched it, and then drew back. In the afternoon it appeared again, peeping in at the west window, stretching long fingers of yellow light across Bennie's desk and receding again.</p>
				<p>Finally school was out. Sheila hurried home. There  would be news. Perhaps Bennie was found and alive! She searched Nell's face. No one said anything, and Sheila as usual asked no questions. <pb n="78 "/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XII">
				<p>BEFORE Thanksgiving Day had arrived, winter had seemed interminable. Fresh snow falling every few days dispelled all hopes of deliverance. Settlers were in truth snowed in.</p>
				<p>The Connors had saved all of their cattle and hogs  thanks to Danny's forethought in allowing them to roam at large; but feed was a serious problem. When the weather permitted, Tim and Danny went to the fields, shovelled [sic] off snow and snapped corn, which they carried home in sacks for the stock. They had fortunately packed their seed corn away in the loft room before the season's first snow. They had also saved their potato crop and some vegetables.</p>
				<p>In the house, submerged as completely as a badger mound, Nell, amidst the prattling of six children and the yelping of a puppy, tried to carry on a systematic  course of study. At the cost of effort she attempted to create a congenial atmosphere within ,the four small walls, but that was not so easily: maintained. There were six children there, and a puppy, and a cactus.</p>
				<p>The cactus, a mysterious thing that bloomed once every hundred years, obstinately held a place by the kitchen window.  Nell had a veneration for the cactus, the only plant brought out from Massachusetts which had withstood the vicissitudes of climate, poultry and what not to which treasured fern and geranium had so soon fallen prey. In the world of snow its green, spiny<pb n="BLACK SOIL 79"/>tongues were mute reminders that somewhere there was a vegetation.</p>
				<p>To Danny the cactus. was a source of diversion. "One, two, three. Let's all touch it. You're afraid." Kitty Ann's ill-aimed action ended in a wail. Blood issued from Margaret's palm.</p>
				<p>"Danny, Danny, I declare if you don't let those children and that cactus alone " Danny, grinning, his large permanent frontals giving his mouth a looseness, his ears slightly lapped protruding between locks of unshorn hair, edged over near little Emmet.</p>
				<p>"Look up here," he whispered, pointing to <emph>The Trial of Robert Emmet. </emph>"There's you. They're going to kill you. And there's your girl. Oh, Emmet has a girl!" "Never mind," Nell comforted Emmet, who ran to her in tears. "When you grow up you can be a great orator like Emmet and you can go to school at Cam bridge."</p><p>"I thought you said <emph>I </emph>was going to school at Cam bridge," Danny interposed. "If you don't stop tormenting these children you won't go anywhere.''Danny oscillated toward the cactus again. "Margaret, do you know what these spines really are? They're little green devils in there, and each one has a nail in the end of its tail."</p><p>"Dear me, Danny, where on earth do you get such ideas?" "Out of my head."In spite of resolutions, Nell's patience often failed and she had to be reminded to "wear her nice face."<pb n="80 BLACK SOIL"/>When the open door disclosed the sweep of desolation about them, she found it necessary at times to leave the clamor of the kitchen and go to the bedroom.</p>
				<p>Occasionally in the evening, slipping her feet into Tim's boots, she walked out on the cleared path and allowed herself the luxury of being alone. She looked wonderingly about at the immaculate earth, the clear stars and the unperturbed moon. The big dipper shone down as it used to shine through the branches of the elms in the Bay State. God who was now caring for them in the East  Aunt Mary, the old streets, the hills, the river  would care for them here in the West white with snow. God was in His Heaven; all must be right with His world.</p>
				<p>Somewhat strengthened, she would reenter her hut  white but for the door  and Tim, much to the amusement of the children, would usually greet her with: "Good evenin', Mrs. Badger. Making a call? Me badgers are all well. How are yours? I think Danny Badger'll be after going head first into a snowdrift if he don't stop his monkeyshines around here.''They had almost no company. People were afraid to venture far from home. The wife of Max tramped through the snow one day and complained to Nell at length on the injustice of her lot.</p>
				<p>"We got money, yes; but we can no laugh at our house. Max, he takes my money. He will not say why he saves it. I want a new shawl. He will not give me money. You see, he must do the business. I can no read, Mrs. Connor, I can no read.''<pb n="BLACK SOIL 81"/>"Begin right now," Nell suggested. "You're never too old to learn." "Oh, now I am too old. And Max say all time I have no brains." "I'd show him what brains I had," Nell said, aroused. "Bring your book here, Margaret. We'll begin right now."And the wife of Max began her instructions in reading. "I will get me such a book," she said enthusiastically, tears streaming down her furrowed face. "Yes, and come over and I'll help you, but don't lisp it to a soul until you can rattle it off," Nell advised, smiling.</p>
				<p>"You are wonderful woman, Mrs. Connor," the wife of Max said, and trotted off again through the snow. In mid-winter, as the weather grew bitterly cold, Tim and Nell without admitting it to each other were ever conscious of the fact that the two haystacks in the yard--their only source of fuel--were steadily being reduced. The thought of their diminishing food supply haunted them, too, as the gaunt grey wolves that howled about at night. They knew that they would always have game, but it seemed disloyal to eat the lean, dazed prairie chickens that found shelter close to the stalks of corn.</p>
				<p>The young Connors, however, were apparently un aware of conditions. They soon fell in with the new order of things: two meals a day and more time to sleep. They enjoyed their isolation; it meant the closest of contact with not only Mom but Pop.</p>
				<p>Tim usually took charge of the group in mid-afternoon, at which time their evening began. They anticipated<pb n="82 BLACK SOIL"/>this time of the day  Tim sang then. Nell's sweet untrained soprano had often filled the house, singing lullabies and hymns; but lately when she sang tears rolled down her face. Tim's singing had a different tempo. His tenor had in it a ringing quality, a reality which carried visions of faraway places. And his reading of poetry was so intoned that the children could not clearly distinguish song from recitation. Books were inadequate and dull compared to the inexhaustible knowledge possessed by Tim, who had not only a new story but an elaboration of the old favorite for each evening.</p>
				<p>On fair days after he had finished choring, doing the milking, and giving a meagre handful of oats or a few ears of corn to the stock, Tim often walked around the big drift in the yard and gained the clearing to the south. Then, looking over the soft white sheet of snow to the east where the gray sky closed down on his deserted world, he wondered what was going on back East. He thought of kinsmen; his brother John; Nell's folks: friends; old Judge De Wayne. . . oh, what would he give to see one of them for just five minutes! He tried to imagine what they were doing, and what was occupying the minds of politicians while he struggled here for mere existence. How quiet that prairie was! Only a slight click from the frozen twigs of the cottonwood broke the stillness. The wind seemed to be resting, regenerating its forces, waiting only for the stimulus of fresh snow, when it would again rage mercilessly; and after lashing him to shelter would howl and moan while it pelted snow against the dwelling and forced it in through every crevice.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 83"/>Usually as Tim, leaving off his reveries, turned the knob of his door and stamped his feet loudly, his eyes twinkled to hear the sudden flurry inside. "Me bootjack!'' he would yell.</p>
				<p>The flurry would increase to a general havoc as children hunted here and there. One evening as he entered, Kitty Ann walked up roguishly, produced the bootjack, and placed it in position before him.</p>
				<p>It was the custom that whichever child presented the bootjack would have first choice in the selecting of songs. Accordingly Kitty Ann shouted: <emph>"Fol de diddle di do." </emph>Danny and Margaret demurred. Kitty Ann had been getting her choice .often of late. Sheila, standing in the background, said nothing. "What is your choice, Sheila?" Tim asked, jerking at his frozen boots.</p>
				<p>"Oh, any one," she answered. Sheila was growing taller and more slender. Her face, unlike those of the Connors, had not lost its summer tan, and in the dim light of the afternoon her dark eyes were large and penetrating.</p>
				<p>"Now, children," Nell spoke up, "hear how Sheila talks. Sheila doesn't make a fuss; she's a little lady."Tim looked at his wife, wondering if she knew that Sheila's apparent good manners were prompted by indifference. He felt chagrined at her apathy.</p>
				<p>"<emph>The Croppy Boy</emph>, I want," Danny shouted. Margaret stepped up before Tim, her flat little bosom. covered with faded, flowered calico ripped from a comforter, her limpid blue eyes filled with tears. "Pop," she said, "Kitty Ann always hides the bootjack so we can't<pb n="84 BLACK SOIL"/>find it for you. And today I found it under Mom's bed and she hit me with it when I took it. See?" She pushed back her brown hair and disclosed a florid temple.</p>
				<p>Tim placed his boots beside the stove and padded about in his stocking feet. "You're a holy terror, Kit," he said, mustering all fierceness possible. "They'll be no passing of you when you grow up. Now for hurting Margaret, she'll be the one to get first choice. What'll it be, Margaret?"When he drew up his chair Margaret rubbed her head against his shoulder. She looked quaint in her flowered, full-skirted dress.</p>
				<p>"I want 'When lilacs last in the doorway bloomed' . .  ." she said. "I don't want you to tune it; I want you to sing it." "Did you ever hear the like of that for a request?" Tim asked his wife.</p>
				<p>Nell, pouring milk into the bowls of mush on the table, answered: "She means, I think, that she wants you to recite it."After grace the Connor flock was busy with mush and milk. The puppy yelped to Danny, who surreptitiously: poured him a share, and Ellen in the highchair clamored for continual tastes.</p>
				<p>Kitty Ann managed a pout with difficulty at any time; and now her attempt to retain protruding lips while disposing of mush and milk was a sight not to be overlooked when novelties were so very rare.</p>
				<p>Accordingly, Tim began in feigned alarm: "Mom, look at Kit's mouth. What do you make of it? I declare, it looks like the snout of a young badger." Kitty Ann fled to the bedroom in tears.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 85"/>Nell, noting the unfinished supper, said disapprovingly: "That bootjack game'll have to stop. They could take turns getting it. They nearly drove me crazy with it all day."Supper over, the stove was filled with hay, the drafts emitting the necessary light. Tim called to Danny, nodded at Kitty Ann's bowl and motioned toward the bed room. Danny carried in the unfinished mush, and Kitty Ann soon reappeared.</p>
				<p>"I guess I'll play me flute tonight," Tim said diplomatically, and the children gathered around him. They heard <emph>Annie Laurie </emph>and <emph>Home to Our Mountains.</emph>Tim told again of his boyhood home in Ireland: the gathering of peat from bogs--"I wish to God we had it for fuel here"--and the collecting of seaweed to fertilize the potato patch. There were fairies, too, both good and bad, and the banshees whose warm breath meant instant death for anyone, regardless of how good a life he had led.</p>
				<p>"Our national schools were where you'd get the floggings," he went on. "There were no Jerome Loutches there. A larger boy held the victim on his back while the teacher did the whaling." There was quiet in the kitchen as Tim spoke; at intervals hay snapped in the stove. "They flogged you for being late for school; they flogged you for little misdemeanors: they flogged you when you memorized imperfectly. I tell you it was a hard lot for the dull boy."</p><p>"Were <emph>you </emph>dull, Pop?" "No, thank God. I could give it to them word for word."<pb n="86 BLACK SOIL"/>Tim told his avid listeners of boyhood life at Dublin, chuckling reminiscently over pranks.</p>
				<p>In tales of New England life, Nell joined. They re called Fair Day and Cattle Show, spoke of steam cars, woods. . . . "Woods! What's woods?" Kitty Ann or Robert Emmet would ask. "Patches of trees that grow," Tim explained, "with out being set out and watered. They have big shady leaves, and there's fruit, too."</p><p>"With apples and everything hanging on 'em," Margaret supplemented. Danny, from his position on the floor, lying on his back with his feet extending up on the wall, said half to himself: "Gosh, I'm going back there when I'm big and eat and eat and eat."</p><p>"Are they bigger'n this house?" Kitty' Ann asked incredulously. And Tim, bestowing on Kitty Ann an extra caress by way of reconciliation, told of oaks whose circumference he could not span with his two arms, of other trees that tossed down nuts, of rows of shady elms, and of birches on whose branches children swung.</p>
				<p>They listened attentively to Tim's recitation of poetry and interpreted it the best way that they could. Robert Emmet's sleepiness was no signal of time: but when Margaret and Kitty Ann rested heavy heads on Tim's chest the end-of-the-day ritual of marking off the calendar took place. Another day was gone. All who Could articulate repeated with Tim a verse that in some intangible way meant that so far all was well. "So goes the day, far, far away, "<pb n="BLACK SOIL 87"/>When March 16 arrived, Tim remarked: "It'll soon be spring; tomorrow will be Patrick's Day." This was a suggestion to relate both fact and legend of the saint so beloved by the Irish.</p>
				<p>"Do you know what I'd like?" Danny said by way of comment. "I'd like to be a saint for a while just to see how it would feel." "It's a clout that you'd be deservin' after the winter, instead of canonization, me lad,'' Tim answered jocularly.</p>
				<p>"Oh, Tim, you must be careful, joking about such things. They'll be confused. And the way you spoke about St. Patrick one would think that there was not another saint on the calendar." Nell was serious.</p>
				<p>Tim sat erect. "Is there another to beat him? Why don't you tell them about some of the saints of New England if they have any since you left? How do you know? Maybe we have the makings of a prairie saint among us."</p><p>"It's not only this, but everything.  They don't know of so many things. Sitting here listening it seems to me that the Irish and that indecent Whitman are the only people who ever wrote anything. Dear, dear, what will these children ever amount to? They've never heard of Longfellow."</p><p>"Yes we have, Mom," Margaret shouted, eager to prevent discord between Mom and Pop. "Week in, week out, from morn till night, you can hear his bellows blow. . . .'"Nell had put on her shawl and was pulling on Tim's boots. Tim could scarcely refrain from smiling as Danny,<pb n="88 BLACK SOIL"/>jumping from the floor, unknowingly capped the climax with : "Ireland will be free from the center to the sea. Hurrah for liberty, said the <emph>Shan Van Voch." </emph>" Nell stepped out into the night. "Off to bed now," Tim announced, "all of ye, I guess we played your mother out. Help 'em in, Sheila," as the children moved off.</p>
				<p>Sheila obeyed silently, as usual. Again Tim caught a depth of mystery in the girl's deep, dark eyes. She was an obedient girl, a generous girl, but she lacked the restless energy of his children. Or was her restlessness subdued as her speech and emotions were subdued? Time alone could tell.</p>
				<p>He opened the door and saw a dark figure standing in the white tunnel. Poor Nell! She's proud, the darlin'. The childer'll grow up all right if we can feed 'em. Wonder if she knows how low the hay is! He called dramatically: "'You are thy father's spirit, Doom'd for a certain time to walk the night; And for the day, confined to fast in fires. . . .'" And, in a natural tone: "Come along in out of that. You'll get your death."The figure moved toward the house. Tim said casually: "Blamed if that wind ain't picking up again." There was no answer; Nell's face was averted. Tim swung her around and held her by the arms. "Nell," he pleaded, "bear with me during this siege, and<pb n="BLACK SOIL 89"/>next summer if the sun shines again and the birds sing you can play the devil with me, I'm doing my best for 'em, Nell." "I know you are, Tim."Although St. Patrick's Day came and went, winter preemptorily held sway. The last of the hay was. burned; and again Tim shovelled [sic] snow from the cornfields, the only remaining source of fuel. The Connors took sick, Sheila first and Kitty Ann worst of all. Tim made a perilous trip for medicine and on his return became a victim to the epidemic. During his illness, Danny carried down the seed corn from the loft and used it as fuel.</p>
				<p>Kitty Ann's delirium reflected the salient points of anxiety of the winter, although Nell and Tim thought they had succeeded in keeping the children in ignorance of true conditions, The sick child fretted: "Bluey has no oats. Bennie is dead  out in the snow." She cried for the bootjack; she raved of apple trees and swinging birch. Her eyes were glassy, her cheeks flushed; only the yellow curls seemed like Kitty Ann.</p>
				<p>One day she recognized her father. "Pop," she said, "hold me." And Tim, with Kitty Ann's thin body in his arms, bowed his head in thanks; the seed corn seemed a very trifling thing indeed, In a strained voice he sang her favorite song: "Fol de diddle di do. Fol de diddle dee." <pb n="90"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XIII">
				<p>WITH Kitty Ann's recovery came signs of spring. The sun shone intensely. The snow which had been strangling the prairie was forced to release one foothold after another, to give up, to disappear. Followed the trickle of running water, Water was everywhere  on roofs, on window panes, filling the yard, flooding the fields and swelling the sloughs. Prairie cocks proudly displayed their plumage and waltzed about on sunny uplands. Meadow larks were rampant. How welcome was their song! Flitting from dried weed to grass, they proclaimed the vital moment of life was now and the past winter a bad dream. "Come on," they chided. "Plant your crops and sing and hope; skies are blue and God is good."People crept out from their shelters, shook off their winter coma, and heeded the call of the meadow larks. "We are coming,'' they answered with quickening pulse. "Only wait until we get seed. Seed! We're coming! We're alive! It is spring and we're alive!"Tim Connor went to the cornfield and husked the remaining crop of corn, but it was sour and soft. It was of no use as fuel, nor was it palatable to the stock. He crushed the ill-fated stalks with a vengeance and sowed grain.</p>
				<p>Neighbors greeted each other <emph>as </emph>strangers from afar; they ignored their recent bitter experiences and spoke of future plans. All were going to break a little more land. Old Buck and Spec, Tim's yoke of oxen, which<pb n="BLACK SOIL 91"/>had foraged during the cold weather, were put to the plow once more. Nell was going to raise turkeys. She planned on trading some duck eggs with Katto Schwartz, who had been having good luck with turkeys.</p>
				<p>Much as they hoped to forget the winter, there were constant reminders. One day Vitchy, the old mongrel, carried a shoe into the Schwartzes' yard. On examining the shoe they found a foot inside. Vitchy led them across the' field to where Bennie Hurd lay. Inside his overcoat was the skeleton of a puppy. Bennie had re moved the puppy from his satchel to a warmer repository.</p>
				<p>While birds flew overhead caroling their nesting songs and a raw wind blew, Bennie, a guest on the prairie, the boy with the boughten clothes, who had left his parents and brothers and sisters in the East and had come West to break the silence in his aunt's heart and home, was placed beside Sheila's mother. There was a baby there now, too, who had arrived during the winter and found the world too cold.</p>
				<p>Katto Schwartz, greatly moved by Mrs. Hurd's grief, gave vent to her own feelings by expressing her opinion of Jerome Loutch. Her raucous tones jarred in the hush that followed the services. "That dumb Loutch," she began; "if my Herman didn't smell blizzard coming that day, all the children mine and Connors' and all would be lost. That dumb teacher is big enough to know something once, but he don't know nothin'. "The crowd nodded in agreement. "I'm going right over and see Webber," Nell spoke  out.  "Katto, I think you're right. I can't help but<pb n="92 BLACK SOIL"/>blame him for turning the children out in the storm with all that loose snow."Butch Fred, the neighborhood bachelor, stepped up to the semicircle of women. The wind tossed his long beard about, commingling it with the shaggy fur on his buffalo coat. He raised his head, disclosing the clear gray eyes that shone below his bushy eyebrows. "In our distric'," he began, "we got just a young girl for teacher. She keep the children in the school all night. I look for them children," he nodded repeatedly for emphasis, "and I don't see them come. I know they be in school and I think I will cook something for them. I make pancakes, a dishpanful, and set them in the oven. I watch the storm. At eleven hour it gets clear. I wrap a quilt around that pan and take it to the children." He smiled reminiscently. "Oh, they were hungry like the little wolves. They were cold, too. I get coal and fix the fire and I see the storm getting bad again. I want to go home. Them little ones they have my quilt and my coat around them. They don't want me to take my coat. They don't want me to go. I stay there and keep the fire till the morning. And then that little teacher she telled me she was so glad I come, She made so brave, so brave, but I guess she was scared all right."Only a few had heard about Dutch Fred's thoughtfulness on that memorable night; but from past experience they knew him to be a real neighbor. There was a silence following his narration. There was no need for words. The sun, sinking lower, was withdrawing the warm rays that had offset the raw, damp breeze. Men buttoned up their coats and women drew their shawls<pb n="BLACK SOIL 93"/>about them. With one accord they climbed into their wagons.</p>
				<p>"Drive me straight to the director's, right now, Tim," Nell commanded. "We'll tell Webber to hire that girl that applied for the school last week. We'll insist on it. A girl will have some manners and some heart and, let's hope, a little knowledge. That Loutch is a big--I-don't-know-what."</p><p>"He's a 'rog-u'," Tim said with a chuckle, "teaching on a permit at that." "A permit! I thought Loutch said he had a certificate." "He said 'certiffy,' Nell, but he really had a permit." Webber was compelled to hire the Alice Inman in question, and Nell Connor sent four children off to school the first day of the spring term.</p>
				<p>Kitty Ann led the group; Danny and Margaret followed; and Sheila, who was carrying a setting of duck eggs to Katto Schwartz, brought up the rear. Holding her basket as carefully as possible, she leaped over patches in the prairie where clear cold water oozed up in the green grass. Her step lagged as she walked on. On all sides was the caroling and calling of birds--lark to lark, bobolink to bobolink. So free. So free. Why must she go to school? She would prefer to stay at home and herd the cattle. But Mom . . . Well . . . Why? Why? There was a gentle pressure, a comfort, in the vitalizing air as it touched her. Her sturdy body, hardly adjusted to the newly acquired curves of adolescence, responded and swung in unison with the spring breeze. Her deep, dark eyes were alight with the visions which life held<pb n="94 BLACK SOIL"/>before her. With face aglow she walked with spring and she <emph>was </emph>spring.</p>
				<p>The younger children waited for her in Schwartzes' yard, where a fractious colt was galloping at large. On seeing the children, Schwartz gathered them into the safety of the house.</p>
				<p>Nick, the oldest boy, was standing in the kitchen wiping blood from his mouth. Sheila gave Katto the basket of eggs and observed some unusual-looking objects in her hand.</p>
				<p>"It's Nick's teeth  got kicked out," Katto explained; and after holding the unsightly teeth toward the children for a view she tossed them carelessly on a nearby shelf. Lightly: "He can keep them and put them in once when he goes to see his girl." Without further concern she began counting the eggs.</p>
				<p>When the Connors left the house, the Schwartz boys were standing in a row in the yard, watching the antics of the disappearing colt. Herman left the group and walked up to them.</p>
				<p>"Ain't you coming to school?" Danny asked. "No, only Matt and Yak go. I herd cattle," He went up close to Sheila. "You tell your mother I watch Connors' cattle on my side of the field. Don't tell them," he said, nodding toward his brothers.</p>
				<p>"All right," Sheila answered, knowing that Her man's act of kindness was not prompted through consideration for Mom Connor. Quite terrified at her own kindly feeling for Herman, she hastened on to the school. During the day she looked longingly out to where the sun was shining on her herding grounds, To be free from books  her pulse quickened as she thought look in Herman's eyes. <pb n="95"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XIV">
				<p>DURING the summer the same expanse of prairie which had so recently opened its arms to the snow and had bared its face to the wind, just so generously nurtured its growth of grain and grass; the wind which had so ruthlessly lashed the area unprotected by trees and hills, serenely now rocked bunches of flowers; and the sky, which lately had shut off the living world, was now blue, enhancing the charm and beauty of a prairie in summer.</p>
				<p>"I feel young again," Tim announced one day as he stood outside the door after his noonday meal. "I don't blame the childer to run off with the last bite in their mouths."Nell joined him in the doorway. Before them a pair of hawks, like trailing black ribbons tinged with a glow from the sun, rose from the misty horizon, sailed high, careened and disappeared.</p>
				<p>"This country, me girl, is like Schwartzes' colt. It's high-spirited like all young things and must be broken, conquered. . . . I t may take more than a few front teeth; but I wouldn't be back East today, Nel1, for all  the comforts in the world." "But the winters," Nell broke in. "Winter won't be so bad again. That was just tantrum, a vagary. Mark me words. This country will soon keep step with the rest of the world and develop into a law-abiding citizen.''"If it just would, Tim."<pb n="96 BLACK SOIL"/>"It will, Nell." In the fall, after the settlers had harvested a good crop and had paid the most exigent of bills, they: sent glowing accounts of the country to friends and relatives. The Connors sent cheerful letters East, but the mail from there showed many changes. The academy that Nell had attended in Northampton was a college now, Smith College. Her uncle Henry had died, cousin Ellen was married, and aunt Mary was alone. Ellen's husband was a consumptive, and the doctor had advised them to go West. They asked: "Should we come?"</p><p>"Bully, bully for them!" Tim ejaculated. "Sure and they can come." "Oh, I'd love to see cousin Ellen and have her close by," Nell said, with tears in her eyes. After their first enthusiasm Nell looked at Tim, and Tim looked at Nell.</p>
				<p>"I don't know," she said. "Ellen's not strong. He with consumption. . . Can they: stand things the way we do? I'd feel responsible . . . the winters." "I know . . . the winters." Nell put down the letter. "Let's leave them where they are, in the name of God.''The year's grist was hauled to a new mill. The Hollanders had erected a genuine Dutch mill with a large cumbersome wheel which was propelled by the fancy of the wind. It not only served as a convenience to the community, but proved to be a curiosity as well.</p>
				<p>Max, who prided himself a model of haste, was the first in his neighborhood to take a grist to the Dutch mill. He called at Connors' enroute home, with no flour.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 97"/>Max was vexed indeed. He had willed the wheel to turn and it had not heeded. That was a most unusual experience for Max.</p>
				<p>Tim chuckled as Max told of the day. Wagons were lined up by the dozens with their grist. There were representatives present of many tongues and creeds, and they cursed and prayed in turn in as many tongues and . creeds. "I go there no more," Max said disgustedly. "I go farther but I go where I will get my flour."As he turned to leave, Tim called: "I'm going over tomorrow, Max, and try it with a few in Irish. I'll send you over some flour tomorrow night." "Huh," Max answered, as he swung his team around.</p>
				<p>Sheila accompanied Tim on his trip to the mill. Danny had been planning all summer on going and had conjured many images of the wonderful mill, but Sheila was more capable to do the required trading, so Danny was left at home. The wind on this day was not capricious, and Tim Connor received his flour. In the evening, more through deviltry than benevolence, he sent Danny over to Max's with a bag of flour.</p>
				<p>Danny, galloping away on old Ned's back, accepted the errand as a retribution. Max's place was a curiosity  anything might happen there. He wondered what Max would say when he knew that Pop got flour.</p>
				<p>Max was not at home, and the wife of Max said that she was very grateful that he was not.</p>
				<p>"No, I can't take the flour anyhow," she explained to Danny. "Max he would get mad if he knew that Tim got flour. No, no," and she returned the sack to the boy. "But come in the home once. I am so glad one from Connors come. I will not ask my gels. Come." She led<pb n="98 BLACK SOIL"/>the bewildered Danny to the bedroom, where she un earthed a book, a Second Reader, from under her straw tick. "Help me once,'' she said and opened the book. "See, here. Read this once."Danny read: "'I built me a nest in the old beech tree, As cozy a nest as ever could be. I wove it with threads to the beech tree bough, And three little birdies are sleeping there now.' '' "'Beesh,'" the woman repeated. "'Bough,'  Why for is <emph>beesh </emph>in this book?"</p><p>"A <emph>kind </emph>of tree," Danny answered, quite moved by the earnestness of the woman. "Bough is <emph>part </emph>of a tree. The bird built its nest in the bough of the beech tree."</p><p>"Oh, thank you," the woman said, smiling. She pressed a nickel into his palm. "Don't let Max or my gels know I give you this."As Danny galloped home with his flour and the nickel, there was a quizzical expression on his freckled face. <pb n="99"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XV">
				<p>NEXT spring before the frost was out of the ground, prairie schooners again appeared on the trail. In their snaillike pace across the country, their canvas covers had a barely perceptible movement  . . .  sailboats leisurely holding their course to the west. The settlers always saluted the driver and if there was a wife beside him on the seat added the customary: "Hooray, the woman!" Children often peered from beneath the canvas cover, but rarely did one see old people in these family groups. It was a young country, for young people. One little mover lad whose family had spent the night in the Connors' yard expressed this quite thoroughly by saying: "We left usses grandma and grandpa, but we didn't leave usses selves."Previous to this time, many sections of land owned by the Government, the Railroads, and eastern speculators lay unbroken and were used by the settlers as herding grounds. Much of this land was now thrown open. In consequence, agents raced about day and night; Tim Connor; too, spent many an hour in aiding new comers to locate.</p>
				<p>One day he noticed a team and rig on the one hundred and sixty acres adjoining his on the south.  He  sauntered over.</p>
				<p>"Lost your chance, Tim," Barnes, the land agent, spoke as he brought his team to a stop and untied the colored rag by which he had been counting revolutions<pb n="100 BLACK SOIL"/>of the wheel.  "you fellows here should be buying this up.  Plenty left yet.  In the market for any?"Tim shook his head.  "Tell you the truth, Barnes, most of us got more now than we can pay for.  Glad to have a close neighbor, though.  Me wife will be, too."</p><p>"This is a young German, an aristocrat.  Can talk seven languages, the description goes.  Not here yet:  but thought I'd measure him up as I was out this way."</p><p>"German," Tim repeated.  "Is he High German, Low German, or just plain Dutch?  Won't matter much if he's such a linguist."</p><p>"Don't know,--placed through an eastern agency." Barnes hammered the remaining stake into the ground and raised his body with difficulty.  "There, guess that's  close enough.  You and him won't quarrel over it, will yuh?"Tim laughed.  "No, I guess not.  This corner is too  low to break, anyhow."A few weeks later, when there was every evidence of a promising harvest, Tim Connor and Schwartz went to town to order machinery.  Tim needed a harvester, and Schwartz a corn plow.  After transacting their business and being refreshed by a toddy and a glass of beer respectively, they were about to climb into their wagon when Barnes rushed from his office dragging with him a very confused young man.</p>
				<p>"Hey!  Gentlemen," he called.  "Here's your neighbor, Johann Hoepner.  Take him along out.  Everything is fixed up.  I'm striking off with a load up north.  Dutch are piling in thicker than hope.  Now is your chance,<pb n="BLACK SOIL 101"/>gentleman, to buy up Iowa land.  It will soon be going it at ten dollars an acre."</p><p>"Come on, me bye."  Tim addressed the newcomer. "No wife?" A fringe of color surged over his pale face.  "No, not yet," he answered seriously. "He is promised."  Schwartz concluded. "Well, bully for him," Connor said. Let's be starting."  And the settlers helped the boy with his numerous boxes and satchels into the rear of the wagon.  They themselves occupied the seat.</p>
				<p>Johann, his yellow hair curled up under a heavy felt hat, his grey eyes luminous, flashing, stood erectly in the wagon and viewed his domain in the new country. He smiled complacently.  Never since he had left Ger many two months before, had he felt so complete an escape.  An escape not only from the military duty, but an escape from all the restrictions of an old life in an old land.  For such as he the prairie had waited:  he was sure of that.  Distinct from the carol of its birds, he caught a  lilting, tuneful song--the voice of the prairie itself--calling in its glamour and strength to the youth in him. The prairie reached up to him; he saw it, he felt it.  He  was a conscious of the feel of a plow in his hands.  He tried to visualize these treeless stretches about him, yellow with grain.  "Oh!"  he exclaimed impulsively. "Mein Gott!"At his ejaculation, both men on the seat swung around.  Connor, sensing the boy's delight, remarked: "Pretty fine stretch of country, isn't it, me lad?" Schwartz shrugged, looked appraisingly at the boy,<pb n="102 BLACK SOIL"/>and alone was cynical. Perhaps Schwartz had adequate reason to be so. Here was a dandy coming, with hands like a baby's. And this year was not going to be a good year, according to his wife's predictions. All spring, as Katto planted and tended the crop, she had prophesied that "the devil," if nothing worse, would take this harvest. And Schwartz was justified in not being in credulous of his wife's statements. A scar on his fore head was a tangible proof not only of her infallibility but also of her strength. So if she deemed it expedient to put in the crop and to predict thereon, it was his part to care for the house and family and not to contradict. However, imbibing some of Tim's geniality, he spoke to the enraptured newcomer in German and pointed off across a slough toward a proposed town.</p>
				<p>Then the men were silent again. The long miles between habitations fascinated Johann. He planned to get rich quickly and to send for Emma. He and Emma alone out here with the sky and flowers--flowers that waited for the touch of children's hands. Why, in Germany people got rich on small acreages. And here . . .</p>
				<p>Schwartz, with jerks of his crooked thumb and with voluble flow of German, indicated to Johann the Schwartz home, Tim Connor's, and the location of Johann's land. Then after an exchange of confidential jargon with Tim, he jumped from the wagon. His short, spare body reduced itself to a black line against the green, a dot on the horizon, disappeared.</p>
				<p>"You'll be but a stone's throw from us, if we put up your soddy there on that swell of land," Tim announced to the newcomer. Johann hardly comprehended.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 103"/>He could but stare at the prairie which had been indicated as his.</p>
				<p>Tim gallantly drew up the team before his own do main: a small house of unpainted boards squatting down on a patch tramped bare of grass, a granary like wise weathered, a thatched shed, a struggling truck patch, pigs wallowing in scrooped-out holes, a bleating red calf tied to the wheel of a plow. A woman was washing in the shade of the house, and around her was a flock of children playing in the piles of cool, black earth which the chickens had roughed up.</p>
				<p>At sight of a stranger, the children scampered behind the house and peeped around a corner. The woman dried her hands on her apron and came to greet Johann.</p>
				<p>Nell Connor was not a large woman. In height she reached only to Johann's shoulder; but there was a well-formed muscularity about her that convinced one of her endurance. Her arms were bare, and her stockingless feet were encased in old shoes. Johann knew that he was welcome when he saw her face: a small-featured face with round blue eyes and sensitive lips; a face that held in it no fear, yet no bravado; a face happy but yet a little sad. Johann swept off his hat and bowed low over her hand.</p>
				<p>Nell noted the damp bandeau caused by the weight of his hat, encircling his curly head, his fair skin tinged with pink from its recent sunning, his gray eyes, his military figure, and his sound, even teeth. Lord save us! A mere boy, trustful and untried! Why had he chosen the prairie?  She smiled at the newcomer. "We'll call you John," she said. "How will that be?"<pb n="104 BLACK SOIL"/>The children soon emerged from their retreat and resumed their play. Nell emptied her wash tub and went into the house.</p>
				<p>Johann sat on the wagon tongue and looked about him. The sun was setting, flooding the prairie with yellow light. A girl approached driving a few red cows. She was so much the color of the sunset, that one might expect her to disappear with its afterglow. Her hair, like spun gold bleached in places to the shade of wild honey, was floating about her shoulders, confined by neither pin nor ribbon. She was more a child than a woman. Her step was light and her body firm and graceful. Her face and feet were tanned brown as copper.</p>
				<p>Johann sat entranced, but only for a moment. He soon dismissed the girl who walked out of the sunset as part of the prairie setting, and his thoughts reverted to Emma . . . his Emma, plump-cheeked and full-bosomed, . . . Emma, corseted so tightly that she puffed climbing the steps from the garden . . . Emma, daintily shod, making embroidery for her wedding clothes. His pulse quickened.</p>
				<p>The girl, having turned the cattle into Tim's care, approached, Her manner toward Johann was shy. "My daughter Sheila,'' Nell Connor called from the doorway. Sheila raised her dark brown eyes and greeted Johann: "I hope you'll get along all right." He bowed low. Though reticent, Johann felt that he had discovered a beautiful land and some very kind people.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 105"/>Next morning Schwartz, not very agreeable, with his team and wagon, and Tim with his team and the breaking plow set about to erect a dwelling for the new settler.</p>
				<p>"They're plowing up a house for the greenhorn," the young Connors sang out. "Great way for you to be talking," Nell chided.    "What if he should hear you?" "Well, that's what Schwartz called him," Kitty Ann argued.</p>
				<p>"Greenhorn, indeed! Why, he has studied seven languages. I wonder how he'll manage here. I'm glad he's so close. We can look after him a little. Poor boy." Johann came to the prairie too late in the season to put in a large crop. His neighbors broke ten acres of land for him, however, and he planted corn by hand, chop ping holes in the sod and covering it with his foot. In this occupation he had his initial experience with natural enemies. The pocket gophers watched him warily and on first occasion dug up the precious corn and carried it off in their pouches. Patiently he replanted, and then stationing himself nearby, shot as many of the invaders as possible.</p>
				<p>"Advise him, Tim," Nell begged, "and don't' let him use up all his ammunition on gophers.  He'll be needing game this winter."</p><p>"Don't you be bothering me with that fellow. Ever since he set foot here you've been stewing about him. Let him work oat his own salvation same as the rest of us. He has no one but himself to worry about." <pb n="106 BLACK SOIL "/>"That's the part that worries me, Tim. He has no one.  All alone like that that.  No one to talk to."But Johann spoke to the corn, as he counted the stalks and propped up weak leaves. "How many stalks today, John?" Danny delighted in calling out. Seriously he made reply: "Seven and twenty; hundred; two hundred." When Schwartz heard that Johann counted his stalks, he said:  "The greenhorn has it in the head."The neighbors could not fully appreciate how Johann had staked his happiness and had sacrificed a fortune in coming to America. His success here would not only  insure transportation and a home for Emma, but it would prove to his father and to hers that there were more desirable forms of livelihood than serving in the German army. As military life was extremely distasteful to him, he gloried in the freedom of the boundless prairie. Living here was almost worth the temporary separation from his loved one. For it would not be for long. In a year or two he must have a home established and transportation saved. And as he worked with his crop he was preoccupied with the thought that Emma was waiting to come to him.</p>
				<p>He was grateful to Nell Connor for garden seeds. He also set out a few trees  small twigs scarcely discernible in the grass. Next spring he would get fruit trees and place them around his land as they did in Germany. He watched his neighbors, noted their industry, and imitated them.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 107"/>His days were busy, working, planning; and his nights were full of dreams. The prairie in its vastness and mystery was conducive to dreaming.</p>
				<p>Near his soddy was a "wallow" in which was a large stone around which many buffaloes had left their skeletons. At evening, Johann would light his pipe and sit on this stone, watching each moon  thin, steel crescents, round discs with smiling faces and squinty eyes, waning moons, and moons reborn. He speculated on the number of moons until harvest. About him night birds winged their swift flight through the dusk. And there was a sharp yelping of young wolves.</p>
				<p>The prairie at night, a blue-domed sky with myriads of stars and a low-hung moon, brought the same reverential spirit that Johann experienced when he had stolen into a dusky alcove of the Cathedral of Cologne during vesper service. There were the high-vaulted ceiling, the myriads of flickering tapers, and the sanctuary lamp.</p>
				<p>But Johann knew no prayer for these occasions. His father had no thought for prayer. Johann had, however, a feathery memory of prayer when he thought of his mother who had died when he was very young. He remembered an open window through which came the scent of the garden. There were prayers repeated, and the door was closed quietly. Bed covers soft as his mother's cheek. Safe. Secure. That was all. Occasion ally, he found an expression in the faces of the mothers about him which was the incarnation of the face that came with his mist-like memories.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="108 BLACK SOIL"/>Such an expression was that of Nell Connor when she looked at him with concern and advised him to get out more. Nearly every day she sent some one of the family to see him. Danny came and the younger ones were a veritable nuisance. They questioned him about his guns, his clothes, his pictures. They foraged in his boxes and thumb-marked his books. Occasionally Nell Connor herself appeared with some treat. Sponge cake right out of the oven, cottage cheese  Johann was very fond of cottage cheese. But, being a youth, he resented her acts of kindness and her look of solicitude as re flections on his sense of independence.</p>
				<p>One day Nell stopped at Johann's soddy enroute to the field with a lunch for Tim. She picked up Emma's picture--a tintype in a frame--carried it to the door, and looked at it intently.</p>
				<p>Johann folded his arms and retreated into the shadow. "Nice girl, John. She seems to have a good, innocent face.  Father in the army, too?"Johann nodded. "An officer." "I see." Nell dusted the picture with a corner of her apron and placed it in its cornice. Then the look on her face: concern, motherly solicitude. Her blue eyes grew misty. "You mustn't stay home and think about her all the time, John. There's a nice family of young folks over at Steindlers'; have you met them yet? Come over Sunday and I'll have them over. Come to dinner.''"I will come Sunday," Johann answered, quite con fused, "I don't know all what you say. I would like to know the English. Would you teach me once to read it better?"<pb n="BLACK SOIL 109"/>"Of course I will, John; or, better still, I'll put Sheila at it and you can help her with Latin or perhaps French. That will be fine." Nell picked up her plate and paused just inside the doorway. "We'll be expecting you then Sunday, John."Nell almost ran across the field with Tim's lunch. "Good luck is coming to us, Tim," she greeted him. There was a tinge of color in her cheeks; her eyes were bright. "Sheila has a chance now to learn something. John is going to teach her Latin and perhaps French in return for help in English."Tim stopped his team and looked at his wife. Before answering he drew the back of his hand across his mouth and drank from the small brown jug in which she had brought fresh water. He recorked the jug and set it in the loose black earth.</p>
				<p>"Can she learn it, Nell?" he ventured. "I, meself, think it a useless procedure. Let him teach her the German. She hears that so much it will be easier for her; and then if we get her ready to teach, it'll come in handy."Tim sat on a plow handle and devoured the sponge cake. "Sheila'll do well to teach,'' he went on, "'and it will take all our skill to get her that far."</p>
                                <p>"Tim," Nell leaned forward, her face alight with interest. "Do you know what I'd like to do for Sheila? I pray for it, Send her back East to school. And who knows, Tim, perhaps we can. . . and after Sheila the others."</p>
                                <p>"Sheila will do well if she teaches the young ones<pb n="110 BLACK SOIL"/>around here. Her wages will be her own, and if she wants to go on, I for one would never thwart her plans; but I don't believe she's the kind you make her out, Nell. She's not ambitious. Can't you see it?''"I'm not looking for flaws in her; and I'm glad she is different. She's gentle, and does as she's told."</p><p>"Yes," Tim broke in, "but did you ever have to tell her <emph>not </emph>to do anything, even a bit of mischief? She seems to have no fire or spirit. Tell me one thing. Can you name one thing she shows any interest in? She goes about taking things by the easy handle, with never a care or thought of the morrow. I believe she has no more responsibility than little Ellen, nor as much."</p><p>"I'm glad she doesn't, the poor child, with no kith or kin. I'm just glad she doesn't worry about things; and I thought you had a heart toward her, Tim."</p><p>"Nonsense, Nell, I have the same heart for her that I had when she came, a bit of a stray colleen; but it's you I'm thinking of, Nell. I don't want to see you disappointed."</p><p>"A lot you care about me and my disappointments. I suppose it will be Danny next that will get the going over." Nell swept away from the field, rage and anger taking possession of her. Tim's words were true enough. Sheila was rather listless; but wasn't it nice that she was, and not like the daughters of Max, who were in a stew over something all the time? And Sheila would learn. Nell would see to that. She would show Tim. She would begin with German and after that the Latin.</p>
				<p>Tim watched after his wife for a moment and noticed the droop of her shoulders. Then he drew his<pb n="BLACK SOIL 111"/>pipe from his pocket, untied a small sack of tobacco, filled and lighted his pipe, tossed the match at his feet and crushed it into the soft earth. Then, slipping the tied reins about his shoulders, he grasped the plow handles, spoke to Jack and Jule, bent over the plow, and began to make a darker furrow in the already black soil. <pb n="112"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XVI">
				<p>ON reaching the house Nell forgot her own recent provocation, for the wife of Max was there and in tears.</p>
				<p>"Oh, Mrs. Connor," she broke out by the way of greeting, "I could cry when I see you and Tim in the field talking. Tim he is a kind man. Max he would not talk unless it was a preach he was giving. Max he would make a good preacher." She was smiling now and making light of her first emotion. "Oh, Mrs. Connor," she continued, "a letter came for me. I opened it. I knew it was for me. I saw the 's' this way after the <emph>'Mr.' </emph>It was a check from my brother, my share from the land. After I open it, I got a scare. I want to paste it shut again but I had tore it. So I went and say my prayers. I think: If I die then I will be ready. I take my little crucifix I got in mission in Dubuque and think there was Jesus suffering, too, and He did no wrong. Then I went out to my man and gave him the letter. I think if he kills me I had one thing: I could read all them little marks and know that my brother was sending money yet." The women leaned toward each other. Their faces almost touched. The wife of Max had a hand on Nell's arm. "Do you know that man got weak-like, so surprise was he when I read those little lines. He didn't strike me once. But oh, I so fear for you, Mrs. Connor. Max said: 'That's what she does, huh? I will fix that smart Mrs. Connor once. She won't be so proud. Some day I will.' So I warn you. I feel so for you."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 113"/>Nell smiled. "I'm so glad you read the letter; but don't worry about me." She put the coffee pot on the stove, "We'll have some coffee and there is a heel of a loaf of cake here yet." She drew herself up before her guest. "Max can't frighten me. I guess I can't get frightened any more. I've seen enough. I had Indians here when there wasn't a house for miles. See the marks of prairie fire?" displaying her arms, "Alone I welcomed Kitty Ann into this prairie and cared for her. And storms and loneliness and hunger. . . ! Your Max can't frighten me. I'm ready for him or anyone else who will try to destroy our chance of making a decent living for our children."  Max's wife looked at her reverently.</p>
				<p>After the women had drawn up to the table, Nell, for custom's sake, inquired after Max's foot. "Not good. He cannot walk much; but today he went to county seat, so," she added, smiling, "I come here."As her guest expatiated on the discoloration of her husband's foot, Max's warning floated in on Nell's consciousness and out again.  "I will fix that smart one once. She will not be so proud.  Some day."  How queer that  was!  What could he know?  Oh, could it be Sheila?  Certainly not.</p>
				<p>Aloud she said: "Have the girls come over Sunday. I want John to meet them.'' And she cleared away their lunch dishes.</p>
				<p>Max's wife was elated. "He'll take a wife," she said, her dull brown eyes animated. "He will be a good one for my Tilly or my Julie." The wrinkles of her face went into deeper furrows, and with her smile her narrow lips tightened over her large teeth. The news was so<pb n="114 BLACK SOIL"/>stimulating that she could sit and converse no longer. "I will go now, and thank you," she said.</p>
				<p>On the following Sunday: afternoon four of the six daughters of Max--Mary, Julie, Katie and Tilly--arrayed in their own and borrowed finery, started on their way to walk to Connors', the marriage market; the greenhorn would be needing a wife. Without envy or malice, the two remaining daughters and the wife of Max watched them from the doorway and wished them all Godspeed, and one of them victory. The existent state of magnanimity of all was not attained without much quarreling and tears. All of them, even Annie, wanted to go; but they finally decided on four as they had suit able clothes for four only. It was understood that the four oldest would go by right of age; but the wife of Max saw no need of Lena going when Lou Hoppe, the hired man, was by all appearances making up to her.</p>
				<p>Lena was for going. Lena was slight and willowy, with the brown eyes of her mother; hers, however, were bright and alive with the buoyancy of youth. Her hair was red like her father's and her body hard and muscular as a man's.</p>
				<p>"We're not promised," she argued. "What did he say, then?" the mother asked. Without pride or shyness, Lena answered frankly: "He said that he couldn't plow for watching me in the field."So, he was watching across at Lena, then, when Mary was his plowing partner! Mary, the oldest, who almost had a match in Dyersville had they not moved away be fore the romance had come to a climax.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 115"/>The wife of Max called Lena aside, "I see it that Lou likes you all right. Come. Stay home now. Think once on Mary; the oldest should go first. Katie and Tilly can go, and let Julie go in your place. Think once on Julie, <emph>too, </emph>so thick and with such big freckles on her face, like Max."Lena acquiesced. The four fortunate girls, though rivals, did not look upon each other as such. With feet and bodies crammed into tight clothing, their faces flushed and expectant, they raised their skirts from the grass, bent their bodies against the ever-blowing breeze, and felt that all could be victorious. The May day, the sense of freedom from work, the sky, the prairie, the pulse and hopes of youth tinged their shadows of doubt. All could win.</p>
				<p>As the wife of Max saw them grow smaller and smaller, she reasoned: Johann might want a red thick one, a red thin one, a black thick one, or a black thin one. She could have done no more; she had sent one of each.</p>
				<p>Meanwhile the girls were going on toward adventure, going dreamily now, their thoughts soaring and carrying them off to high places. This experience in itself was a luxury, for in their usual day they had no time or energy for dreaming. In the field, if they: were not intent on their work, the plow would slip; and in the evening their straw ticks crinkled so restfully that with only a glance at the stars they fell asleep.</p>
				<p>Max, who had been over south looking at his corn, swung around and was now before the girls, hobbling along using a stick for a cane. His powerful figure was foreboding as it expanded before them.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="116 BLACK SOIL"/>"Ya, where are you going?" he asked. The girls, guilty as criminals, abashed and fearful, stood. Mary, the oldest, to whom they looked as spokes man, was absorbed in brushing seeds from her skirt.</p>
				<p>Katie, "the black thin one," more independent than the others, perhaps because she was meeting Pete Schwartz away from home occasionally, spoke up: "To Connors'. Mrs. Connor say we shall." "Where is Lena?" "Home." "Why?" "She is tired from plowing, She shall rest." With a flourish of his cane, Max indicated the direction of their house. "Go home."The four marriageable girls turned as one and retraced their way. Katie rather indifferently, Mary and Tilly bitterly, and Julie in tears.</p>
				<p>The wife of Max, so trained to silence, established a precedent by rising in defense of her action. In consequence, she was beaten terribly.</p>
				<p>That night Tilly and Julie, with their heads under the covers, decided to run away to Sioux City on first opportunity. Katie crept away from the house when all were in bed and met Pete Schwartz on the prairie. Mary showed no reaction to the afternoon's proceedings, un less she was more silent and a harder worker than ever.</p>
				<p>Nell had watched for the Steindler girls on Sunday while Sheila and Johann exchanged their knowledge of language. Once she thought she saw them coming across the field; but when they: did not arrive, she knew that Max had detained them. So, keeping the children from annoying the two students, she noted their application.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 117"/>While Sheila mechanically repeated the German words, her dark eyes left the book to rest quizzically on Johann's face; Johann, oblivious to any scrutiny, taught religiously.</p>
				<p>After the spring term of school ended, Danny anticipated a summer of excitement. A well-digger was coming to dig a new well; a carpenter was going to build another room, a bedroom for Sheila; Danny was to move up and be the sole occupant of the loft-room, to have the protection of the old hatcher's wings and view the country through the old hen's eye: and  best of all he was going to accompany his father when he went to town to bring home the harvester.</p>
				<p>Vacation offered much to the younger Connors, too. Expeditions on the prairie usually brought discoveries. And there were Johann and his mysterious house close by. When the lonely neighbor had not visited with Connors for awhile, Nell sent the children to see him. "Clear off over and see John a while. He'll be dead with the lonesome." As Johann rested outside his shanty in the evening, the mob would bear down upon him. Kitty Ann delighted in grabbing his hat for a chase. Robert Emmet clamored to hold the large watch with the heavy fob bearing the Kaiser's image. Ellen, her light curls bobbing as she toddled about, prattled inarticulately, attempting to repeat the last phrases of the others by way of emphasis. Was there anyone who could ask as many questions as Danny? And at Margaret's imaginative tales, Johann knew that he appeared stupid and incredulous. He could not even feign a hearty response to the children who approached him in, as many channels as there were children; he could only catch Kitty<pb n="118 BLACK SOIL"/>Ann, rescue the hat and smooth it carefully to form, and sit silently. He never sent the children home, neither did he welcome them.</p>
				<p>They bothered Johann no more after the well-digger, Ben, arrived. Next to Pop the well-digger was the most wonderful man in the world. Never after he had driven his bony nag into the yard was he a moment alone in his waking hours, nor did he wish to be.</p>
				<p>The well could not be dug where Nell had wished it. She had hoped that it could be built near the house so that in time they could have a narrow walk built to it  that is, after they got the pigs and stock fenced in,  but after Ben had "witched" the ground with a willow crotch he announced that there was no water under the desired spot. It was several rods from the house that the willow turned the proper way to indicate a vein of water.</p>
				<p>While Ben worked he talked incessantly. There seemed to be a memorable incident or a song for every day of his existence; and he found six eager minds and as many pairs of eyes ready to hold as true, fact and make-believe alike. Ben had led a varied life. He had been a cowboy on the plains, he had been in the Civil War, he had worked on the railroad, he had built houses and he had dug wells.</p>
				<p>Ben was the first baldheaded man that the young Connors had ever seen. Accordingly, they must find out at intervals what was the matter with his head.</p>
				<p>"That's where I was scalped by an Indian," he repeated. "You see they thought that I was dead, so they just took off the scalp-lock and left me. The skin growed<pb n="BLACK SOIL 119"/>together nice and smooth and here I am, digging your Poppy a well."On warm evenings the family, with Ben, sat outside the door. The nights were full of insect chirps, the croaking of bullfrogs in the slough, and the sound of growing corn and grain. Dragonflies, their wings silver in the moonlight, darted near, and an occasional owl screeched weirdly. Ben's voice, solemn, droning, gay, as the song demanded: "For I'm a young cowboy and I know I've done wrong,"One evening Ben went to the granary where he kept his belongings and produced a fiddle. Tuning it up and holding it across his knee, he gave his repertoire  a varied one. When he finally struck up <emph>The Irish Washerwoman, </emph>there was a twinkle in his eye. As he knew they would, Tim and Nell began to dance. Repairing to the kitchen, they faced each other and jigged. Nell was light as a feather on her feet, and Tim brought his down in true clog fashion. Kitty Ann led the children, and they: all joined in the dance.</p>
				<p>"It's a long time since I heard them old-timers, them treasures," Tim said smiling. "Where did you get a-hold of them?"</p><p>"In the army," Ben answered. "My chum was a young Irishman. This was his fiddle. After he left me and I was alone I learned them pieces in his memory, Finer lad never lived. Being here sort of brings him back."Although the Connors were in an exultant frame of mind and called for an encore, Ben would play no more that night, Putting his fiddle in his worn case, he went to his quarters in the granary.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="120 BLACK SOIL"/>When the well was almost finished and the new wooden pump lay in the yard waiting to be set in, the Connors had their first peddler. A dark-skinned, foreign-looking man, wearing store clothes and with a cumbersome pack strapped to his shoulder, knocked at the door.</p>
				<p>"How do," he said to Nell. She answered: "How do." "You be English," he announced rather than asked. "Yes." "I be English. You be Cat'lic?" Nell nodded. "I be Cat'lic. I show you my goods."When "the goods" were displayed, the young Connors swarmed over the man and his wares. Could any one imagine so many things to be in one satchel! "Can I have this? Can I have this?" they asked.</p>
				<p>"Don't tore it. Don't broke it," he pleaded, trying to rescue the most valuable "goods." Nell interposed and placed the children in a row, in seeing but not in reaching distance.</p>
				<p>"I have no money," she repeated, as the peddler insisted on selling her articles of his own selection. "You have a nice scissors that I would like to buy if I could. I need a scissors. How much is it?"</p><p>"Seventy-five cents," he stated. "Take one, nice lady. You can buy one. Me poor man. Me send money to wife in Arabia. You got money."</p><p>"No," Nell smiled. "I can't buy. Thank you for showing them. Move back, children, so he can pt his trays in."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 121"/>"You be nice lady. You give me supper and bed and I give you something." Nell said: "All. right, you can take your pack to that granary there. There is where you will sleep." The peddler refused to allow the goods out of his sight.</p>
				<p>That evening, as they gathered outside the door, the peddler sat aloof. He drew a sheet of paper from his pocket and resting it on the palm of one hand began on its right-hand corner to make a series of hieroglyphics across to the left. The crowd pressed close to him, watching him as he wrote dexterously.</p>
				<p>Ben commented: "I've seen a good many people of all kinds and knocked about as much as anyone; but that beats all. Thought that scratching was left to the Chinese."</p><p>"Arabic. We had some of that back East," Tim said. "Come here," Ben said, ignoring the guest with the exotic atmosphere. "Come here, Emmet, and I'll see if I can show you the Black Hills tonight." Catching the boy by the two ears, he attempted to raise him from the ground. "Still too heavy," he announced. "Too much mush and milk. Afraid, sonny, you'll have to wait until you grow up to see the Hills."After the peddler had finished writing, he said he would go to bed and went towards the granary. Thereupon Ben stood up and stretched lazily. "Guess I'll be turning in, myself."The peddler occupied the oats bin, and the well-digger the wheat bin. Each was very suspicious of the other. During the night at the least sound both would sit up and face each other across the partition.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="122 BLACK SOIL"/>Next morning before the peddler departed he gave Nell not the scissors but a towel bordered in red. Nell thanked him; he said he would come again, asked if the neighbor to the east were Dutch, High Ger man, Luxemburger, Catholic, shouldered his pack, and started off.</p>
				<p>"Did your Mommy get the scissors?" Ben asked Danny: as he emptied a bucket of yellow clay. "No, she got a throw." "A 'throw'?" "Yes, a fancy towel to tie on a chair" "What did he say?" "Oh, he asked if Catholic and German lived in the next house." "Gad, why didn't she fool him?" As a relay runner waits only for the touch of his ally's hand to dart off, so Danny at Ben's inspiration followed after the disappearing figure.</p>
				<p>"Say mister," he yelled. "Where are yuh going? Going to Schwartzes'? Say! better, not go there, They're not Catholic." "Not Cat'lic?" Danny shook his head. "Me don't care." "Ain't you Catholic?" Danny asked. "No," he answered. Danny returned to the well-digger. He was puzzled. "Well, he told Mom he was English and a Catholic," Danny argued.</p>
				<p>"That's the way he gets the people's attention at the door, sonny. He finds out from the neighbors and then that's what he is for the occasion."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 123"/>Tim was amused at the peddler's attempted duplicity. Nell was rather chagrined. She displayed the "throw," however; and after the children had gone to bed she told of their excitement over the peddler's wares. "They went for that satchel like chickens for a hot mess. I was actually mortified."Tim and Ben only chuckled; men didn't seem to understand. The peddler, such as he was, was a guest,  and the children hadn't known how to act.</p>
				<p>Nell brushed back her hair a bit with the palm of her hand, an action that she had lately acquired. "They're growing up so wild. Wonder the man gave me anything, they worried him so. And Danny overtaking him and telling him that today. If anything had happened to him at Schwartzes' we would have been responsible. As it was, Katto drove him off the place with the pitchfork."Ben roared heartily, "I'd give anything to have seen that. I'd give a whole lot."The well-digger then sat up straight. "Folks," he said, "you've got the finest bunch of young ones that I ever set my eyes on, and I've seen a plenty. Don't you fret now about manners," he turned to Nell. "These polished manners are like a cloak that anyone can put off and on; but real manners come from the heart. That's what counts. These young ones got the stuff in them. Some day that Danny will be doing something  running a locomotive into the country or be on his way to Washington. Sheila's as pretty a picture as I've ever seen, and I've seen a plenty. Some dandy will be trying to steal her off your hands one of these days. Margaret lives in a world of her own; and Kitty Ann is a rascal after my own heart."<pb n="124 BLACK SOIL"/>"There now, Nell, listen to that," said Tim, well pleased. "Now maybe you won't be doing so much use less worrying. The childer didn't suit that heathen of a peddler, but they suit Ben, a dang sight better judge, I'm after saying."</p><p>"But poor John, I guess, thinks they are savages." Nell was tired. She had had a long day, what with the extras and the children.</p>
				<p>"That Johann, or whatever he calls himself," Ben spoke up, "will do well to stay over there and stare into the eyes of that vacant-faced girl he has in that frame. Your black cow has more expression than she has."</p><p>"Oh, Ben," Nell admonished. "She, has a good face, and John surely loves her.'' "Deliver me from hot Dutch love," was Ben's conclusion. After the well was finished and a tight platform built above it, Ben said that he would stay and build on Sheila's room. The Connors were delighted; but after the room was finished they must allow him to go away and dig other wells.</p>
				<p>Tim went to town and got some money at the bank to pay Ben. The children were tearful at his leave-taking. "Don't pick up with some Dutchman, now," he said to Sheila. "Wait till the right man comes along. That Herman Schwartz is sort of keeping an eye on you. Be ware."Danny clung to Ben's hand. "Sonny," the well digger said, closing a gold coin in the grimy fist, "your Mommy thinks that you haven't got much chance here;<pb n="BLACK SOIL 125"/>but I'm going to tell you this. You can be whatever you want to be and make of yourself whatever you wish. Anyone with ambitions and a Poppy and Mommy like you got holds their future in their hand just as you hold <emph>that." </emph>He pressed his hand around the boy's. "And I'm coming back."The old nag, unused to the bridle, yielded reluctantly as Ben gave a jerk to its rein, "See," he said, "Prince don't want to go, neither," which brought smiles to the children's faces. Seeing them thus, he left.</p>
				<p>"Saints be praised," Nell said when Danny disclosed the gold-piece in his hand, "he has given us back nearly as much as we paid him."Ben gone, the youngest Connors ran off to visit the neglected Johann. Sheila and Danny left with the cattle. Tim went to the field. Alone, Nell stood with her hand on the new pump. She took a drink of the fresh water. Its clearness and coldness gave her a sense of great luxury. A good well. The bright new addition to the house. Later on, a harvester. A promising crop . . . prosperity indeed. Perhaps this year they could earn something besides interest money. Interest! There would be more interest now. How much interest would they have to pay before these luxuries  no, necessities, so prized that they seemed like luxuries  were paid for?</p>
				<p>Well, she couldn't answer. She didn't know. She could only do her best and trust in God. Such crops were assuring and showed promise of good things. The grain just heading out was glossy in the sunlight, the prairie luxuriant with growth, and the corn so tall that the black earth was entirely shut from view. Tim was plowing in the distant green, and Johann's figure was bent<pb n="126 BLACK SOIL"/>over his sod corn, hoeing, hoeing, hoeing. How slavishly poor Johann worked! Well, the young ones would be the cause of his stopping to draw his breath. .  .</p>
				<p>When the children entered Johann's patch of sod corn they  Margaret and Kitty Ann and Robert Emmet and Ellen  were walking abreast. Johann hurried to meet them, admonishing: "Watch out! Watch out once for the little corn."</p><p>"We ain't breaking your old corn,'' Kitty Ann answered. "Mom said that you can have water from our new well," Margaret said, hoping to gain favor. "Ben is gone, gone,'' Robert Emmet said sadly. "Tell your mother thank you. I will come for water," Johann said in a tone of dismissal, and resumed his hoeing. Perhaps the children in Johann's former life could be dismissed thus, but not the Connors of the prairie.</p>
				<p>Kitty Ann thrust a brown little foot in the path of the hoe; Robert Emmet and Ellen did likewise. Ellen crowed with delight. It was a great game. Margaret, discerning the displeasure in Johann's eye, drew back.</p>
				<p>Johann would take no risks hoeing under such circumstances. We cupped the handle of the hoe with both hands, rested his chin thereon, and stared at the children.</p>
				<p>"Let's go over to Pop,'' Margaret suggested. "Pop's got nicer corn than you." This from Kitty Ann. Johann did not argue. Annoyed, Kitty Ann added: "I wish the ground squirrels had eaten your old corn all up." "I'm going to tell Mom on you,'' Margaret threatened the younger sister.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 127"/>Not yet satisfied, Kitty Ann lagged behind the others. At the edge of the field she pulled up a stalk of corn and held it up to Johann; then, tossing it on the ground, she ran and caught up with the rest.</p>
				<p>Johann went to the sod house for a little water and reset the stalk in its place. Mrs. Connor was a fine lady, he thought, but those young "Connors. . . .! Picking up his hoe, he resumed his work in the field.</p>
				<p>Johann was determined to get on in America. He knew that hard work would get him there; but he would have to know English. Sheila did not help him as much in her hour's time as Mrs. Connor did in a few minutes. Sheila, he concluded, was a good herdswoman but would never make a teacher. He had made headway in his studies while the well-digger was at Connors', for then he had not been disturbed or annoyed. He realized that he was learning the language readily, and wishing to master it he kept at it, repeating idioms and conjugations while he worked in the field, which was from dawn until night hid the green stalks. <pb n="128"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XVII">
				<p>ONE June morning Johann, as usual, was hoeing in his patch of sod corn when the sun, baring the nightly mysteries of the sky and prairie, pushed up its face over the rim of the world. A quivering breeze stirred the phlox and made music in the coarse slough grass. The reach of the prairie was limitless. In its waving motion, its distant shanties and soddies bobbed like flotsam. Wee fluffs of cloud, enhancing the blueness of the sky, sailed by, became a mist, and melted away. And the sky remained as blue.</p>
				<p>The morning slipped away. The sun was in the zenith; still Johann remained in his field. He saw Nell Connor hoeing potatoes nearby, working also without regard for time.</p>
				<p>Suddenly a large, dark cloud appeared in the west. Broadening out and roaring, it moved directly toward them. Terrified, Johann recalled confusedly strange phenomena. What was it? Anything might happen in a new country. The apparition as it settled lower became more and more terrifying. Its rumbling sound changed to a sonorous hum. The sun lost its light.</p>
				<p>"Bad storm!" he shouted, as he ran toward Nell, who with uplifted face stood like a statue, staring into the sky.</p>
				<p>The sky was filled with a storm of black flakes, the dark particles singling out and becoming more defined in shape as they descended. He heard a buzzing, saw shining wings, long bodies, legs. . .</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 129"/>"Grasshoppers!" Nell's agonized voice rang out. <emph>"Grasshoppers! </emph>May God preserve us the scourge of the prairie is upon us." He saw her sink to the ground and cover her face with her hands.</p>
				<p>Johann shouted and brandished his hoe. The horde descended. He tried to defend his field . . . his corn was a mass of shining bodies sucking, sucking the tender juices. He worked feverishly, knocking off feeders only to give place to others. He, himself was covered with grasshoppers. They crawled over his face, his eyes, and invaded his clothes. The limitless stretch of prairie was not vast enough to hold them all. He surrendered to them, and went toward Connors. As he walked, his boots became slimy with crushed bodies.</p>
				<p>The succulent prairie grass was converted into a moving mass as the hoppers piled up in their greed. Nell joined him in the yard. "Thank God we're safe, anyhow," she said.</p>
				<p>Tim, who was at the county seat with Weiss, could not return home before evening; but Sheila, who was herding, and Danny who was taking his father's place plowing corn soon came running in. "The horses are gone," Danny announced, crying with fear and excite men. "When it got so dark they acted so funny I un hitched their tugs and they ran away. I can't even see where they went."</p><p>"They'll come back. Don't bother about them. It's a miracle they didn't kill you." Nell's face was as white as chalk. Her blue eyes were dark. She was trying hard to regain her self-control.</p>
				<p><pb n="130 BLACK SOIL"/>"The cattle went wild, too," Sheila broke in, all out of breath. "They: bellowed so and sniffed the ground like when they see blood. I put for home."</p>
                                 <p>"Let 'em go. Don't go near 'em. They can go where they want now--there's nothing to save, I guess," Nell said with resignation.</p>
				<p>Robert Emmet and Ellen, still terrified, clung to Nell. She held them closely, wishing to impart to them some of her trust, her thanks. . . . "The children might have been killed by those frightened animals."Hysterical shrieks broke in on the temporary calm. From across the field they saw Katto Schwartz approaching. Johann moved back toward the house as she faced him. Shaking her fist first in the direction of the sky and then at the pests at her feet, she went through her repertoire of imprecations. Stamping her calloused bare feet, she crushed the slimy horde with a vengeance. While the sun shone on her glazed calico dress and disclosed tawny strands in her dishevelled [sic] hair, she ground her teeth and was shaken by a tremor whish agitated her excess of flesh.</p>
				<p>Mrs. Connor's attempt at calming her was of no avail. "Come," she said finally. "I'll make the coffee." "All right," Katto acquiesced, her voice lowered considerably. "We'd better drink it once before something gets it from us. I said the devil would get the crop; but we got good measure  all hell is turned loose."Johann declined to have coffee with the women. Be wildered, he moved toward his soddy which he found veneered a shiny brown. He had never had a door, so the invaders had entered and taken possession of his<pb n="BLACK SOIL 131"/>house, even testing the edibility of his old red stove. He went to the field for his hoe, and began his futile struggle to dislodge them.</p>
				<p>The Connor children watched for their father, while they worked in the garden helping Nell wrest what was possible from the plunderers.</p>
				<p>Danny talked glibly. "Hey, you old pigs! Get off of those carrots." It was really a hand-to-hand struggle, for the invaders persisted in having their share, even while the vegetables were being pulled.</p>
				<p>Margaret spied a dark speck in the east. Soon they recognized horses' bobbing heads, and like a flash they ran to meet Tim and Weiss.</p>
				<p>There was an exchange of waving, then a series of "Hello, Pop," and the children climbed into the wagon. "Pop, we got the grasshoppers!" "And they put out the sun . . .!" "My, we were so scared!'' "They ate everything up, Pop. John thought it was a cyclone; but when Mom saw their wings and every thing, she knew it was grasshoppers." " and she cried, too." "We fighted with them in the garden. Our cave is full of stuff."Peter Weiss stood silently in the wagon. The joints of his hands were knobbed as he held the reins tightly. An occasional tear trickled down his beard. . . . He could see his farm.</p>
				<p>The children spied a wooden pail. "What's that?" they asked at once.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="132 BLACK SOIL"/>"I see that they didn't carry you or your curiosity away," Tim said lightly. "I brought you some jelly." "Jelly? What's jelly?"Tim drew out his knife, ripped up the lid of the pail, and gave each child a quivering, ruddy slice. "Here's a bit of a taste now and you can put some on bread when we get home."</p><p>"M-m-m, it's good," they commented in unison. "And Pop," Margaret took up the recital of events again, "Katto got mad and sent her curses up to God. She won't go to Heaven, will she, Pop?" "Even as you and I, childer. Katto's all right. There's no harm in Katto."Tim could see the destruction in his own fields now. His usually erect figure slumped dejectedly and he swallowed hard. "Everything all gone, eh? Wheat patch, too?"</p><p>"Yes," Danny answered. "They bent the stalks. See, Pop, the patch is all brown."That evening they spoke little of grasshoppers, al though the insects were omnipresent, clicking, jumping and dashing their bodies against the house. Tim, as usual, related his experiences at the county seat and told the news picked up that day.</p>
				<p>Nell, lulling Ellen on her knees, asked: "Bid you get Weiss's trouble fixed up all right? Was it so serious as he imagined?"</p><p>"Well, serious enough," Tim answered with a reminiscent smile. "A St. Paul concern had a chattel mort gage on his two hogs and a spavined mule that he'd brought back from the Black Hills. Last winter his<pb n="BLACK SOIL 133"/>family ran short of food, so they ate the hogs; and to cap the climax the old mule died. So Weiss was in a terrible way: he was afraid it was to jail he'd have to go."</p><p>"Did you settle it for him?" "I don't think they'll bother Weiss, any more about it. Young Peck was there to represent the company--Peck's a fine, decent fellow, After he had made his plea, I stood up and told them that the family was forced to eat the hogs or starve, and that the old mule had with stood all other calamities in its cosmopolitan life, but the chattel mortgage had proved fatal. The court had a great laugh, and the case was dismissed."</p><p>"Childer, you should have seen the funny fellow they had there today," he went on. "His clothes were a mass of rags sewed and quilted together. They said he'd been around the country for some time and when people spoke to him he got down on hands and knees and crepe into the cornfields. As he was scaring the people,  the sheriff rounded him up and brought him in. And he discovered that in between the layers of his tatters was money, paper money, gone to chaff with dry rot. And he had gold on him, too. 1 saw him there. He wasn't old; he had a fine face and looked bright. I couldn't help but think he had good connections. He wouldn't give his name. He only said: 'Call me John Doe.' I believe they took him to Cherokee."</p><p>"What else did you see, Pop?" "There was a hay twister for sale there. Twisted the hay up slick as a whistle. Bunch of us settlers looking at it in the morning thought we might buy one together<pb n="134 BLACK SOIL"/>in the fall; but after we saw that scourge of hoppers land, I guess we thought no more of hay twisters. . . . That white courthouse was painted brown in a few minutes."The impending depression forced itself in. Tim got up and walked out of the house. He went through the grove and stood on the edge of the cornfield. The moonlight, bright as day, revealed the luster of the shiny pests, and the snapping and crackling of corn was like the subdued noise of cattle feeding.</p>
				<p>Tim thought of neighbors who shared his fate as he saw their groves  dark rectangles against the sky. By their height one could determine the length of time the owner had been in the country. Schwartz's grove completely hid his house. Van Den Hull had one peeping window in which a yellow light gleamed. Johann's shack remained a clod of black earth.</p>
				<p>In the grove behind him and in the fields before him was the eerie rustling, a sucking away of the food of his family. Just when they had dared to hope and had been so bold as to involve themselves more deeply in debt  the well, Sheila's room, the harvester  had come this calamity, Surely they would not force him to take that harvester when there was no harvest. He would write and cancel the order.</p>
				<p>The children's words returned to him. . . . Mom had cried. "Poor girl! Poor childer! I picked the devil's own country for them. This prairie charmed me like a snake, to strike not only me but Nell and the young ones as well, . . . Yes sir, the devil's own country!</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 135"/>Still, can fortune always be so bad? It's a long lane that hasn't a turn!"He walked back to the house. The light was turned low. The even breathing and sleepy mutterings of healthy children filled the house. Nell was kneeling by the open window of the bedroom, her dark hair hanging down her back, her face resting on the sill. She was praying, in an attitude of dejection. The hundreds of eyes watching her through the window completely shut off her vision of the stars.</p>
				<p>"Nell," Tim spoke out. "Good luck will come to us yet, I'm a-thinking. 'The darkest hour is just before the dawn.' "Johann could not accept this calamity so philosophically as did the Connors. He tried to seek out a reason, but there was no reason; there was no justification for such a phenomenon.</p>
				<p>"It's God's will, John. Accept it as such and you can bear it better," Nell repeated. "Remember, God never closes one gap but He opens another. Keep your trust in God."But Johann could not be convinced. Often he stood in the doorway where he had succeeded in scraping a pile of the pests, and allowed them to become scattered again as he leaned on the handle of his hoe asking : Why? Why? Why the incongruity in the scene before him? Sometimes he felt raised to the capability of real struggle when he contemplated the sky so blue, so guileless, the prairie--a strange place, holding the answers to his questions in its sinister silence. In his<pb n="136 BLACK SOIL"/>meditations he felt cut off from the world. All about him nothing was distant, yet all was distance.</p>
				<p>There was no harvest time that year, for there was no crop to harvest. All the fields about were stripped, and Johann's sod corn was reduced to sod; coarse grass again found root. Tearfully he looked at his ten acres which had lost their identity as a patch under cultivation. Toil wasted, hope deferred.</p>
				<p>"You must learn to accept fate," Tim Connor said again and again, but Johann could not be resigned to the caprices of a new country. He saw only its un fairness. The fact that Emma's coming must be postponed dominated his thoughts. Other people, daily events, were unreal, like voices in a fog. It perturbed him not at all that movers were headed East. Too, many of the neighbors were leaving. Schwartz said that he would stick as long as Connor and starve with him. Max Steindler scoffed at hard times  Max had other resources, his wife's money. The Hollanders were staying. A few neighbors, however, of whom Nell Connor had become very fond, were loading their household goods into the wagons. Among these were the Hurds, who were going back to New Jersey. Nell went over to see them and asked if Johann could move their granary and live in it through the winter.</p>
				<p>"Take it all," Mr. Hurd said, "I don't ever want to set eyes on this godforsaken country again. It's taken my wife's health, all our inheritance, our best years, and--Benny.  I turn my land over to the hoppers. Take the buildings. I wouldn't give you five dollars for the whole township. I'll never come back."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 137"/>"I'll not say come back. I'd like to be going myself,  back to civilization and decency," Nell said, wiping her eyes, "but Tim would never leave, I know he wouldn't. And I suppose I'd be worrying, too, about those we left behind. Goodbye and good luck. Think of us when you come into your kingdom."And the Hurds followed in line with the discouraged settlers who swung their horses toward the East. <pb n="138"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XVIII">
				<p>DURING this exodus, there was a great demand for horses--horses to carry people out of the country. Many of the immigrant settlers had never used oxen; consequently were unaccustomed to them. Jake Sheckel, the livery man at Casper Center, had sold most of his best teams and was out scouring the country for substitutes. He called at Connors'.</p>
				<p>"Let's give him Jack and Jule, in God's name," Nell suggested, "and Buck and Spec can do all the hauling we'll need." Tim brought the team from the barn for appraisal. He was being hounded for interest money. Winter was coming, and there must be food and clothing.</p>
				<p>"I hate to give 'em up," he argued. "Poor faithful critters brought me in out of many the blizzard, But it's a blessing we have them to sell."Nell moved up to the liveryman. "You'll be kind to them? They're not large and can't pull heavy loads."</p><p>"Livery work won't hurt them," Sheckel answered brusquely. "They're not my style of horse, but I don't expect business to be great this year. Tell you what I'll do. I'll buy them now and give you a good price; but I won't sell them until I see you first. Maybe when the country'll be demanding fleeter horses, you will be in a position to buy them back."</p><p>"Now that's kind of you. I'll have no fear of them in your keeping," Nell replied.</p>
				<p>So the hard shiny money was placed in Tim's hand,<pb n="BLACK SOIL 139"/>and Jack and Jule were led away. In a row, the Connors  from Tim to Ellen  watched them out of sight. Poor Jack and Jule, who had come between them and want!</p>
				<p>Next day Tim went off to town in great spirits to pay interest, but he returned home rather disconsolate. In the mail had come a notice of the arrival of his harvester at Malcur, the terminus of the road. The company had not accepted his cancellation of the order. He must take it whether or no. "Any man that had land," they argued, "could pay for a harvester. A bargain is a bargain."Nell knew that Tim, though clever enough in pleading the case of another, was easily overcome in his own defense. They would make him buy that harvester! She  failed to convince him of the righteousness in not accepting it, so she dispatched Danny for Schwartz.</p>
				<p>"You're a dumb fool if you buy that, Tim," Schwartz began. "Yes, but they say that I'll be having to pay for it whether I take it home or not. In that case, I'd better get it." "Pay for it!" Schwartz repeated. "Now, Tim, you know as well as I do that you got nothing to pay for that harvester. Everything you got is mortgage same as mine." He spat tobacco vehemently. "They can't make you pay for it if you don't take it. That's threats, Tim, threats. You know that, too, same as I."Katto, having caught the drift of the argument, offered advice. "I tell him if I was you that he and harvester can rot there at depot before you take it home and make more mortgage and interest. <emph>Interest. </emph>They think, by Gutt, that's all we got to pay  interest !"<pb n="140 BLACK SOIL"/>"That's right, Katto," Tim agreed. "That's all we do pay. Some of us can't even pay that." "I got my cornplow," Schwartz added, "and use it before grasshoppers come, but he can wait for pay. I got no pay."</p><p>"You tell him for me," Katto's face was close to Tim's again, "that if he wants pay to try and get it once. He won't try another time." "I'll go over and see .him tomorrow and hear what he has to say," Tim said calmly. "I don't want trouble about it. I'd sooner take it."</p><p>"That's the kind of fool you are, Tim, dumb fool," Schwartz spoke up once more. "I'd stay away from there. If you got so much to pay for things you don't use, maybe you could pay for my cornplow once." He shifted his feet from their right-angled position, drew his forefinger across his nose and limped away; Katto followed, paddling along in her bare feet.</p>
				<p>Tim's determination to make a trip to the railroad filled Danny with delight  now he could go to a distant town. After Schwartzes left, he climbed to the top of his corner tree to sight the cattle, "Next time I climb you," he said, "I'll know what a train looks like."He saw a red speck in the distance  the herd  and ran off to help Sheila bring in the cows. As he bounded over jointed blue stem, with Captain at his heels, he rejoiced that tomorrow he would see what was behind that line where the curving sky met the grass, back of Webber's willows. He would see hills, and trees that grew without being set out and watered, and trains and big houses and towns.</p>
				<p>After supper that evening Tim went to a meeting of<pb n="BLACK SOIL 141"/>settlers who wished to denounce the Herd Law. "People  who have no crops cannot buy barbed wire," they argued, "and cattle must be given food."Danny, uninterested for the time in Herd Law agitation, washed his feet with soap and hot water. Nell washed his face and tawny head. He said his prayers in the kitchen and climbed to the loft. Through the small window he watched a patch of stars and the milky way, and the filigreed tip of a cottonwood stirring very gently, very gently. . . .</p>
				<p>The low room was filled with white light when he awoke. He ran to the window to look for clouds. The yard was full of shadows  trees crisscrossed each other; the moon shone, sharp and clear as crystal. The voices of his parents floated up to him; there was the odor of barley coffee. It was morning! Dressing quickly, he climbed into the kitchen where Tim was eating. Pre occupied, Tim did not notice Danny until the boy spoke: "We're starting awful early, ain't we?"Tim, chewing rapidly, said without looking at him: "Son, you'd better stop at home and help Sheila with them cows. They got into Max's bit of flax yesterday. Sheila won't be able to handle them alone, now once they got a taste of it. Max complained last night  and you couldn't blame him. Funny Sheila didn't tell us about it." He stood up and kicked in his chair.</p>
				<p>Tim was a tall man, straight and slender, with an aquiline nose which gave him a severe look; his kind blue eyes were not noticed by Danny that morning, as he kept them lowered, preoccupied. "Devil's own job 1 have on hand today."Danny slipped out of the house and ran like a<pb n="142 BLACK SOIL"/>wounded deer. Through high weeds, the grove, to the corner tree. He flung his arms around the tree and pressed his face against its bark. If the tree would only enfold him and render him insensible to life. Perhaps it would. . .!</p>
				<p>A catbird shrieked at him. From the prairie came: "Kildee, kildee." Salty tears found their way to the boy's lips. His tension relaxed. Relief had come with weeping.</p>
				<p>He stiffened a little as he heard his name pitched high and sweet: "Danny, Danny." As an answer he gave way to more violent sobbing. After a few moments he, felt himself being loosened from the tree, and he looked into Nell's face. He saw a thin woman with graying curly hair. There were tears in her round blue eyes, but her lips smiled; in her hand she held his gingham jacket and pants.</p>
				<p>"Come on,'' she said, "you must hurry and get changed because I want you to look respectable in the bank. I hope your father won't have to take that harvester."Not until after he was dressed and combed could he find voice. "Can I <emph>go</emph>? Did Pop say I could?" "Yes, I'll manage the cows with Sheila. Queer Max should have saved a field of flax."Danny did not answer her, nor could he assist with the hitching. Like a stranger he climbed to the seat of the wagon. Tim came from around the shed. He had on his best shirt and a greenish felt hat.</p>
				<p>Buck, the big ox with teeth worn off flat as squash seeds, was led to the wagon:  Spec, grazing across the yard, came over slowly and stood in his place on the<pb n="BLACK SOIL 143"/>other side of the tongue. The key was fitted into the bow, the heavy chain wound around the tongue and fastened, and then Tim took his place beside Danny.</p>
				<p>Nell, with Ellen in her arms, stood on the doorstep in the half light as they struck off to Malcur, following the north-south trail. Nell's face--round blue eyes glistening, full red lips smiling--floated along with Danny.</p>
				<p>After they had passed the corner school and Webber's willows, Danny sat up and watched closely for strange sights. There was a haze in the distance which would disappear with the coming of the sun. The sun rose. Now he would see! Sunlight, however, disclosed nothing unusual: wild roses mottling the grass; glossy backed grasshoppers; rosin weeds oozing out gum; curlews uttering prolonged piercing calls; prairie chickens slipping away from the feet of the oxen; black, newly dugout badger mounds.</p>
				<p>Mile after mile was traveled: the sun moved higher and higher. They came no nearer to the line where the sky and prairie met.</p>
				<p>"Here's the big slough now," Tim remarked. Danny's hopes arose. He would see something here? Nothing: humped-up blue heron, muskrats swimming toward conical houses, marsh wrens, yellowheads, wild ducks trailed by young.</p>
				<p>"When will we come to the end of this?  When will we see big trees, Pop, and hills?  I thought we'd see hills." "No, child, not here. The prairie here is this way Over around the Sioux you find some hills and a bit of timber. Look, see the thunder heads?" Tim pointed to a range of billowy clouds above the horizon. "The<pb n="144 BLACK SOIL"/>heat is sweltering. I was just thinking about Aladdin's lamp. Did 1 ever tell you that story?"</p><p>"Oh, I know that story, Pop." "Well, we'll have it again. That lamp would come handy here."  As Tim related the story, Danny forgot the heat of the sun. He was rubbing Aladdin's lamp and was bringing to the prairie all the mysteries of the outside world.</p>
				<p>Tim nudged him and pointed. "There's Malcur now, there before us. How do you like it?" "Why  it's just a few houses  like our house and the corner school." Danny was in tears. "Come, come, me bye. Dry up. I guess the sun was too hot for you."Arriving in the town, Danny discovered that the people were not different from themselves. And Pop was not in awe of the strangers, but joked and shook hands with them. Pop was too easy with the implement dealer. He bought the harvester, and got money in the bank for a payment. That would make Mom feel bad.</p>
				<p>Danny went over to the railroad track. He knelt and felt of the iron and of the wood, and noted how they were fastened together.  Standing, he looked to where the shiny rails reached the eastern horizon, It required a train to carry one beyond this prairie. He closed his fists and raised his chin while his eyes dreamily followed the scintillating rails. "When I get big. . .</p>
				<p>Large drops of rain splashed about him. Thunder mumbled.  He hastened to the wagon. They were loading the harvester.  Having placed two heavy planks across the top of the wagon box, and calling all by<pb n="BLACK SOIL 145"/>standers to give a lift, they hoisted the new piece of machinery on the planks, and it projected over the sides of the wagon. It was a large, awkward harvester with which one had to bind the bundles by hand  a little improvement over the old reaper.</p>
				<p>Rain which had been threatening came on in a great flood. Tim and Danny ate a lunch of crackers, cheese and gingersnaps; bought a few groceries, and waited for an abatement of the storm.  About three o'clock the downpour ceased and the sun appeared. Climbing into the wagon, they set out for home and after a few hours travel drove into a deluge of rain and wind. A piece of old quilt was rolled around the groceries and they were placed directly under the harvester. Evening came early, darkness fell, and the rain continued. Tim could not see to guide the oxen, and they lunged the wheels in and out of the deep ruts. In this jerking, one of the side planks slipped; a corner of the harvester dropped on the wagon box, and a bolt loosened from its fastening grated on the wheel. They tried to lift the corner on to the plank again, but it was impossible  the bolt continued to rasp on the wheel.</p>
				<p>Before entering the big slough, Tim touched up Buck and Spec with the goad. As the oxen drew the heavy  load through the swollen slough, one heard loud breathing, the stamping of powerful legs, and the swishing, swishing of water from the wheels.  It was necessary to lift the groceries to the seat, as water flowed over the box of the wagon. The contact of the displaced bolt and wheel squirted water on Danny's head.</p>
				<p>Suddenly both oxen stopped with a jolt, lowered their heads, and drank in long gulps.  Tim used his goad<pb n="146 BLACK SOIL"/>freely, but they did not move.' Danny looked up at Tim  the darkness hid his face.</p>
				<p>The oxen drank a long time. Then simultaneously they raised their heads  stamped and slipped  stamped and found footing  there was a lunge  the chain sang like a fiddle  the axles creaked  the bolt began its rasping on the wheel  a spray of water hit Danny's head  they were on their way again. The oxen left the road often, and Tim crawled on hands and knee until he found the trail. Then he led the oxen until the wheels fitted into the rut, and they moved on.</p>
				<p>Danny was nodding, and shivering with chill and anxiety, when Tim roused him. "We're near home now. See that light? Sit up and keep your eye peeled. Help me watch for it again."Danny rubbed a soaked sleeve across his eyes and sat up. There was a speck of red in the darkness. It glowed and disappeared. It flashed again like a firefly. Finally it grew larger and stop dodging away. Tim, then, unmindful of ruts, led Buck and Spec toward it.</p>
				<p>As the snorting, creaking outfit stopped before the red square of light, a second larger square darted out to them  Nell stood in the doorway.</p>
				<p>Danny went in first and carried the groceries. As Nell helped him into a dry shirt, he silenced her with his impressions: "I got to see a railroad track. We nearly got stuck in the big slough. .  ." He ate heartily of hot corn mush and milk and was up in bed before Tim came in. The rain beat on the hatcher's wings, but the bed was warm and dry.</p>
				<p>The kitchen door slammed; shoes dropped on  floor. <pb n="BLACK SOIL 147 "/>"Make me a bowl of tea, I'm wet without but dry within."</p><p>"I have it steeping. I see they made you take it." "Yes, I took it. James gave me a loan at sixteen per cent for a first payment." <emph>"Sixteen </emph>per cent! I hope to the good Lord we'll have use for a harvester next year. Here's dry clothes."Ellen was fretful. Nell was humming one of Ben's ' songs. Danny tried to follow the tune with the words within." "You can hear the hungry coyotes  "Next morning, with Johann's help, the harvester was unloaded and stored away in the grove. The young Connors danced about it in great glee; but Nell followed it as though it were a coffin.</p>
				<p>Tim aided Johann in moving Hurd's wooden structure to <emph>his </emph>premises. Johann bought a few boards and put in a tight new door. After reestablishing himself he felt more secure from the invading host, although his patch of window was often darkened. But he could not evade the hoppers. They dared to alight on Emma's tintype, and to deface the love letter which he wrote so painstakingly. They evidently wished to put an end to his sole consolation, his love; but in this they would fail. Emma's letters were manna, better than food or companionship. Her letters were his only comfort.</p>
				<p>One morning, having arisen early to walk fifteen miles to the post-office, Johann saw his neighbor's boy, Herman Schwartz, outside his door awaiting his ap­pearance. Herman was holding a box tightly in his arms and was shivering a little from chill. He raised his round white head to Johann. His small gray eyes, bright<pb n="148 BLACK SOIL"/>and mysterious, shone as though they dwelt on some continual joy anticipated or remembered.</p>
				<p>Johann knew of Herman's passion for drawing on anything available. He had seen him lingering around a cabin in construction as a buzzard hovers about a stray chicken.</p>
				<p>Shyly now Herman advanced toward Johann, shifted his weight from one foot tothe other, tilted his bright-eyed head, and said: "I make you something on yournew door." "All right, Herman, go ahead."And Johann walked toward town carrying a letter to Emma close to his heart, while Herman hopped about and made a drawing on the inside of the new white door.</p>
				<p>That evening when Sheila and Danny, driving in the herd, approached Johann's shanty they saw an immense grasshopper on the open door. As they drew near, its legs and antennae seemed to oscillate. Danny immediately summoned his family, and on arriving they stood in a sort of fascination before the gigantic hopper. Herman had secured paints, and the hopper's brown back was glossy, the eyes red and malevolently glaring.</p>
				<p>"If 'twouldn't offend Herman, I'd like to run the whitewash brush over the door," Nell said, perceiving Johann returning from town. "It gives me the creeps." "Perhaps John won't mind it," Tim answered. "We'll see." Johann arrived, tired and dejected--he had received no letter from Emma.</p>
				<p>"Big grasshopper might eat you up," Kitty Ann<pb n="BLACK SOIL 149"/>addressed him. He didn't smile with the others; in fact, he seemed unimpressed.</p>
				<p>The Connors returned home. Johann went inside and closed the door; thus he swung in the grotesque hopper. He lighted the lamp, and brought into relief the weird companion in the desolate cabin. While con­templating the painting he experienced a great sadness, and with this sadness came pity, a pity not for himself but for Herman. In Germany he would have a chance and might become a great artist; but here . . . "O Gott!"By late summer, the grasshoppers had disappeared. The mellow sun of autumn then revived the prairie. Where there was sufficient moisture, grass grew up anew; and, in these green patches, wild sunflowers and the delicate orange blooms of resin weed formed yellow islands which rushed to greet the eye until frost. The first frost covered the prairie with crystal; white and scintillating in the moonlight, multicolored in the first rays of the sun. Freed tumble weeds, little circus children in full skirts directed by the wind, performed untiringly on the level arena. Winter followed, with snow and unrelenting cold. The landscape was a stretch of white, a white sheet which for days and weeks grew thicker. Again the blue sky changed to a curtain of gray which shut out the world. <pb n="150"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XIX">
				<p>EVERYONE made preparations for cold weather. Houses were banked with sods until they had the appearance of earth houses. Yards were filled with stacks of slough hay. Sheds were re-thatched. All avail­able provisions were stored. And the prairie bowed to winter.</p>
				<p>Johann, as those about him, twisted slough grass for fuel and ground corn in his coffee mill for flour. But he was alone. There were no sounds in his house. Day after day and night after night he heard only the wind sweeping across the prairie. Alone with his thoughts ... he wrote to Emma, conscious of a futility in the repetition of hopes and plans. There were long, monotonous weeks between. the arrivals of mail. At times the silence and vastness of the outside were depressing, and the coyotes' howling around his shanty at night brought wild dreams.</p>
				<p>But there was music on the prairie with the coming of spring--music and hope. The prairie released from gluttonous jaws and death, reveled in its rebirth. Its grasses were soft and green; its people walked sprightly, making every step a dance. The Connor children raced with the swift white clouds and raised their faces to the caressing air. There was much talk of seed grain, of breaking more land, and the gossip following belated newspapers and letters.</p>
				<p>In May Mr. Connor brought Johann a letter in the fine, shaded script which all the neighbors had learned<pb n="BLACK SOIL 151"/>to recognize. He waved the envelope from the wagon and Johann, with quickened pulse, hurried across the prairie.</p>
				<p>He read that Emma had not had a lonely winter. Emil, his second cousin, had felt sorry for her and had taken her about. Johann turned pale as he folded the letter, and there was a childish, hurt look in the face that he raised to his neighbor.</p>
				<p>Tim   listened   sympathetically.   "Well, John, she won't be there next winter," he said with confidence.</p>
				<p>Johann shook his head dubiously. "And Emil, yet, Ernil, such a one." Suddenly he imbibed some of Mr. Connor's enthusiasm; he drew himself up proudly and orated: "This year I put in eighty acres. Look at the blue sky. In autumn, she can come." He answered the letter that evening and walked to the post-office during the night, saving the day for field work.</p>
				<p>Although the settlers worked slavishly and planted every available acre to compensate for former losses, Jo­hann was the most untiring worker in the neighbor­ hood. He was in his fields each morning when chirping birds were yet invisible. While he worked, he planned. When Emil's dark face intruded on the dreams so wist­fully woven, he clutched his plow handles more vigor­ously, driving the share deeply into the sod. Johann had his own plow now and a mortgage on his one-hundred-and-sixty.</p>
				<p>In due time, wheat, oats, and then corn covered the blackness of the cultivated land. People were hopeful but skeptical. They watched the sky at each sudden clouding up, until it was a common sight to see entire families shading their eyes silhouetted against the horizon,<pb n="152 BLACK SOIL"/>each one believing his own eyesight best. Sheila had a piece of colored glass, and often on the prairie she might be seen as a bronze figure peering at the sun, with hair disheveled and the wind whipping a tattered dress around her muscular body. Tim came upon her thus one day and he stood and noted her curiously. The sun which had lavished its gold in her hair had heightened the color of her face. It was the pollen of the flowers that flecked the blackness of her eye. She was part of it all, as natural, as primitive. There was the majesty of the prairie in her figure, and something of its mystery in her eyes. "It's true for Ben, the well-digger. She belongs here. Funny that Nell in her great love for her can't see that she is different!"Aloud he said: "There's not a cloud, Sheila, me gypsy colleen. Don't be ruining your eyes with that glass. Come along, we'll take the cattle in."As they walked along, Sheila was silent as Tim expa­tiated on the looks of the crops. "They were cowards that left a country like this. Blackguards."Johann also prided himself on the appearance of his fields--his, the newly-arrived farmer's--until one day he saw a missing strip of grain, which he attributed to a balk in sowing. Next day there were many missing strips. Connor and Schwartz had done faulty sowing, too, he noted. But what was such a little loss where there was so much land, he thought, dismissing it.</p>
				<p>Tim Connor startled him one morning as he was eating his breakfast, by pounding on his door. "John," he called--there was a tremor in the voice usually so cheerful. "John, what in blazes are we going to do?"<pb n="BLACK SOIL 153"/>  Johann, bewildered, his blonde hair standing upright on his head, hurried outside and raised his eyes in the direction of the sky. "There is nothing," he said. "Come, I'll show you." Tim led the way to the field and knelt beside the so-called "balk." "Look! They have us again!"The ground was fairly alive with small, wingless in­ sects--the larvae of the grasshoppers. "The grass is full of 'em, too," Tim added disconsolately. "I'm sorry to be the one to have such news for you. I saw 'em last night. I went to tell Schwartz, and he was coming to tell me, and we met. It'll be hard on Nell."Realization finally dawned on Johann. <emph>The crop was gone!</emph> He sank to his knees and buried his face in his hands.</p>
				<p>Tim, his hand on the boy's head, looked across at his own home, where a bluish curl of smoke was melting into blue sky. Nell. The children. Another baby coming. The boy before him broken in the first disappointment and bitterness of life.</p>
				<p>"We'll get Emma here yet, John. Don't give up. We mustn't give up. Can't give up. Come over and have a bite of breakfast with us."Johann attempted to speak but could not. "John, it's pretty tough for you, I know; but wouldn't you sooner have Emma there where she has enough to eat, there in luxury, than to have her here with you in misery? If my family was secure I'd think little of the lonesome, John.  I could stand it."Johann shook his head and muttered: "No, no." When Tim returned to his own yard, Nell called<pb n="154 BLACK SOIL"/>from the doorway: "Your breakfast'll be tasteless wait­ing." Still Tim stayed in the yard doing unnecessary things: putting water in a chicken trough, going in and out of the barn, picking up a stray cob. Having decided on a plan, he went to the house, where he was greeted with roars of laughter--Ellen was performing under the tutorage of Danny.</p>
				<p>"Stand like Schwartz, Ellen." Ellen placed two chubby feet at right angles; and all looked at Tim for comment. "Now show us how Schwartz walks." And Ellen thereupon placed two hands behind her, humped her shoulders, and walked with a decided limp.</p>
				<p>Tim could not refrain from smiling. He did not com­ment on the child's accomplishment; but blurted out: "Nell, would you and the childer like to go back East for a spell if I could see some way to get you the money?" "Lord save us, Tim, have you been drinking? Or is it hard up you are for joking this morning?"Contrary to custom, Tim had no repartee. He took a bite of potato and a gulp of coffee, swallowing with difficulty. "What ails you, Tim?" Nell asked, wife-like, eyeing him sharply.</p>
				<p>Tim rose from the table and gave his chair the char­acteristic kick. His eyes were glassy. There was a drop of moisture on the tip of his aquiline nose. "The crop-- the crop's gone again," he said. "Young grasshoppers."After the Connor ensemble had viewed the devastators, it was Nell who assured the tragic young faces raised to her. "God is good, children. We may die here<pb n="BLACK SOIL 155"/>with other complaints but we'll never die with the hunger. Mark my words. I feel it." And to Tim: "We'll sell off the silverware and some other things to that new hotel in Shelbourne. Fool we'd be to take all our money to ride on a train. What'd we do back East? Hang our heads? <emph>No.</emph> I'll never hang my head nor will my chil­dren ever hang their heads because we came to the West. No-siree. There's that old carpetbag--the first mailbag used in Hadley--" she said to the children, "we'll hunt that out, Tim, and you can be striking off toward Shelbourne."Tim was greatly relieved. Thank God for Nell's man­agement and cheer. "I'll walk, Nell, and not be bothered with the oxen. I'm a peddler now, childer. Me present faith, politics, and nationality are in jeopardy. They shall be changed at every door."</p><p>"Tim, such talk. The young ones might think you were in earnest." Nell was silent to Tim's responsive banter. She was selecting the silverware, fondling some pieces and shining others with a corner of her apron. "Look, Tim. The tablespoons we got from Panifers at Amherst."</p><p>"Nice spoons." "I'll never forget the first time I met the Panifers,"  she said reminiscently, polishing the treasures. "I went up to Cattle Show with my uncle, and we met the Panifers. They took us to Dickinsons' with them for tea. Emily was serving it on the veranda of their large house. She is a poet, children. People rarely see her, and she poured tea for your granduncle and me. I wonder, Tim,<pb n="156 BLACK SOIL"/>could I keep one spoon without losing too much on the set?" "Better give the set if you give any."Nell also packed silver received from a Northampton cutlery where Tim had been employed for a time. It was a heavy load. Tim shouldered the bag containing the wedding gifts of other days and struck off.</p>
				<p>Johann, seeing him, was roused from his lethargic despair. He arose and stumbled to his shack--it was dark inside after the outer glare. A streak of light entering over his shoulder fell upon a statue of St. Christo­pher which Emma had given him; he had placed it upon the cornice beside her picture. Emma, with plump face and sleek hair, watched him blandly from her little frame. She had plenty to eat. Did she know? Could she ever understand? If she would only wait! And she had to go with Emil, yet . . . Emil, that wolf.</p>
				<p>His eyes, accustomed to the dimness, saw the sordid ness of his home: unplastered walls, bed, stove, table, few dishes, remnants of food, clothes and implements hanging from the scantlings. A ray of light scintillated on a metal weight of a dangling rope which had been used in moving the shanty. He turned to the doorway. Standing there, the sunlight painted his face with despair that proved the struggle of boyhood against adversity had failed. The light, too, heightened the dun coloring in the tattered jeans and shirt which hung loosely on his thin body. His neglected beard and his blonde, curly hair were at variance with each other. Before him were shan­ties, clods of earth scattered about by a contriving Hand, brave and struggling as the settlers themselves. His destitute<pb n="BLACK SOIL 157"/>neighbors filed in mute procession before his consciousness, but he could not conceive nor did he try to conceive even a temporary remedy for present conditions.</p>
				<p>Meanwhile settlers were meeting and deciding that it was useless to expect any crop at all; they must turn to other ways of earning a living. Many who formerly had been artisans went to Des Moines and other towns in search of employment. Schwartz and his oldest son, Nick, went out of the devastated region to secure farm work. Two of Max's daughters, Tilly and Julie, took advantage of the exodic movement and ran away to Sioux City, where they hoped to find work as hired girls. Tim, having disposed of his silverware to good advantage, sent to Northampton for cutlery and became a veritable peddler.</p>
				<p>Johann, not being skilled in any special line and lack­ing the ingenuity to attempt anything new, spent the days killing the larvae in his fields. Katto made sport of him: "The greenhorn got it in the head." But Nell looked with sympathy at the poor boy.</p>
				<p>"Gosh, John, you're foolish," Danny repeated. "Don't you see? They come right back on again." Unmindful of comments or advice, Johann worked feverishly, his whole body becoming an automaton acting to rid at least part of his fields of the scourge.</p>
				<p>By June he realized that his work was useless. The larvae, having received their wings, began to fly, and his fields were again infested even as the others. Coming and going with favorable winds, the hoppers sought food, richer fields. Migratory swarms, some so large that they eclipsed the sun and revealed the stars, brought terror to   <pb n="158 BLACK SOIL "/>the hearts of all. Nell, alone with the children, grew every day more hopeless and disheartened.</p>
				<p>Tim's homecomings were occasions of great delight. He brought not only food but cheer, sincere or feigned, and news, both pathetic and humorous.</p>
				<p>The devastation was general in northwestern Iowa. Trains found it necessary to carry sand. In locations where the hoppers gathered in great numbers on the rails, grease from their crushed bodies imperiled the safety of the train; the track accordingly had to be liberally sanded before progress could be made.</p>
				<p>Despite the grasshopper plague, politics was active in preparation for the fall election. There was great rivalry for state representative. All realized that someone should be selected who could secure relief measures for his district. Nate Young, "a high-toned lawyer," who was so wealthy that he burned coal for fuel, was opposing Jim Lang, who styled himself "a hay-twister."Tim refrained from telling of the many prairie shacks with the door nailed shut, of the pitiful tales from set­tlers' families, of despair, of lean cattle and hungry children. His own children were petulant and hollow-eyed. He knew that they, like himself craving the greens which they could not procure, were conscious of a constant gnawing hunger.</p>
				<p>But the news which really interested the Connors was that a bounty again had been put on gophers. Led by Danny, they spent the entire day on the prairie. Schwartzes were out, too, and the remaining daughters of Max. They hauled water, made snares, and used all ingenuity possible to secure pelts. Pelts were used as <pb n="BLACK SOIL 159 "/>money and could be handed over the counters for five cents in trade.</p>
				<p>Nell tried to interest Johann. "Why don't you get out and catch some gophers, and earn a little? It will be good pastime for you, anyhow. Go along with the children. Clean up the pests. They will be eating your corn next year," she added, hoping to impress him.</p>
				<p>"No, I plant no more corn for hoppers and gophers," he answered dejectedly. "Don't give up so soon, John. See how long we've been here, and we haven't given up like that," Nell tried to argue. But it was useless. She knew nothing would convince Johann but a good harvest, and that she could only hope for.</p>
				<p>The pendulum of gayety which swung so religiously in the Connor home stopped one summer morning to welcome Connors' sixth child. Tim dispatched Danny for the wife of Max; Sheila disappeared on the prairie; Margaret gathered the younger ones around her in the grove and bade them kneel down. "Pray for Mom," she said. "Pray for Mom."Tearfully and full of wonder they obeyed. Later as they gathered about Mom and the new sister, their eyes were still round, their faces solemn. But Mom smiled! . . . Their bewilderment vanished.</p>
				<p>And as the spirit of happy living took up its regime again, little Alice, "the baby born in grasshopper times," accepted her home on a barren prairie.</p>
				<p>Johann, when he heard the announcement, was sit­ ting on his big stone listlessly watching, with glassy blue<pb n="160 BLACK SOIL"/>eyes, the gluttonous grasshoppers sucking the moisture from the oozy bottom of the wallow, denying the flit­ting blue-winged ephemera footing for their brief day. He started at the sound of a voice calling to him. It was Danny's.</p>
				<p>"I got a new sister. Gosh, she's funny looking. Pop says she's the color of the grasshoppers, but Mom says she's the prettiest baby of all."Johann experienced a peculiar feeling, a relief on hearing the message--the lives of the settlers were affecting him, although he did not realize it. "Wait," he called to Danny. "I go along."When he greeted Mrs. Connor she said nothing, simply smiled at him. In her face he saw something of the beauty and the ruggedness of the Hartz mountains and the calm of a prairie twilight.</p>
				<p>"I go to town," he told her, "and bring the baby a birthday gift." "Never mind, John. Save your money."During Nell's indisposition, the wife of Max cared for the new baby, and Sheila had charge of the house. Herman Schwartz, who at any time might be seen about the prairie, was often at hand to carry water or twist fuel for Sheila.</p>
				<p>One day as Johann left the Connors' house, Herman came from behind the barn, his eyes, losing their irresponsible look, filled with tears. He held his hand over his heart and shifted his weight from one bare foot to the other. "If I get an artist," he said profoundly, "I will paint Sheila."<pb n="BLACK SOIL 161"/>Johann was absently watching the over-fat Plymouth Rocks scratching in vain among the hoppers, with which they were gorged, for a shoot of grass.</p>
				<p>Herman, bareheaded, his light hair bleached white, edged up more closely to Johann, whose old felt hat without a ribbon band hung limply in ripples about his face. The younger boy said falteringly: "Sheila loves you, Johann. I am afraid for it."Johann had noticed Herman's feet; he was always disturbed when he saw those feet, remarkable feet that could combat the thorns of the sloughs without festering, feet free from abrasions. Johann himself, not being able to replace his boots, walked gingerly and not with impunity even in the yard. He made no comment on the announcement so painful to Herman, but walked off toward the big stone to dream his own dreams. But he could not dream--Emma had not written for a long time.</p>
				<p>The wife of Max enjoyed her service in the Connor home. She told Max that she should receive pay, and he allowed her to come, Mary now being able to care for him. A pleasant week was her payment.</p>
				<p>"It's just like a visit. Like when I lived in Dyersville I went to visit my brother." Tilly and Julie had good places, she said, with Yankee families in Sioux City. "But I feel so bad once for Lena. Lou and Lena are promised now. They want to go to Sioux City, too. They can not marry here, for Max will stop it. He don't want that Lou shall leave. Lou is a good hired man, but I want that they shall not go without marriage."    <pb n="162 BLACK SOIL "/>"They mustn't," Nell said, raising herself to her el­ bow. "Alice'll have to be baptized--we'll see Father Leurmann then, and arrange a marriage for later on. I'd like to get to Mass, too, some time before the cold weather. And I believe I could understand the German sermon pretty well now."</p><p>"You can understand," the wife of Max assured her. "You talk good, too. You learn quick." "I don't know what I talk now--a little of every­thing, I guess. But we have a harder time learning your language than you have learning ours."The wife of Max was not convinced. If only she could read the third reader with the ease even of Kitty Ann! She made progress, however, in her reading and writing during her week's stay, for there were lessons daily. Nell and Alice were not difficult patients, and the time passed with regret.</p>
				<p>"I must be getting out now," Nell announced one day. "I'm tired of the bed, and there is so much waiting for me. That John worries me--his girl seems impatient. Sheila must be gotten ready to teach. The county can not open the schools till winter--it has no funds--but we'll have Sheila ready by that time."The wife of Max showed her approval of all Nell said by displaying her square yellow teeth.</p>
				<p>Sheila, leaning against the kitchen window, did not approve. She had no ambition for teaching. Secretly, too, she wanted to run out, off, away on the prairie. Life seemed kinder out there. Flights of migratory hoppers were less portentous, and perplexities were more ephemeral.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 163"/>When Nell, pale, smiling, with lines added to her face, was at her post again, Sheila resumed her work and play with the children. "Take out your History," Nell reminded, "and be looking it over. Your History will require extra study. I won't have time to take you for a week or two."As the Herd Law was disregarded, herding required the taking out and bringing in of the cattle at schedule time. The interest in gopher hunting waned after the unwary had been caught. Only Danny remained per­sistently at it.</p>
				<p>Sheila traveled far with the cattle as they sought out something to crop. Often she sat with her textbook neglected in her lap, her eyes fixed on the line where the sky met the prairie, weaving her future life: a haze of prairie mysteries, soft caressing winds, birds' songs, sun­ sets and afterglows--and with the afterglows came a lover--who would the lover be? Would it be Herman? Would it be Johann? Who <emph>would</emph> the lover be? Did someone answer? "Me-e. Me-e-e." No, it was only the wind in the grass, the clicking of hoppers. Dutifully Sheila would pick up her History and open it at the Revolutionary War.</p>
				<p>At such times, Herman, springing from a tuft of grass where he had been hiding, would present her with some dainty: a small parcel of brown sugar, or a cleanly washed turnip. And as Sheila ate the treat with relish, she felt that the answer she heard in the grass was not Herman's.</p>
				<p>Occasionally at night she would try to recall her imagery of the day, but her dreams then were dreams of <pb n="164 BLACK SOIL "/>a land of plenty--food, clothes, no books to study, homes without arduous duties, and where there was painless childbirth.</p>
				<p>Neighbors met occasionally and discussed conditions; but Johann remained isolated. In vain did Nell try to arouse him, to make him give vent to his feelings, or to confide in her. In spite of her visits he remained aloof.</p>
				<p>He barred his door at night. To him the grasshoppers had become a symbol, an army starving out the settlers. It was war, a war without the satisfaction of bloodshed or slaughter; it was more horrible than the wars of his people which he had come to America to escape. Every ­thing was wrong! Perhaps this Iowa should never have been settled! The plowing up of its original beauty was no doubt a desecration. If that were the case, he was powerless to remedy it; everyone was powerless. Avoid­ing neighbors, he pondered. Bareheaded and barefooted, he walked miles on the prairie as though to some destination; but he sought only a solution, a relief. He re turned each night under a tranquil sky, dazed and heart­ sick, his only companion a sinister shadow stalking along, out of harmony with the contours of the night.</p>
				<p>Nell Connor pleaded incoherently, seeing tragedy in the young man's face. "Go back to Germany--take your little money and go back East. You could teach a language there. Your father would be glad to see you through, John."Johann could not answer; but after his well-meaning neighbor had disappeared, he thought of what she had said.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 165"/> Yet he knew that he would not return to Germany if he had had the money. He was too proud for that. How his father would laugh! No doubt he would be glad to see him. His return would be an overwhelming defeat. He could never yield to it. ... To see Emma? Go back to Emma, defeated? Emma had said that she would come to him when he should send. He had very little money. But he would take some of that money and buy a birth gift for the Connor baby. Nell Connor was a fine lady.</p>
				<p>In Nell Connor's mind there was always a prayer, a hope, a plan to give her children a happy life and every advantage available ; and she was happy now in spite of the "scourge" in anticipating one ambition Sheila was going to be a teacher. Sheila's indifference, she inter­preted as lack of appreciation due to youth. So during the late summer she worked patiently with the girl, questioning and repeating answers until it became mo­notonous to Danny.</p>
				<p>"Gosh, Mom, I know the answers and the questions, too." At which Sheila flashed her dark eyes, and Nell answered with a flourish of her arm: "Clear away out of here and, if it's that smart you are, hear Margaret with her Catechism."Margaret on summer days was not in the mood for Catechism, so Danny climbed his corner tree or roved away with Cap at his heels, in search of gophers. To Danny his life on the prairie was purely existence, a time of physical growth preparatory to real life, which   <pb n="166 BLACK SOIL "/>would be experienced when he could get behind there where the sky cupped down, so grudgingly shutting the world out. Watching the horizon, he was filled with power and was confident in his own capabilities. He closed his fists firmly, holding there in his palm, as Ben had said, his future. While Cap wagged his tail and tried to interpret the seriousness in his master's face, Danny glanced from his calloused feet and tattered clothes back to the curtained sky. His wish was a vow: "When I get big . . ."Margaret, seated in a patch of wild sunflowers, settled disputes and gave advice to the colony of flowers with threats of grasshopper raids if they did not live in harmony.</p>
				<p>Kitty Ann and Robert Emmet wished for many things. "Most of all I want a room in my house just full of white bread," Kitty Ann usually began. "Bread and 'lasses," added Robert Emmet. "Yes, bread just soaked with molasses. And another room with lettuce and candyand other stuff, and when you opened the door out would roll a big, big head of cabbage." And Ellen, squatting beside them, listened approvingly.</p>
				<p>Nell often joined in what she called "building air castles." As they gathered around the door at night, Robert Emmet usually began: "Tell us about when the grass­ hoppers go."When the hoppers seemed to be thinning out, it was <pb n="BLACK SOIL 167 "/>not so presuming to speak of a railroad coming some day, a town, perhaps; but after a migratory swarm piled up three inches deep in the yard, air castles tottered perilously before Nell's swimming eyes.</p>
				<p>"What if they stay all the time, Mom? What if they stay seven years?" "Gosh, we'll all be old then," from Danny. "I'll be twenty years." Nell answered: "They can't stay like that, children.  There's a God over us." <pb n="168"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XX">
				<p>REPORTS that Indians were prowling about reached the Connors. Katto had been "over west" administering to a sick relative when Indians had come begging, and Katto had chased them off with her favorite weapon--the pitchfork.</p>
				<p>Tim verified other rumors, too, and put his family on their guard. The settlers became alarmed. Children were warned about going far from the house; and old fire ­arms which had been used in late years only for hunting were cleaned and equipped.</p>
				<p>"You'd better take the gun, Tim, in the name of God," Nell suggested, truly worried. Indians in the face of everything else! "You have no protection from them at all on the prairie." "What would I be wanting with that heavy musket? If any Indian gets near me I'll sell him one of me knives." "Don't sell them to Indians," Kitty Ann cried in alarm. "They'll come and kill us with 'em."</p><p>"The gun is fixed up and loaded there--there'll be hardly an occasion to use it. These prowling Indians are nothing new. Mostly old squaws and children. Men are busy in Dakota. They are deathly afraid of the soldiers at Fort Dodge. They run from any uniform, so they won't come much farther east. If need be, give them a little something and they'll go on. If you see them coming, get John over to be here with you," Tim advised, treating the matter lightly.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="BLACK SOIL 169"/>"John?" Danny repeated with disgust. "Gosh! Why, he's afraid of the grasshoppers; he'd hide from an Indian." "You be the man of the house, then, Danny, and run them off," Tim said on leaving.</p>
				<p>As Tim traveled from town to town, Nell and the children marched beside him; they were omnipresent. During the day when he was in conversation and con­ tact with people, his family retreated tentatively; but at night they returned familiarly to his side. When over­ taken on the prairie by fog and forced to await the stars or sun, he did not sleep. Instead he gazed into the dense fog, so symbolical of their present outlook. Tim knew that the fog must lift some time, but for the present it was there and he was lost. Night sounds were unduly harsh; night prowlers near--he could hear them swish­ing through the grass.</p>
				<p>He thought of his many debts, the mortgage--grass­ hoppers, the winter, Indians. Nell had such a horror of Indians. In earlier days she had hidden the children when Indians passed. She had awakened him at night: "Listen! Tim, could that be Indians?" And old squaws and young ones were prowling about now to add more misery. Was Nell never to be free from Indians? Would Nell and the children ever have bare necessities? And she had never a complaint for herself, only a worry for the children. They were to have had comforts galore in the West. ...</p>
				<p>As Tim lay on the ground, he watched the fog lift. Stars came out like familiar friends. There was the big dipper, whose handle curved down protectingly in the<pb n="170 BLACK SOIL"/>direction of home. His destination ofttimes lay in the opposite course.</p>
				<p>Tim would stand up, adjust his pack, and continue his way convinced that better days were in store for them. If only they could hold out some way . . .</p>
				<p>One day during Tim's absence Danny sighted horses on the horizon. That evening the Connors learned that Indians, an old woman and a boy, had been at Max's; the boy held the horses while the squaw entered the house and pried around the kitchen for food. Max, on hearing of their arrival, got from his bed with difficulty. At sight of the grizzled man, the squaw ran toward the door, but Max intercepted her and standing on his "bad leg" he braced himself against the door jamb while with his "good leg" he accelerated her retreat.</p>
				<p>As the Connors were eating their dinner of cornbread and milk a few days later, Kitty Ann pointed and yelled: <emph>"Indians!"</emph> They were in the yard. Two old women-- each with a child behind her--riding two small, bony ponies, one of which was hitched to a travois. Several wolf-like dogs accompanied them. The women, dirty, wrinkled, and disheveled, entered the house and grabbed remnants of cornbread from the table. The young Connors secreted themselves under Mom's bed. Sheila stood by calmly, and Danny--where was Danny? One of the squaws spoke to the other, an older woman, and motioned to Nell's iron kettle.</p>
				<p>As the older woman put the kettle in her sack, Nell stepped forward. "No, you can't have that," she said. The old women guffawed; but their expressions of disdain changed to alarm when they noticed two blue trouser legs and a long blue coat with brass trimmings <pb n="BLACK SOIL 171"/>appear on the rungs of the ladder. There were blue coat sleeves, too, but no hands, a freckled face and a blue cap --Danny in a soldier suit of blue. At sight of him the old woman forced the iron kettle from the bag and threw it on the floor. They ran from the house, climbed their horses, and followed by their gaunt dogs galloped away.</p>
				<p>"I tell you, I put the run on 'em," Danny said proudly. He did not join in the following outburst of laughter, nor could he divine just what Nell meant when she said, with tears in her eyes, "Daniel, you are worthy to be the cousin to the captain who wore those clothes."Indian fears became less disturbing as neighbors ex ­changed news of the simple manner in which the squaws were repulsed. Food was brought from secreted store­ rooms, and children resumed their roaming of the prairie.</p>
				<p>One afternoon, as Sheila and Danny were taking the razorback hogs out for a run, a young buck Indian suddenly stood directly in their path. Evidently he had been lying flat in the grass. Tall and lean as a weed, he towered formidably above the children; his chin was pointed, his nose slightly flat. His dress was a compromise between that of a settler and an Indian; jeans and shirt, moccasins, long hair in two braids bound into a turban around his head. Apparently finding delight in his present situation, he smiled, showing teeth white and even. His dark eyes were fixed on Sheila.</p>
				<p>"Soldiers here?" he asked pleasantly. "Soldiers?" Sheila repeated naively, fascinated by the tall, fearless man whose eyes were searching her own. "Soldiers." <pb n="172 BLACK SOIL "/>"Hundreds of 'em," Danny broke in. "Where?" he asked banteringly. "Sleeping, I guess," Danny answered, "after their hard night." He knew that his voice quaked a little and that it was not convincing. He looked toward Sheila for help, but "she just stood there staring like a gawk."The Indian's smile broadened to a grin, and he looked down at the boy curiously. Danny drew his body to its full height, but his frightened look betrayed him. He heard the Indian say: "Wild Goose will not harm pale face."After another penetrating look at Sheila, the Indian asked again: "Soldiers here?"And Sheila, her face transfigured in the first raptures of admiration, could notanswer; but her mouth in some unaccountable way formed the word: "No-o."</p><p>"You live--?" he questioned, pointing toward Connors'. Sheila nodded.</p>
				<p>He stood for a moment with folded arms, appraising her. All at once he walked away and as quickly swung back. Picking a wild sunflower, he held it close to her hair, then shook his head. "You have more of sun than yellow flower. Wild Goose names you Sun-in-the-Hair," he said solemnly, and hurried away.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="173 "/>
				</p>
			</div>
			
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
