<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main Document Type//EN"
"http://infomotions.com/alex/dtd/tei2.dtd">
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>George H. Jessop's Gerald Ffrench's Friends in electronic form</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Originally Prepared by </resp>
					<name>Erica Dillon</name>
				</respStmt>
				<principal>Matthew L. Jockers, Stanford University Department of English</principal>
				<sponsor>
					<name>Stanford University</name>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Stanford, California 94305</addrLine>
					</address>
				</sponsor>
				<funder>
					<name>Stanford Humanities Lab</name>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Stanford University, Stanford, California 94305</addrLine>
					</address>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Distributed by The Irish-American West Project of the Stanford Humanities Lab</name>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Stanford, California 94503</addrLine>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<p>This e-text is freely available for non-commercial purposes</p>
				</availability>
				<date>2003</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>Jessop, George H.  Gerald Ffrench’s Friends.  New York: Longmans, Green and Co.<note type="abstract"/>
						<name type="region">Pacific</name>
						<name type="country">United States</name>
						<name type="city">San Francisco</name>
						<name type="state">California</name>
						<name type="Demographic">Rural</name>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>This text was prepared for use in the Irish-American West project of the Stanford Humanities Lab at Stanford University. The two principal goals of this project are (A) to bring the wealth of western Irish–American literary and historical writing to the Internet in a scholarly project and (B) to counter the existing eastern bias in Irish-American scholarship, by providing an online collection of primary source material and scholarly articles devoted to exploring the works of western Irish-Americans.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p>Suspected errors in the text are marked with a "[sic]" but not corrected.</p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p>Hyphens that occur at the ends of lines have been removed, except in cases where it is possible the author intended the hyphen.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<titlePage>
				<docTitle>
					<titlePart type="main">GERALD FFRENCH'S FRIENDS</titlePart>
				</docTitle>
				<byline>By</byline>
				<docAuthor><name type="first">GEORGE</name><name type="middle">H.</name><name type="last">JESSOP</name></docAuthor>
				<docImprint>
					<publisher>LONGMANS, GREEN, &amp; CO.</publisher>
					<pubPlace>NEW YORK</pubPlace>
					<docDate>1889</docDate>
				</docImprint>
			</titlePage>
			<div type="legal">
				<p>COPYRIGHT, 1889</p>
			</div>
			<div type="other">
				<p>15 EAST SIXTEENTH STREETTROW'SPRINTING AND BOOKBINDING COMPANY,NEW YORK.GERALD FFRENCH'SFRIENDSBY THE SAME AUTHOR:JUDGE LYNCH: A Romance of the California Vineyards.CHECK AND COUNTERCHECK: A Tale of Twenty-five Hours.(With Brander Matthews.)</p>
			</div>
			<div type="preface">
				<p>PREFACE.MR. GERALD FFRENCH'S journalistic career on the Pacific Coast covered a period of five years--from 1873 to 1878.  In this time it was his fortune to meet a great many Irishmen, with several of whom he became more or less intimately associated.  The Irish colony in California is important both in numbers and influence, and Mr. Ffrench's situation offered unusual advantages for a study of the more prominent peculiarities of the members of that colony.  The purpose of these chapters is to depict a few of the most characteristic types of the native Celt of the original stock--as yet unmixed in blood, but modified by new surroundings and a different civilization.  All the incidents related in this book are based on fact, and several of them are mere transcripts from actual life, with no more material alteration than seemed necessary to throw the veil of fiction over the identity of the characters.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="dedication">
				<p>TOBRANDER MATTHEWSIN GRATEFUL ACKNOWLEDGMENT OF MUCH KIND ENCOURAGEMENT AND VALUABLE ADVICE</p>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div type="chapter" n="George H. Jessop's Gerald Ffrench's Friends in electronic form">
				
				
				<p>Just outside the eddy of the crowd, almost in the doorway of the "Evening Mail" office, Gerald Ffrench stood and waited.  He fidgeted and grumbled a little: that was mainly the result of impatience.  He rubbed his eyes frequently, for the sand-dust was penetrating; and two gold coins<pb n="108 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>which he rattled in his hand gave out a musical clinking.  They were both twenty-dollar pieces, for this was Saturday evening and pay-day at the office of the "Evening Mail."Presently a short, thick-set man with a dark beard left the building and joined him.  The new-comer wore a soft felt hat, a rather shabby pea-jacket, and a pair of spectacles.  The rest of his attire was more conventional.  Gerald greeted him with a reproach for his delay, and the two stepped into the street, moving southward with the crowd.</p>
				<p>"It's all very well for you, Jerry," said Ffrench's companion.  "You can feed the cashier with theatre tickets, and get your money ahead of your turn.  I'll bet you were paid in gold too," he added, with some touch of injured feeling in his voice.</p>
				<p>Gerald laughed, and clinked his two coins together.  "Of course," resumed the other.  "Look at me!" and from each pocket he produced a roll of whity-brown paper which looked heavy, and, as every Californian could tell at a glance, contained forty half-dollars.</p>
				<p>"That reminds me--" said Gerald.  "Wait a minute, Doc."  They were passing a money-broker's office, and the younger man went in, leaving the other on the sidewalk.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 109"/>They had always called him "Doctor," this man of the spectacles and shabby pea-jacket, but whether of law, physic, or divinity none of "the boys" at the "Evening Mail" had ever thought to inquire.  His real name was Brown, and he was probably quite as ignorant of the origin of his learned title as was any man of the scores who addressed him by it.  Possibly it grew out of his glasses.</p>
				<p>"Well?" he queried, as Gerald emerged from the broker's office.</p>
				<p>"Dollar and a quarter premium," answered Gerald, who had two of the whity-brown rolls in his hand besides some loose silver.</p>
				<p>"That's it!" said the Doctor, with an indignant sniff.  "Two and a half extra on your week's salary.  Who wouldn't be in the cashier's good graces?"Gerald indulged in a covert smile.  The pair were warm friends and roomed together; but the Doctor had a habit of railing at his lot, and this special complaint recurred every Saturday night.  It always ended in the same way, and Gerald waited for the suggestion that invariably closed the subject.  It soon came.</p>
				<p>"You're going to treat on that, I suppose?"By this time they had crossed Market Street, and were continuing southward along Third.  On an un-<pb n="110 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>pretentious corner stood a grocery, its front embellished with sacks of potatoes and baskets of vegetables, its windows crowded with cans of preserved meats, sardine-boxes, and the like, and its door invitingly open and level with the wooden pavement.  A ruddy eruption of signboards all over the exterior announced that one P. Gerraghty dwelt within, and dealt in groceries of all kinds; also in fine wines and liquors and imported cigars.  Evidently, Mr. Gerraghty was ashamed of neither his name nor his business.</p>
				<p>The two friends passed the long counter, with its flour-scales and its sugar-scales, and its flourishing Saturday trade in dry groceries.  Gerald had returned no answer; the Doctor had made no further remark.  His suggestion was about to be acted upon.</p>
				<p>At the rear of the store proper was a snugly fitted-up bar-room, and over this portion of the establishment Mr. Gerraghty presided in person.  He was a tall man with a dark mustache, and had a slight cast in his eye; not exactly the person you would care to meet on a lonely road at midnight, yet, withal, popular with his neighbors and a political power in his ward.  He was standing at the end of the bar in conversation with a customer.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 111"/>This latter was an old man, low in stature, spare of frame, shabbily dressed, and quite insignificant in appearance.  His hair was of a brick-dust hue, plentifully sprinkled with gray; he wore a straggling beard of the same color, flecked with the same signs of advancing age; he lifted a pair of small, cunning eyes as the new-comers entered.  Evidently he recognized one of them.</p>
				<p>"Ah, Docther, how are ye?" he said, in the broad, strongly accented tones which at once stamp the speaker as born somewhere west of Dublin City and east of Shannon Shore.  The Doctor only nodded; the little man turned to resume his conversation with Gerraghty; but that functionary, seeing the two newspaper men range up to the bar, took his place behind it.</p>
				<p>"What's yours, Doc.?""Cocktail," said that gentleman, laconically.</p>
				<p>"Two cocktails," began Gerald, and then he hesitated.  California hospitality does not wait for an introduction to proffer liquid refreshment.  "What will your friend take?" he added, with a jerk of the head toward the little Irishman, and in a tone loud enough to be overheard by the latter.</p>
				<p>"Thank ye; I'll take a dhrop o' whiskey," he answered, sidling between the two.  A glass was<pb n="112 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>set out, and the "dhrop" he took was a fair sample of his national love for exaggeration.</p>
				<p>The Doctor performed the ceremony of introduction.  "Mr. Ffrench, Mr. Quinn."  Such was the brief formula.</p>
				<p>Mr. Quinn put forth an uninviting hand--not too clean, very thin, with large flat nails, and a net-work of sinews and veins prominent below the big knuckles.</p>
				<p>"I'm glad to mate ye," was Mr. Quinn's remark.</p>
				<p>"You ought to know each other," said the Doctor.  "You're a Westmeath man, aren't you, Mr. Quinn?""That's what I am," he replied.</p>
				<p>"Well, Jerry's from Westmeath too.""What part?"  The clannish instinct which is so strong in most Irishmen was evidently well developed here.</p>
				<p>"Not a great way from Athlone," answered young Ffrench, indifferently.</p>
				<p>"Ay, but where--which side?""Well, I don't exactly know how to explain," said Gerald, laughing good-humoredly.  "You never heard of a small village called Lasson, I suppose?""Heerd of it!" shouted Quinn, apparently in a<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 113"/>state of wild excitement, "heerd of it!  Wasn't I born there--wasn't I--stop, tell me--"  In his agitation he clutched the lapel of Gerald's coat and hung on to it, looking up into his eyes with a strange, beseeching expression.  "Tell me, are ye anything to his honor Mr. Gerald Ffrench, o' the Park?""Only his son, that's all," replied the young man, laughing.</p>
				<p>The effect of these words on the little Irishman was grotesque enough.  Dropping his hand from Gerald's coat he backed out into the centre of the room, and there uncovering, made so deep a bow, that the rim of his soft hat swept the floor.  Gerald looked and felt rather foolish.  He had roughed it too long in America to appreciate this kind of homage, even if it had met him on his father's avenue; and here, in a San Francisco bar-room, with Doc. Brown grinning at his elbow and Gerraghty rattling among the glasses in front of him, it seemed particularly absurd and out of place.  Yet what could he do?  The old man was evidently sincere in his hero worship and enjoyed it thoroughly.</p>
				<p>Would the idiot keep on bowing and scraping forever?  Gerald felt that the situation was becoming intolerable.  The awkward silence must be<pb n="114 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>broken by some more direct means than that suppressed chuckle of the Doctor.</p>
				<p>"I suppose you knew my father, if you came from Lasson?" he said.</p>
				<p>The old man stepped forward.  There was a singular change in his tone, a mixture of deference and exultation, as he replied:"Indade an' I did, sir; knew him well.  He was me landlord--no, that 'u'd be yer grandfather, rest his sowl!  Yer dada was only a boy when I left the ould counthry.  Maybe ye mind me, sir, or me father--ould Luke Quinn, at the cross-roads.  But sure how could ye?  It's forty years since I left thim parts."Gerald intimated that his recollections did not extend so far.</p>
				<p>"An' why would you?  Pat"--this to Mr. Gerraghty, who still stood behind the bar--"let me inthrojuice ye to Mr. Ffrench, o' Ballyvore Park; wan o' the raal ould stock.  I've walked over ivery fut of his property whin I was a gossoon, an' I'd tire Betty if I druv her over the half of it in wan day."Mr. Gerraghty did not seem very deeply impressed, but guessing that another order for drinks was imminent, he assumed a bland smile.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 115"/>"Ye'll take a dhrop o' something wid me?"  And without waiting for a reply the old man went on.  "The best in the house, Pat, for Mr. Ffrench!"Mr. Ffrench found the situation more and more embarrassing.  He attempted to explain that the property in question did not belong to him, but to his brother; but this produced no sort of impression on Quinn.</p>
				<p>"Sure it's all in the family; the raal thing, the grand ould stock!  Sure it's proud an' happy I am to mate ye in America."By this time the glasses had been set out, again, and Doctor Brown, finding that something tangible was about to come of the queer scene, had laid aside his grin for the present and addressed himself to the serious business before him.  But Quinn indignantly pushed the whiskey-bottle aside.</p>
				<p>"Don't ye know no betther nor that, Pat Gerraghty?--and one o' the raal Ffrenches o' Ballyvore foreninst yer bar.  Champagne, yer sowl ye!"And champagne it was, a second bottle succeeding the first, for Mr. Quinn's hospitality was of the absolute sort which takes no denial.  Meanwhile he plied Gerald with adulation and recounted so many evidences of the former grandeur of the family that the young fellow began to feel a becoming<pb n="116 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>sense of his importance, and to realize that the population of California in general, and the editor of the "Evening Mail" in particular, had not treated him with the consideration due to his rank and station.  Even Mr. Gerraghty, under the influence of his own champagne, thawed sufficiently to admit that it was a fine thing to see the aristocracy travelling about the world.</p>
				<p>It needed a peremptory refusal to stop Mr. Quinn at the third bottle.  Doctor Brown, whose eyes were beginning to snap and sparkle behind his spectacles, would have offered no decided opposition; but the Doctor was of very little account in the present company, and twinkled but feebly, with a reflected light, beside the greater luminary.</p>
				<p>Convinced at length that he had touched the limit of Gerald's conviviality, the old man produced a buckskin purse and proceeded to select-from a goodly store of gold coins the sum necessary to defray the cost of the entertainment.  When he had settled he accepted Gerald's handshake, after a faint show of reluctance.</p>
				<p>"Ye'll be here for a few days, I suppose?" he said, clinging to the hand which, now he held it between his own, he seemed in no hurry to let go.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 117"/>"Here?  In San Francisco?  Oh, yes, certainly," answered Gerald, somewhat surprised.</p>
				<p>"That's right, it's worth seein'; an' no one can show you round any betther nor I can.  I've been on the coast since '46, an' I mind whin ivery fut o' these strates round here was nothin' but sand an' sage bushes.  Maybe now," he added, persuasively, "ye've nothin' to do to-morrow.  If ye'll mate me here at eleven, I'll have Betty out.  Sure Sunday's a good day for a dhrive; an' she's an illigant mare to thravel, though av coorse nothin' to what ye're used to.  Ye ought to see the stables at Ballyvore Park, Pat.  Divil such a four in hand iver was seen in Westmeath."  And leaving Mr. Quinn to entertain his host with tales of the vanished glories of Ballyvore, the two friends went out.  As they passed through the grocery they heard the old man's voice:"Gimme a dhrop o' whiskey, Pat.  Champagne's cowld stuff for the stomach."Gerald did not fail to ask the Doctor for such information as he could furnish regarding this new acquaintance.  It was scanty enough.  Brown had met him in court, where Quinn was prosecuting a case against some defaulting tenants.  All Gerald could learn was that the old man owned a great<pb n="118 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>deal of real estate in the southern portion of the city, and was reputed to be very wealthy.</p>
				<p>The following day Ffrench found Quinn at the hour and place appointed, and after a "wee dhrop"--Gerald won golden opinions from the old man by asserting that he preferred whiskey to champagne--Betty made her appearance.  She was a slashing-looking bay mare, and showed plenty of fire and breeding.  Though the buggy was plain and the harness shabby, she would have attracted the attention of the knowing ones in any show or fair.  Gerald, who had all an Irishman's love for a good horse, began to look on Mr. Quinn with more favor and respect.</p>
				<p>The drive was long and pleasant.  Weather never interferes with an excursion in California, where a glance at the calendar, not at the barometer, tells whether rain will fall or sun will shine on a given day.  The old fellow was amusing, too, in his own way.  He was full of anecdotes about the Ireland of forty years ago.  He had left his native land at five and twenty, and had not revisited it since; nor had the possibility of change entered his head.  He was surprised to hear that Gerald's father had died several years before, though he acknowledged, on reflection, that "his honor would<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 119"/>be full oulder nor meself if he'd lived till now."  The young people of the present generation were, of course, strangers to him.  By and by he took up a question that had occasioned Gerald some surprise at their last meeting.</p>
				<p>"An' whin are ye goin' home, sir?""I don't know," said Gerald, vaguely.  "I'm living here, you know.""Here!"  The old man bounded in his seat from sheer amazement, and the spirited mare broke into a wild gallop which it took him some moments to check.  Then he turned and looked at his companion.</p>
				<p>"I live here; I'm working here; I've been at it for three or four years," explained Gerald.</p>
				<p>At first the old man's face expressed boundless astonishment, but gradually a cunning look came into his little eyes.  "Wurruk!" he repeated; "d'ye mind that now?  Let me look at yer hands."  He examined Gerald's soft palms.  "Yes; I thought so.  Sure ye don't expect me to believe the like o' that, sir.""I don't work with pick and shovel," said Gerald, rather indignantly; "but I'm working for my bread just the same, I'm on the staff of the "Evening Mail," like Doctor Brown."<pb n="120 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>"An' what d'ye do that for?" asked Quinn.  The expression of bewilderment on his hatchet face, enhanced by the comic confusion of his wind-blown hair and whiskers, was whimsical.  He looked like a terrier dumfounded.  Gerald laughed.</p>
				<p>"I work because I am obliged to.  Ballyvore belongs to my brother, as I told you last night."The extraordinary fact that this young fellow had to earn his living appeared to be beyond the old man's power to grasp.  "I thought there was money enough in it for six families," he gasped, at length.</p>
				<p>"There's mighty little money in Ireland nowadays," laughed Gerald, lightly; "and not much of that comes the landlord's way.""Get up, Betty," said the old man; and half a mile of the dusty road was passed in silence.  His mind was evidently occupied with reminiscences of the old-time glories of Ballyvore, for by and by disjointed utterances began to escape him.</p>
				<p>"Goold, solid goold!  I've seen it!  Wine an' whiskey, bottles--no, but barrels of it.  Four hundhred acres in the domain, sixteen horses in the stable, silver an' goold plate, an' the estate runnin' over the best o' two baronies."  He started erect in his place with a jerk that set Betty capering again.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 121"/>"But sure ye must have had some of it.  It ain't in raison."This was a sore subject with Gerald.  "I had my share," he said, stiffly, "and--and I spent it.""I'll go bail ye did, like the jintleman ye are!  Get up, ould woman!"  Another long stretch of road lay behind the mare's swift hoofs before Mr. Quinn spoke again, and then it was only to ask some trivial question about the duties of a newspaper man.  Gerald could not help fancying that his revelations about the Ireland of to-day and the knowledge of his present employment had combined to sink him several degrees in the old man's favor.  Not that he cared.  Why should he?  Quinn was a character in his way, and worth studying.  He kept an uncommonly good trotter, too; but he was poor company, manifestly ignorant, and, judging from the place where they had first met and the purpose of the several halts they had made that day, probably a disreputable old drunkard--and certainly no fit companion for Gerald Ffrench.</p>
				<p>Dinner at the Twelve-Mile House and a rattling spin home along the San Bruno Road finished the day.  They drove down Market Street in the gathering twilight and Mr. Quinn pulled up before Gerraghty's store.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="122 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>"Does he live here, I wonder?" thought Gerald, as he alighted.  "It looks like it."  Then, resisting all the old man's entreaties to step inside and "thry something to lay the dust," he set out for the California Theatre, for even Sunday night has its claims on the time of a San Francisco dramatic critic.</p>
				<p>Old Quinn grasped his hand warmly at parting.  He had quite conquered his diffidence in that respect.  "Look in an' see me whenever ye do be passin'," he said, "I do be here the most o' the time; an' any day ye feel like havin' another dhrive behind Betty, why, only say the wurrud.  It isn't yer father's son that should be ridin' in thim blaggard street-cars."THE "Glorious Fourth" came and went, marked by unwonted splendor and noise all over the Union, and underscored with black in the private annals of Doctor Brown, who was called upon to surrender his desk at the "Evening Mail."  That gentleman's turn for conviviality and his talent for chronic faultfinding had combined to embroil him with the managing editor, and he had received an intimation that his resignation would be in order.  Brown had never saved a cent in his life, and Gerald realized<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 123"/>with some misgivings that his forty dollars a week would for the present be called upon to support two instead of one.  He was walking down Third Street on the following evening, in a somewhat despondent frame of mind, when he was loudly called by name from the door of Mr. Gerraghty's grocery.</p>
				<p>Old Quinn had evidently been celebrating the birthday of his adopted country after his own fashion, and he had not done celebrating yet.  His small eyes were ablaze with excitement, his shirt was rumpled, his attire otherwise in disorder, and his "Misther Ffrench, Misther Ffrench!" sounded hoarse and strident.</p>
				<p>Gerald would willingly have passed on, but this was not to be.  The little man haled him into the group that surrounded the door of the grocery, and proceeded to introduce him by name to every member of the party, with a running commentary on the splendors of Ballyvore and an enthusiastic indorsement of the young fellow himself as "wan o' the raal ould stock."This was a disagreeable experience.  The old man was undeniably the worse for liquor; most likely, as he had abundant leisure and more money than he knew what to do with, drunkenness was his normal condition.  Gerald extricated himself<pb n="124 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>with some difficulty from these maudlin attentions, and continued on his way.  Clearly Mr. Quinn was not an acquaintance to be cultivated.</p>
				<p>Yet it was difficult to avoid meeting him.  Gerald lived in Howard Street, and naturally had to pass Gerraghty's door at least twice a day, and Gerraghty's was evidently the old man's headquarters.  Sometimes he would be in the saloon, sometimes in front of the grocery; but, as he had said himself, he was there "most o' the time."  In the course of a few weeks he had fully digested the idea of Mr. Ffrench's servile position--for so he evidently considered it--and set himself with a faithful persistence that was almost touching to lighten its burdens by every means in his power.  Unlimited liquor appeared to the old fellow the simplest and most direct alleviation; and as Gerald could not always fence successfully with such persistent hospitality he soon found himself drinking more than was good for him.  Loans of money were frequently proffered, in sums ranging from five to one hundred dollars, but these Gerald invariably declined.  Finally one day--it was the 1st of August, and an appointment had been made in which Betty was involved--the old man's liberality took a flight as magnificent as it<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 125"/>was unexpected.  Gerald found him, as had been arranged, in Gerraghty's saloon.  He was poring over a morning paper, but looked up as the young fellow entered.  "I was gettin' the news," he said, with an odd expression, half of doubt, half of bravado, the significance of which Gerald did not at the moment understand.</p>
				<p>"Have you?  There's not much in the papers to-day," he answered.</p>
				<p>"There is not.  You've read them, I suppose?" inquired Quinn.</p>
				<p>"Yes, I looked them over at breakfast.""An' now what sthruck ye in them?  What was the biggest bit of news ye could find?""Nothing," said Gerald, laughing.  "Did you find any?""Divil a wurrud," answered Quinn with a sigh.</p>
				<p>This kind of colloquy was not unusual.  The old man seemed to be an attentive reader of the papers, and he rarely met Gerald without asking him his opinion on the news of the day.</p>
				<p>"It seems to me you never find much news, Mr. Quinn," remarked Ffrench.</p>
				<p>"What's the raison I don't?  Sorra much has happened this twenty years that I can't tell ye."  The old man spoke rather warmly and seemed<pb n="126 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>hurt and indignant.  After a few minutes he went out to fetch the buggy, and Gerald turned to Gerraghty, who occupied his usual place behind the bar.</p>
				<p>"What's the matter with Mr. Quinn?  He seems out of sorts this morning."Gerraghty had a friendly feeling for Gerald, in whom he recognized a source of profit only to be gauged by the young man's capacity for liquids.  Before answering he peeped round the bar to assure himself that Quinn was out of ear-shot.</p>
				<p>"The ould fellow can't read," he said with a grin.</p>
				<p>"Can't read!" repeated Gerald, profoundly astonished.  "Why, I see him reading the paper every day.""Ye see him houlding it; but divil a line of it can he spell.  He can't neither read nor write; an' when he has business at the Hibernia Bank he has it fixed so that they let him in ten minutes before the doors are opened, so that no one won't see him make his mark.  Oh! he's quare.""But what does he take the papers for?" asked Gerald, to whom this revelation was almost incredible.</p>
				<p>"So as to fool you an' others like you.  Oh, he's cute; but ivery wan who knows him well sees how<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 127"/>it is.  No one dar' hint as much to him though.  Whisht! here he's comin'."  And Quinn entered.</p>
				<p>His ill humor had already evaporated and they started in good spirits.  This time their course lay among the small residence streets which abound in that neighborhood.  It was the first of the month, and the old man was out collecting his rents.  He visited a number of the little frame houses which are crowded together in that populous quarter and returned from each with a double handful of silver.  A large bag which lay under the seat of the wagon grew rapidly in bulk and weight as the day advanced.  It was plain that the old fellow's wealth was no fable.</p>
				<p>"How much are you worth, Mr. Quinn?" asked Gerald, in a moment of pardonable curiosity.</p>
				<p>The old fellow leered at him with a cunning expression.  "I'll tell ye," he said, " for maybe ye'll need to know wan o' these days.  A little over a quarter of a million."  Gerald gasped.  He knew Quinn was well to do, but had never imagined that his means approached such a figure.  The other noted his astonishment with evident satisfaction.</p>
				<p>"I suppose you must have struck it rich in the diggings in the old days?" Ffrench remarked by way of saying something.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="128 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>"I never struck a pick in the ground in Californy, an' I w'u'dn't know the color if I seen it," said Quinn.  Then he closed his left eye, and laid his head on one side like a disreputable but preternaturally wise old magpie.  "What's the use o' goold?  Ye can spind that, but ye can't spind land.  When I come here all this, was sand-hills.  I bought it by the acre, and I've sowld a good share of it by the fut.  There's nothin' like land," he ejaculated with a fervor that was almost pious in its intensity.  "See here, Masther Gerald!  Is yer brother married?""No," answered Gerald, not a little surprised by the sudden question.  "Why?""It's a sin an' a shame, sir, that you should be wastin' yer life here among a lot of rayporthers not fit to black the boots o' the likes o' ye.  It's home ye ought to be, an' livin' like a jintleman.""On what would I live like a gentleman if I were at home, I'd like to know?" inquired Gerald, laughing.</p>
				<p>"Och, if that's all, yer honor, ye can have five thousand dollars to-morrow--ten, if five isn't enough; an' more whin that's done.  Go home, yer sowl ye, an' go into Parleymint--ye've the brains to do it; an' if it's only money's wantin', come to ould Luke Quinn."<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 129"/>There was no mistaking this offer.  It was made in sober earnest, and the old man's sincerity was unquestionable.  It was difficult for Gerald to make him understand the impossibility of such a scheme, but he did comprehend that his generous proposal was not accepted; and the refusal seemed to cut him to the heart.  Despite all the efforts of the younger man, the drive was finished in silence.</p>
				<p>That day Gerald wrote to his sister and asked her to find out what she could about a family named Quinn, who had lived near Lasson in his grandfather's time, and had been tenants on the estate.  He also attempted a little missionary work with the old man, and tried to get him away from Gerraghty's saloon and its unfailing rounds of drinks.  Old Quinn's health was far from robust, and the young man could not help noticing the growing effects of this incessant dissipation.  His success was not conspicuous; but he fancied he was of some service, and the old man took the interference in good part.  This and the remembrance of Quinn's hearty, disinterested generosity combined to raise him considerably in Mr. Ffrench's estimation.</p>
				<p>It was not till near the end of August that Doctor Brown heard of a fresh opening for his talents.  He was offered a place on the "Sacramento Union,"<pb n="130 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>and he was to start at once.  But here a difficulty presented itself.  It would require about twenty dollars to settle up various little matters and pay the fare.  Gerald, who had been supporting both himself and his friend for nearly two months, had no cash on hand and none to hope for till salary day.  The Doctor had made an ineffectual attempt to borrow, and now it seemed as if the poor fellow must lose a good chance for want of a paltry twenty dollars.  Gerald determined to put his dignity by and ask Quinn for the money.</p>
				<p>He found the old man in Gerraghty's and prompt to accommodate him.  "Twinty, is it?" he said--"no, but fifty.  Come wid me, an' I'll get it for ye at wanst."  This rather surprised Gerald, who knew that Quinn habitually carried large sums about him.  However he accompanied the old fellow, assuming that he would take him to the Hibernia Bank, where he kept an account.  Not so, however.  They crossed Third Street, and proceeded along one of the narrow thoroughfares in which Mr. Quinn's house property lay.</p>
				<p>He was in high good humor.  The question of the loan had brought up the subject of money, always a favorite topic with a man who has plenty.  He narrated how many appeals were almost daily<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 131"/>made on his purse, and explained with a crafty leer how he avoided them.</p>
				<p>"Only yisterday," he said, "that fellow wid the specs--the Docther, ye call him--wanted to sthrike me for twinty.  D'ye think he got it?  Not much.  I've no money for the likes o' him."  Gerald, who had several times been on the point of explaining that the loan he solicited was for the Doctor's use, congratulated himself that he had not spoken.</p>
				<p>"Not but what he has a great rispict for me," pursued Quinn.  "They do all have the hoight o' rispict for me round these parts.  When I towld the Docther that money was tight an' I c'u'dn't raise the like, sez he, 'Quinn, ye're an ould misanthrope,' sez he.  I mind the wurrud well, for I med him say it over two or three times;" and the old fellow grinned in his appreciation of this peculiar compliment.</p>
				<p>By this time they were in Jessie Street.</p>
				<p>"Be aisy now," said Quinn, "I'll bring ye the money in two shakes of a mare's tail."  And he ran nimbly up the steps of one of the frame houses which owned him as lord.</p>
				<p>He returned presently, evidently greatly chagrined and discomfited.  "W'u'd ye belave it," he exclaimed angrily; "here it is within two days o' the first o'<pb n="132 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>the month, an' the dhirty mane spalpeen won't gimme a thrifle of a few dollars in advance o' the rint that'll be due the day afther to-morrow."Gerald hastened to assure him that if he had not the money by him it was no manner of consequence, that he had no intention of occasioning his kind friend any inconvenience, and much more in the same strain, but the old man cut him short by running up the steps of another house.  The same result followed; and it was not till he had failed in four several attempts to borrow the amount among his tenants that he drew the faded buckskin purse from his pocket, and, pouring a mingled mass of gold and silver into his shaking hand, entreated Gerald to take whatever he required.  Gerald selected a twenty-dollar piece, thanked him, and withdrew, much marvelling at the old man's business methods.</p>
				<p>THIS oddly assorted friendship continued without interruption throughout the winter of 1876.  A quarrel had nearly arisen when Gerald after a few weeks brought back the twenty dollars and attempted to return it.  The old man seemed so<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 133"/>sincerely hurt and grieved that Gerald relented and pocketed his pride and his gold-piece together, preferring to remain under an obligation which, after all, he could not cancel, rather than wound Quinn in what was seemingly the only sensitive point of his nature.  Emboldened by this triumph, the old man recurred to his favorite scheme of "making a jintleman o' Masther Gerald;" but here the young man was immovable, and the other discontinued his persuasions with a sigh that "the likes o' him should have to wurruk."In due course Gerald received an answer from his sister.  After the usual quota of home gossip and news, he came upon this paragraph:"There are no Quinns on the place now.  There was a family on the Athlone side of Lasson, but they were cleared out in grandpapa's time.  Mr. Brooke remembers them well, though, and speaks of old Luke Quinn as the worst tenant, and most inveterate poacher on the property.  The son was a worse scamp than the father, and went to America.  Mr. Brooke says he must be quite an elderly man if he hasn't been hanged.  The old man gave no end of trouble to grandpapa, who was finally compelled to take up the farm.  Mr. Brooke thinks that old Quinn was transported afterward, but he isn't sure.  What on earth do you want with all<pb n="134 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>this queer Old World history?  Are you going to write a book?"And so the letter branched out to other topics.</p>
				<p>Undoubtedly the wealthy Mr. Quinn of San Francisco was no other than the scapegrace son of a worthless father, and the respectable agent of Ballyvore seemed to think that if he was still alive it was only because the hangman had neglected his opportunities.  "It's a strange world," reflected Gerald; "but whatever he may have been before I was born, he has loyalty to the old name now, and a soft spot in his heart for the old country."Mr. Ffrench was surprised to find that he had learned to like the old man before the last clouds had rolled away from the spring of 1877.  The mixture of shrewdness and simplicity; the transparent pretence of education, at which he had long ceased to smile; above all, the evident pride and delight which Quinn took in his society--all appealed strongly to the warmer side of his nature.  The old man still introduced him to his friends as "wan o' the raal ould stock," and prosed away in his cups about the splendors of Ballyvore; but the cadet of that ancient house was growing accustomed to this.  The two drove together every Sunday, saw each other at least once every day, and patronized Ger-<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 135"/>raghty at frequent intervals, to the entire satisfaction of that enterprising grocer.</p>
				<p>One day--it was early in June--Gerald, on his way home, missed the familiar figure from the door of the grocery.  He gave the matter little thought at the moment, but when another day passed without his seeing Quinn, he stepped into the store to inquire.</p>
				<p>Poor old man!  He had met with an accident on the road the previous day--had been thrown from his buggy and picked up insensible.  Gerraghty did not know whether he had a "load" at the time, but opined that he had.  Anyhow, he was in a bad way.  The saloon-keeper spoke feelingly, as one who deplored the possible loss of his best customer, and Gerald became seriously uneasy.  He would go and see Quinn at once.  Gerraghty furnished the address, and advised him to carry a bottle of whiskey to the patient; but this he declined.</p>
				<p>As he walked toward Mission Street he remembered with some surprise that he had never yet visited Quinn in his own home.  He did not even know whether the old fellow was married or single, though negative evidence naturally inclined him to the latter view.  They had always met in the street or in Gerraghty's store, which was odd considering<pb n="136 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>how closely the bonds of their strange intimacy had been drawn in the past year.  But here was the number, only a few doors up Mission Street, and his hand was on the bell.  It was answered by a civil-spoken Irishwoman, who, in reply to his inquiry, showed him into a room on the ground floor.  As he entered, a Mr. Conley, a lawyer with whom he had some slight acquaintance, passed out.  Gerald was surprised at the warmth with which this gentleman shook his hand, and he fancied he caught the words "lucky fellow" in the whispered greeting; but he had no time to speculate on their application.  Poor old Quinn lay on the bed--a cheap, uncomfortable-looking bed, quite in character with the ill-furnished, cheerless room.  He looked thin and shrunken under the coverlet, and very weak.  A stranger, evidently a physician, turned from the bedside as Gerald entered, but the old man beckoned him back and feebly extended his hand toward his visitor.</p>
				<p>"Docther," said he in a faint, hoarse whisper, "I want to inthrojuice ye.  This is me fri'nd,"--there was an emphasis of indescribable pride about this word, and he repeated it--"me fr'ind Mr. Ffrench o' Ballyvore Park.  Wan o' the raal ould stock, sir, an' the grandest in the barony."<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 137"/>"Oh, hush, hush, Quinn!" cried Gerald, deeply shocked.  The old man's adulation seemed to him ghastly and unnatural at such a time.  The doctor acknowledged the introduction by a curt nod, and taking up his hat and gloves moved toward the door.  "You mustn't try to talk much, Mr. Quinn; I'll look in again in a couple of hours," he said, and went out.</p>
				<p>"How did this happen?" asked Gerald, drawing a chair to the bedside and taking the thin old hand in his own; "and why didn't you send to let me know?""It was a poor place to bring you to, Masther Gerald, an' I didn't like; but sure I'm glad to see you now you are in it.""But why should a man of your means live like this?"  The question leaped to Gerald's lips, but remained unspoken.  As he looked he realized that it mattered little where the old man should live--or die--now.</p>
				<p>"An illigant place entirely," muttered old Quinn, "and he come to see me!  Ah, Masther Gerald, it's aisy seein' you're wan o' the raal ould stock."He was silent a moment, and then began again.  "Arrah, bad cess to ye, Betty; wasn't trottin' good enough for ye, but ye must turn to an' kick the<pb n="138 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>wagon over?"  Another pause, "Masther Gerald, Masther Gerald, avick!""What is it, Quinn?""I had Counsellor Conley here just now doin' some writin' for me.  I write an illigant hand, but I'm wake wid this thrubble.""I saw him, Quinn.  What about it?""We didn't get to finish.  Rache me it there, av ye plaze.  See it beyant?"Gerald found a large legal-looking sheet of paper lying on the table among cigar-butts and broken glasses.  He handed it to the old man.</p>
				<p>"Yer honor can finish it for me, as well as another.  All it wants is me name.  Write it down at the ind."The first line of the document, boldly engrossed in large letters, caught Gerald's eye.  He read it at a glance: "Last will and testament of Luke Quinn."  He stared aghast.</p>
				<p>"Sign your name?" said the young man.  "I can't do that.""An' why not, whin I give ye l'ave?  Sure who'll be a haporth the wiser?""I can write it, but we must have witnesses; and you must touch the pen and say over some form, which I have forgotten."<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 139"/>"Och, what's the use of all that botheration?  The lawyer would ha' finished it for me, only I was wake and c'u'dn't go on.  Whisper, Masther Gerald, avick.  Write 'Luke Quinn' at the bottom o' that, an' it'll be the betther for ye.""But indeed, Quinn, it would be impossible," said Gerald, sorely put out by the old man's helpless pleading.  "It would mean no more than if it had never been written, and would only get me into trouble.""Who's to know?" urged Quinn.  "Whisper till I tell ye--no one will misthrust but I wrote it meself; no one knows me hand, an' me writin's the very moral o' yer own anyway: ye c'u'd make twins o' thim."Gerald could hardly repress a smile.  The old man continued to urge and entreat, but, as may be imagined, without result.  Finally he said: "Put it back thin; I'll l'ave it till to-morrow.  Maybe I'll be well enough to do it meself by that time.  I won't kape ye here any longer, Masther Gerald.  I think I c'u'd doze a bit."Gerald withdrew, promising to look in the first thing in the morning; and, having ascertained from the woman of the house that Mr. Quinn was in good hands, returned home.  He could not help<pb n="140 An Old Man from the Old Country."/>laughing at the old man's attempt to sign his will by proxy, but he was uneasy and anxious nevertheless.</p>
				<p>The same evening Mr. Conley called upon him and told him that his old friend had died in his sleep, probably about an hour after Gerald had left the bedside.  "And do you know," added the lawyer, "you came as near inheriting three hundred thousand dollars as a man can come and not get it?""How was that?" asked Gerald, listlessly.  The news of Quinn's death, though not unexpected, had come upon him with the suddenness of a shock, and affected him deeply.</p>
				<p>"I'll tell you," said Mr. Conley.  " It must be six months ago that Quinn instructed me to draw up his will.  He left you everything, but from that day to this he never would sign it.""Why not?" asked Gerald.  He readily guessed the cause, but he was determined to keep the old man's secret.</p>
				<p>"Sometimes one reason, sometimes another.  When he met with this accident he sent for me post-haste to bring the will.  Did he sign?  Not a bit of it.  He was too weak, he said.  I offered to call in witnesses and fill in the signatures in his<pb n="An Old Man from the Old Country. 141"/>presence in the usual way.  He became bitterly indignant.  'What, make me mark!' he said, 'I never did that in me life, and I won't begin now.'  I was just leaving when you came in.""Where will his money go?" asked Gerald.</p>
				<p>"Oh, to his relatives in Ireland, I suppose," said the lawyer.  "That kind of man always has plenty."The following Sunday there was a big funeral--an Irish funeral, with scores of carriages and unlimited whiskey.  Gerald Ffrench attended, and so did Mr. Gerraghty--Doctor Brown was in Sacramento.  Gerald's eyes were a little misty as the earth fell on the coffin--a very handsome coffin with a silver plate.  The old man had grown on him wonderfully, and he missed him more than he could have believed possible.</p>
				<p>The contest over Luke Quinn's property is going on still in the California courts.  Every Quinn in the State is represented by counsel, but flowers are not often seen on the old man's grave.  It is only occasionally that Gerald Ffrench's Sunday stroll takes him in the direction of Lone Mountain.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="142"/>
					<pb n="143"/>
					<pb n="144"/>
					<pb n="145"/>"NOT another step, Dr. Lynn," said Gerald Ffrench, stopping the old gentleman at the gate in the hedge which divided the Rectory lawn from the churchyard, "I won't have you coming any farther.""My dear boy," returned the rector with a kindly smile, "I am still in my own domain and I won't be dictated to.  Besides, the little walk will do me good.  I shall see you at least as far as the lower road."The gate swung behind them and they threaded the narrow path among the grave-stones.  It was an obscure little country burying-ground and very ancient.  The grass sprang luxuriant from the moldering dust of three hundred years, for so long at least had these few acres been consecrated to their present purpose.  Gerald stopped once or twice to decipher, as far as the failing light of the January<pb n="146 The Last of the Costellos."/>afternoon would permit, the inscription on a stone near the path.</p>
				<p>"You won't find many new-comers," observed the rector.  "A few of course: the years must bring their changes, and you have been away--let me see---""Six years," said Gerald, with a half sigh, as he recalled the hopes that had withered, the ambitions that had faded, the pleasures that had vanished, and the residuum that had lingered from six years of active, breathing life.  And yet he was only twenty-seven.</p>
				<p>At twenty-one he had left the home-nest, behind those trees which broke the horizon line in the north.  His wanderings had led him far afield.  He had fallen into the whirring machinery of life, and the machinery had jarred and hurt him.  Now he had come home for a few weeks of rest and pleasure.  He knew it could not be for long, for he had, with infinite pains and labor, carved for himself a little niche in the world's great gallery, and he could not afford to leave it empty.  In other words, he was a young journalist, holding a good position on a San Francisco daily paper, and he was enjoying what was left of a three months' vacation in Ireland.  And three weeks of that scanty remainder<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 147"/>would be consumed in travelling back to his duty.  All these reflections entered into the young man's sigh and gave it a touch of pathos.</p>
				<p>"Well, I won't go any farther," said Dr. Lynn, halting at the boundary wall, spanned by a ladder-like flight of wooden steps which connected the churchyard with the little by-road.  "I'll say good evening, Gerald, and assure you I appreciate your kindness in coming over to spend a long day with a stupid old man.""I would not hear thine enemy say that," quoted Gerald with a light laugh.  "I hope to spend many another day as pleasantly before I turn my back on old Ireland."  He ran up the steps as he spoke, and stood on the top of the wall looking back to wave a last greeting before he descended.  Suddenly he stopped.</p>
				<p>"What's that?" he asked, pointing down among the graves.</p>
				<p>The rector turned, but the tall grass and taller nettles concealed from him the object, whatever it might be, which Gerald had seen from his temporary elevation.</p>
				<p>"It looks like a coffin;" and coming rapidly down again the young man pushed his way through the rank growth.  The clergyman followed.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="148 The Last of the Costellos."/>In a little depression between the mounds of two graves lay a plain coffin of stained wood.  It was closed, and an attempt to move it showed that it was not empty.  A nearer inspection revealed that the lid was not screwed down in the usual manner, but hastily fastened with nails.  Dr. Lynn and Gerald looked at each other.  There was something mysterious in the presence of this coffin above ground.</p>
				<p>"Has there been a funeral--interrupted--or anything of that kind?" asked Gerald.</p>
				<p>"Nothing of the sort.  I wish Bolan were here.  He might have something to say about it."Bolan was the sexton.  Gerald knew where he lived--within a stone's throw of the spot--and volunteered to fetch him.  Dr. Lynn looked all over the sinister black box, but no plate or mark of any kind rewarded his search.  Meanwhile young Ffrench sped along the lower road to Bolan's house.</p>
				<p>The sexton was in, just preparing for a smoke in company with the local blacksmith, when Gerald entered with the news of the uncanny discovery in the churchyard.  Eleven young Bolans, grouped around the turf-fire, drank in the intelligence and instantly scattered to spread the report in eleven<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 149"/>different directions.  A tale confided to the Bolan household was confided to rumor.</p>
				<p>Blacksmith and sexton rose together and accompanied Gerald to the spot where he had left Dr. Lynn, but Dr. Lynn was no longer alone.  The rector had heard steps in the road; it was a constabulary patrol on its round, and the old gentleman's hail had brought two policemen to his side.  There they stood, profoundly puzzled and completely in the dark, except for the light given by their bull's-eye lanterns.  But the glare of these lanterns had been seen from the road.  Some people shunned them, as lights in a graveyard should always be shunned; but others, hearing voices, had suffered their curiosity to overcome their misgivings, and were gathered around, silent, open-mouthed, wondering.  So stood the group when Gerald and his companions joined it.</p>
				<p>In reply to general questions Bolan was dumb.  In reply to particular interrogations, he did not hesitate to admit that he was "clane bate."  Gerald, seeing that no one had ventured to touch the grim casket, hinted that it would be well to open it.  The crowd, which had been mostly collected by the young Bolans, not finding such a feast of horror as the highly-colored narratives of the sex-<pb n="150 The Last of the Costellos."/>ton's family had led it to expect, appeared to favor the suggestion.  There was a dubious murmur and a glance at the constables as the visible representatives of the powers that be.  The officers tightened their belts and seemed undecided, and Dr. Lynn took the lead with a clear, distinct order.  "Take off the lid, Andy," he said.</p>
				<p>"An' why not?  Isn't his riverince a magisthrate?  Go in, Andy, yer sowl ye, and off wid it."  Thus the crowd.</p>
				<p>So encouraged, the blacksmith stepped forward.  Without much difficulty he burst the insecure fastenings and removed the lid.  The constables turned their bull's eyes on the inside of the coffin.  The crowd pressed forward, Gerald in the front rank.</p>
				<p>There was an occupant.  A young girl, white with the pallor of death, lay under the light of the lanterns.  The face was as placid and composed as if she had just fallen asleep, and it was a handsome face, with regular features and strongly defined black eyebrows.  The form was fully dressed, and the clothes seemed expensive and fashionable.  A few raven locks straggled out from beneath a lace scarf, which was tied around the head.  The hands crossed beneath the breast were neatly gloved.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 151"/>There she lay, a mystery, for not one of those present had ever seen her face before.</p>
				<p>Murmurs of wonder and sympathy went up from the by-standers.  "Ah, the poor thing!"  "Isn't she purty!"  "So young, too!"  "Musha, it's the beautiful angel she is be this time.""Does anyone know her?" asked the rector; and then, as there was no reply, he put a question that was destined for many a day to agitate the neighborhood of Drim and ring through the length and breadth of Ireland: "How did she come here?"The investigation made at the moment was unsatisfactory.  The grass on all sides had by this time been trampled and pressed down by the curious throng, and such tracks as the coffin-bearers had made were completely obliterated.  It was clearly a case for investigation by the coroner, and when that official arrived and took charge, the crowd slowly dispersed.</p>
				<p>Gerald walked home immersed in thought.  He was late for dinner at Ballyvore Park, and his brother and sister plied him with questions when he explained the cause of his delay.  But he could not hazard even a conjecture in the way of explanation.  A dead girl had been found, and no one,<pb n="152 The Last of the Costellos."/>neither Dr. Lynn nor any one else, could tell who she was or whence she came.</p>
				<p>The inquest furnished no new light.  Medical testimony swept away the theory of murder, for death was proved to have resulted from organic disease of the heart.  The coffin might have been found at any time within thirty-six hours, for it could not be shown that anyone had crossed the churchyard path since the morning previous; indeed, a dozen might have passed that way without seeing that which Gerald had only discovered through the accident of having looked back at the moment that he mounted the wall.  Still, it did not seem likely that an object of such size could have lain long unnoticed, and the doctors were of opinion that the woman had been alive twenty-four hours before her body was found.</p>
				<p>In the absence of suspicion of any crime--and the medical examination furnished none--interest centred in the question of identity; and this was sufficiently puzzling.</p>
				<p>The story got into the newspapers--into the Dublin papers--afterward into the great London journals, and was widely discussed under the title of "The Drim Churchyard Mystery," but all this publicity and a thorough investigation of the few<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 153"/>available clues led to nothing--no one was missing; widely-distributed photographs of the deceased found no recognition, and the quest was finally abandoned, even in the immediate neighborhood.  The unknown slept beneath the very sod on which they had found her.</p>
				<p>Gerald Ffrench, who, like most good journalists, had a strongly-developed detective instinct, alone kept the mystery in mind, and worked at it incessantly.  He devoted the few remaining weeks of his stay in Ireland to a patient, systematic inquiry, starting from the clews that had developed at the inquest.  He had provided himself with a good photograph of the dead girl, and a minute, carefully-written description of her apparel, from the lace scarf which had been wound round her head, to the dainty little French boots on her feet.  These last were Brussels--made, and stamped with the maker's name.  The jacket had come from a London furrier, and the dress--a plain black silk, but of fashionable cut, and expensively trimmed--was from one of the great Paris shops--the Magasin du Louvre.  The first examination had exhausted all these sources of information without result.  None of the tradesmen in the three capitals indicated could remember to whom they had sold these articles, especially as it<pb n="154 The Last of the Costellos."/>was impossible to furnish an approximate limit of time.  Railway officials and hotel-keepers, supplied with the photographs, could not say that they had ever seen the original in life.  Even the coffin--a cheap, ready-made affair--could be traced to no local dealer in such wares.  A chatelaine bag, slung around the waist of the dead girl, had evidently been marked with initials, for the leather showed the holes in which the letters had been fastened, and the traces of the knife employed in their hurried removal.  But the pretty feminine trifle was empty now, and in its present condition had nothing to suggest, save that a determined effort had been made to hide the identity of the dead.  The linen on the corpse was new and of good material, but utterly without mark.  Only a handkerchief, which was found in the pocket, bore a coat-of-arms exquisitely embroidered in the corner.  The shield was covered with a particular pattern in blue and white, on which were three ornamental crosses in gold, and above was displayed the head and shoulders of a knight as a crest.  Gerald, whose smattering of heraldry told him so much, could not be sure that the lines of the embroidery properly indicated the colors of the shield, but he was sanguine that a device so unusual would be recognized by the<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 155"/>learned in such matters; and, having carefully sketched it, he sent a copy to the Herald's College, preserving the original drawing for his own use.  The handkerchief itself, with the other things found on the body, was, of course, beyond his reach.</p>
				<p>While awaiting an answer from the Herald's College, young Ffrench was by no means idle.  His brother's dog-cart was at his service, and, in company with Larry, the groom, the young man made an active canvass of the neighborhood.  He was far from satisfied with the way the local authorities had gone to work.  In matters beyond his scope--in the inquiries that had been made in distant cities--he was content to take the information thus obtained, but it was not in this direction he looked to find his clue.  He built great hopes on the embroidered handkerchief, and was astonished when the coroner pooh-poohed it as a means of identification.  He also thought that the search for the undertaker, who had supplied the last shelter for the beautiful dead, had been too lightly given over.  He had a theory, of course; what detective, professional or amateur, ever started on a quest without one?  Gerald's theory was that the girl had died suddenly, and her companions, probably foreigners, ignorant of the laws of the country and un-<pb n="156 The Last of the Costellos."/>willing to be embarrassed by them, had procured a coffin, and left the deceased for burial at the nearest graveyard.  This would argue that the woman had died somewhere in the immediate vicinity, and it was on this hypothesis that Gerald was working.  He considered that it would have been impossible to convey the body for any considerable distance, either by road or rail, without attracting attention, and he could imagine no possible reason why anyone should have attempted so troublesome a task.  If she had met a violent death, it might be another matter; but testimony at the inquest had been clear on that point.</p>
				<p>And so Edward Ffrench's tall chestnut horse, Shan Van Vocht, whirled the light dog-cart over the muddy Westmeath roads most days during Gerald's last week or two in Ireland, and the young journalist had ample opportunity during these excursions to ponder over all the phases of his search in silence, or to discuss them with Larry, the groom.</p>
				<p>But it all led to nothing.  If the coffin had been procured in the vicinity, none of the local undertakers would admit the transaction, and Gerald was reduced to hope that the embroidery on the handkerchief might supply the missing clew, and he chafed inwardly as day after day went by with-<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 157"/>out bringing any answer from the Herald's College.</p>
				<p>It came at last, not very long before the approaching close of his vacation forced him to leave Ireland.  Gerald found the long-expected letter awaiting him on his return from one of his fruitless quests.  Eagerly he tore it open, but what he read only seemed to make the mystery deeper.</p>
				<p>The arms had been readily recognized from his sketch, and the college, in return for his fee, had furnished him with an illuminated drawing, showing that the embroidery had been accurate.  The shield was "vair, three cross crosslets in bend, or."  Crest, "a demi-knight ppr."  Motto, "Nemo me impune lacessit."  The bearings and cognizance were those of the noble family of Costello, which had left Ireland about the middle of the seventeenth century and had settled in Spain.  The last representative had fallen some sixty years ago at the battle of Vitoria, in the Peninsular War, and the name was now extinct.  So pronounced the unimpeachable authority of the Herald's College.</p>
				<p>From this Gerald concluded that the handkerchief had been marked by some one accustomed to copy blazonries; he thought it likely that the work had been done in a French convent.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="158 The Last of the Costellos."/>And yet he had seen those very arms embroidered on a handkerchief which had been found in the pocket of a nameless girl, whose corpse he himself had been the first to discover some two weeks before in the lonely little burying-ground at Drim.  What was he to think?  Through what strange, undreamed-of ramifications was this affair to be pursued.</p>
				<p>A few days before the date fixed for his departure, Ffrench walked over to the Rectory to say good-by to Dr. Lynn.  The old gentleman had christened Gerald as a baby, had lectured him as a boy, and had been a good friend to him ever since, and the young man was not ungrateful.  But this time his visit had an object beyond the ostensible one of courtesy.  Gerald knew that the rector was an authority on county history, and thought it possible that the old gentleman could tell him something about the Costellos, a name linked with many a Westmeath tradition.  He was not disappointed, and the mystery he was investigating took a new interest from what he heard.  The Costello had been one of the midland chieftains in Cromwell's time; the clan had offered the most determined resistance, and it had been extirpated, root and branch, by the Protector.  The estate of Ballyvore had once<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 159"/>formed portion of the Costello property, and had been purchased by Gerald's ancestor from the Cromwellian Puritan to whom it had been granted on confiscation.</p>
				<p>The young man was now deeply interested in the inquiry, and to it he determined to devote every moment of the time he could still call his own.</p>
				<p>But the last week of the young journalist's visit home slipped away without result, and one fine morning Larry drove him into Athlone to take the train for Queenstown.</p>
				<p>"Ye'll not be lettin' another six years go by without comin' home agen, will ye, sir?" said the groom, who was really concerned at Gerald's departure.</p>
				<p>"I don't know," answered Gerald; "it all depends.  Say, Larry!"" Sir! ""Keep an eye out, and if anything turns up about that dead girl let me know, won't you?"  Ffrench had already made a similar request of his brother, but he was determined to leave no chance untried.</p>
				<p>"An' are ye thinkin' o' that yet, an' you goin' to America?" asked Larry, with admiring wonder.</p>
				<p>"Of course I'm thinking of it.  I can't get it out of my head," said Gerald, impatiently.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="160 The Last of the Costellos."/>"Well, well, d'ye mind that, now?" remarked the groom, meditatively.  "Well, sir, if anything does turn up, I'll let ye know, never fear; but sure she's under ground now, an' if we'd been goin' to larn anything about the matter we'd ha' had it weeks ago."Gerald shook hands with the faithful Larry at parting, and left a sovereign in his palm.</p>
				<p>The groom watched the train moving slowly out of the station, then he spun the coin in the air, caught it, and spat on it "for luck," as he explained to himself.  When the train was out of sight, he climbed back into the dog-cart and shook the reins over Shan Van Vocht's chestnut back.</p>
				<p>"It's a mortial pity to see a fine young jintleman like that so far gone in love with a dead girl."This was Larry's comment on his young master's detective tastes.</p>
				<p>Meanwhile Gerald Ffrench, speeding southward through the varied scenery of Munster, was taking himself seriously to task.</p>
				<p>"I must drop all this nonsense," he reflected, "or I won't be fit for work again when I get back.  It is a mystery, and it has baffled me.  Well, lots of mysteries are never solved, and I suppose this will be one of them.  I must think of something else.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 161"/>I wonder if the 'Frisco boys will be glad to see me when I turn up again;" and so, being in a smoking carriage, he lit his pipe, and gradually forced his mind into other channels.</p>
				<p>At Queenstown he bought a paper and looked over it while the tender was carrying him--in company with many a weeping emigrant--to the great steamer out in the bay.  From time to time the journals still contained references to the subject which was uppermost in Gerald's thoughts.  The familiar words, "The Drim Churchyard Mystery" caught his eye, and he read a brief paragraph, which had nothing to say except that all investigations had failed to throw any light on the strange business.</p>
				<p>"Ay, and will fail," mused Ffrench as the tender came alongside the steamer, "at any rate, if anything is found out it won't be by me, for I shall be in California, and I can scarcely run across any clews there."And yet, as Gerald paced the deck and watched the bleak shores of Cork fading in the distance, his thoughts were full of the banished Costellos, and he wondered with what eyes those exiles had looked their last on the old Head of Kinsale a quarter of a millennium ago.  Those fierce chieftains,<pb n="162 The Last of the Costellos."/>to whom the Ffrenches, proud county family as they esteemed themselves, were but as mushrooms; what lives had they lived, what deaths had they died, and how came their haughty cognizance, so well expressing its defiant motto, on the handkerchief of the nameless stranger who slept in Drim Churchyard--Drim, the old, old graveyard--Drim that had been fenced in as God's acre in the days of the Costellos themselves.  Was it mere chance that had selected this spot as the last resting-place of one who bore the arms of the race?  Was it possible the girl had shared the Costello blood?</p>
				<p>Gerald glanced over his letter from the Herald's College and shook his head.  The family had been extinct for more than sixty years.</p>
				<p>GERALD FFRENCH went back into harness on his arrival in San Francisco more readily than he had anticipated.  He liked his work and returned to it refreshed from his three months' vacation.  He found it easy to relegate the jolly days in hunting-field or at cover-side to their proper place in his life--mere pleasant memories to be talked over with the companions of the hour of idleness and<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 163"/>dismissed at the call of duty.  It was more difficult to banish recollections of Drim churchyard and what he had found there, and this subject, though Gerald kept it to himself, was often present in his thoughts, and filled much of his leisure time with the purposeless speculation it engendered.  Purposeless, because he had exhausted conjecture during the long journey over ocean and continent, and there was scarcely a theory, possible or impossible, which he had not mentally tested and dismissed.  Still the grim riddle and its hidden solution exercised a fascination upon the young man which he strove in vain to resist.  Often, in the solitude of his own room, he would enliven the pipe he was accustomed to smoke before retiring by producing from his desk the only tangible evidence which this baffling case had left in his hands--the photograph of the dead girl and the illuminated shield he had received from the Herald's College.  These he would lay before him, while he went step by step over the whole of the strange story with which they were connected.  He opened every letter that he received from home with a vague hope that something new might have come to light.  But there was never even a reference to the mystery.  The whole matter had evidently dropped from the gossip of the<pb n="164 The Last of the Costellos."/>country side, and the old burying-ground at Drim shrouded its secret well.</p>
				<p>About two months after Gerald's return to California a despatch was received from the "Evening Mail's" regular correspondent in Marysville, relating the particulars of an encounter between the Mexican holders of a large ranch in Yuba County and certain American land-grabbers, who had set up a claim to a portion of the estate.  The matter was in course of adjudication in the Marysville courts, but the claimants, impatient at the slow process of the law, had endeavored to seize the disputed land by force.  Shots had been fired, blood had been spilled, and the whole affair added nothing to Yuba County's reputation for law and order.  The matter created some talk in San Francisco, and the "Evening Mail," among other papers, expressed its opinion in one of those trenchant personal articles which are the spice of Western journalism.  Two or three days later, when the incident had been almost forgotten in the office, the city editor sent for Gerald Ffrench.</p>
				<p>"Ffrench," said that gentleman as the young man approached his desk, "I've just received a letter from Don Miguel y--y--something or other.  I can't read his whole name, and it don't much matter.  It's Vincenza, you know, the owner of that<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 165"/>ranch where they had the shooting scrape the other day.  He is anxious to make a statement of the matter for publication, and has come down to the Bay on purpose.  Suppose you go and see what he has to say?  He's staying at the Lick."The same morning Gerald sent up his card, and was ushered into the apartment of Don Miguel Vincenza, at the Lick House.</p>
				<p>The Señor was a young man, not much older than Gerald himself.  He had the appearance and manners of a gentleman, as Ffrench quickly discovered, and he spoke fluent, well-chosen English with scarcely a trace of accent, a circumstance for which the interviewer felt he could not be sufficiently grateful.</p>
				<p>"Ah, you are from the 'Evening Mail,'" said the young Spaniard, rising as Gerald entered; "most kind of you to come, and to come so promptly.  Won't you be seated?  Try a cigar?  No?  You'll excuse me if I light a cigarette.  I want to make myself clear, and I'm always clearest when I'm in a cloud."  He gave a little laugh, and with one twirl of his slender fingers he converted a morsel of tissue paper and a pinch of tobacco into a compact roll, which he lighted and exhausted in half a dozen puffs, as he spoke. <pb n="166 The Last of the Costellos."/>"This man--this Jenkinson's claim is perfectly preposterous," he began, "but I won't go into that.  The matter is before the courts.  What I want to give you is a true statement of that unfortunate affair at the ranch; with which I beg you to believe I had nothing whatever to do."Señor Vincenza's tale might have had the merit of truth; it certainly lacked that of brevity.  He talked on--rolling a fresh cigarette at every second sentence--and Gerald made notes of such points as he considered important, but at the conclusion of the Spaniard's statement the journalist could not see that it differed from the published accounts, and he told the other as much.</p>
				<p>"Well, you see," said Vincenza, "I am in a delicate position.  It is not as if I were acting for myself, I am only my sister's agent--my half-sister's I should say--poor little Catalina--" and the speaker broke off with a sigh and rolled a fresh cigarette before he resumed.  "It's her property, all of it, and I cannot bear to have her misrepresented in any way.""I understand," said Gerald making a note of the fact.  "The property, I suppose, passed to your sister from--""From her father.  I was in the land of the liv-<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 167"/>ing some years before he met, and wooed, and won my widowed mother.  They are both dead now and Catalina has none but myself to look out for her--except distant relatives on the father's side, who will inherit the property if she dies unmarried and whom she cordially detests."Gerald was not particularly romantic, but the idea of this fair young Spaniard, owner of one of the finest ranches in Yuba County, unmarried, and handsome, too, if she were anything like her brother, inflamed his imagination a little.  He shook hands cordially with the young man, as he rose to go, and could not help wishing they were better acquainted.</p>
				<p>"You may be sure I will publish your statement exactly as you have given it to me, and as fully as possible," said Gerald.  Before the young heiress had been mentioned the journalist had scarcely seen material enough in the interview for a paragraph.</p>
				<p>It is fair to presume that Señor Vincenza was satisfied with the treatment he received in the "Evening Mail," for a polite note conveyed to Ffrench the expression of his thanks.</p>
				<p>So that incident passed into the limbo of forgetfulness, though Gerald afterward took more interest in the newspaper paragraphs, often scant<pb n="168 The Last of the Costellos."/>enough, which told of the progress of the great land case in the Marysville courts.</p>
				<p>A curt despatch, worded with that exasperating brevity which is a peculiarity of all but the most important telegrams, wound up the matter with an announcement that a decision had been reached in favor of the defendant, and that Mr. Isaac Hall, of the law firm of Hall &amp; McGowan, had returned to San Francisco, having conducted the case to a successful issue.  Gerald was pleased to hear that the young lady had been sustained in her rights, and determined to interview Mr. Hall, with whom he was well acquainted.  Accordingly, after two or three unsuccessful attempts, he managed to catch the busy lawyer with half an hour's spare time on his hands, and well enough disposed to welcome his young friend.</p>
				<p>"Mr. Hall," said Gerald, dropping into the spare chair in the attorney's private room, "I want to ask you a few questions about that Marysville land case.""Fire ahead, my boy; I can give you twenty minutes," answered the lawyer, who was disposed to make a great deal more of the victory he had won than the newspapers had hitherto done, and who was consequently by no means averse from an interview.  "What do you want to know?"<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 169"/>"Hard fight, wasn't it?" began the journalist.</p>
				<p>"Yes," replied Mr. Hall, "tough in a way; but we had right on our side as well as possession.  A good lawyer ought always to win when he has those; to beat law and facts and everything else is harder scratching; though I've done that too," and the old gentleman chuckled as if well satisfied with himself.</p>
				<p>"That's what your opponents had to do here, I suppose," remarked Gerald, echoing the other's, laugh.</p>
				<p>"Pretty much, only they didn't do it," said the lawyer.</p>
				<p>"I met Vincenza when he was down last month," pursued Gerald.  "He seems a decentish sort of a fellow for a greaser.""He's no greaser; he's a pure-blooded Castilian, and very much of the gentleman," answered Hall.</p>
				<p>"So I found him," assented Gerald.  "I only used the 'greaser' as a generic term.  He talks English as well as I do.""That's a great compliment from an Irishman," observed Mr. Hall, with another chuckle.</p>
				<p>"I suppose the sister's just as nice in her own way," went on Gerald, seeing an opportunity to satisfy a certain curiosity he had felt about the<pb n="170 The Last of the Costellos."/>heiress since he first heard of her existence.  "Did she make a good witness?""Who?  What sister?  What the deuce are you talking about?" asked the lawyer.</p>
				<p>"Why, Vincenza's sister, half-sister, whatever she is.  I understood from him that she was the real owner of the property.""Oh, ay, to be sure," said Mr. Hall, slowly; "these details escape one.  Vincenza was my client; he acts for the girl under power of attorney, and really her name has hardly come up since the very beginning of the case.""You didn't see her, then?" asked Gerald, conscious of a vague sense of disappointment.</p>
				<p>"See her!" repeated the lawyer.  "No; how could I?  She's in Europe for educational advantages; at a convent somewhere, I believe.""Oh," exclaimed Gerald, "a child, is she?  I had fancied, I don't know why, that she was a grown-up young lady.""I couldn't tell you what her age is, but it must be over twenty-one, or she couldn't have executed the power of attorney; and that was looked into at the start, and found to be quite regular.""Rather late in the day to be going in for education, isn't it?" remarked Gerald.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 171"/>"Not at all," answered the lawyer.  "What opportunities could she have had in Yuba County?  Indeed, now I think of it, the girl must be about two-and-twenty, for they went to Europe last year, and she waited till she was of age and able to arrange her affairs personally before she would start.""I see," said Gerald, slowly; but the topic had started Mr. Hall on a fresh trail, and he broke in:"And preciously they must have arranged them.  Do you know we came within an ace of losing, all through their confounded careless way of keeping their papers?""How did they keep them?" inquired Gerald, listlessly.  The suit appeared to be a commonplace one, and the young man's interest began to wane.</p>
				<p>"They didn't keep them at all," exclaimed Mr. Hall, indignantly.  "Fancy, the original deed-- the old Spanish grant--the very keystone of our case, was not to be found till the last moment, and then only by the merest accident; and where do you suppose it was?""I haven't an idea," replied Gerald, stifling a yawn.</p>
				<p>"At the back of an old print of the Madonna.  It had been framed and hung up, as an ornament, I suppose, heaven knows when; and by and by some smart Aleck came along and thought the Mother<pb n="172 The Last of the Costellos."/>and Child superior as a work of art, and slapped it into the frame over the deed, and there it has hung for ten years, anyhow.""That's really very curious," said Gerald, whose attention began to revive as he saw a possible column to be compiled on the details of the case that had seemed so uninteresting to his contemporaries.</p>
				<p>"Curious!  I call it sinful--positively wicked," cried the old gentleman, wrathfully.  "Just fancy $200,000 hanging on the accident of finding a parchment in such a place as that.""How did you happen to find it?" asked Gerald.  "I should never have thought of looking for it there.""No, nor any other sane man," sputtered the lawyer, irritated as he recalled the anxiety the missing deed had caused him.  "It was found by accident, I tell you.  Some blundering, awkward, heaven-guided servant knocked the picture down and broke the frame.  The Madonna was removed, and the missing paper came to light.""And that was the turning-point of the case?  Very interesting, indeed," mused Gerald, who saw in the working out of this legal romance a bit of detective writing such as his soul loved.  "I suppose they'll have sense enough to put it in a safer place next time."<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 173"/>"I will, you may bet your life.  I've taken charge of all the family documents, and if they get away from me they'll do something that nothing's ever done before," and the old lawyer chuckled with renewed satisfaction as he pointed to the massive safe in a corner of the office.</p>
				<p>"So the deed is there, is it?" asked Gerald, following Mr. Hall's eyes.</p>
				<p>"Yes, it's there.  A curious old document, too; one of the oldest grants I have ever come across.  Would you like to see it?" and the lawyer rose and opened the safe.</p>
				<p>It was a curious old document, drawn up in curious old Spanish, on an old, discolored piece of parchment.  The body of the instrument was unintelligible to Ffrench, but down in one corner was something that riveted his attention in a moment, and seemed to make his heart stand still.</p>
				<p>There was a signature in old-fashioned, angular hand-writing, "Roderiguez Costello y Ugarte," and opposite it a large, spreading seal.  The impression showed a knight's head and shoulders in full armor, and below it the shield, vair, with three cross crosslets, or; and the motto:<pb n="174 The Last of the Costellos."/>Point for point the identical blazonry which Ffrench had received from the Herald's College in England; the shield that he had first seen embroidered on the dead girl's handkerchief at Drim.</p>
				<p>"What's the matter with you?  Didn't you ever see an old Spanish deed before, or has it any of the properties of a Medusa's head?" inquired Mr. Hall, noticing Gerald's start of amazement and intent scrutiny of the seal,"I've seen these arms before," said the young man, slowly.  "But the name---" he placed his finger on the signature.  "Of course I knew Vincenza's name must be different from his half-sister's; but is that her's?""Ugarte?  Yes," replied the lawyer, glancing at the parchment.</p>
				<p>"I mean the whole name," and Gerald pointed again.</p>
				<p>"Costello!"  Mr. Hall gave the word its Spanish pronunciation--Costelyo--and it sounded strange and foreign in the young man's ears.  "Costello, yes, I suppose so, but I don't try to keep track of more of these Spaniards' titles than is absolutely necessary.""But Costello is an Irish name," said Gerald.</p>
				<p>"Is it?  You ought to know.  Well, Costelyo's<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 175"/>Spanish; and now, my dear boy, I must positively turn you out.  I have just half an hour for my clerk to fill me full before I attend a reference."Gerald went straight home without returning to the office.  He unlocked his desk and took from it the two results of his first essay in detective craft.  Silently he laid them side by side and scrutinized each closely in turn.  The pale, set face of the beautiful dead, as reproduced by the photographer's art, told him nothing.  He strove to trace some resemblance, to awaken some memory by long gazing at the passionless features, but it was in vain.  Then he turned to the illuminated shield.  Every line was familiar to him, and a glance sufficed.  It was identical in all respects with the arms on the seal.  Of this he had been already convinced, and his recollection had not betrayed him.  Then he placed the two--the piteous photograph and the proud blazonry--in his pocket-book, and left the room.  He went straight to the office of the "Evening Mail" and requested a week's leave of absence.  This was obtained, not without some difficulty and a few sharp words; but it was obtained, which was all Ffrench cared about.  The same evening he took his place on the Sacramento train en route for Marysville.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="176 The Last of the Costellos."/>IT is a long eighteen miles from the capital of Yuba County to the village of San Luis, near which, as Gerald ascertained, the Ugarte ranch is situated.  There was no public conveyance to the village, but Gerald found little difficulty in obtaining a team at a Marysville livery stable, pledging his word and his credentials as an "Evening Mail" correspondent for its safe return.  With minute instructions as to his route, which resolved themselves into a direction to leave Marysville by the south and keep the straight track till it went no farther, he started.  The drive, as a drive, was far from enjoyable.  It was near the close of the long, dry California summer, and the red dust lay inches thick in the road, whirling up in blinding clouds under the horses' feet, and settling on the traveller's garments, in his hair, in his eyes, with an intrusive persistence.  Every bush by the way bore on arid branches a burden of offensive particles.  Gerald was compelled to cough the dust out of his throat and rub it from his eyes at least a dozen times for every mile of that weary journey, and the level red track stretched for six long leagues across the parched tule lands of Yuba.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 177"/>It was growing dusk as young Ffrench drove into San Luis.  The village consisted of a plaza--four rows of irregularly built houses, with wide intervals between them, all fronting on a large dusty square.  The buildings were of wood, some painted a staring white, some displaying the natural tints of the discolored timber.  There might have been two score of them in all.  One, dignified by a broad veranda, was labelled "Hotel," and, on the opposite side of the plaza, above a door, swung a rudely painted sign, representing two drunken men endeavoring to support one another, with the legend below, "Los Dos Amigos."  This was evidently the liquor shop of the place, for its windows were adorned with whiskey labels and brewery chromos.  There was not much sign of life in the square; a few men lounged about or sat smoking on the sides of a large horse-trough which, surmounted by a pump, occupied the centre.  They seemed indolent and indifferent, and took little notice of Gerald as he pulled up in a cloud of dust and tried to single out some one to question.</p>
				<p>"Can you tell me whereabouts is the Ugarte ranch?" asked Gerald, choosing a man who stood, hands in pockets, leaning against the pump.  "It's somewhere near here, isn't it?"<pb n="178 The Last of the Costellos."/>"'Pends on what yer call near," said the individual addressed, bringing one hand and a huge twist of tobacco into sight.  He gnawed a piece from the mass and then cast a critical eye over Gerald's equipage.  "Ye've come a right smart piece I'm thinking?""From Marysville," answered Ffrench.</p>
				<p>"Ay, them plugs shows it," remarked the man, and relapsed into silence.</p>
				<p>"Can't you tell me where the Ugarte ranch is?" repeated Gerald, after a moment's silence.</p>
				<p>"Who'd yer wan ter see there?  Vincenza?" asked the other.</p>
				<p>It was at the tip of Gerald's tongue to tell the fellow to mind his own business, but he restrained himself.</p>
				<p>"Yes, Vincenza," he answered.</p>
				<p>"Wal, let's see!  Yer take that there road running out by the corner, and keep the sun at yer back till yer get ter the foot of the mesa--""How far is it?" interrupted Gerald, to whom this elaborate direction suggested distance.</p>
				<p>"Matter o' twelve miles," replied the other, indifferently.</p>
				<p>Ffrench cast a look of despair at his weary horses.  It was evidently impossible to take them much further, and besides, night was falling.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 179"/> "Twelve miles!" he said.  "I'll have to wait till to-morrow.""Ay, do, stranger," cried the other, brightening up into a faint show of interest.  "Put yer team up at the livery stable, get a shake-down for yourself at the hotel, and come over to Los Dos Amigos after supper.  I'll scare yer up a game of monte, or somethin', to keep yer amoosed, or I'll bust trying."Without committing himself to any acknowledgment of this hospitable proposition, Gerald drove slowly across the plaza toward the stable.  A horsy looking young fellow, who stood before the entrance chewing a straw, came forward and, to Ffrench's intense astonishment, accosted him by name, and in the broad, familiar dialect of Western Leinster.</p>
				<p>"May I never ate another bit if it isn't Masther Gerald Ffrench," he said.  "Well, well, well, but it's good for sore eyes to see ye.  Come out here, Steve, and take the team.  Jump down, Masther Gerald, an' stretch yer legs a bit.  It's kilt ye are entirely."A swarthy little Mexican appeared as Gerald alighted and led the tired horses into the stable.  Then the young journalist took a good look at the<pb n="180 The Last of the Costellos."/>man who seemed to know him so well, and endeavored, as the phrase goes, to "place him."The face seemed familiar--a sharp, thin, close-shaven face, with small, gray eyes, and bushy, black brows, and about the cheeks and chin that peculiar blue tint which is the silent protest of a banished beard.  He felt he had seen the man more than once, but where, or when, or under what circumstances he could not for the moment determine.  The other did not leave him long in doubt.</p>
				<p>"Ye don't mind me, yer honor, an' how wud ye?  But I mind yerself well.  Sure it's often I druv ye and Mr. Edward, too.  I used to wurruk for Mr. Ross, o' Mullingar.  I was Denny, the post-boy--Dennis Driscoll, yer honor; sure ye must know me.""Oh, yes, to be sure; I remember," said Gerald, as recollection slowly dawned upon him.  "But who'd have thought of finding you in a place like this?  I didn't even know you had left Ross's stables.""Six, sivin months ago, yer honor.""And have you been here ever since?  I hope you are doing well," asked Gerald.</p>
				<p>"Iver since, sor; an' doin' finely, wid the blessin' o' God.  I own that place," pointing to the stable, "an' four as good turnouts as ye'd ax to sit behind."<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 181"/>"I'm glad of it," cried Gerald, heartily.  "I like to hear of the boys from the old neighborhood doing well.""Won't ye step inside, sor, and thry a dhrop o' something? ye must be choked intirely wid the dust.""I don't care if I do," answered Gerald.  "I feel pretty much as if I'd swallowed a lime-kiln."A minute later the two were seated in Denny's own particular room, where Gerald washed the dust from his throat with some capital bottled beer, while his host paid attention to a large demijohn, which contained, as he informed the journalist in an impressive whisper, "close on to a gallon o' the raal ould stuff.""And how did you get such a start?" inquired Gerald, with some curiosity.  "I didn't even know you were going to America, and I think you drove me once at least while I was at home last winter.""I did, sor; an' it's little I thought o' goin' to Ameriky thin, an' as for this little contimptuous place, I'd niver heerd tell of it.  It's a quare story.""Suppose you tell it me," said Gerald, pouring out a fresh supply of beer.</p>
				<p>The other held the demijohn in an affectionate<pb n="182 The Last of the Costellos."/>embrace, as though it were a valued friend, while he tilted a fair amount of whiskey into his glass.</p>
				<p>"A quare story," repeated Denny; "an' if I was in ould Ireland, divil an open wud I open me mouth about it; but here, in these outlandish parts, what odds does it make?  There was a foreign jintleman thravellin' in Ireland last winter"---"Was his name Vincenza?" inquired Gerald, starting from his seat as the possibilities of the coming revelation were borne in upon him.</p>
				<p>"That was his name," answered Denny, "though I didn't know it at the time.  Is yer honor acquainted wid him?""Yes--no--I have met him," said Gerald, angry at himself at having allowed the exclamation to escape him.  "But what has he to do with your being here?""Everything," answered Denny, with a grin.  "He's a great rich jintleman an' owns all the land round here for moiles.  He brot me up here wid him, an' bought me these turnouts an' set me up in business.""That was very kind of him," commented Gerald; "it isn't every gentleman you drive does as much for you.""It isn't ivery jintleman I dhrive puts as quare a<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 183"/>job on me as he done.  Now, listen, Masther Gerald, an' tell me what ye think o' this."  Denny moistened his lips with a few drops of the "ould stuff," cleared his throat, and proceeded.  "The jintleman--Mr. Vincenza, as I know him to be now--was thravellin' wid his sister, as purty a young lady as iver I seen, an' they cum to Mullingar on the evenin' thrain from Dublin, last January it was.  I was at the station wid Mr. Ross's close carriage, for it was a rainy night, waitin' for any fare I might pick up off o' the train.  Mr. Vincenza comes up to me an' he sez, sez he, 'D'ye know where' Drim is, me boy?'  'Why not, sir?' sez I, as why shouldn't I.  Wid that he wint back and brot the young lady out o' the station.  She was donny and wakely, it seemed, an' she kept a lanin' on his arrum.  The two were colloquin' together in some foreign lingo I knew nothing about, but it was plain to be seen that she was hell-bent to go to Drim, an' he wanted to stay in Mullingar that night.  Well, to mek a long story short, she had her way, and they got into the carriage, he helpin' her, for he was mighty tinder of her.  I started an' druv along middlin' aisy, an' whin I was about a mile on t'other side o' Kinnegad I heerd some one callin' to me out o' the carriage, 'Stop, dhriver, stop!' so I pulled up and the jintle-<pb n="184 The Last of the Costellos."/>man opened the dure and got out.  Sez he, 'Get down driver,' sez he, 'me sister's tuk very bad.'  That's the way I come to know she was his sister.  Before that I tuk thim for husban' an' wife.  Well, she was mortial bad, surely--wake an' faint, an' roll-in' her eyes terrible.  I'd unhooked wan o' the carriage lamps an' held it for light.  Well, to mek a long story short, she died thin an' there, an' I was that scared I didn't know which side o' me was uppermost.  The jintleman tuk on terrible, an' kissed her dead face, an' called her all sorts o' soft names in his foreign lingo.  At last he straightens up, an' he sez to me, 'Dhriver,' sez he, 'this is a bad business.'  'Ye're right, sir, it is,' sez I.  'I was afraid of somethin' like this,' sez he, 'she had heart disease an' it's killed her.'  'It's a mortial pity thin, sir,' sez I, for her face was as calm and paceful as an angel's, an' she luked beautiful in the lamp-light.  Wid that he fell to cryin' an' kissin' her agen, an' then he sez, sez he, 'D'ye know of any undertaker in the neighborhood where we cud git a coffin for the poor thing?' sez he.  'I do sir,' sez I; for I thought o' Fergus Farrell, just outside o' the town o' Kinnegad, not half a mile from where we was that minit.""Fergus Farrell!" interrupted Gerald.  "Did you get that coffin from him?"<pb n="186 The Last of the Costellos."/>"We did that, sor; from no one else.""The confounded liar," muttered Ffrench, for the aforesaid Farrell was one of those whom he had cross-questioned in his canvass of the Westmeath undertakers; but Denny's story had reached an interesting point, so Gerald only spared time for a single malediction, and then urged the other to proceed.</p>
				<p>"We found Farrell, sir, an', after a bit of a talk betune the foreign jintleman an' himself, a coffin was brot out an' the young lady was put in it.  The jintleman tuk his knife an' ripped somethin' off the bag she wore at her side, and then Farrell nailed the coffin down.  It 'ud do full as well, he said, an' it 'ud take a long time to screw it.  Then the jintleman gave Fergus money--a whole fistful o' notes--an' I thought it was a big price for a coffin, but I sed nothin'.  They put it on the dhrivin sate, becase they cudn't get it inside.  I didn't like it much, but the jintleman sed I should be well ped--and so, you see, I was.  'Where to now, sir,' sez I.  'To Drim Churchyard,' sez he, an' off I went.  I thought it was mighty quare, the whole thing, but it was the best o' me play to say nothin'.  Whin we got to Drim, I druv in be the lower road; it was close onto midnight be that time, an' we lifted the coffin over the wall where the steps is, an' set it<pb n="186 The Last of the Costellos."/>among the grass a little back.  Then the jintleman knelt down by it in the wet and done a little prayin', I judge, and he got up an' sez, 'She'll rest there where she wished to rest,' and then we went back to the carriage.  'Aren't ye goin' to bury her, sir,' sez I.  'No,' he sez, 'others must do that.  I have no time,' an' wid that he climbed up on the box nixt to me, though it was pourin' rain.  'Back to Mullingar,' he sez, an' away we druv.  Well, the whole way he was tellin' me what an' illegant place Ameriky is, an' how he was goin' straight back, an' wouldn't I like to come.  There was no end to what he was goin' to do for me.  He swore a big oath there was nothin' wrong in this night's wurruk, that he loved his sister better nor his life, an' that he'd done all he had done becase it was her last wish.  Well, to mek a long story short, before we got to Mullingar I was hot to go back wid him to Ameriky.  He said we must start at wanst, but that med no odds to me, for I'd none belongin' to me.  Well, he got off at the railway station, an' towld me to come to him there as soon as I'd druv back the carriage; an' he ped a good price for his dhrive.  Well, I guv in the carriage, and towld the masther that I was goin' away for a few days, an' then I kem to the station.  We tuk the early mornin' thrain for Ath-<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 187"/>lone, an' from that down to Queenstown, where we caught the steamer the very same day.  An' I'm doin' well here, an' have niver regritted comin'.""A very curious story, indeed, Denny," said Gerald.  "Do you remember what day of the week all this happened?""I do sir, for it was a Tuesday night we left the young lady in Drim, an' we tuk the Wednesday's steamer at Queenstown.""So," reflected Gerald, "they were on the broad Atlantic when I saw the coffin among the grass that Wednesday evening.""Denny," resumed Ffrench, after a short silence, during which he had written a few lines on his card, "couldn't your helper--what do you call him?""I call him Steve, sor, for short, but his real name is Stefano.""Well, couldn't he ride over to the Ugarte ranch and give this card of mine to Señor Vincenza?""Why not, sor--but wait now.  Ye're not goin' to tell Mr. Vincenza all I've towld ye, sor, for he's kept his wurrud be me, an' I'd ha kep mine be him an' niver whispered all this only, ye see, it was a quare thing, an' it bothered me, an' bein' as I have a great rispict for yer family, Mr. Ffrench an'---""Make your mind quite easy, Denny," said Ger-<pb n="188 The Last of the Costellos."/>ald.  "You've done no harm in telling me this.  As you say, it happened in Ireland and this is California.  I came out on purpose to see Mr. Vincenza--here, I'll read you my card.  All it says is, "Please come over to San Luis as soon as possible; most important business."Half an hour later a mustang loped out of the square and vanished in a cloud of dust.  Stefano was in the saddle and he carried Ffrench's card in his pocket.</p>
				<p>Señor Vincenza appeared the following morning just as Gerald had finished breakfast.  The ranchero remembered the representative of the "Evening Mail" and greeted him cordially, expressing his surprise at Gerald's presence in that part of the country.  The Spaniard evidently imagined that this unexpected visit had some bearing on the recently decided law-suit, but the other's first words dispelled the illusion.</p>
				<p>"Señor Vincenza," Ffrench said, "I have heard a very strange story about your sister, and I have come to ask you for an explanation of it."The young Spaniard changed color and looked uneasily at the journalist.  "What do you mean?" he asked.  "I do not understand you.  My sister is in Europe."<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 189 "/>"Yes," answered Gerald, "she is in Europe--in Ireland--she fills a nameless grave in Drim Churchyard."Vincenza leaped to his feet, and the cigarette he had lighted dropped from his fingers.  They were in Gerald's room at the hotel, and the young man had placed his visitor so that the table was between them.  He suspected that he might have to deal with a desperate man.  Vincenza leaned over the narrow table, and his breath blew hot in Ffrench's face as he hissed: "Carrambo!  What do you mean?  How much do you know?""I know everything.  I know how she died in the carriage on your way from Mullingar, how you purchased a coffin and bribed the Kinnegad undertaker to silence; how you laid her, in the dead of night, among the weeds in the graveyard; how you cut her name from the chatelaine bag, and did all in your power to hide her identity.  Do you recognize that photograph; have you ever seen that coat of arms before?" and Ffrench drew the two cards from his pocket and offered them to Vincenza.</p>
				<p>The Spaniard brushed them impatiently aside and crouched for a moment as if to spring.  Gerald never took his eyes off him, and presently the other straightened up, and, sinking into the chair behind<pb n="190 The Last of the Costellos."/>him, attempted to roll a cigarette.  But his hand trembled and half the tobacco was spilled on the floor.</p>
				<p>"You know a great deal, Mr. Gerald Ffrench.  Do you accuse me of my sister's murder?""No," answered Gerald.  "She died from natural causes.  But I do accuse you of fraudulently withholding this property from its rightful owners, and of acting on a 'power of attorney' which has been cancelled by the death of the giver."There was a moment's silence, broken only by a muttered oath from Vincenza as he threw the unfinished cigarette to the ground, and began to roll another--this time with better success.  It was not till it was fairly alight that he spoke again.</p>
				<p>"Listen to me, young man," he said, "and then judge me as you hope to be judged hereafter--with mercy.  My sister was very dear to me--I loved her--oh, God, how I loved her!"  His voice broke and Gerald, recalling certain details in Denny's narrative, felt that the Spaniard was speaking the truth.  It was nearly a minute before Vincenza recovered his self-command and resumed.</p>
				<p>"Yes, we were very dear to each other; brought up as brother and sister, how could we fail to be?  But her father never liked me, and he placed re-<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 191"/>strictions upon the fortune he left her so that it could never come to me.  My mother--our mother--had died some years before.  Well, Catalina was wealthy; I was a pauper, but that made no difference while she lived.  We were as happy and fond a brother and sister as the sun ever shone upon.  When she came of age she executed the 'power of attorney' that gave me the charge of her estate.  She was anxious to spend a few years in Europe.  I was to take her over, and, after we had travelled a little, she was to go to a convent in France and spend some time there, while I returned home.  But she was one of the old Costellos, and she was anxious to visit the ancient home of her race.  That was what brought us to Ireland.""I thought the Costello family was extinct," observed Gerald.</p>
				<p>"The European branch has been extinct since 1813, when Don Lopez Costello fell at Vitoria; but the younger branch, which settled in Mexico toward the end of the eighteenth century, survived until a few months ago; until Catalina's death, in fact, for she was the last of the Costellos.""I see," said Gerald.  "Go on.""She was very proud of the name, poor Catalina, and she made me promise, in case anything hap-<pb n="192 The Last of the Costellos."/>pened to her while we were abroad, that she should be laid in the ancient grave of her race--in the churchyard of Drim.  She had a weak heart, and she knew that she might die suddenly.  I promised.  And it was on our way to the spot she was so anxious to visit that death claimed her--only a few miles from the place where her ancestors had lived in the old days, and where all that remains of them has long moldered to dust.  So you see, Mr. Ffrench, that I had no choice but to lay her there.""That is not the point," insisted Gerald.  "Why this secrecy?  Why this flight?  Dr. Lynn, I am sure, would have enabled you to obey your sister's request in the full light of day--you need not have thrown her coffin on the ground, and left to strangers the task of doing for the poor girl the last duties of civilization."  Gerald spoke with indignant heat, for this looked to him like the cruelest desertion.</p>
				<p>"I know how it must seem to you," answered Vincenza, "and I have no excuse to offer for my conduct but this.  My sister's death would have given all she possessed to people whom she disliked.  It would have thrown me, whom she loved, penniless on the world.  I acted as if she was still living, and as I am sure she would have wished me to<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 193"/>act; no defence, I know, in your eyes; but consider the temptation.""And did you not realize that all this must come out some day?" asked Ffrench.</p>
				<p>"Yes, but not for several years.  Indeed, I cannot imagine how you have stumbled on the truth."And Gerald, remembering the extraordinary chain of circumstances which had led him to the root of the mystery, could not but acknowledge that, humanly speaking, Vincenza's confidence was justified.</p>
				<p>"And now that you have found this out, what use do you intend to make of it?" asked the Spaniard, after a pause.</p>
				<p>"I shall publish the whole story as soon as I return to San Francisco," answered Gerald, promptly.</p>
				<p>"So, for a few hundred dollars, which is all that you can possibly get out of it, you will make a beggar of me?""Right is right," said the young Irishman.  "This property does not belong to you?""Will you hold your tongue--or your pen--for $50,000?" asked the Spanard [sic], eagerly.</p>
				<p>"No, nor for every dollar you have in the world.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="194 The Last of the Costellos."/>I don't approve of your practice, and I won't share your plunder.  I am sorry for you personally, but I can't help that, I won't oust you.  I will make such use of the story as any newspaper man would make, and so I give you fair warning.  You may save yourself if you can.""Then you do not intend to communicate with the heirs," began Vincenza, eagerly.</p>
				<p>"I neither know nor care who they are," interrupted Gerald.  "I am not a detective, save in the way of my profession, and I shall certainly not tell what I have discovered to any individual till I give it to the press.""And that will be?" asked the Spaniard.</p>
				<p>"As soon as I return to San Francisco," answered Ffrench; "it may appear in a week or less.""Thank you, Señor: good morning," said Vincenza, rising and leaving the room.</p>
				<p>Three days later Señor Miguel Vincenza sailed on the outgoing Pacific Mail Steamer, bound for Japan and China.  He probably took a considerable sum of money with him, for the heirs of Catalina Costello y Ugarte found the affairs of the deceased in a very tangled state, and the ranch was mortgaged for nearly half its value.</p>
				<p>Gerald Ffrench's story occupied four pages of the<pb n="The Last of the Costellos. 195"/>next issue of the "Golden Fleece," and was widely copied and commented upon over two continents.  Larry, the groom at Ballyvore, read the account in his favorite Westmeath "Sentinel," and, as he laid the paper down, exclaimed in wonder:"Begob, he found her!"<pb n="196"/>
					<pb n="197"/>
					<pb n="198"/>
					<pb n="199"/>"YES, you kin hev breakfast; but about a team--wall, I'll see."Thus spoke the clerk of the Eureka House, a young man of aggressive manners, whose stubbly black hair stood out from his head as if bristling defiance toward every point of the compass.  He looked harassed, and had laid aside his coat.  This might be the usual way of welcoming the coming guest in Humboldt County, but Gerald Ffrench did not appreciate it.  He was fresh from twenty-four hours of an ocean not always so pacific in its name, and the floor seemed to heave under his feet like the deck of the little steamer that had brought him from San Francisco.  He silently accepted the direction of the clerk's finger and entered the dining-room.</p>
				<p>The regular breakfast-hour at the Eureka House was past and the long table had been cleared off, except at the extreme end, where a little oasis of doubt-<pb n="200 Under the Redwood Tree."/>ful tablecloth dotted with dishes relieved the barren expanse of stained redwood.  Thither Gerald was marshalled by a communistic-looking waiter, who simplified the young gentleman's choice of viands by remarking, "There's beefsteak.""Nothing else?" inquired Ffrench, dropping into his place with a half-bow to a gentleman already seated opposite.</p>
				<p>"And coffee," said the waiter.</p>
				<p>"Beefsteak and coffee be it," answered Gerald, seeking vainly for a napkin.  Then, as he raised his eyes from the futile search, he became conscious that his fellow-guest was regarding him intently across the narrow table.</p>
				<p>"You'll know me again if you see me, my friend," thought young Ffrench, and then, being little troubled with false modesty, he returned the stare with interest.</p>
				<p>The other drummed lightly on the board with his knife and never wavered in his unwinking gaze.  He was a big man, with broad shoulders and mighty chest; and if his length of limb were at all proportionate to his apparent height as he sat, his stature should be almost gigantic.  A pair of blue eyes lighted up a shrewd, good-natured face, clean shaven except on the chin, whence depended a long auburn<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 201"/>beard.  His age might have been fifty or more, and his costume was the most elaborate that Gerald had yet seen in Eureka; for not only did the stranger boast a white collar and a neck-ribbon, but a frock coat of black cloth was buttoned across his broad breast.  There is something reassuring in a frock coat, especially on the outskirts of civilization.  If it is not worn by a gambler it is pretty sure to be the property of a self-respecting man, and the garment in question, though of country cut and too wide for its wearer, big as he was, had its effect on the young traveller.</p>
				<p>Finding this wordless communion of eyes growing intolerable, Gerald broke the silence with a casual remark suggested by the service of the hotel.</p>
				<p>"You come in by the Pelican, I suppose?" said the big man, wholly ignoring young Ffrench's observation, and settling down, with obvious enjoyment, to a system of cross-examination.</p>
				<p>Gerald admitted that he had so come.</p>
				<p>"A great steamer the Pelican, entirely," resumed the other.  "She was built for a blockade-runner, I suppose you know.""I didn't know," answered the younger man; "but I should say she was quick enough and uncomfortable enough for anything."<pb n="202 Under the Redwood Tree."/>"Comfort!" sniffed the big fellow, with an indescribable inflection of contempt.  "But I suppose ye're used to it down the coast.  You come from--eh?""I came from the bay yesterday," answered Gerald; and then, divining from the other's look of bewilderment that this description of the city of the Golden Gate might not be so all-sufficing in Northern California as in the southern counties, he added, "from San Francisco, you know.""Oh, ay, Frisco!  We don't know nothin' of any other bay here but Humboldt Bay, an' I was just wonderin' what kind o' fish you might be," said the stranger, breaking into a hearty jolly bass laugh that was pleasant to hear.  He threw back his great head and showed every one of an enviable set of teeth as he roared at his own little joke with a simplicity that was not without its attraction.  But at this moment the waiter entered, and the gentleman's mirth abruptly ceased.  He seemed to case himself in a visible armor of dignity, as if ashamed that he had so unbent, and he addressed the attendant in his gruffest tones.</p>
				<p>"That's the steak, eh?  Very well.  Now tell Partridge to bring my team around in twenty minutes."<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 203"/>"I will, Mr. Kearney," answered the waiter, slapping Gerald's portion down with a fine air of indifference and moving toward the door.</p>
				<p>"Say!" Ffrench called after him.  "Do you know if that clerk of yours has made up his mind if he can let me have something to drive to Tacara?"  The waiter evidently heard, for he looked back, but he left the room without condescending to reply.  Gerald turned to his plate with a muttered oath and was conscious of a growing desire to kick somebody--that cub of a waiter, for instance.  The coffee was vile and the steak utterly unmanageable.  Ffrench enviously watched his neighbor gnawing placidly through the tough, leathery mass and drinking the liquid libel without a wry face.  The young traveller was in anything but a good temper, and yet he could hardly help smiling as he noticed how comically the red beard wagged in unison with the regular motion of the big man's jaw.  Presently the latter paused a moment.</p>
				<p>"From Frisco, eh?" he remarked, slowly.  "Now I wouldn't wonder if ye come up after ducks.""Well, I didn't," retorted Gerald, snappishly.  "There are plenty of ducks there.""So there are, so there are," said Mr. Kearney, in the soothing tone he might have adopted to a frac-<pb n="204 Under the Redwood Tree."/>tious child; "but there ain't much except ducks here--ducks an' redwoods.""Perhaps I came after the redwoods," replied Gerald, amused in spite of himself at the other's manner.</p>
				<p>"Well, ye might.  Goin' lumberin', eh?""No, I'm a correspondent of the San Francisco 'Evening Mail,' and I've come here to write up the lumber industry.""So, a correspondent," Mr. Kearney pronounced the word as if the young journalist had been implicated in divorce proceedings,--"a correspondent; an' ye want to go to Tacara?""Yes, if I can get a team--or even an answer-- in this hole," replied Ffrench, his indignation boiling to the surface again.</p>
				<p>"Well, I'm goin', an' I'll drive ye over with pleasure.""No! will you really?  I'll be very much obliged," answered Gerald, eagerly.</p>
				<p>"No obligation in life," returned the big man.  "Ye're as welcome as the flowers in May; an' as I'm in the lumber business there myself, maybe I can give you a few points will come in handy."Ffrench expressed himself, as he felt, very grateful for this timely and unlooked-for kindness.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 205"/>"Finish your food, then, an' we'll start," said Kearney, whose empty plate bore witness that he practised what he preached.</p>
				<p>"Finish my food!" cried Gerald, hotly.  "I've had all the leather I want for one morning.""Ah, ye're used to comfort down the coast," remarked Mr. Kearney, meditatively, as he rose.  Gerald, though above middle height, felt like a pigmy beside the big man as the latter dropped a great hand familiarly on his shoulder and half steered, half pushed him toward the door.  Before they left the dining-room Kearney paused a moment.</p>
				<p>"I've had comforts, too, an' like 'em," he said.  "I was down to Frisco once an' dined at the Poodle Dog restoorant;" and with a chuckle at the recollection of a pleasant event in his life he passed out into the office.</p>
				<p>Gerald paused a moment to pay for the breakfast he had not eaten, and the warlike clerk remarked, with ill-dissembled delight, that no team could be had till evening--"maybe not then."Gerald did not attempt to disguise the satisfaction with which he retorted that if there were twenty teams he would not take one of them, and catching up his light valise he left the Eureka House.  The clerk looked after him with a vindic-<pb n="206 Under the Redwood Tree."/>tive expression, as if debating whether it was worth while to pursue and chastise the parting guest; but seeing the young man take his place in Mr. Kearney's carriage, he subsided behind the counter, conscious that there was no prospect of another stranger till the next arrival of the Pelican, three days hence.</p>
				<p>The stout road-wagon was drawn by a good-looking pair of American horses--in California so called as distinguished from mustangs--and they drove through Eureka at a rapid pace.  Mr. Kearney pulled up at the outskirts of the town in front of a small general store.</p>
				<p>"Catch on to them lines," he remarked, handing the reins to his companion; "I'll keep ye no time waiting."  And he swung his bulky form out of the wagon, which rebounded when relieved of his weight.  With a single gigantic stride he crossed the narrow sidewalk and vanished in the shop.  He reappeared after a brief interval with sundry packages in his hands and a small bundle of gaily painted toy balloons attached to his button-hole.</p>
				<p>"D'ye know what them are for?" he inquired as he set the team in motion.</p>
				<p>"I should say you have some little folks at home," answered Gerald, smiling.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 207"/>"I have a boy, sir," replied Kearney, beaming with delight.  "The cutest little beggar in the State o' California, an' that's sayin' a big word.  But sure what call have I to be talkin' about him?  Won't you see him yourself?"Gerald expressed the happiness he would feel at making the young gentleman's acquaintance.</p>
				<p>"I don't know: ye come from Frisco, an' ye see more down there nor we do; but I'd back him agen any lad o' his age an' weight under the canopy; and as for learnin'--but there!  Jimmy shall have every chance, so he shall.  It isn't up here among the redwoods that I'm going to raise him.""Fine country, though," remarked Gerald, looking around him.  They were clear of the town by this time, and on a steep, miry road, which skirted the shores of the bay, making frequent turns to avoid the long "tide-waters" which ran up to the very foot of the wooded hills bordering the track to the right--tall, abrupt hills, clothed to their summits with the gigantic redwoods that make the wealth of Humboldt County.</p>
				<p>It was a bright autumn morning, succeeding a week of almost incessant rain, and the atmosphere was so clear that the range of vision seemed limitless.  The air was calm and still, but up among the<pb n="208 Under the Redwood Tree."/>lofty forest tops there was an incessant trembling and rustling, as though a breeze were stirring there.  At every turn of the road a little pond disclosed itself: none of the deeply shaded hollows seemed to be without one--some far off, sending a gleam of silver through the columned forest, others almost at the roadside, and not a few communicating with the tide-water.  Wild-fowl of all kinds dotted the surface of these miniature lakes, or filled the air with their clangor as they rose, disturbed by the passing vehicle.  Gerald thought he had never seen such a woodland landscape, and grew enthusiastic in its praise.</p>
				<p>"It is fine," admitted Kearney, letting his eye rove a moment over forest and water, and then bringing it back to the matter in hand--the care of his team over a road-bed as rough as the channel of a mountain torrent.  "It is fine; but no place to rear a youngster, for all that.""Why not?" asked Ffrench.</p>
				<p>"No eddication--whoa! gently there, my beauties--an' I believe in eddication as I believe in lumber; there's nothin' in the world to beat it, if it's sound.""You're quite a philosopher, Mr. Kearney," remarked Gerald.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 209"/>The big man turned square round in his seat and looked his companion in the face.</p>
				<p>"Am I labelled, or what's the matter with me that ye know me?" he asked.</p>
				<p>"I heard the waiter at your most exclusive hotel address you by name," answered Gerald, laughing.</p>
				<p>"It's none o' my hotel; if it were--well, since you're so wise, won't you make me as wise as yourself?""Certainly," said the journalist.  "My name is Gerald Ffrench; very much at your service.""Ffrench!  Ye ought to be an Irishman by that," remarked Kearney.</p>
				<p>"Certainly; I was born in the county Westmeath," replied the young man.</p>
				<p>"D'ye mind that now?  Give me yer hand, Mr. Ffrench.  I'm always proud to meet a countryman in these out-o'-the-way parts.""You're from the old country, then?  I might have guessed as much.""Well, you might," returned the other.  "I'm from the townland o' Crogher, barony o' Magharafelth, county o' Limerick, an' my name is Michael James Kearney, an' I've never been ashamed of any o' them.  God save Ireland!"As the conclusion of this speech seemed to be in<pb n="210 Under the Redwood Tree."/>the nature of a doxology, Gerald did not feel called upon to make any reply, nor did his companion appear to expect one.  Indeed, his whole attention was for the moment occupied by his horses, which, startled at the sudden appearance of a small boy from behind one of the giant redwood trunks, began to plunge and rear in a rather alarming manner.</p>
				<p>"Stand still, Tom!  Whoa, Jerry!" cried Kearney, quickly bringing the frightened team under subjection.  Then he turned his attention to the immediate cause of the confusion.</p>
				<p>"Well, Jimmy, is that yerself!  Jump aboard, my boy, an' see what I've brought ye from Eureka.""Hurrah!  I see something anyway," answered Jimmy, whose sunburned features, beneath a shock of red hair, bore a curious resemblance to those of Mr. Kearney.  The child, whose age might have been seven or eight, climbed into the wagon with the agility of a monkey, and immediately grasped at the little plump of balloons, which, to Gerald's intense though secret amusement, had danced and floated above Mr. Kearney's head all the way from Eureka.</p>
				<p>"Have some behavior, Jimmy!" expostulated that gentleman in a bass whisper; "don't you see some one there?"<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 211"/>"Who is he, Dad?" inquired Jimmy, not the least abashed, and without taking the trouble to moderate his voice.  "'Tisn't the new ox-hand, is it?""No, it's a gentleman," answered his father; and then, turning to Gerald with a smile, half-deprecating, half-embarrassed, and wholly winning, he added, "Ye see, I told ye this was no place to raise a boy.""I think you've raised as fine a boy as I've clapped eyes on for many a day," rejoined Ffrench, heartily.  "You'll take me round to-morrow and show me where I can get a shot at a duck, won't you, Jimmy?""I will; an' if Dad will let me, I think I can find you a bear," cried the youngster, eagerly.</p>
				<p>This was more than Gerald had bargained for, but he contented himself with saying, "Oh, we'll look for the duck first;" and then added, as an after-thought, "but surely your father doesn't let you go where you'd meet such dangerous game?""Yes, he does, when he goes himself," answered young Nimrod.  "There isn't much he doesn't let me do, anyhow."There was something of apology in Mr. Kearney's tone as he hastened to explain his son's in-<pb n="212 Under the Redwood Tree."/>dependence by his invariable formula, "You see, this ain't no place to raise a boy, anyhow."The drive from Eureka had been long, though pleasant, and Gerald, arguing from the presence of the child that his destination was at hand, ventured to ask if it was much farther to Tacara.  He was emboldened by observing that the road, which had run through a sylvan solitude for many miles, now showed occasional signs of life--a logger's hut peeped here and there from among the trees, a wreath of smoke curled up from the hillside, and occasionally the bark of a dog broke the silence as the wagon passed.  But though not without circumstantial evidence of human habitation, the region seemed to Gerald as wild and desolate as ever.  Therefore he was the more surprised at Mr. Kearney's answer.</p>
				<p>"Tacara!  We passed through it ten minutes ago."Gerald gasped:"Those cabins and---""Yes, that's all the Tacara there is to it.""Where am I going then?""Home with me, I hope," said Mr. Kearney, heartily; "and if ye can enjoy yerself as I'd like to have ye, it's not very soon ye'll be wantin' to leave me."<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 213"/>Here was a hearty invitation, most opportunely extended.  Gerald was glad to accept it in the spirit in which it was offered, the more so as he had gathered that Mr. Kearney was the great lumber dealer of the district, and in fact the founder and maintainer of Tacara.  From no such point of vantage as Kearney's house could the journalist have hoped to study the staple of Humboldt.</p>
				<p>The team drew up before a spacious, substantial residence, built of wood, indeed, as was every house within a circuit of fifty miles, but well finished, with glazed windows and shingled roof, and offering plain evidence of comfort.  Ffrench attempted a few words of modest disclaimer before entering, but Mr. Kearney cut him short.</p>
				<p>"What nonsense ye're talking!  Ye've come out here to write up the redwoods; where better could ye go than into the thick o' them?  Ye'll see little and hear nothin' else; an' as for the trouble--what trouble?  It's glad I am to have a countryman an' a man of eddication to talk to; an' come in with ye without another word."Gerald found himself in a low, square hall, panelled in unstained timber of the country, and communicating with the rest of the house by doors of the same material.  The evening was chilly, and a fire <pb n="214 Under the Redwood Tree. "/>of logs was burning brightly.  The floor was covered with the skins of bear and of several species of wildcat.  Half a dozen rifles and shot-guns depended from a rack on the wall.  It was a comfortable apartment, and as the tired traveller seated himself and stretched his toes toward the welcome blaze he could not but acknowledge that his lines had fallen in pleasant places.</p>
				<p>Presently Jimmy reappeared.  He had insisted on accompanying the man who had driven the team to the stable, and he came back full of the exuberant life of youth and perfect health.  He was anxious to pilot Gerald forth before dark in search of a duck, but to this the young man would in no wise consent.  He preferred to sit by the fire and chat with his host, whom he found a singularly well-informed man, allowing for the limitations his secluded life had imposed.  With every detail of lumbering he was naturally familiar; and as this was the subject of conversation, Gerald was perhaps inclined to give him credit for more intelligence than he really possessed.  The correspondent's notebook was called into frequent use; he learned all the history of the great trees from the moment they were attacked with saws and axes on their lonely hillsides, till, having been dragged down by<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 215"/>yokes of oxen from their steep fastnesses, one log at a time, they were passed through the saw-mill on the level or floated down the nearest tide-water to the bay.</p>
				<p>Presently a substantial supper made its appearance--quail, wild duck, and the remains of a cold rabbit-pie, flanked by a large wheaten loaf and a jug of capital cider.  As soon as full justice had been done to these good things the host produced pipes and a bottle of whiskey, and over these the interview was concluded, to Gerald's pleasure and profit.</p>
				<p>Mr. Kearney as he rose invited the young man to visit the saw-mill on the following morning.</p>
				<p>"Ye'll have a walk through two, or, three mile o' redwood forest to get there," said the big man, "an' that's an experience worth havin'; 'an there ye can see how the cattle start some o' them big logs down to tide-water, an'--an'--in fact, ye'll' have lots to see, an I won't ask no better fun than showin' ye.  An' now good-night to ye, for the sun never sees me in bed any mornin' barrin' Sunday."Gerald's room was small but well ventilated arid scrupulously clean, and his bed was comfortable enough to wring from him a sigh at leaving it when his host thundered at the door and a gray misty light struggling through an eastern window<pb n="216 Under the Redwood Tree."/>showed that the day was at hand.  A hearty breakfast, accompanied by better coffee than young Ffrench had expected to find so far from civilization, occupied half an hour or so, and the sun had fairly risen when they stepped out under the redwoods.</p>
				<p>Gerald never forgot that morning walk.  The redwood forest has little or no underbrush, and the giant trunks rise sheer from the ground, unmarred by branch or twig, till, spreading out a hundred feet overhead, they meet to create the twilight of the grove.  The two men moved on amid a solitude that seemed unbroken since the world began; their steps were noiseless on the soft carpet of pine-needles, shed during uncounted ages from the giants above them.  The pillared vistas extended on all sides, sombre, silent, awe-inspiring.  Ffrench felt as if he were traversing the aisles of some cathedral, but incomparably older, vaster, grander than any built by man's hands.  A faint murmurous sound--a sound that seemed the accompaniment of silence--stole down from spreading boughs whose form and direction were lost in their own gloom and distance.  Despite the deep calm that weighed on all below, a breeze was stirring in the tops of the redwoods.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 217"/>Gerald roused himself with an impatient start.  He was growing sentimental, and stanzas of the &lt;poemTitle&gt;"Talking Oak"&lt;/poemTitle&gt; flitted vaguely through his mind and, strove to adapt themselves to those "giant boles," whose circumference he could scarce have measured in a dozen paces.  He looked at his companion.  Surely, in an experience of so many years, Mr. Kearney had outworn any emotions the forest was capable of inspiring in his broad breast.</p>
				<p>Mr. Kearney was crushing the withered needles beneath his massive tread, and tracking his way unhesitatingly through a labyrinth that to Gerald seemed trackless.  The black coat and the white collar that had been donned in honor of Eureka had given place to a stout flannel shirt, belted in at the waist; and the big man looked the better for the change--more solid and business-like.  He was glancing at the timber with a practical eye, occasionally pausing to rest his hand against one of the great trunks and to glance upward, as if to estimate how high it ran before branching.  The young journalist mentally compared him to a butcher appraising the value of a likely beef before he ordered it slaughtered.  Gerald loved fine timber, and he spoke with this feeling strong in him.</p>
				<p>"It seems a sin and a shame to cut down such<pb n="218 Under the Redwood Tree."/>trees," he said, with a touch of indignation in his voice.</p>
				<p>Kearney turned and looked at him.</p>
				<p>"Eh!  That's the way it seems to you, I don't doubt.  Look deeper, man, look deeper."Gerald stared at him in astonishment, but Mr. Kearney went on.</p>
				<p>"It's the destiny of every forest to be first cut down and then cut up for the use o' man.  Which had the biggest share of honor--the trees that was left standin' in Tarshish, or them that was brought to Jerusalem to build Solomon's temple?"Had Solomon himself in all his glory appeared in one of the dim arcades he could scarcely have surprised young Ffrench more than did this utterly unlooked-for reasoning in the man beside him.</p>
				<p>"For see here now," pursued Kearney, having paused a moment for the answer that did not come; "this tree's a-growin' here an' has been for a thousand years, maybe two; no man knows till she's cut an' shows the rings in her.  Down she comes to-morrow, we'll say, an' then what?  Maybe this wood will floor a ball-room, an' be touched by pretty feet you'd sooner kiss nor the Pope's; maybe it'll build the house that the President of the United States'll be born in; maybe a bit of<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 219"/>it'll be the soundin'-board of a pulpit, an' echo God's word preached to the savin' of who knows how many souls.  Isn't that better for it nor growin' an' rottin' an' shakin' pine-needles down on your head an' mine?"By this time Gerald had found his tongue.  "I had no idea you were so imaginative, Mr. Kearney," he said.</p>
				<p>"I dunno as it's all imagination," answered Kearney.  "Maybe it is: anyhow, it's possible, an' one thing's sure.  Let this timber stand, an' never a foot but an Injun's will pass under its shadow, cut it down, an ye fill the bay with sails, ye put bread in men's mouths, an' ye give me the means o' doin' what I'm bound to do--makin' a man o' Jimmy such as his father never had the chance to be.""You re right and I'm wrong," cried Gerald, somewhat-touched by the earnest note in his host's voice as he uttered the last words.  "They're fine trees; but down with them, and make a ladder for your boy to climb as high as you'd like to see him."Kearney grasped the young man's hand.  "Thank ye, Mr. Ffrench.  The boy'll climb, an' he can't go too high to please me.  His mother, God rest her! was the best woman in the world, an' maybe she's left some o' her nature behind her with Jimmy."<pb n="220 Under the Redwood Tree."/>"You have lost her, then?" said Gerald, softly.  Somehow he felt drawn very close to this kindhearted giant, and the dim, sibilant forest seemed a fitting place for an interchange of confidences.</p>
				<p>"Ay, lost is the word," replied Kearney, bitterly.  "She lies somewhere out yonder where no man will ever find her grave."  He waved his arm with a broad gesture in the direction of the ocean.  "Come on, Mr. Ffrench," he continued, without apparent pause.  "Ye've many a new sight to see to-day, an' the saw-mill's the first o' them."But when they reached the mill all was in confusion.  A new ox-hand, engaged the day before, had yoked a score of oxen to a great log and started it down the hill on which it had been felled, as is the manner of Pacific coast lumbering.  And an accident had befallen--not unheard of in its fashion, but generally horrible in its results.  The load had moved freely, the ground being slippery from recent rain, till a steep grade was reached.  Here it broke from control, and, gaining impetus as it slid down the hillside, the great log plunged among the oxen, killing and maiming more than half the team.</p>
				<p>So much Kearney heard with comparative composure.  It was an accident that had happened before, and was not always to be prevented by any<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 221"/>degree of care.  He expressed pity for the poor oxen, and bit his lip as he cast up the pecuniary loss.</p>
				<p>"Who did ye say was in charge?" he demanded presently.</p>
				<p>"The new ox-hand--Jarl, they called him.  He was a Norway man," answered the foreman.</p>
				<p>"An' how did ye come to set a new hand to move a log out of any such awkward place as Oorah Hill?" asked Kearney, angrily.</p>
				<p>"Wall, there weren't nobody else, and he was an old hand.  He'd been lumbering in Mendocino," explained the foreman.</p>
				<p>"An' where is he now?  Let me say a word to him," cried Kearney, his temper evidently getting the better of him.</p>
				<p>The foreman fell back a step and looked aghast.  "Why, didn't you understand?" he said.  "Jarl's dead; the log went over him and crushed him flatter'n a pancake."An instant change came over the big man's face.  "Holy St. Patrick! ye don't tell me," he gasped.  "The poor fellow, the poor fellow!  I wouldn't have had the like happen for--well, well, well!  Mr. Ffrench," he added, turning to the journalist, who had been an interested listener, "I've been twenty<pb n="222 Under the Redwood Tree."/>odd years in the lumber business, an' they call it a risky trade, but that's the first life I've ever lost among my men."Gerald attempted a few words of sympathy, but Kearney did not seem to hear them.  "Poor fellow, poor fellow!" he muttered.  "Well, every man's time's got to come sooner or later, but that's the end o' my luck."A low wailing cry, the voice of a child sobbing in the abandonment of sorrow, came from a shed on the right.  Kearney started as he heard it and glanced nervously around.</p>
				<p>"Whisht!  D'ye hear that?" he asked.  "Is there a child anywhere here, or is it the---"  He paused as the piteous sob again cut the silence.</p>
				<p>"It's the child, his little girl," said the foreman.  "She's been taking on dreadful, and no wonder.  He wasn't much to look at; but he was all she had, I reckon.""His child--whose?" asked Kearney.</p>
				<p>"Why, Jarl's, to be sure.  She come up with him from Mendocino."The big man sank down on a pile of shingles and buried his face in his hands,"My God, my God! this is too much," he murmured.  "Is it orphans I'm makin' in me ould<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 223"/>age?"  Then he started to his feet and dashed his hat to the ground with a sweeping gesture.  "To hell wid the oxen, to hell wid the lumber!" he shouted.  "As for the poor Norway boy, there's a good God above that'll look out for him, but I'm goin' to see that this child won't be left an orphan.  Where is she?"He strode forward and entered the shed, Gerald keeping close behind him.</p>
				<p>All that was mortal of the poor Norwegian lay on a long bench in one corner.  The shockingly mangled form was covered with a blanket, but the face was unscathed, aud [sic] death had been too sudden to leave much trace on the features.  It was a commonplace face of the Scandinavian type--the face of a peasant.</p>
				<p>A little girl, apparently about ten years old, was seated on a low stool at the dead man's side.  She had flung her blue-checked apron over her head, and was moaning and rocking herself to and fro in an agony of grief.  Very gently, very tenderly the big man stooped over the child and drew the apron away.  She glanced up and checked her sobs--at first from astonishment at the sight of this great bearded stranger, but she soon seemed to recognize, with the intuitive welcome sorrow has for sympathy, that she was looking at a friend.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="224 Under the Redwood Tree."/>"That's right," said Kearney, soothingly.  "Can ye speak English, honey?"The little mourner nodded.  Her blue eyes were brightening through their tears, and with an odd, womanly gesture she pushed the tangle of pale wheat-colored hair back from her temples.  Kearney went down on one knee and lifted the girl on the other.</p>
				<p>"What's yer name, darlint?" he whispered in a tone of indescribable gentleness.  Gerald could not but notice how much more strongly marked was the man's Irish accent since this trouble had come upon him.</p>
				<p>"Inga," answered the child.</p>
				<p>"Well, Inga, will ye come home wid me?  Ye can't do anythin' for poor dada," he hastened to add as her eyes turned toward the motionless figure on the bench.  "Poor dada's gone to heaven, an' all that's to be done for him here I'll do."He rose up to his full magnificent height, still holding the little girl in his arms and gathering her close to his breast.</p>
				<p>"Let me kiss my father," pleaded Inga.  Her speech had no trace of her foreign birth; indeed, it seemed likely she had first seen light in the New World.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 225"/>"Why not ?" said Mr. Kearney.  His voice still kept its caressing tone and he did not set the child down, but held her so that she could press her lips to those of the dead man.  Then he bent over the poor Norwegian and traced the sign of the cross on his forehead.</p>
				<p>"I dunno what was his way o' thinkin'," he whispered, "but he'll be none the worse o' that anyhow."Then, stooping his lofty head, Mr. Kearney passed the low door, crossed the mill-yard, where the hands all stopped to watch him, and so out into the dim, cool twilight of the forest, pressing the little orphan close to his breast.</p>
				<p>Gerald was surprised at the impressible nature which his host showed, and forebore for a day or two to trouble him with the questions suggested by the strange, new life of the lumber-camp.  But the big man's spirits recovered their tone very rapidly, and he exhibited the same mixture of boyish lightness, shrewd business thought, and queer, unexpected imagination that had captivated Ffrench in the first instance.  The young man found himself greatly taken with Kearney, and if he was anxious to use the lumberman in the interest of the San Francisco "Evening Mail," that purpose was distinctly second to his admiration for Mr. Kearney's<pb n="226 Under the Redwood Tree."/>character.  Meanwhile Kearney himself lived on his hard-working, uneventful life.  The introduction of little Inga into the household must have worked a greater change than Gerald was able to appreciate, but she was a quiet, unobtrusive child, and seemed content to spend her evenings looking up into Mr. Kearney's face with widely opened blue eyes, occasionally pushing back the masses of her pale golden hair with a quaint, old-fashioned gesture.  She and little Jimmy were wonderful friends, and there was always a note of compassionate tenderness in Mr. Kearney's voice when he spoke to her.  Probably he was more alive to the extent of the child's loss than she, better cared for now than ever in her life before, could possibly have been.</p>
				<p>So passed a few days, and Ffrench collected many facts of interest to the lumber trade, and shot several ducks and quail and saw a black bear.  He was fond of wandering in the gloom of the redwood forest with no companions but the children; and the strange, still atmosphere of the place, with the mysterious rustle of that ever-present breeze overhead, seemed to have a soothing effect even on Master Jimmy's effervescent spirits.  As for Inga, whether it was due to her recent loss or was natural to her, she was always a quiet child.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 227"/>The day after her father's funeral the little girl was even more silent than usual.  She sat apart, weeping in corners, with her head in her hands and her tangled hair dropping unheeded over her face.  Mr. Kearney checked Jimmy's rude play several times out of consideration to Inga's feelings, and the child soon retired, complaining of a headache.</p>
				<p>The next morning Gerald, whose hours had ceased to be so early as those of the rest of the household, came upon Mr. Kearney, equipped in black coat and white collar, climbing into his wagon.</p>
				<p>"Hullo!  Where away now?" asked the young man.</p>
				<p>"I'm goin' into Eureka," answered Kearney.  "I'd ask ye to take a seat, only I've some one to bring back wid me.  I'm goin' after the doctor.""Is there any one ill?" inquired Gerald.</p>
				<p>"N--no," said Kearney, slowly.  "Anyway, I want the doctor to tell me whether there is or no.  Inga was complainin' of a headache last night, an' she has a sore throat this mornin'.  Get up, Tom; go along, Jerry!"  And he drove off.</p>
				<p>"Decidedly Kearney means to do his duty by the orphan," reflected Gerald, as he strolled under the redwoods.  "It's well for her that it was in the employ of a man like that her father lost his life."<pb n="228 Under the Redwood Tree."/>Mr. Kearney returned with the doctor in the afternoon, and Gerald, arriving late from the ponds with a good bag of wild ducks, perceived that something was amiss at the house.  Little Jimmy, in evident spirits, was coming out of the door, followed by his father.  The latter carried a small bag and an armful of blankets.</p>
				<p>In a few words Mr. Kearney explained the state of affairs.  Inga had scarlet fever, and it was thought better that Jimmy should sleep at the mill for the present.</p>
				<p>"Is she very ill?" inquired Ffrench.</p>
				<p>"No," answered Kearney.  "The doctor says it's a very mild case.""Where did she catch it?" asked the young man.</p>
				<p>"Nobody knows.  Down in Mendocino, where they come from, I suppose," answered the lumber dealer.  "The doctor says it's a week, maybe two, since she was where the infection was."Kearney looked pale and worried, but Master Jimmy, to whom the idea of sleeping at the mill had all the attraction of a picnic, seemed much elated.</p>
				<p>Gerald turned, and accompanied them through the darkening shades of the forest.</p>
				<p>"It's foolish I am, maybe," remarked Mr. Kearney as he walked home with Gerald after seeing<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 229"/>the boy made comfortable for the night, "but I can't help it.  Sure Jimmy's all I have, an' I think the world o' him; but this is a poor place to rear a lad."Gerald represented that Jimmy would be far more exposed to infection in a city or in a great school than in a retired place like Tacara, but the father interrupted impatiently.</p>
				<p>"It's not that I'm thinkin' of.  We've took him away from the fever time enough, please God.  It's not that; it's his eddication.  D' ye know, Mr. Ffrench, that with a fair start that boy has a better chance in life than I had--ay, or you, for all your Trinity College breeding?""How so?" asked Gerald.</p>
				<p>"Because he was born in that house there under the redwoods," said the elder man proudly; "because he was born a citizen of the sovereign State of California, and is eligible to be President of the United States, or will be in thirty-three years time."Gerald forebore to remind the ambitious father that many thousands are born every year with the same eligibility, and Mr. Kearney repeated the word several times, rolling them on his tongue as if he savored them.</p>
				<p>"President of the United States!  And why not?  Isn't he born eligible?"<pb n="230 Under the Redwood Tree."/>Little Inga made a good recovery.  She was to all appearance a delicate child, yet the disease seemed to have taken no hold of her, and yielded quickly to Dr. Granby's skilful treatment.  But the very day the orphan was officially pronounced convalescent Gerald met his host in the woods near the saw-mill, wandering bareheaded, tossing his arms aloft in extravagant gesticulation, and evidently a prey to the wildest excitement.</p>
				<p>"Oh, don't talk to me, don't talk to me!" moaned the distracted man.  "Jimmy's got the faver.""No," said Gerald.  "Oh, don't say that, Mr. Kearney.  Are you sure?""The doctor's wid him now.  He sent me out because I couldn't rest aisy."Knowing how the poor fellow was wrapped up in his boy, Ffrench was fully able to appreciate his anxiety.  The young man did his best to console and cheer his friend, and urged Jimmy's strong constitution and healthy life, but the father shook his head.</p>
				<p>"It's the strongest that have it the worst.  Look at that donny slip of a girl beyant, an' how she went through wid it."Ffrench urged that this was hopeful, since the disease would seem to be mild in type; but Kearney could take little comfort from this argument.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 231"/>"We'll see, we'll see," he said, and presently re-entered the mill.  Gerald did not meet him again that day.</p>
				<p>Poor Kearney's worst fears were realized.  The infection that had touched the delicate girl so lightly laid firm hold on the sturdy lad, and day by day he grew worse.  Dr. Granby, an old friend of the lumber dealer, almost lived at Tacara, and exhausted all that science could do in behalf of the little sufferer.  All in vain!  After an illness of five days Jimmy died about eleven o'clock on Monday morning.</p>
				<p>All work had been suspended at the mill during the child's sickness, for it had been considered inexpedient to move him back to the house, and the noise of the great saws would have disturbed him.  Gerald, who had done his share in nursing the little patient, was with him at the last, and so, of course, was his father, who had scarcely left the bedside or closed an eye during those five weary days.  The old man--he had begun to show his years since Jimmy sickened--was holding the sufferer's hand and talking in a strain of soothing childish babble, when the doctor stepped forward and drew him away from the bedside.  He followed his friend unresistingly, supposing that Dr. Granby had some<pb n="232 Under the Redwood Tree."/>direction to give, but happening to glance back he realized the great change that had come upon the face of his boy.  Then his grief had vent--passionate, unrestrained, violent.  The whole nature of the man seemed altered.  Gerald had known him as a decorous, kindly gentleman; he saw him now as a savage.  Leaping back he seized the doctor by the collar and pinned him with gigantic force against the wall.</p>
				<p>"Answer me, ye thafe, answer me before I shake the life out of ye!  Why did ye kill me boy?"Gerald sprung forward to the assistance of Dr. Granby, who really seemed for the moment in personal peril, but the doctor was equal to the occasion.  Looking the frenzied man squarely in the eye, he said:"Aren't you ashamed of yourself, Michael Kearney, to show your black passion in the presence of the dead?  I did my best for your boy, and you know it."The other relaxed his hold and glanced again at the bed.  He pushed the doctor aside and flung himself across the little corpse with a howl of anguish that sounded scarcely human.</p>
				<p>"Ah, Jimmy, me darlint, me beautiful boy--why did ye die, why did ye die?  Ochone, ochone an' wirasthru! where was ever the like o' ye--so bould, so hearty, so full o' sperits?  It's only a few hours<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 233"/>that ye were runnin' around wid twice the life in ye that ever I had--an' ye so young, so clever, an' born wid such a grand start!  Ah, why did ye die, why did ye die?</p>
				<p>Inexpressibly pained and shocked, Gerald tiptoed over to the doctor.  The stricken father was still lying across the bed, and his loud lamentations sank into inarticulate moaning.</p>
				<p>"Hadn't we better get him away?" asked the young man below his breath.</p>
				<p>The doctor shook his head.  "Impossible," he replied.  "We must wait till this paroxysm exhausts itself.  I have seen him so before--when his wife was drowned.""Poor fellow!" murmured Ffrench,"He got over it before and he will get over it again," said the doctor, "though, to be sure, he had the boy then and he has no one now.  I am very fond of Mike Kearney.  He has a noble heart, but at times like these he appears at his worst.  Civilization and education came to him rather late in life, I fancy, and when such a grief stirs him the depths of his nature come to the surface--the nature of a barbarian, almost of an animal."Again the powerful voice rose in wild and purposeless lamentation.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="234 Under the Redwood Tree."/>"All I had--God help me--all the life that was left me, an' he lyin' there like a log.  What have I done that the like should come to me?  Now it may go, but divil a prayer will I ever say; for what have I to pray for?  Divil resave the kind word or kind thought will I ever give to anyone.  The whole world may go to hell for me."He rose from the bed and drew himself up to his full height.  His face was very pale, and every feature was working with emotion.  He seemed to have aged ten years in the few days that had elapsed since Gerald met him.</p>
				<p>The doctor came to his side.  "Mr. Kearney," he said, "you had better go home and take a little rest.  I will walk down to the house with you.""Home!" thundered Kearney; "what sort of a home have I?  Why should I go to the house when it's here me little Jimmy is lyin' an' a stranger's brat below there in his place?  Ay, but I will go; she killed him--it's herself brought the death to him.  Begorra, I will go home, if it's only to throw Jimmy's murderer out of it."He stepped to the bedside and bent over the child's form.  "Good-by to ye, Jimmy, me darlint," he whispered in a tone of infinite tenderness, "though it's little use kissin' cowld clay.  Come,<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 235"/>boys; I'm goin' home," he added, turning from the bed.</p>
				<p>A woman had been hired to act as nurse during the boy's illness.  Terrified by Kearney's extravagant grief, she had been cowering in a corner of the room.  She now came forward, as the men left the place, and busied herself in bestowing the last attentions that little Jimmy would ever need at human hands.</p>
				<p>Through the dim aisles of the redwood forest, over the soft, thick carpet of withered pine-needles, under the giant branches murmuring their eternal monotone, the three men passed to the lonely house by the tide-water.  Kearney was a little in advance, tossing his arms, shaking his head, gesticulating wildly, and muttering a broken jargon, half English, half Irish, that mingled discordantly with the rustle of the passionless pines.  Gerald thought that grief had crazed the poor fellow, but suddenly he turned and addressed the young man, rationally enough, though in an unexpected manner.</p>
				<p>"Mr. Ffrench, I liked ye the first time I seen ye, an' I like ye yet, but ye see for yerself that ye bro't no luck to me.  'Twas the first day ye come here that Norway chap fell under the log--the only man ever I lost in five and twenty years' lumberin',<pb n="236 Under the Redwood Tree."/>an' nothin's gone right with me since.  It's all led up to one p'int, an' that is---"  His voice broke, but after a moment's pause he went on, controlling himself with a mighty effort:"I'll ax ye to go home, Mr. Ffrench--off down the coast where ye belong, or out o' Tacara anyhow.  In ten years' time, if I live that long, I'd like to see ye ag'in; but now I can't bear to look on your face.""Whatever you like, Mr. Kearney," answered Gerald.  "I had hoped to stay here and perhaps be of use to you in the first days of your trouble, in return for all your kindness to me, but if my presence is painful to you--""Ye'd betther go, ye'd betther go," said Kearney, huskily.  "Ye'll be goin' to Eureka to-day, doctor, I suppose; ye've done yer d---' [sic]  He checked himself.  "There's nothin' more for ye to do here, an' ye'll take the young man wid ye."They had just emerged from the shades of the great trees and were entering the clearing in which the house stood.  Kearney was a little in advance, when Gerald saw him abruptly stop and cover his face with his hands.  Little Inga was running from the door to meet them, and she went straight to the father with a loving inquiry for Jimmy.</p>
				<p>"Take her away, take her away," he muttered<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 237"/>hoarsely; "don't let me see her."  Then he faced round on the child, who shrank back, trembling at his white face and blazing eyes.  And' then with uplifted hand he cursed her.</p>
				<p>"For shame, Mr. Kearney, for shame!" cried Dr. Granby, springing forward.  "The little girl is not to blame.""Who said she was?" said Kearney.  "I wish she had done it a purpose, an' I'd 'a' had one moment's happiness while I was tearin' her to pieces.  But out she goes--the home she's brought sorrow to is no place for her; out she goes.  The world's big an' broad outside o' Tacara."Astounded at such words from lips that had never yet breathed aught for her but kindness, Inga crouched on the ground at the old man's feet.  As was her way in trouble, she had flung the little apron over her head and was weeping, as her heaving shoulders testified, but weeping silently.  Gerald stepped forward.</p>
				<p>"Mr. Kearney," he said, "when I saw how you took that poor orphan from her dead father's side, how you comforted her and made her future your care, I thought I had never seen so noble a deed so kindly and graciously done.  But now, sir, if you cast her off and break her little heart with your<pb n="238 Under the Redwood Tree."/>cruelty, I don't care who you are, I don't care what your grief may be--you are a brute."Moved by the child's piteous figure, Gerald spoke hotly, without weighing his words or taking much thought of their consequences.  As he ceased speaking he drew back a step, for Kearney's eye and manner were threatening, and the journalist looked for an immediate assault.  But the issue was otherwise.</p>
				<p>"Who's axin' to hurt the child?  Take her away, do what ye choose wid her, but ye might as well ax 'me to stare at the sun at noonday as bear the sight o' her.  I can't do it.  She hurts me eyes, she hurts me heart.  I'll tell ye what, Mr. Ffrench," and Kearney came to his side with eager step and an almost fawning manner--"can't ye take her back to Frisco wid ye?  Oh, don't think of the expense--I'll bear that, I'll provide for her for life, only don't ax me to see her.  Take her wid ye.  Sure there must be schools or the like down the coast where they'll take childher if they're well ped for it.  There is for boys, anyhow, for I had one in me mind for Jimmy--God help me, for Jimmy;" and the strong man fairly broke down, and covering his face with his hands, sobbed aloud.</p>
				<p>"Don't interfere with him, don't speak to him,"<pb n="Under the Redwood Tree. 239"/>said Dr. Granby; "that'll do him more good than anything else.  You go into the house and get your belongings together while I go round for the wagon.  We'll start for Eureka at once; and of course you'll take the child, as he says.""I don't know," murmured Gerald, helplessly.  "Such a charge is altogether out of my line.""You will take her to San Francisco and put her at a good school.  There your responsibility ends, for Kearney will certainly be as good as his word, and provide for her well."Before Ffrench could answer, Inga had come to his side and slipped her little hand into his.  The child had the faculty of making friends in her loneliness; and Gerald, with a puzzled sense of unfitness, accepted the trust.</p>
				<p>Kearney was lying on the ground, face downward, his whole frame shaken by emotion.  He seemed to be utterly regardless of what was passing; but as Gerald led the little waif toward the house, he raised his head.  "Ye needn't be afeard, Mr. Ffrench," he said.  "I'll do all that I said, an' I'll write to me agent in Frisco to settle it all."  Then turning to Inga, who had shrunk trembling to Ffrench's side at the first sound of Mr. Kearney's voice, he added: "Don't be afeard, you either,<pb n="240 Under the Redwood Tree."/>little girl.  I've no hard feelings left for ye at all, at all; only, God forgive ye, ye've broken me heart."These were the last words Gerald heard him speak.  When the sound of wheels announced the departure, Kearney raised his head for a moment and waved his hand in farewell; then he let his face sink on the ground again and lay as still as if sleeping.  The shadows of the redwoods were growing longer as the sun sank toward the west, but the house was still clothed in the brightness of the autumn afternoon.</p>
				<p>"He'll be better so," the doctor said as he urged the team up the steep track.  "An hour's sleep, let him get it how or where he can, will be worth much to his tired and tortured brain."Gerald looked back as the wagon reached a turn in the road.  The house was still visible, and the long, dark shadow of the redwood forest had crept closer to the prostrate man.  The doctor stood up and looked back.</p>
				<p>"He's certainly asleep," he observed.  "When the sun leaves him he'll wake because of the cold."Poor Kearney!  He would awake in time to see the shadow on his home.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
