<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main Document Type//EN"
"http://infomotions.com/alex/dtd/tei2.dtd">
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>George H. Jessop's Gerald Ffrench's Friends in electronic form</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Originally Prepared by </resp>
					<name>Erica Dillon</name>
				</respStmt>
				<principal>Matthew L. Jockers, Stanford University Department of English</principal>
				<sponsor>
					<name>Stanford University</name>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Stanford, California 94305</addrLine>
					</address>
				</sponsor>
				<funder>
					<name>Stanford Humanities Lab</name>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Stanford University, Stanford, California 94305</addrLine>
					</address>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Distributed by The Irish-American West Project of the Stanford Humanities Lab</name>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Stanford, California 94503</addrLine>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<p>This e-text is freely available for non-commercial purposes</p>
				</availability>
				<date>2003</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>Jessop, George H.  Gerald Ffrench’s Friends.  New York: Longmans, Green and Co.<note type="abstract"/>
						<name type="region">Pacific</name>
						<name type="country">United States</name>
						<name type="city">San Francisco</name>
						<name type="state">California</name>
						<name type="Demographic">Rural</name>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>This text was prepared for use in the Irish-American West project of the Stanford Humanities Lab at Stanford University. The two principal goals of this project are (A) to bring the wealth of western Irish–American literary and historical writing to the Internet in a scholarly project and (B) to counter the existing eastern bias in Irish-American scholarship, by providing an online collection of primary source material and scholarly articles devoted to exploring the works of western Irish-Americans.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p>Suspected errors in the text are marked with a "[sic]" but not corrected.</p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p>Hyphens that occur at the ends of lines have been removed, except in cases where it is possible the author intended the hyphen.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<titlePage>
				<docTitle>
					<titlePart type="main">GERALD FFRENCH'S FRIENDS</titlePart>
				</docTitle>
				<byline>By</byline>
				<docAuthor><name type="first">GEORGE</name><name type="middle">H.</name><name type="last">JESSOP</name></docAuthor>
				<docImprint>
					<publisher>LONGMANS, GREEN, &amp; CO.</publisher>
					<pubPlace>NEW YORK</pubPlace>
					<docDate>1889</docDate>
				</docImprint>
			</titlePage>
			<div type="legal">
				<p>COPYRIGHT, 1889</p>
			</div>
			<div type="other">
				<p>15 EAST SIXTEENTH STREETTROW'SPRINTING AND BOOKBINDING COMPANY,NEW YORK.GERALD FFRENCH'SFRIENDSBY THE SAME AUTHOR:JUDGE LYNCH: A Romance of the California Vineyards.CHECK AND COUNTERCHECK: A Tale of Twenty-five Hours.(With Brander Matthews.)</p>
			</div>
			<div type="preface">
				<p>PREFACE.MR. GERALD FFRENCH'S journalistic career on the Pacific Coast covered a period of five years--from 1873 to 1878.  In this time it was his fortune to meet a great many Irishmen, with several of whom he became more or less intimately associated.  The Irish colony in California is important both in numbers and influence, and Mr. Ffrench's situation offered unusual advantages for a study of the more prominent peculiarities of the members of that colony.  The purpose of these chapters is to depict a few of the most characteristic types of the native Celt of the original stock--as yet unmixed in blood, but modified by new surroundings and a different civilization.  All the incidents related in this book are based on fact, and several of them are mere transcripts from actual life, with no more material alteration than seemed necessary to throw the veil of fiction over the identity of the characters.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="dedication">
				<p>TOBRANDER MATTHEWSIN GRATEFUL ACKNOWLEDGMENT OF MUCH KIND ENCOURAGEMENT AND VALUABLE ADVICE</p>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div type="chapter" n="George H. Jessop's Gerald Ffrench's Friends in electronic form">
				<p>
					<pb n="1"/>
					<pb n="2"/>
					<pb n="3"/>MR. MARTIN DOYLE, Mr. Andrew Cummiskey, Mr. Peter O'Rourke, Mr. Frank Brady and Mr. James Foley were seated in the private snuggery behind Mr. Matthew McKeon's sample-room on Washington Street, San Francisco.  It was late in the evening of Thanksgiving Day, 1874, and these gentlemen had met by appointment to discuss a very serious and important matter of business.  The apartment was small and its atmosphere was changing into a pale blue haze.  This was due to Mr. McKeon's cigars, one of which was wielded by each of the party.  From the saloon outside muffled sounds of holiday revelry stole in, swelling into positive uproar when the host opened the door, which he did every ten or fifteen minutes, to put in his head to inquire if "the jintlemen wanted anything."  To each of these appeals Mr. Martin Doyle made the same reply: "Nothin', Mat, noth-<pb n="4 The Rise and Fall of"/>in'; we're here for business, not for dhrink."  And the door was closed again.</p>
				<p>The truth was that all five were patriots of the most advanced type, and had met to determine upon the best means of freeing old Ireland from the bloody and tyrannical yoke of the Saxon oppressor.  It is true that "opprissor" was the word used in their frequent repetition of this formula, but the meaning was the same.</p>
				<p>In spite of the periodical refusal of McKeon's offers of refreshment, the table round which they were seated was fairly furnished with drinkables; perhaps this circumstance emboldened them to decline further supplies.  Messrs. Cummiskey, Brady, O'Rourke, and Foley paid attention to a portly bottle of Kinahan's L L, the contents of which they qualified in varying proportions with hot water, lemon, and sugar.  Mr. Doyle's tastes had become so vitiated by long residence in America as to lead him to prefer simple Bourbon whiskey; but, this detail apart, he was as true an Irishman still as on the day, now some twenty-five years ago, when, a lank, ungainly boy, he had entered Tapscott's office in Liverpool and engaged passage for the land of promise.  Indeed, it was Mr. Doyle who had called the present meeting together.  <pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 5"/>By ten o'clock the bottles were almost empty, and the cigar smoke had grown so dense that the mild features of Robert Emmet, who stood in all the glory of green uniform and waved a feathered hat exultantly from an engraving above Mr. Foley's head, could scarcely be distinguished.  Mr. Martin Doyle's notable scheme had been thoroughly discussed in all its details, and the proud projector arose somewhat unsteadily.</p>
				<p>"Fri'nds and fellow-countrymen," he began, "the death-knell of Saxon opprission has nearly sthruck.  Ye can come in, Mat"--this to Mr. McKeon, whose head appeared in the doorway--"ye can come in; we've most finished, an' we'll be havin' a dock a dorrish prisintly.  Well, as I was sayin', the Saxon opprissor---""To hell wid him!" broke in Foley, impulsively, and the rest of the company contributed a deep-voiced "Amin!""Misther Foley, and jintlemen," expostulated the speaker, "I have the flure.  We're agreed, I belave, that the pin is mightier nor the sword.  All in favor of that proposition will signify their assint by sayin' 'Aye.'  Conthrary minded, 'No.'  The ayes have it, and it is so orthered.  Therefore, jintlemen, we bein' prisint here this night do agree each to con-<pb n="6 The Rise and Fall of"/>thribute the sum of wan hunthred dollars, bein' five hunthred dollars in all, to defray the immejit expinses of startin' a wakely journal, the same to be called 'The Irish Aigle.'"Enthusiastic cheers drowned the speaker's voice.  He smiled, answered a pantomimic suggestion of McKeon's with a nod, and, draining the glass which the host handed to him, proceeded.</p>
				<p>"We five jintlemen here prisint, havin' the cause of an opprissed people at heart, do hereby resolve ourselves into a thryumvirate to solicit further conthributions from local pathriots, an' such aid in the way of advertisements an' subscriptions as we may be able to secure.  All in favor of this plan will signify the same by sayin' 'Aye.' Conthrary minded, 'No.'  The ayes have it, and it is so orthered.  Mr. Foley, Mr. O'Rourke, Mr. Brady, Mr. Cummiskey, and me unworthy silf, as members of the Thryumvirate, will git to work.  Long life and success to 'The Irish Aigle!'"As soon as the toast had been duly honored, Mr. Cummiskey took McKeon aside and pointed out to him the immense advantage he would reap from advertising his saloon in the new organ.  The representation which appeared to have the most weight with the liquor dealer lay in these words:<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 7"/>"Ye see, Mike, the offices of 'The Aigle' will be only three dures from you and sivin from Jerry McManus.  Now, ye know yersilf pathriotism is dhry work, and McManus knows it too."On the strength of this argument the astute Mr. Cummiskey booked a ten-dollar "ad" on the spot, and laid the foundation of that generous rivalry between the two saloon keepers which afterward became such an important factor in the well-being of "The Irish Eagle."The preliminary work of engaging a suitable office and hiring type was undertaken by Mr. Doyle, and was executed, as the legend in his own shoe-store set forth, "with promptness and despatch."  Two weeks afterward the first number of the new paper was for sale on the news-stands, glorious with a rampant eagle flaunting a Celtic motto from its beak.  The reading matter was largely made up of patriotic poems and clippings from other journals of the same way of thinking, but the editorial page was original--thoroughly, unquestionably original.  The united wisdom of the Thryumvirate had been expended on that effort.  There breathed the fiery utterances of Cummiskey, the butter-seller; there sparkled the neat epigram of O'Rourke, the truck-man; there were set forth the lucid arguments of<pb n="8 The Rise and Fall of"/>Foley, the tanner; there the reader might trace the sportive fancies of Brady, the bookbinder; and the whole bore witness to the massive genius of Martin Doyle, the shoemaker.  It was a great number, and its appearance was duly celebrated at McKeon's by the Thryumvirate, resolved for the moment into a mutual admiration society.</p>
				<p>At this meeting a new arrangement was made.  The paper should be edited, not by the whole committee acting as a body, but by the individual members holding office in rotation.  The five issues succeeding the first came out in this way, and lost nothing in originality even if they suffered in variety.  Peter O'Rourke began the series and Frank Brady brought up the rear.  Each recurrent editor was thoroughly satisfied with himself, but felt hurt to see the line of policy he had projected during his week of office ruthlessly abandoned by his successor.  It became evident that something must be done in the interests of uniformity.  The paper was pulling five ways at once, and, doubtless for that reason, had so far failed to deal any really fatal blow at British institutions.  Everyone felt this, and the eyes of the nation were upon Mr. Martin Doyle.  That gentleman rose to the occasion, and called an extraordinary meeting of the Committee<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 9"/>of Stockholders.  The enterprise had been duly incorporated according to the laws of California, under the name of "The Eagle Publishing Company."  The session took place in McKeon's saloon, and Mr. Doyle laid the matter before his colleagues in a neat impromptu speech.</p>
				<p>"Ireland," he remarked, "has groaned for six hunthred years beneath the yoke of the Saxon opprissor."  Mr. Doyle's oratory had the merit of taking up his subject at the very beginning.  Having briefly called attention to the principal groans which had been uttered by the suffering island during the centuries referred to, the speaker proceeded.</p>
				<p>"At a pravious meetin' of this honorable body it was determined that the best and most immejitly practical way of rightin' the wrongs of our suffering counthry was to dissiminate them broadly through the world; to call on all Irishmen in ivery climate under heaven to organize an' be free, an' to paint the black behavior of the Saxon tyrant in the brightest colors.  Wid this object we started 'The Irish Aigle,' the first couple of numbers of which have already reached England and sthruck terror to the sowls of a bloody and sowlless aristocracy.  But, jintlemen, we cannot disguise from ourselves the fact that no tanjible result has yet been per-<pb n="10 The Rise and Fall of"/>juced, and this I atthribute to the followin' rason, namely, to wit: while we are all alike annymated by the same burnin' love of freedom, we differ in matters of daytail.  While wan advycates the sword, another is of opinyun that an open risin' would at prisint be primature.  We all belave in organization, but no two of us has the wan notion as to the manes and maning of organization.  Therefore the paper sez wan wake wan thing, and another wake another, which is confusin' to the ignorant pathriot; an' that many of our best pathriots is ignorant, it is not you, me fri'nds, nor me will deny.  The ignorance of the masses is another crime on the bloody bade-roll of Saxon opprission.  Therefore, jintlemen, what I propose is as follows, namely, to wit: that we do ingage a jintleman of scientific attainments an' practised litherary vocations, to idit this journal an' say for us what we have to say betther nor we can say it for ourselves, an' such a jintleman I have been fortunate enough to discover an' unearth.  He is an Irishman, av coorse; a native of the county Westmeath, an', what is more to our purpose, a graduate of Thrinity College, Dublin.  He is young, but sure Robert Emmet was young, an' he'll come all the ch'aper on that account; an' he is racently from the ould <pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 11"/>counthry, an' therefore posted in all the latest daytails of its sufferin's.  His name is Ffrench, wherefore we may assume that he is a near relative of the immortal liberathor, Daniel O'Connell.  Now, jintlemin, we can arrange the business part later; all I want to do now is to take the sinse of this Thryumvirate in the ingagin' of an iditor for 'The Irish Aigle.'  All in favor of that proposition will signify the same by sayin' 'Aye.' Conthrary minded, 'No.'  The ayes have it, an' it is so orthered."There could be no doubt as to the approval with which this speech was received.  "A great idea intirely," "Couldn't be betther," "A sthroke of janius," were a few of the phrases in which the Thryumvirate endorsed the proposal of its spokesman.  Mr. Doyle, with a brief "Ye'll excuse me, jintlemin," and a modest consciousness of having deserved well of his country, withdrew.</p>
				<p>"Ye done grand work wid your issue of the paper, Andy," remarked Mr. Foley, "it was raally great.""I thought it wasn't bad, Jim, till I seen yours," responded Mr. Cummiskey, "an' thin I seen what a man of native originality c'u'd do wid the subject;" and so, like hand and glove patriots as they were, each proceeded to exalt his neighbor and complacently to drink in such dews of applause as de-<pb n="12 The rise and Fall of"/>scended on himself, till Mr. Doyle returned and introduced Gerald Ffrench.</p>
				<p>"Mr. Ffrench, jintlemen," he said; "a man of rare scientific attainments and university eddication."  All rose, and one after another grasped Mr. Ffrench's hand.  This operation was conducted silently, and reminded Gerald of a chorus of conspirators in opera-bouffe.  As Mr. Foley, the last to advance, dropped the young man's fingers, he remarked in a husky whisper, and with a suggestion of emotion in his voice:"This is a great day for Ireland.""Ye're right, it is," said Mr. O'Rourke.  Then he stepped to the door and called: "Mountain dew, Mat, and bug juice for Mr. Doyle.  Ye can drink the ould stuff?" he added, turning to Gerald.  Gerald admitted that he could, and then the conversation languished.  All resumed their seats, and the ten eyes of the Thryumvirate were levelled at the young man.  He bore the scrutiny uneasily, and his color rose.  They were "taking stock" of him.</p>
				<p>Gerald Ffrench was about twenty-three, and a fair specimen of a class of young men of which the Silent Sister turns out several hundred every year.  At this time he had been in America some eight months; in San Francisco less than two.  He came<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 13"/>of a good old Irish family, and had received the younger son's portion of two thousand pounds immediately after his twenty-first birthday.  He had read a little for the bar, and did not like it; he had thought of entering the army, but did not quite fancy it; on the whole, it occurred to him that he could not do better than to try his fortune in the United States.  He left Ireland for New York, but did not travel direct.  He first visited London, and thence passed over to Paris.  He found the latter city very fascinating, and remained there some time.  Then, as it was so close at hand, he thought it a pity not to see the Vienna Exhibition, and he went to Vienna and saw it.  The young fellow, accustomed to deny himself nothing, and with more money in his pocket than he had ever possessed before, did not exercise a becoming frugality.  When he had had enough of Europe he sailed for America, and New York was scarcely less to his taste than the Old World capitals.  He lingered there for several months, but finding himself unappreciated, he started for California.  He selected the route by Panama, and treated the voyage over tropic seas as a veritable pleasure trip.  In San Francisco he remained, possibly because he had not money enough left to go farther.  It was not till he had changed<pb n="14 The Rise and Fall of"/>his last twenty-dollar piece, however, that he realized his position.  He had received all he was entitled to and had spent it.  That twenty dollars, represented by a fast-diminishing pile of silver, must be replaced by his own exertions.  For what was he fitted, this young man endowed with nothing but health, a good education, and a certain amount of superficial experience?  He did not know.  He wandered about the streets and envied the blacksmiths and the bricklayers.  He would willingly have bartered his education for a good trade.  Then he began to write for the papers, but speedily found that the qualifications which had won him an occasional medal for composition at Trinity College were of no value at all in the city department of a newspaper.  Again and again were his contributions rejected with the curt remark, "We've no room to print essays."  He offered to write editorials, but was laughed at, though he felt he could have amended the halting English of many of those oracular utterances.  His rounds of the journals entailed much wear of heart and of shoe-leather, and but little silver solace.  Still he made a few acquaintances, and it was one of these, an Irishman, and the city editor of an evening paper, who introduced him to Doyle as the very man for" The Irish Eagle."<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 15"/>Gerald had jumped at the idea eagerly, and had succeeded in impressing Mr. Doyle with a due sense of his attainments.  His eyes sank before those of the Thryumvirate, however.  A single question from any one of those shrewd-looking, middle-aged Irish men might prick the bubble and display him in his true colors--as a man who knew no more of the routine work necessary for a paper than he did of casting its type.  He might have reassured himself.  Not one was there who did not regard him as an incarnate battering-ram, built expressly to level the battlemented tyranny of England in the dust.</p>
				<p>McKeon entered with the refreshments.  "Will ye oblige us wid the last number of 'The Irish Aigle?'" said Mr. Doyle, solemnly.  Mr. Cummiskey on the right, Mr. Foley on the left, Mr. O'Rourke in front, and Mr. Brady from the rear, simultaneously offered one to their chairman.</p>
				<p>Gerald, who had been led to study the paper by the first hint of the honor in store for him, saw this and hurriedly restored his own copy to his pocket.  The action, however, had not passed unnoticed, and called forth an approving smile from the Thryumvirate.  Mr. Doyle took a paper from the man nearest him, and waved it in the air.  He was evidently loaded and primed for a speech.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="16 The Rise and Fall of"/>"By the unanimous vote of mesilf an' colleagues," he began, "you, Mr. Ffrench, are called to the iditorial chair of this journal.  The stipind will be siventeen dollars and a half a wake."  He paused to let his words have their due effect.  Gerald leaned back with a sigh of relief.  It would go hard but he could retain his position for one week at least, and $17.50 looked to him like boundless wealth.  The Thryumvirate was watching him.  He felt that he was called on to say something.</p>
				<p>"Very liberal, most happy," he muttered; and then, as no one spoke and the silence became embarrassing, he ventured to add, "By the bye--'Irish Eagle,' you know.  Isn't it rather an odd name?""Why?" asked Mr. Doyle, severely; and Mr. Brady, who had not suggested it, hastened to add: "Maybe Mr. Ffrench could think of a betther?"Thus appealed to, Mr. Ffrench, after some hesitation, thought that a more personal name--something like the "Fenian," or the--  He was interrupted by a very tempest of opposition, and sat appalled at the fury of the storm he had called forth.</p>
				<p>"Fenian!"  "The dhirty rats!"  "The cowardly time-servers!"  "They're the curse of Ireland!"  Such were the exclamations that broke from the<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 17"/>group; but presently Mr. Doyle's voice rose in connected statement, dominating the confusion.</p>
				<p>"Misther Ffrench," he said, "I'd have ye to know that this organization is thorough.  We are no advycates of half-measures, and we propose to free Ireland, if we have to swim in blood to do it.  We are advanced Nationalists; we're far beyant the Fenians!  We say, 'Burn London,' 'Burn Liverpool,' 'Import cholera germs into Dublin Castle!' 'Blow up Windsor Castle!' 'Put to the sword the Houses of Parleymint'--ay, Irish mimbers and all, for they're no betther nor the rest, keepin' terms wid the bloody Saxon opprissor.  An' if an army of thim half-hearted Fenians was in it, I'd say blow thim up too; for they're no use, an' they're only palterin' wid the liberty of their counthry.  The day of Vinegar Hill is over.  It's not in the open field we'll honor thim by burnin' powdther, but undher their houses, undher their bridges, undher their public buildin's, an' that's the mission of 'The Irish Aigle."Gerald's astonishment that any class of Irishmen should be, as Mr. Doyle phrased it, more "advanced" than the Fenians, was swallowed up in amazement at this vigorous denunciation.  Like most young Irishmen of family and education he<pb n="18 The Rise and Fall of"/>had no sympathy whatever with the discontent of the peasantry, and, indeed, he had only vaguely heard of its existence before he came to America.  There, however, he had soon found, to his surprise, that from the mere fact of his being an Irishman, it was accepted as inevitable that he must hate England and everything English.  To the brother of the Conservative member, Edward Ffrench of Ballyvore Park, all this had seemed absurd enough, but he had let it pass without comment.  Now he found himself the central figure of a knot of men who talked bloodshed, and savored the word as they uttered it as though it were pleasant of taste--men who condemned war and battle-fields as not murderous enough, and who scouted as insufficiently villainous the most reckless organization he had ever heard of.  However, brief as had been his newspaper experience, he had learned that in journalism it is not seldom necessary to support one side openly while secretly holding the opposite tenets.  This he had come quite prepared to do, and this explosion, murder, and sudden death horrified him for a moment, till the very extravagance of the language brought its own comfort.  It was something to laugh at, not to revolt from, this little group of Irishmen proposing to wreck Great Britain from<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 19"/>the back-room of a San Francisco saloon; and then there was the $17.50 to think of.  He could not afford the luxury of high principles.  He would humor the joke, and write an article on blowing up the Thames, if they wanted it.  It would put money in his pocket and would not affect the Thames.</p>
				<p>"'With regard to the title of this journal," proceeded Doyle, waving the sheet, "it was silicted by me wid the approval of me colleagues here for the followin' raisons, namely, to wit: In the first place, the aigle is the emblem of America; for we are all American citizens, an' the counthry of our adoption is sicond in our affections only to that of our birth.  In the nixt place, the aigle is universally regarded as the burrud of freedom: I niver seen wan free mesilf, nor any other way than in a cage at Woodward's Garden beyant, but it is so rigarded.  This is 'The Irish Aigle;' high may she soar, an' long may she wave, an' deep be her talents in the black heart of the Saxon opprissor!"As soon as the wild applause which this sentiment evoked had subsided, Mr. O'Rourke rose.  "I propose," said he, "that we do now adjourn to the office, and install Mr. Ffrench in the iditorial chair, afther havin' inthrojuiced him to our foreman.  All<pb n="20 The Rise and Fall of"/>in favor of this proposition will signify the same by--But as all rose at once, it was not considered necessary to press the question to a vote.</p>
				<p>The editorial offices of "The Irish Eagle" occupied a single room at the top of a neighboring building.  The apartment was divided into two unequal portions by a board partition which did not reach to the ceiling.  In the outer room was the "plant" of the paper, consisting of a few cases of type, a roller for "pulling proofs," and half a dozen galleys.  There was an imposing-stone in the centre on which lay the forms just as they had come back from the printer.  A shaky old man was distributing type at one of the cases.  To him Gerald was duly presented.  "Mr. Ffrench, this is our foreman, Mr. Mike Carney.  Mike, this is the new iditor.  Come inside now, an' take charge;" and the whole party trooped into the sanctum.</p>
				<p>It was a small place, and seemed crowded when all had entered.  The furniture was scanty, consisting of a large table, a few office stools, and an arrangement of shelves against the partition for the accommodation of the unsold copies of the paper.  The table was littered with exchanges, and a volume of the poems of Thomas Davis lay on the floor.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34;"/>
					<pb n=" "/>
					<pb n="21"/>Mr. Doyle at once proceeded to business.  "The paper goes to priss Fridays," he said; "so ye see, this bein' Monday, ye have no time to lose.  How are ye off for copy, Mike?""Bad," answered the old printer.  "I've a little reprint, but no original matter at all.""We'll soon remedy that," said Gerald, cheerfully, with all the ready complaisance of a new hand.  "How many editorials do you generally have?""The more the merrier," said Mr. Cummiskey.  "Now, here's a good subject--'The Duty of the Day.'  I started it mesilf."  Gerald took a slip of manuscript from his hand.  It was written in pencil, and showed many corrections and interlineations.  It was not easy to read, but the new editor was in no position to neglect a hint.</p>
				<p>"Since MacMurragh flourished and died a traitor's death," so Mr. Cummiskey's contribution began, "there has been only the one duty for Irishmen, and that is vengeance."  Gerald paused in thought.  Who was MacMurragh, when had he flourished, and for what had he been hanged?  He wished that his new employers would not deal so much with obscure history.  He ventured an observation.</p>
				<p>"Undoubtedly the judicial murder of the unfortu-<pb n="22 The Rise and Fall of"/>nate MacMurragh calls for exemplary vengeance," he began.  A howl of execration interrupted him.  "The vilyan!  The thraitor!  The bloody agint of Saxon opprission!"  Evidently he was on the wrong track, and MacMurragh was anything but popular.  Gerald read the paragraph again, but it furnished no new light.  "Let me see," he said, tentatively; "what was the exact date of MacMurragh's--ah--ahem--death?""Elivin hundhred an' sivinty-sivin," shouted the Thryumvirate as one man.  Evidently MacMurragh belonged to a familiar historical epoch.  Gerald swallowed his surprise and merely remarked, "Ah, yes; I had a dispute with Professor Galbraith once on that very point.  He maintained that it was 1188, but I knew I was right.""Av coorse ye were," said Cummiskey, triumphantly.  "Sivinty-sivin, an' I'll maintain it agin the wurruld.""But," ventured Gerald, "as your article is on the duty of the day, don't you think we are going back rather far for an illustration?""Who the divil wants an illusthration?  It's an apoch: since Dermot MacMurragh--bad cess to him for that same--invited the English into Ireland, the counthry has nivir been quit of them.  Our duty<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 23"/>began that day, an' it hasn't changed since.  It's to kill ivery Englishman.""But to do that we must organize!" broke in Foley, springing on his favorite hobby at a bound; "organize an' be free!  That's the lesson to tach Irishmen to-day.  Make yer first article on organization, Mr. Ffrench.""With pleasure," said Gerald.  "Do you advocate any particular plan of organization?""Niver heed the plan.  Jist organize.  Whin Irishmen the wurruld over are wilded into a solid newclayus, thin the death-knell of Saxon opprission will be flashed abroad visible as the firmymint.  Thim's the very wurruds I stated in me own iditorial on the subject.""And a noble sintiment it is," said Mr. Doyle.</p>
				<p>"Nobly expressed," added Gerald, with a bow to Mr. Foley, thereby making that gentleman a friend for life.</p>
				<p>"Without wishin' to dictate to ye, Mr. Ffrench," remarked Doyle, after a brief pause, "I'll ax if ye know anything about dynamite.""I know it is a very powerful explosive," said Gerald, somewhat surprised, "and that it bids fair to take the place of all other preparations of nitroglycerine; but why?"<pb n="24 The Rise and Fall of"/>"Why?" repeated Mr. Doyle, in a deep voice.  "Because what Ireland needs is a powerful explosive; what England will get is a powerful explosive; that's the why, an' the chief mission of 'The Irish Aigle' is to bear powerful explosives to the sufferin' children of Erin, whether they cower beneath the glassears of the North or hide their woes under the thropics.  Come, jintlemin, that's all that's to be said.  We won't waste Mr. Ffrench's time any longer.  If ye want any information as to daytails, Mike Carney's the boy to give 'em ye.  Good day to ye, sir."  And the Thryumvirate filed out, leaving Gerald to collect such meaning as he might from the suggestions offered, and to condense them into an article which should teach the Irish race that the duty of the day was to organize dynamite.</p>
				<p>As time wore on, Gerald found himself face to face with a difficult task.  Having entered upon his duties with a tacit assumption of qualification, he felt obliged to live up to the character he had brought with him.  This prevented him from asking questions, at least directly, and he was constantly on the watch to pick up any unconsidered crumbs of knowledge that might fall in his way.  Being engaged as an expert, he could not learn as an apprentice, and yet the trivial details of even such an<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 25"/>office as that of "The Irish Eagle" were all new to him.  Mike Carney quickly fathomed his ignorance; but the old printer was good-natured, and not only kept the young man's secret, but made an elaborate pretence of belief in him.  This, of course, did not impose on Gerald, who reciprocated by always observing the fiction of Carney's sobriety, and the two got on very well together.  The editor learned something every day.  He soon came to distinguish between brevier and nonpareil, and he corrected his proofs without marking errors in the middle of the line as they happened to occur.  The Thryumvirate never suspected that an editor was being educated in the office, and the tangible results, as shown in the paper, were on the whole satisfactory.  Gerald always wrote at least three articles--one on organization, one on the manifest duty of Irishmen, and one on the theory and practice of dynamite.  These essays--for they were nothing less--abounded in long words and involved sentences, and in so far as they were incomprehensible to the patriots gave eminent satisfaction.  There could be no doubt of the new editor's ability and scholarly attainments.  But Doyle, who had all his life been accustomed to call a spade a spade, and an Englishman a bloody, brutalized robber, detected a certain weakness in the<pb n="26 The Rise and Fall of"/>academic phrases of the young collegian.  "Our hereditary enemies," "the despoilers of our land," etc., were to the Irishman far less direct and forcible than "spawn of the Saxon thraitor," or "red and pitiless monster," and Gerald's incapacity to realize the fact that an Englishman of moral life or good intentions is as much a creature of fancy as the unicorn, was at first rather trying to the patriot.  "But he's young," Doyle would remark by way of consolation, "and he hasn't been ground under the heel of the Saxon for over forty years as I have;" which, as the speaker had been a resident in the United States for a quarter of a century or thereabout, was quite likely to be the truth.</p>
				<p>But, all in all, Gerald suited them very well.  His editorial utterances took on more of the tone of his surroundings, and while still marshalling his verbal three-deckers for weekly action, he contrived now and then to throw a hot shot into the enemy's stronghold which delighted Doyle himself.  As for Foley, he had sworn by the young man from the first, and committed to memory long passages from the paper and recited them as opportunity offered, either in the bosom of his family or in McKeon's saloon.  Gerald soon began to enter with spirit into the game of vilifying the Saxon.  His common-<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 27"/>sense told him that no harm could result from the frothy nonsense, and he even took a mischievous pleasure in sending his brother a copy of the paper each week.  These, however, were addressed by the boy who wrote the wrappers.  He would not have identified himself with the sheet for twice his weekly salary.</p>
				<p>This same salary was the principal thorn in young Ffrench's bed of roses.  It was never paid.  He received money, to be sure, when his necessities urged him to press for it; but it was five dollars at one time, two at another--sometimes only fifty cents.  "When the paper gets upon its legs"--that was the only answer he received when he asked for a settlement.  There was no regular paymaster.  A request addressed to Mr. Doyle, who seemed the moving spirit, would call forth some such answer as," Money?  Av coorse; why not?  Can ye get along wid three dollars till to-morrow?"  But to-morrow, in the sense that Gerald looked for it, never came, and the Eagle Publishing Company sank deeper and deeper into his debt.</p>
				<p>Indeed, the paper was not prosperous.  Subscriptions fell into arrears; advertisers did not pay up.  McManus withdrew the card of his saloon altogether, on the ground that McKeon received all<pb n="28 The Rise and Fall of"/>the office patronage.  Carney was forthwith provided with a dollar and instructed to go out and invest it over McManus's bar.  This he did with scrupulous exactitude, but without result, unless his incapacity for work during the remainder of the day can be regarded as such.  The change of whiskey didn't agree with him, he said.  The following week McKeon reduced his advertisement.  "As long as McManus don't put his card in the paper," argued McKeon, "there's no sinse in my carryin' such a big 'ad.'"  Truly the "Eagle" had fallen on evil days.</p>
				<p>The fact was that, though all five of the original promoters were enthusiastic in their self-sought mission, they had not calculated upon, nor could they afford, the constant drain which the paper made upon them.  The office rent had to be paid; also the paper bill, and the weekly account for presswork.  Gerald and Carney were less imperative items in the expense account, and they had to wait accordingly.  The latter was not exacting: as long as he had a few "bits" to spend for liquor he seemed satisfied, and Gerald was at least making a living, such as it was, which was more than he had been able to do before.  His receipts may have averaged eight dollars a week, and he paid the bal-<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 29"/>ance willingly as the price of experience, confessing to himself that he was only an apprentice.</p>
				<p>An appeal to the wealthy Irishmen of the State, drawn up by Gerald and signed by the Thryumvirate, did not meet with conspicuous success.  There were few responses.  Mr. Patrick Byrne, the millionaire vine-grower of San Antonio County, sent a full-page advertisement of his "Golden Wine" marked for one insertion, and enclosed his check for two hundred and fifty dollars.  But this afforded only a momentary respite.  The paper bill took most of it; Gerald and Carney got ten dollars apiece.  Evidently things could not go on in this way.  "The Irish Eagle" was falling after a brief flight of some six months; it was slowly starving to death, and the first pound of dynamite was still unbought--the lowest step of Queen Victoria's throne was still unshattered.</p>
				<p>The end was not long deferred.  Gerald had just finished a handsome obituary notice of Mr. Phelim O'Gorman, a wealthy and prominent Irish resident who had died the day before, and Mike Carney was engaged in embalming the virtues of the deceased in cold type, when the Thryumvirate filed slowly into the editorial sanctum.  There was gloom on the brows of the patriots, and sorrow in their tones.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="30 The Rise and Fall of"/>Mr. Martin Doyle flung a small sheaf of advertising bills on the table.  "I can't collect the first cint," he said, with a groan.  The groan was echoed by his colleagues, and the editor looked serious and sympathetic.  He felt that this was not a moment to urge the question of his arrears, though during the last few weeks the sum had rolled up with startling rapidity.</p>
				<p>"They wouldn't organize," remarked Mr. Foley, despondently.  "They might have been free by this time if they'd only have organized.""They've niglected the clare duty of the day," said Mr. Cummiskey; "an' this is what it's brought us to."Mr. Doyle cleared his throat and rose, but evidently he did not feel equal to a rhetorical flight.  He only said:"At a meetin' of the stockholders of the Aigle Publishing Company, duly called an' convaned, it has been decided to discontinue the publication of 'The Irish Aigle' for the prisint."The announcement did not take Gerald wholly by surprise.  He had been looking for something of the sort.</p>
				<p>"And what about me?" he asked.</p>
				<p>"This issue will be printed an' published as<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 31"/>usual," said Mr. Doyle.  "It's all med up, anyhow, an' goes to priss to-night.  Afther that, Mr. Ffrench, the company will have no further call for yer services.""You owe me, as I suppose you are aware," began Gerald, but a storm of indignant protests drowned his voice.</p>
				<p>"Bad cess to the dhirty money!"  "Is it yer arrairs ye're thinkin' of whin the last hope of Irish indipindance is shattered in the dust?  "Aren't we all losers together?" and much more to the same effect.  Gerald waited till silence was restored, and then attempted to renew his appeal, but Mr. Doyle turned on him with oppressive dignity.</p>
				<p>"Ye're an Irishman, Mr. Ffrench, I belave?"Gerald admitted his nationality.</p>
				<p>"Very well, thin; it's proud an' thankful ye ought to be to make a thriflin' sacrifice for the land of yer burruth."  In moments of excitement or emotion Mr. Doyle's native Doric took on a richer tone.  "We've all med our sacrifices for the good cause.  Let this wan be yours."It was impossible for Gerald to explain to these perfervid patriots that their cause was not his--that all his sympathies, all his habits, bound him to the class they were aiming to overthrow.  Out of his<pb n="32 The Rise and Fall of"/>own mouth, or rather out of his own editorials, they would have convicted him as something more advanced than a Fenian; weak, indeed, in details of Irish history, but sound to the core on the great question of Irish liberty.  As he sat silent, vainly seeking some reply to this appeal to his patriotism, the Thryumvirate rose as one man and stalked from the room.</p>
				<p>From the case outside Mike Carney could be heard in a flood of song:The old printer was occasionally patriotic in his cups.  Gerald likened "The Irish Eagle" to dying swan, and realized that the end was near.  The following week was one of anxious inaction.  Ffrench vibrated between the office and McKeon's saloon; Carney confined himself strictly to the latter.  The Thryumvirate was seldom visible, and had it not been for a lucky accident, the editor of "The Irish Eagle" would have left that paper penniless.  A son of the late Mr. Phelim O'Gorman, pleased with the prominence given to his<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 33"/>father's virtues, and ignorant of the suspension of the paper, entered the office one day and found Gerald seated, like Marius, alone among the ruins.  The greater part of the edition was still unsold on the shelves, and when Mr. O'Gorman, Jr., asked for a few copies of the issue containing the notice of his father's death, the editor was prompt to accommodate him.  How many would he have?</p>
				<p>"How many can you spare me?""All you want," answered Gerald, briskly; and young O'Gorman purchased two hundred "Irish Eagles" at their regular retail price of ten cents apiece, and departed, leaving Gerald with a glow of gratitude in his heart and a twenty-dollar piece in his pocket.  He gave the defunct publishing company credit for this amount in his account for arrears.</p>
				<p>So fell "The Irish Eagle."Gerald Ffrench turned, his back on Washington Street and patriotism, and took himself, his talents, and his new experience to more sordid and businesslike journals.  He began to meet with more success.  He had learned habits of thrift and industrious routine, and he had imbibed a hearty hatred for Irish Nationalists and all their ways.  This last fact, however, was long unsuspected by Foley, Cummis-<pb n="34 The Rise and Fall of"/>key, and the others.  Mr. Martin Doyle, in particular, followed the career of the dethroned editor with deep interest, and considered him the shining light of the San Francisco press.  He used to point out Gerald with pride as one who "had worked hard and med his sacrifices for the cause."  He even invited the young man to attend a banquet of the Red Branch Knights on St. Patrick's day.  This invitation was declined, Gerald keenly recalling that immortal anniversary the year before, and his mortification when the Thryumvirate had insisted on having "The Irish Aigle' printed in green ink in honor of the day.  But that was all over now.  Mr. Ffrench had resumed his ancestral rôle as a "Saxon opprissor," though the scattered members of the Thryumvirate were slow to believe it.</p>
				<p>Conviction came on them at last, and with crushing force.  A certain noble earl was murdered in Ireland under circumstances of peculiar barbarity.  The victim was an old man, but he was also a large land-owner, and a howl of exultation at his death and execration of his memory went up from all the Irish societies.  An important election was at hand, and the city papers, willing to cater to the Irish vote, took up the cry.  The murdered earl was<pb n="&#34;The Irish Aigle.&#34; 35"/>branded as a tyrant, tales of harrowing evictions were invented and ascribed to him, and it was broadly hinted that he had received no more than his deserts.  This was more than Gerald Ffrench could stand.  He had known the old gentleman in former days, had dined at his table, and been "tipped" by him as a school-boy.  He sat down and wrote a letter to "The Golden Fleece," a weekly paper of wide circulation.  He took the earl's murder for a text, and told all he knew of the "wild justice of revenge" as executed by a blunderbuss from behind a hedge.  His heart guided his pen; he rang out a withering impeachment of the methods of his countrymen, and signed it with his full name.</p>
				<p>Mr. Martin Doyle, Mr. Andrew Cummiskey, Mr. Peter O'Rourke, Mr. Frank Brady, and Mr. James Foley met the same evening in the private snuggery behind Mr. Matthew McKeon's sample-room on Washington Street.  Mr. Doyle had a paper in his hand.</p>
				<p>"Have ye read it?" he asked.</p>
				<p>All admitted that they had.</p>
				<p>Mr. Doyle arose.  "Fri'nds an' fellow-counthrymin," he said, "this letther, difindin' the mimory of a black-hearted landlord; this letther, callin' the<pb n="36 The Rise and Fall of"/>noblest atthribute of our common humanity, the atthribute of rivinge, a crime, was written by Gerald Ffrench (groans).  Is he an Irishman?  ('No, no.')  I don't care a trauneen if he was born in Westmeath; I don't value it a kippeen if he was eddycated in Thrinity College; it's nothin' to me if he did idit 'The Irish Aigle' for filthy lukker; I here and now do brand and stiggatize him as a vile spawn of the Saxon opprissor.  All in favor thereof will signify the same by saying 'Aye.'  Conthrary-minded, 'No.'  The ayes have it, and it is so orthered."All recorded their votes of censure against Gerald, even Mr. Foley, who acquiesced with a shake of the head, adding, "But he had grand ideas intirely about organization."  Mr. Cummiskey took the suffrages of the party on the advisability of waylaying the culprit some night and giving him "the bating he had deserved," but this was overruled by Mr. Doyle.  "It's no use, boys," he said; "a diginerate Irishman like that wud think nothin' of app'aling to the police for purtection.  L'ave him alone.  Vingeance will overtake him, along wid the rest of the accursed Saxon brood." <pb n="37"/>
					<pb n="38"/>
					<pb n="39"/>PHILOSOPHERS tell us that life is a circle, but it is not often a circle that rounds and completes itself within the observation of a single spectator.  The mighty curve stretches forward and backward, but even in the case of our nearest friends it is but a limited zone that falls under our notice.</p>
				<p>Many a man, whose taste has led him to observe the varied figures that troop across his path, has with struck with some particular face; has watched it as it lingered; has recalled it as it vanished, and has turned back to the big magic-lantern show amid which we live with the feeling that here was an individuality worthy to be fixed in less fleeting colors.  But he cannot fix it.  The romancer may shape and pursue through a world of selected adventures the being he has created; but the observer<pb n="40 A Dissolving View of"/>of nature must be content with the brief glimpse afforded him, as his specimen is carried across a microscopic field of vision.  And yet this fellow-mortal, of whom we know so little, may be the hero of an epic, but in our hearing that epic will never be sung.  He may be the genius who is destined to shake the world, but he has passed beyond our ken ere he puts his hand to the lever.  We all have had peeps at possible prodigies, but before anything had occurred to justify our expectation the slide was withdrawn from the magic-lantern and the scene changed.</p>
				<p>It was in San Francisco, many years ago.  Then Big Bonanza shares went begging at twelve dollars apiece; since then they have commanded thousands; now they are back at tens again.  Poor men have become rich, rich men have become poor, and many who were the briskest have stepped aside out of the ranks.  Fifteen years have passed--and that is a long space on a Golden Gate calendar--since Gerald Ffrench was the editor of the "Irish Eagle," and filled many columns of that ephemeral sheet with essays on political dynamite.</p>
				<p>One morning he had a visitor.  There was a sharp knock on the open door of the office, and a voice inquired:<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 41"/>"Is this the office of the 'Irish Aigle'?"Gerald Ffrench glanced up and answered in the affirmative.  He was well used to callers in the editorial sanctum, patriots from the Pajaro Valley and other outlying districts, who never visited San Francisco without stopping at the "Aigle" to ascertain if, perchance, that mighty organ of the Pacific coast Nationalists had fulfilled its mission, and driven into the sea the British garrison in Ireland.  So, with a cheery tone as who should say, "England is all right as yet; but wait, we are not idle," Gerald bade the visitor enter.</p>
				<p>The latter came forward briskly, and dropped into the other chair.  Ffrench saw at a glance that this was no horny-fisted farmer from Pajaro, no politician from Sacramento, no ditcher from the tule lands.  He was an Irishman, of course--his presence in the "Eagle" office proved so much--but so far as Gerald could determine, he was a hitherto undescribed specimen.  He was a man of thirty-five or thereabouts, and his light-brown hair was long and dishevelled.  His face was as the face of a Nazarite, for no razor had ever touched it--a queer, small-featured face, masked by a thicket of whisker, and lit by bright, eager blue eyes.</p>
				<p>"Are you the iditor?"<pb n="42 A Dissolving View of"/>His brogue was distinct and unmistakable, and yet he spoke like an educated man.  Gerald was puzzled.  He simply bowed, and waited.</p>
				<p>"I've been a journalist, off an' on, for a good many years," the stranger went on.  "I'm an Irishman by burruth, though you mightn't think it, for I've been so much away from the ould counthry that wandering on a foreign strand has dulled the spache of fatherland.""I think I should have recognized you for a fellow-countryman," answered Gerald, suavely, "and I'm glad to meet a brother journalist, Mr.--Mr.---""Meagher, sir; me name is Meagher--Carrick Meagher.  It sounds like the name of a town, I know," he went on, apologetically; "an' so in wan sinse it is, but it's my name, too.""Have you been long in San Francisco, Mr. Meagher?" inquired Ffrench, as soon as he had introduced himself to his new acquaintance.</p>
				<p>"Not long, sir, not long.  I came up from Callao last wake in a sailing vessel.  Sartin sarcumstances," he went on, dropping his voice to more confidential tones, "not wholly unconnected wid a distinguished Peruvian family, compelled me to abandon a lukkerative position there, an' once more to clasp to my<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 43"/>bussum that chilling but familiar phantom, the wide, wide wurruld."Meagher was a very little man, but so tiny was the office and so expansive was the gesture that he used to emphasize his words, that a whole flock of unsold "Eagles" came fluttering down from the shelves where they roosted.  With a hasty apology he set about remedying the mischief he had caused.  As soon as he had finished he resumed his seat.</p>
				<p>"And now, Mr. Ffrench, I've come to apply for a position on the staff of the 'Irish Aigle.'"Gerald checked the smile that rose to his lips, and answered gravely.  He could not but notice that Meagher's garments, though whole and respectable, were worn with that indescribable touch of deprecation which goes with a single suit.  He had caught a touch of wistfulness in the question, as the little fellow put it, and he fancied that the blue eyes which peered so sharply out of the tangle of straw-colored hair might well owe some of their eagerness to hunger.--Yes, to hunger.  There is no city in our civilization where that torture of the destitute does not follow close on empty pockets.  Gerald realized that a few weeks ago he had not been many meals ahead himself, and that the "Irish Eagle" had intervened only just in time.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="44 A Dissolving View of"/>But was that patriotic bird endowed with power of wing to support a double burden?  Its editor might well doubt it.  He shook his head, and explained the position to Meagher.  The paper had been started quite recently by a little knot of patriots, and it was far from being a paying concern.  There was no staff--only one young editor and one old printer, and the salaries of both were already in arrears.  And then, by way of softening the blow--for that it was a blow the other's face clearly showed--Gerald applied the styptic generally recommended in California for all wounds of the mind and most wounds of the body; he invited his new acquaintance to come down to the corner and have a drink.</p>
				<p>McKeon's bar looked bright and cheerful, and McKeon's "free lunch" was spread with true Californian prodigality.  This lunch afforded as good a meal as a man need ask--soup, joint, vegetables, bread, and cheese; but it was "free" only in the sense that all who paid for liquid refreshments were welcome.  To the man without a "bit" in his pocket, it was only one degree more substantial than a feast of the Barmecide.  He could look, but he could not touch.  Mr. Carrick Meagher, however, in right of Gerald's invitation, quickly showed<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 45"/>that, brief as had been his sojourn in San Francisco, he was no novice in the mysteries of a free lunch.</p>
				<p>But appetite is intermittent, and Meagher, although by no means certain when such another opportunity might arise, was at last compelled to desist.  As the pair passed through the saloon, Mr. Martin Doyle accosted Gerald and proffered further hospitality, at the same time requesting the favor of an introduction to his "frind."Doyle was the president of the Eagle Publishing Company, and the most active of the governing body, which, though it consisted of himself and four friends, was generally known as the "Thryumvirate."  The introduction appeared to afford satisfaction both to Mr. Doyle and the stranger, and the former's invitation to "thry a drop o' somethin'" was promptly and cheerfully accepted.  Meagher, fortified by a hearty meal and exhilarated by a little whiskey, became quite talkative; but his talk was interesting even to Gerald, while it seemed to hold Mr. Doyle spellbound.  Very soon that gentleman suggested an adjournment to the back-room, where, with a bottle and glasses on the table and a big cigar between his lips, he listened with bated breath to Meagher's accounts of where he had been and what he had seen.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="46 A Dissolving View of"/>He was last from Peru, as he had told Gerald; he had been employed in some metallurgical works at Callao, and he assured his hearers that he was a first-class practical assayer and mineralogist.  He did not touch on the reason why he abandoned the position further than to remark, with his hand on his breast, "A leedy's name must be sacred; ye'll excuse me, gintlemen, if I pass that by."Gerald found it difficult to associate with the tender passion that diminutive figure and quizzical little monkey face, but he was polite enough to smother a laugh; while Mr. Doyle seemed to appreciate the situation, and to respect the other the more for his reticence.</p>
				<p>"To be sure, Mr. Meagher--to be sure," said honest Martin.  "I admire yer delicacy.  But tell me, where were ye afore ye went to Peru?""I was war correspondent for the Cork 'Examiner,' an' I was shut up in Paris the whole of the siege.""Do you tell me, now ?" asked the wondering Doyle.  At this time the great Franco-Prussian struggle was fresh in people's minds, for it was as long ago as '74 that the "Irish Eagle" flourished.</p>
				<p>"I was indade, an' a great deal of trouble I had.  No remittances from my paper could I get, an' many<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 47"/>a day I walked the boulevards hungry, wondering what was the best thing I could do.""An' what did ye do?" inquired Doyle, with unabated interest, while Gerald experienced a certain relief at learning that his new acquaintance's penniless predicament was nothing new to him.</p>
				<p>"Well, I enlisted as a mobile--that was four sous a day, an' a loaf of bread, and a shake-down in the Prince Eugene barracks."Gerald became grave again, as he realized that this device was impracticable in San Francisco.  At the same time, though Meagher was very glib with names, dates, and facts, the young editor began to suspect that the little man was romancing.</p>
				<p>"An' ye were a soldier!" cried Doyle, admiringly.  "Did ye iver kill a Proosian?""Never saw one that I know of till the day they entered the city.  No; I was more like a kind of policeman."At this modest statement Gerald's confidence rose again.  If the new-comer had been merely bragging, it would have been so easy to sacrifice hecatombs of foes.</p>
				<p>"Then I went a good deal wid the Irish colony--as many of them as were left," resumed Meagher.  "The name I bore was passport enough for that."<pb n="48 A Dissolving View of"/>"An' d'ye mane to say that ye're related to the great, the immortal pathriot, Thomas Francis Meagher?" inquired Doyle, in a tone of awe-stricken admiration that made Gerald a little uncomfortable.  A pretty end it would be to his hospitality if his resignation were to be desired the following day, to make room for this ready-tongued upstart!</p>
				<p>But Carrick's answer reassured him.  The Irishman might be a great boaster, but he was no liar, even when a lie was to his manifest advantage.</p>
				<p>"No, I don't think I am--I never could trace any relationship, anyhow; but you know yourself that nobody named Meagher need stand long knocking at an Irishman's dure.""In troth an' he needn't!" answered Doyle, with enthusiasm; but he cooled down as he perceived how this deft and destitute little stranger had entrapped him into an admission which it might be inconvenient to live up to and impossible to retract.</p>
				<p>Carrick saw his advantage, and drove it home.</p>
				<p>"Now, as I'm temporarily embarrassed--in fact, as I haven't a cint to me name," he began, and Doyle shivered as he prepared to dodge the impending loan--I've been thinking I might be able to do something for your paper."<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 49"/>Doyle breathed again.  This was a business proposition, which could be met on a business basis.</p>
				<p>"Well, I dunno," he said, slowly; "money's tight an' pathriots is poor.  The 'Aigle's' not to say on a payin' footin'.  Besides that, Mr. Ffrench here is fully aquil to all the wurruk that is to be done---""I don't doubt that at all," interrupted Carrick, with a queer little bow to Gerald, "an' I wouldn't presume to interfare wid him.  But I've been looking at the paper.  It wants some fresh departments.  What d'ye say to a Paris letter, now?""I dunno," answered Doyle, slowly.  "It sounds big and would look big---""To be sure it would--'From our own Paris correspondent;' an' it would trate of Irish affairs in the French capital.  Paris is full of pathriots.""Sure I know that," replied Doyle, feebly; "but I know no wan in Paris, an'---"" Ach, if that's all," interrupted Carrick, with an indescribable snort of triumph, "I'll write you a Paris letter ivery wake in your own office.  What's wanted for a letter?  That ye know the city you're writin' from an' the people in it.  Well, I know that--at laste the Irish colony, an' that's all you have to care about.  Then with the French papers to kape me up to the time--an' those I can get here--I'll<pb n="50 A Dissolving View of"/>turn ye out such a letter as any wan of your readers would swear came straight from the Boulevard des Italiens, av they'd ever happened to hear of such a place."Martin Doyle wavered visibly.  "An' how much would ye charge for the like?" he asked, at last.</p>
				<p>Carrick Meagher's sharp blue eyes shot a quick glance through their hairy foliage.  He was evidently settling in his own mind the maximum figure which the other might be expected to stand.  Nevertheless, the pause was scarcely noticeable, and the answer came unhesitatingly: "Three dollars a letter.""It's a go," answered Martin, knitting his brows ever so little.  "Now let's have wan more drink to wet the bargain, an' then get to wurruk."Carrick Meagher had gauged his man's financial stature almost to an inch.  If he had asked for five dollars, the negotiation would have ended then and there.  Martin Doyle had made up his mind to pay two dollars and a half per letter, but he had accepted the proposition, not considering fifty cents worth haggling over.</p>
				<p>So Carrick Meagher joined Gerald Ffrench on the staff of the "Irish Eagle."<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 51"/>FOR a few weeks the Paris letters appeared regularly.  They were remarkably clever, and, notwithstanding the circumstances under which they were written, had an air of reality which might have imposed on readers far more critical than any for whom they were intended.  By degrees, however, the correspondence grew intermittent, and finally ceased altogether.  Modest as was the price agreed upon, it was not always paid.  Indeed, any one of the "Thryumvirate" would much prefer to spend two dollars over McKeon's bar in treating a creditor than one dollar in paying him.</p>
				<p>Carrick Meagher, who was really a brilliant man, soon fell into the ways of the new city, and, without attaching himself to the staff of any particular newspaper, was able to earn a good income by contributing special articles to the various Sunday editions.  He had an easy, graphic style--not particularly polished, but always readable--and he was an expert on various subjects.  At one period of his wandering life he had followed the sea, and he could write with knowledge on ships and sailors.  He was a good practical metallurgist, and in California that is a trade which always commands its price.  But<pb n="52 A Dissolving View of"/>Carrick refused many tempting offers to resume his old profession, and contented himself with writing about it.  His was a vagrant genius, and the independent Bohemianism of the life he led suited him perfectly.</p>
				<p>Gerald and Meagher remained fast friends through it all.  Even after the latter had left the "Eagle," he was always ready to assist its editor with his advice, or even with his pen when work pressed, and this at a time when the briefest article he wrote commanded fifteen or twenty dollars.  In his moments of despondency he liked to entice Gerald away to some congenial haunt, and there discourse of his broken heart and the beautiful dark-eyed señorita who pined for him in Lima.</p>
				<p>"Pobre cita," he would sigh, with a languishing roll of his funny little head.  "The love that is sundered by seas an' years hath nothing to live on but thoughts an-' tears."Meagher was fond of interlarding his speech with scraps of verse, few of which Gerald could identify, while most of them were wholly unknown to him; so that he sometimes doubted whether to class these adornments of his friend's conversation as quotations or improvisations.</p>
				<p>The true story of Carrick's ill-fated love may<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 53"/>as well be set down here, though Ffrench did not learn it till long afterward--not till H. M. S. Tenedos cast anchor in San Francisco Bay, and Ffrench made the acquaintance of a certain lieutenant who had known Meagher in Callao.  The Irishman had seen the beautiful daughter of a high Peruvian official, as she drove past him in her carriage on the Paseo de los Descalzos.  His combustible heart had taken fire at once, and happening to meet her a few days afterward near his place of business in Callao, he assumed that the lady returned his affection, and had merely sought the port for an opportunity of seeing him.  In this conviction he had gone straight to Lima, called upon her father, and requested his daughter's hand.  The old gentleman did not look with favor on the suit, and when he had consulted the young girl, and ascertained that she had never heard of her presumptuous wooer, he secured Meagher's dismissal from the government smelting-works in which the young man was employed, and gave him to understand that his future prospects in Peru were by no means rosy.  Under these circumstances, Carrick found it advisable to depart, and he sailed for San Francisco without a single word or a second glance from the lady for whose sake he had borne so much.  But he always kept her memory<pb n="54 A Dissolving View of"/>green, and spoke of her--but never by name--with profound emotion.</p>
				<p>Gerald, knowing nothing of all this, sympathized with his friend as one crossed in love and despotically separated from all he held dear; while Carrick, his eyes suffused with tears or blazing with excitement, according to the mood that happened to be uppermost, would bewail his evil fortune or drown his sorrows in whiskey, and sing almost in the same breath "<songTitle>The Girl I left Behind Me</songTitle>," or a French drinking-song in praise of "la dive bouteille."The little fellow was as honest as the day, profusely generous, and endowed with a mind originally brilliant, and now stored, by reading and travel, with scraps of all sorts of unexpected and fascinating information.  These are the equipments of a very agreeable companion, and such Ffrench found him; but Meagher had his drawbacks.  He was absurdly theatrical in speech and manner, and this effect was enhanced rather than lessened by his diminutive stature--he was only just over five feet--and by the quizzical way his little face peeped out from his jungle of whisker, which nothing would persuade him either to trim or shave.</p>
				<p>But such peculiarities were of small moment.  Gerald soon ceased to notice them, and the two<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 55"/>spent most of their evenings in company.  Carrick's stories of travel and adventure, surprising as most of them were, established their truthfulness by various minute details which no repetition could vary.  He had endured many buffets from fortune.  Once he had been rich--he had located a gold mine in Mexico; every possible test had borne witness to its value, and he had almost concluded the sale of a half interest for one hundred thousand dollars.  But on returning to his location, accompanied by the experts whose report was to be final, he could not find the mine.  The whole face of the country had changed.  Carrick's claim had vanished, and the fortune he had so confidently reckoned upon lay buried beneath hundreds of feet of miry, pasty water.  A mud volcano had come between Carrick and competence.</p>
				<p>On another occasion he had been enlarging on the advantages of quick and straight shooting.  "Niver pull a pistol unless you mane to shoot," he said, "an' niver shoot unless you mane to kill."  This maxim he illustrated, as was his custom, by sundry leaves culled from the book of his experience.  Gerald ventured to doubt one specially "tall" feat of marksmanship.</p>
				<p>"If I had me own gun," answered Carrick.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="56 A Dissolving View of"/>"But sure I may as well have it as not.  I can afford it now.  Come along wid me."He led his friend to an adjacent pawnshop, and there regained possession of a revolver which he had been compelled to pledge in the early days of his destitution.  Ffrench witnessed half an hour's practice in a Kearney Street shooting-gallery, and acknowledged that Carrick had not exaggerated his skill with the weapon.</p>
				<p>The Irishman was fond of the theatre, and was positively greedy of Shakespearean performances.  He was always in his place before the curtain rose, and would sit through the five acts, motionless, silent, his eyes fixed on the stage.  He was very critical of the acting in his favorite masterpieces.  A popular tragedian arrived from the Eastern States, and gave, in the course of his repertory, two nights of <playTitle>Othello</playTitle>, supported by a local company.  Carrick was present, of course.  Mr. Kemble Scott played Iago the first evening, and Othello the second.  It so happened that after the latter performance Gerald and Carrick Meagher, in search of refreshment on their way home, wandered into the hotel which Mr. Kemble Scott patronized, and there found him.</p>
				<p>The actor had met Ffrench in New York during the latter's brief and, bright days of splendor.  He<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 57"/>remembered the young fellow, and greeted him warmly.  Gerald took occasion to present his friend, Mr. Meagher, and the great man acknowledged the introduction with a patronizing nod; but Carrick had small sense of reverence, and absolutely no discretion.  He had formed a decided opinion as to the merits of the two performances he had seen, and was as ready to discuss them with the person most concerned as he would have been to argue with Herr Wagner on the future of music, or to set right Professor Agassiz on a question of zoölogy.  With his wonted volubility Carrick began:"I'm glad to mate ye, Mr. Scott.  I saw your two impersonations this wake.""Indeed?" answered the actor, with the stereotyped smile which he reserved for the compliments to which he was well accustomed.  "I trust you do not consider your time thrown away?""Not complately," was Carrick's unexpected reply.  "There were plenty of good pints in your representation of Iago; but your conciption of the character of the dusky Moor was altogither erroneous."Mr. Kemble Scott was completely taken aback.</p>
				<p>"Indeed!" he stammered, at last.  "I trust, Mr.--Mr.--I beg your pardon, but your name escaped me."<pb n="58 A Dissolving View of"/>"There's me card, sir," responded Carrick, handing the other the bit of pasteboard.  "I know how hard it is to catch a name as yet untrumpeted of noisy fame, but for all that there's mine, and it's one I've no call to be ashamed of."By this time the tragedian had mastered--as he imagined--the script on the card.</p>
				<p>"Well, Mr. Meagre "--he began; but a bellow of indignant expostulation from Carrick cut him short:"You needn't thry to make fun of me nor of an honored name, becase I ventured to indulge in a bit of just criticism, which, av I'd known ye were so sinsitive, I'd have kept to meself.""I beg your pardon," interposed Mr. Kemble Scott, still polite, though by this time he was not certain he had not to do with a madman.  "I beg your pardon "--he scrutinized the card again--"but if you can pronounce M-e-a-g-h-e-r any way except Meagre---""Ye can pronounce it Mar, sir--same as if it rhymed wid 'star,' which you're fond of calling yourself.  Mar-r-r-r, av ye plaze, wid th' accint on the r, an' good-evenin' to you."With this Carrick stalked wrathfully from the room muttering as he went, "I'm wrong to be<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 59"/>vexed at the poor fellow, for av he can't read an' can't act it's a bad lookout for him in his ould age."Gerald lingered to offer the perplexed tragedian such explanations as were possible, and this ended the incident.  Meagher, however, absented himself from the theatre during the remainder of Mr. Kemble Scott's engagement.  Not even to see his favorite "<playTitle>Hamlet</playTitle>" would he condone the insult offered to his honored name.</p>
				<p>Shortly after this occurrence--the most lasting effect of which was to inspire in Carrick a settled distaste to American actors--the "Irish Eagle" folded its wings, and died without a struggle.  Meagher's advice and assistance now became invaluable to Gerald, and it was mainly owing to his friend that the young editor quickly secured humbler but more remunerative employment on the city press.</p>
				<p>FOR two years this oddly assorted friendship had subsisted, unbroken by even the most passing coolness, when a series of events led to a separation which Ffrench has almost ceased to hope will not prove permanent.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="60 A Dissolving View of"/>Gerald was attached to a stock and mining journal, and he frequently had occasion to lay under contribution his friend's expert knowledge of the subjects of which it treated.  He was accordingly always well pleased to see Carrick enter the office.</p>
				<p>Looking in one forenoon, as he often did, Meagher found Gerald seated, pen in hand, surrounded by specimens from an Arizona mine, which it was his immediate duty to panegyrize, or, in the language of the street, to "boom."The little man dropped into a seat, and heaved a deep sigh.</p>
				<p>"I dramed of my pobre cita last night," began Carrick.  "Ah, love for a year, a wake, a day, but alas for the love that loves alway.""Bother your pobre cita!" exclaimed Ffrench, impatiently.  In these moods, as he knew from experience, Carrick could seldom be reckoned on for counsel or assistance.</p>
				<p>"Ah, ye're young," said Meagher, not in the least offended; for he had at the service of his friends a temper which nothing could ruffle.</p>
				<p>Gerald silently wrote on.</p>
				<p>"What are ye doin'?  Erectin' a column?" inquired Carrick presently, when the stillness had lasted as long as his voluble nature could endure.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 61"/>"Trying to," replied Gerald, briefly.  "I've a notice of this mine to write up for to-morrow's paper.""This mine!" echoed Meagher, who had amused himself looking over the specimens at Gerald's elbow.  "These half-dozen mines, you should say.""Well, I shouldn't, smarty!" retorted Ffrench, who had been put out by the other's unseasonable love reminiscences.  "These are all from one mine.""Well, they're not; you can't fool me!" cried Carrick, with an awakening of professional interest.  "Wan, two, three, four--these specimens are faked.  They never came from wan mine, nor from ten miles from wan another.  It's a salted claim they're playin' on you, my poor Gerald.""Are you sure?" exclaimed Ffrench, dropping his pen.</p>
				<p>"Am I sure?" repeated Carrick, disdainfully.  "Do I know quartz from bitter spar, an' aither of them from metallic sulphides?  What's that?  Iron pyrites.  An' what's that?  Quartzose gangues.  An' will you dar' to tell me they all came out of the wan mine?  Go' long wid ye!""This is serious," said Gerald.  "I know Verplanck fancies this mine very much, and is going to put money in it.  Suppose we send for him."<pb n="62 A Dissolving View of"/>The office boy was despatched to summon the proprietor of the paper; and to him, in more temperate language, Carrick repeated the conclusion he had arrived at from his inspection of the specimens.</p>
				<p>Mr. Verplanck knew his informant well, and had often profited by his trained experience in matters of mineralogy.  The result of half an hour's conversation was an order to Gerald to tear up the article he had commenced, and begin another, denouncing the Ida mine as one of the biggest frauds that had ever been attempted on California Street.</p>
				<p>Mr. Verplanck's virtuous indignation was whetted by the fact that he had himself narrowly escaped becoming a victim, and he instructed Ffrench not to spare his superlatives.  Before the hour of next day's "Board" Ida's character was ruined.</p>
				<p>But no man can put a stop to a nefarious scheme whereby others expect to profit without making an enemy of someone.  The identity of the expert whose timely opinion had dealt a death-blow to this promising swindle was an open secret.  Meagher received profuse thanks and other more substantial expressions of gratitude from those whose money he had saved; but in certain quarters "curses not loud, but deep" were breathed on the "meddlesome little Irishman."  Unfortunately, among those<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 63"/>whose game he had spoiled were some who were accustomed to carry their irritation beyond the blasphemy point--men whose path it was dangerous to cross, and who were not wont to stick at trifles in pursuit either of profit or of vengeance.</p>
				<p>A few nights after the exposure of the "Ida swindle," as it was called, Gerald and Carrick attended a performance at the California Theatre.  They had supper afterward at the Poodle Dog, and it was long past midnight when they turned into Mission Street, on their way home; for the two inseparables roomed together.  Mission Street is a lonesome neighborhood after ten or eleven at night, and for block after block the friends had the sidewalk to themselves.</p>
				<p>Suddenly, as they passed the corner of Fifth Street, three men sprang out of a dark doorway.  Their feet echoed on the deserted pavement, and Gerald turned just in time to see a murderous bludgeon above his head.  Instinctively he raised his arm, and caught the blow as it descended.  The limb dropped to his side, numb and useless, and a feeling of faintness crept over him.  The loaded stick was poised for a second blow.  Gerald could only close his eyes and wait for it.  He could not stir from the spot; he could not even look to see<pb n="64 A Dissolving View of"/>how it fared with his companion.  There was no time to collect his thoughts or rally his energies.  Not three seconds had elapsed since he was walking gayly homeward, and now he stood, maimed and helpless, expecting nothing but death.</p>
				<p>One, two--sharp and clear rang out the twin reports of a revolver.  Ffrench opened his eyes.  The blow had not fallen, and the assassin lay writhing at his feet, clutching the heavy "knuckle duster" in his convulsive grasp.  In that moment the young journalist had tasted the bitterness of death.</p>
				<p>Carrick Meagher stepped across a second form, prostrate like the other, but motionless, and covered with his pistol a shadowy figure, still visible a dozen paces off, but fast vanishing in the darkness.  Gerald found his tongue.</p>
				<p>"Shoot, shoot!" he cried, in a trembling voice.  "He'll be out of sight!"Carrick appeared to deliberate a moment, and then returned the revolver to his overcoat pocket.</p>
				<p>"An' let him go," he said, unconcernedly.  "Niver shoot a man unless you've got to--that's always a good rule.  Let's look at these fellows, an' see what's the matter wid 'em."Matter enough.  One lay stone dead--shot<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 65"/>through the heart; and the other, even while they tried to raise him, breathed his last.</p>
				<p>As they laid the body down, Carrick noticed that Gerald did not use his left arm.</p>
				<p>"What's wrong wid ye?  Did he get in a lick at ye?""Yes; I stopped the first blow with my arm," answered Gerald.</p>
				<p>"An' a good job ye did," replied Carrick.  "I dodged the welt that fellow med at me, an' then I pulled iron.  Draw quick, shoot straight--them two mottoes, along wid a gun you can depind on, will carry a man across the wurruld."Gerald's reply, begun in a spirit of incoherent gratitude, was cut short by the sounds of footsteps rapidly approaching.  A policeman, attracted by the pistol-shots, came up at a run.  No doubt it was the fear of some such interruption that had impelled the assailants to choose, instead of firearms, the more silent and no less deadly bludgeon.</p>
				<p>"Here, what's the meaning of all this?" inquired the officer, as he halted.</p>
				<p>"It manes," answered Carrick, calmly, "that some of the smarties who tried to put up a job on the Ida have been trying to put up a job on my frind an' me, but I got the drop on them."<pb n="66 A Dissolving View of"/>Subsequent investigation proved that Meagher had correctly divined the motive of the attempt on his life at the very instant of its failure.</p>
				<p>Other officers were summoned, and the dead bodies were carried away.  The policeman who first appeared arrested Gerald and Carrick, and the party retraced its steps to the City Hall.</p>
				<p>Meagher was uneasy and inclined to be restive under restraint.</p>
				<p>"It's all very well for you to talk," he said, in answer to a reassuring remark of Gerald, "but I don't like it.  I spent a whole wake in the lock-up at Valparaiso by rason of a scrape that I had no more to do wid than Noah's grandfather; an' I tell ye I don't like it."But their detention was brief.  As newspaper men, both were well known at headquarters, and, late as was the hour, Mr. Verplanck and several substantial citizens soon appeared in response to an urgent message.  Bail was quickly arranged, and the friends found themselves at liberty.</p>
				<p>"What shall we do now?" inquired Gerald, as they quitted the gloomy building on Kearney Street.</p>
				<p>"Go home an' go to bed.  What else?" was Meagher's matter-of-fact reply.  "Sure it's after three o'clock."<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 67"/>Gerald expressed his willingness to retire, but positively refused to repeat the lonely tramp up Mission Street.  He wished to go to a hotel, but it was difficult to make Carrick understand his reasons.</p>
				<p>"Is it the other chap you're afraid of?" he asked.  "I'll bet you a dollar he's running yet.  Av he'd been any less scared, I'd have shot him too.""No, it isn't the other chap I'm afraid of, but have you no nerves, man?  Do you feel like passing the place where those fellows were shot down not two hours ago?""Sure they're gone," answered Carrick.  "Didn't you see them taken out o' that before we left it?"At last Gerald carried his point, and Meagher, grumbling at what he called "a sinseless bit of extravagance," secured accommodations at the Occidental.</p>
				<p>The inquest completely exonerated the two journalists, and its revelations made a three days' hero of Carrick Meagher, who, however, bore his honors uneasily.  As soon as the verdict of "justifiable homicide" had been rendered, he was at pains to ascertain that his bailers had been discharged from their bond.  Then he went straight to the Pacific<pb n="68 A Dissolving View of"/>Mail Company's offices and purchased a ticket for Hong Kong.</p>
				<p>"What do you want that for?" inquired the bewildered Gerald, when Meagher displayed his purchase.</p>
				<p>"I want it to go to China wid, an' that's where I'm going on the very first steamer, an' that's the day after to-morrow.""What for?" gasped Ffrench.</p>
				<p>"Well, several rasons.  I've been longer in 'Frisco than I've any business to stay in any wan town; then I've been over a good share of the wurruld, an' niver yet seen a Jap or a Chinaman on his native heath; an' there's another rason.""What is it?" inquired Gerald,"Well--niver mind what it is," answered Carrick.  "Isn't it enough that I'm blue-moulded for want of a bit of change?  Let that content you.""But it does not content me," urged his friend.  "You are doing well here; you're happy and comfortable---""Ah," sighed Meagher, "it's little ye know.  Pobre cita!""Well," pursued Ffrench, "she'll worry you just as much in China as she does here, and you won't have me to talk to.  Come, take hack your ticket--you<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 69"/>can get rid of it, I'm sure--and stay where you are.  You had no notion of this sudden flitting a week ago.""Well, I hadn't," admitted Carrick, with a burst of candor.  "It's this way, Gerald.  There's only wan thing in the wurruld I'm afraid of.  If they locked me up, I'd die or go out of my head, I couldn't stand it.""But why should they lock you up?  You have committed no crime, and a jury has exonerated you.""I haven't much confidence in a jury," answered Meagher.  "I saw too much of them in Ireland when I was a boy.  What odds what wan jury says?  Did you niver hear of a flaw in an indictment, an' isn't it full as aisy to find flaws in an acquittal?  No, I'll skip out to China while I'm free, an' while it won't cost Verplanck nor anyone else a cint, as it would av I had to be bailed again."Gerald lost patience.</p>
				<p>"Can't you understand?  The law says"--he began, but Meagher interrupted him:"What odds what the law says?  It's always sayin' wan thing an' manin' another.  I've no use for law; I niver had, an' I hate the sight of it.  I can't help it; I was born so.  I'd like a country<pb n="70 A Dissolving View of"/>where ivery man's hands had to keep his own head, an' where there were wild bastes an' divils instead of lawyers.  Day after to-morrow I'll sail for China, an' av ye'll come down an' see me off I'll take it kindly of you, Gerald."And on the day appointed he did sail.  Gerald, with many another friend, was on the wharf when the big steamer moved out, for the little Irishman had become both popular and famous.</p>
				<p>Ffrench's eyes grew misty as he watched the small familiar figure, till distance rendered it indistinguishable.  Then he turned slowly away, wondering if they two would ever meet again.  He put no faith in Carrick's promises to write, for he observed that the wanderer appeared to have left no correspondents behind him in the various lands he had visited.  Ffrench's misgivings were justified.  Many a mail came from the distant East, but never a line in the odd, sprawling handwriting which Carrick Meagher affected.</p>
				<p>Gerald has paid more than one visit to his Irish home since those "Bonanza Days of the Seventies;" he has made frequent sojourns in the Eastern States; but he has never met his quaint and brilliant friend.  He thinks of Carrick Meagher now as of a dissolving view of a very strange humanity;<pb n="Carrick Meagher. 71"/>coming out of the unexplored darkness, shining for a brief space with a fascinating lustre, and fading away again into unknowable obscurity.  The circle of their two lives touched only at a single point.</p>
				<p>Still Gerald cherishes the hope that he may see or hear of him again.  No strange and mysterious individuality can arise to defy speculation without bringing up in Ffrench's mind thoughts of the vagrant genius who ate and lived with him for two years in San Francisco.  When the young journalist read of the White Pasha, who had so wondrously appeared in the heart of Africa, he was seized with a wild idea that this might be his old friend.  For Gerald Ffrench is well convinced that this was no ordinary man, and that no commonplace fate awaits him.  Some day or another, in some strange and distant country, in some startling, unexpected way, Gerald looks to see written across the history of his time the eccentric signature of Carrick Meagher. <pb n="72"/>
					<pb n="73"/>
					<pb n="74"/>
					<pb n="75"/>THE party of sight-seers was more than an hour late for dinner, but that made no difference to mine host of the Pico House, who received it with smiles and would listen to no apologies.  The visitors secretly exchanged congratulations, for their appetites had lost nothing by the delay and they had the dining-room to themselves.  Mine host presided in person, since these were guests that he delighted to honor--representatives of all the leading papers of the Pacific Slope, each a living pen suggestive of boundless possibilities in the way of free advertising.  The last link had been welded in the chain connecting Los Angeles with the great world; the last rail of the new extension of the Southern Pacific Railroad had been laid; not twenty-four hours before, the first through train from San Francisco had steamed into the new station, and this baker's<pb n="76 At the Town of the"/>dozen of journalists had come down to write up the new road.  They were lingering to write up Los Angeles, and should not the Pico House receive its share of favorable mention?  Certainly it should, if unwearied hospitality and courteous attention on the proprietor's part could touch the hearts of newspaper men.</p>
				<p>A merry party they were--a few from Sacramento, San José, and Oakland, but the greater number from the Golden Gate.  The vineyards and orange groves of Southern California were new to them; they had been driving all day long through a semi-tropical fairy land; they were mostly young men, and as happy as school-boys out for a holiday.  Had the host but known, it needed not this capital dinner with its accompanying fusilade of champagne corks to keep them in humor.  Los Angeles was sure of a good notice.</p>
				<p>There is a limit to the appetite even of hungry "scribes."  The tables were cleared, cigars were lighted, and the conversation, which had died down to a dropping fire during the meal, flashed out brilliantly all along the line.  The host, who was a martyr to gout, after seeing that none of the elements for conviviality were wanting, limped off with the waiters, but lingered a moment at the door to<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 77"/>catch the last strain of the musical honors with which his health had been received.  Then Los Angeles was discussed with a fervor of praise that must have made the angelic ears of the pretty little city tingle.  The strangers from the North sought, from such of their number as might be supposed to possess it, information on all possible and impossible points--the climate, the neighborhood, the antiquities, the beauty of the women, and the character of the men.  And all thought that the pioneers of '49 had missed their opportunity when they had selected that sand-spit at the Golden Gate as the site of the metropolis of the Pacific Slope.</p>
				<p>Gerald Ffrench, the accredited representative of the San Francisco Evening Mail, felt his honors slipping from him.  All day long he had been the oracle of the quartette in his own particular carriage, and his decision on doubtful points had been accepted as final.  To be sure, he had never before been in Southern California, but he had read up exhaustively in preparation for the trip; and most Irishmen, particularly at six and twenty, are apt to consider their information, whether acquired at first or second hand, as something well worth having.  But now Graham Stokes, of the Golden Fleece, had quietly assumed a monopoly - of knowledge.  It<pb n="78 At the Town of the"/>could not be denied that Stokes had a personal acquaintance with the country, and had lived there for nearly two years, part of the time at Los Angeles and part at Santa Barbara.  He could speak Mexican-Spanish too, and if he had been infected by any of the raptures that thrilled the rest of the party, he had managed to keep the fact to himself.  Calmly and confidently, he confuted two or three of Gerald's book-made theories, and established himself as king of the company, reducing the younger man to silence and champagne.</p>
				<p>Graham Stokes was not popular among his brother journalists.  Perhaps they did not understand him.  In the first place, he appeared to have a greater command of money than was usual among Californian knights of the quill, and this was regarded as hardly respectable.  In the next place, he had never been known to spend a dollar on anyone but himself--a most damning count in the indictment.  Then, he dressed too well, and shaved every day, and wore gold eye-glasses.  He never touched wine or spirits in any form--a circumstance so unusual at that day and place as to furnish grave ground for the worst suspicions.  Nor could his abstinence be ascribed to any morbid conscientiousness, for there was an ugly story afloat that it was he who had led away poor<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 79"/>Doc. Brown the very day that esteemed member of the guild had obtained his envied detail on the Humboldt business, and had intoxicated him so grossly that the Summons superseded Brown and sent another man in his place.  And it was notorious that Graham Stokes had secured the coveted mission.  Here were grounds enough for unpopularity, without counting that he was a man of nearly forty, while most of his compeers were under thirty, and that he was very vain of his good looks, in a community which assuredly did not try to make the most of any favors of that kind which Heaven had granted its members.  Doc. Brown had characterized him, not in the heat of debate, but in a judicially weighed and calmly expressed opinion, as "a treacherous, slimy snob," and the description had been generally accepted as accurate.</p>
				<p>Still Graham Stokes had a manifest advantage in a gathering like the present.  Nobody liked him, but, as he was not generally understood, so he was generally feared; and he certainly knew more about the subject of immediate interest than did all the rest of the party put together.  As the information he furnished was merely of a nature to amuse curiosity and of no value for publication, he gave it freely.  On points of importance he exhibited a reserve<pb n="80 At the Town of the"/>which did not escape Frank Hale, of the Union, who whispered to Gerald Ffrench that he would back the Golden Fleece to print the best Los Angeles letter after all.  This was gall and wormwood to Gerald, but he contented himself with remarking that Stokes seemed in such an unusually giving mood to-night, that it would not be surprising if he ended by giving himself away.</p>
				<p>Meanwhile Mr. Stokes, finding his audience to his mind, was chatting quite amiably.  He had got on the subject of female beauty, always a favorite with him, and proceeded to fire the imagination of his hearers with glowing accounts of dark-eyed señoritas, olive of complexion and lustrous of tress, who had figured in the lighter passages of his life in the sunny South.  The man was as vain as a peacock, and as he caressed his stubby moustache and related his adventures in his peculiar falsetto voice, Gerald felt as though he would have made some personal sacrifice for the privilege of giving the speaker one good, hearty kick.</p>
				<p>"Here's a note for ye, Mr. Stokes," said a waiter, entering the room.  Mr. Stokes took the little folded paper with an accession of importance.  Its appearance proved that he had correspondents in the Town of the Queen of the Angels, and the man-<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 81"/>ner of its arrival showed that he, at least, was no stranger.  The waiter had accosted him by name.</p>
				<p>" How did it come?" he asked, leisurely opening the missive, which was without envelope or seal.</p>
				<p>"It come be hand, sor; more betoken be a very yallow hand," answered the waiter, with a grin.</p>
				<p>Mr. Stokes cast his eye over the paper and appeared both annoyed and perplexed.  "Why, it's two miles off," he muttered; "more!"  Then he glanced at his watch and fidgetted in his chair.  Finally he read the note again.  It was evidently of the briefest.</p>
				<p>The incident had already raised Graham Stokes several degrees in the estimation of his companions.  The message might be commonplace, but to their excited fancies it breathed of a moonlight tryst under the blossom-laden orange-boughs.  Graham's stories had given their thoughts a turn in that direction.  Conversation was suspended, and all waited to see what would come next.  The waiter stood, balanced on one foot, with his eyes fixed on the ceiling.  Apparently he was whistling softly to himself, but if so it was only the ghost of a tune, for no sound escaped his puckered lips.</p>
				<p>Stokes seemed nervous and undecided.  He read the note a third time, and then, with the air of a<pb n="82 At the Town of the"/>man who has made up his mind, he crushed it together in his hand and thrust it into his pocket.</p>
				<p>"Can I have a saddle-horse, right off?" he asked.</p>
				<p>"To be sure, sor.  Why not?" answered the waiter, without removing his eyes from the ceiling.</p>
				<p>"Very well; tell them to bring one round at once," said Stokes; and then, as the waiter took himself and his phantom whistle toward the door, he added, "what kind of a night is it?"The waiter paused with his hand on the latch.  "It's a nice night, sor.""What do you mean by a nice night?" asked Stokes, impatiently.</p>
				<p>"There's a bit of a moon an' a nice breeze blowin'," explained the waiter.</p>
				<p>"The fellow talks as if I was going yachting," said Graham.  "Off with you now, and have that horse round in five minutes or less."The waiter vanished, apparently whistling a quick-step, and Stokes rose.  Half a dozen voices were heard in eager question, but he shook his head with a Sphynx-like smile,"You must excuse me, boys," he replied, in his affected voice, "I never talk about such things.  I shall be back before eleven, and I'm really sorry to leave this pleasant company; but, of course--<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 83"/>The men exchanged glances as the door closed on Mr. Stokes.</p>
				<p>"'He never talks about such things,'" cried Hale, indignantly.  "I'd like to know what else he's been talking about for the last half-hour.""He's only putting on frills," said Gerald Ffrench.  "I saw that note annoyed him like the deuce when he first read it.  Most likely it's a dun.""I don't know the manners and customs of the Los Angeles duns," remarked Tom Murphy, "but if they have the winning ways to take a man from the dinner-table and make him ride a couple of miles to meet them, they deserve to prosper--that's all.""Very likely he's written the note to himself, then," suggested Ffrench; and, as illustrative of the esteem in which Mr. Stokes was held by his fellow-workers, it may be added that this hypothesis was not without supporters.</p>
				<p>Up from the street came the sound of hoof-beats, as of a horse fast ridden.  All listened, and Hale held up his finger.</p>
				<p>"Well, if he's made a rendezvous with himself, he's gone to keep it, that's all," exclaimed that<pb n="84 At the Town of the"/>young gentleman, as the trampling died away in the distance.  "Whatever he's gone after, though, I'll bet he won't have luck with it.""Why so?" inquired Murphy.</p>
				<p>"Didn't you notice that we sat down thirteen at table," answered Hale.  "It didn't worry me any, for I knew I was one of the boys.  We are all twelve of a kind, and Graham Stokes was the odd man in this gang, if anyone was.""Now, fellows," cried Gerald, briskly, "we're here in a new town, and we haven't begun to look into the night side of it yet.  Come on, and let us take in the sights, if there are any."Gerald thought that Stokes, present or absent, had occupied quite enough of one evening.  The diversion was entirely successful.  Fresh cigars were lighted, hats were sought for, and the journalists--an even dozen of them now--started out to see Los Angeles.</p>
				<p>Long before eleven they were all back again on the hotel piazza.  They were vaguely disappointed.  What they had expected to see, not one of them, probably, could have told; one thing was certain, whatever it was, they had not seen it.  They lounged in groups about the door or on the steps.  The host, half-sitting, half-lying in a hammock, was enjoying<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 85"/>the last cigar of the day and talking to Ffrench, Hale, and one or two others.  The waiter, his work done, was standing at the foot of the steps with his hands crossed behind him.  He was looking up at the heavens, and the silent whistle was stereotyped on his lips.  Perhaps he was calling the Dog Star.</p>
				<p>"Yes, I knew him well," the host was saying in answer to a question from Hale.  "He didn't live at my house; but he was in and out a great deal.  That was six months ago."Gerald Ffrench left the group.  He was sick of the sound of Graham Stokes's name.</p>
				<p>"He lived here quite a while, didn't he?" asked Hale.</p>
				<p>"Over a year, off and on," answered the host.  "He had some job in connection with the railroad.  I don't exactly know what.""Was he well liked?"The host laughed.  "Those that made him pay cash liked him well enough.  Those that trusted him didn't.  I've nothing against him."At that instant the rhythmic beat of a galloping horse's hoofs was heard far up the silent street.  The sound grew rapidly.  All looked up and the host struggled into an erect attitude.  Even the waiter brought his eyes earthward and listened.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="86 At the Town of the"/>With flapping empty stirrups and trailing bridle, a bay and white mustang came on at full speed.  On reaching the Pico House he wheeled in his tracks so abruptly that he almost fell.  Then, recovering his stride, he dashed past the building toward the stables.</p>
				<p>The host was all alert in a moment, and despite his gout hobbled quickly to the end of the veranda and looked over.  "He's gone straight into the yard," he said, and then, meeting the blank looks of the group of newspaper men, to whom the riderless steed suggested a tragedy, he added: "Wasn't that the horse Mr. Stokes had this evening?"No one could answer; no one had seen Mr. Stokes ride away.  Yes, the waiter had, and he banished the whistle from his lips and spoke straight to the point.</p>
				<p>"The same horse, sor.""Run round to the stable then, Pat, and tell some of those greasers to come and bring their lanterns."Pat was off like a shot, following the same road the mustang had taken.</p>
				<p>"Do you think---" faltered Gerald.  The host cut him short.</p>
				<p>"That an accident has happened?  Of course I<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 87"/>do, or why should Pedro have come back alone?  At any rate, it's our business to see.  I wish I could go myself, but it's all I can do to walk the length of this piazza."Gerald felt faint and queer.  If any serious accident had happened to the man whom he had been hating so industriously all the evening, this visit to Los Angeles would be anything but a pleasant memory.  The host's next words were more reassuring.</p>
				<p>"Of course, it mayn't be anything.  Mr. Stokes may have hitched the beast up somewheres, and he may have broke loose and run home.  Still, I don't see why he should have acted so frightened, unless---"  The rest of the remark was lost as the speaker leaned over the piazza railing and looked in the direction of the stables.  Lights were twinkling there, and presently half a dozen Mexican helpers appeared, carrying large lanterns and headed by Pat, the waiter.  The latter had put on a nondescript head-covering of the sombrero order.</p>
				<p>"What's that on your head, Pat?" demanded his employer.</p>
				<p>"Me caubeen," answered Pat, taking it off for a moment and examining it critically before he replaced it.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="88 At the Town of the"/>"I mean, are you going with the searching party?""Why not?""Go if you want to," answered the host.  "I'd like to go myself, but--" he broke off impatiently, and pointed up the street.  "Now, boys, that's the way Pedro came, and that's the way you have to go to look for the señor.  Look for him well.  Savey?" -"Si, señor," answered one of the Mexicans, and they started.  Of course the newspaper men went also.  Professional duty would have impelled them, even if the missing man had not been a brother of the craft.</p>
				<p>On reaching the end of the street the Mexican in advance stooped and examined the ground carefully by the aid of his lantern.  A short scrutiny sufficed, and he turned from the river and led the party westward at a brisk pace.  They were soon clear of the town, and it was not difficult to trace the hoof marks in the sandy soil, even without other light than that furnished by a thin crescent of a moon.  Where there was any doubt the lanterns were called into use.</p>
				<p>Ffrench walked beside Pat.  The waiter's eyes were withdrawn from heavenly things and fixed unwinkingly on the sand at his feet.  His whistle<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 89"/>was almost audible.  He was evidently pondering deeply.</p>
				<p>"What do you think of this business, Pat?" the young journalist asked.</p>
				<p>"Bad, sor, bad," returned the other, without raising his eyes.</p>
				<p>"But mightn't the horse have broken away from some place where Mr. Stokes had hitched him?""He might, sor; divil a doubt of it, an' he might have tied a bit of cactus to his tail by way of keepin' him from missin' the spur, but I don't think he did.""What do you mean?" asked Gerald, surprised.  "Was there a bit of cactus tied to his tail?""There was, sor, an' a raal thorny bit, too.""How do you account for that?" asked the young man.</p>
				<p>"I don't account for it, sor; cactus is one of them things that won't bear accountin' for."Ffrench was profoundly puzzled.  Evidently someone, either Stokes or some other person, had sent the horse home and had taken precautions that he should lose no time on the road.</p>
				<p>They were fairly among the orange groves by this time and their progress was slower, for the light of the lanterns was required at every step.  There had been a high wind earlier in the evening, and it was<pb n="90 At the Town of the"/>still blowing, though with diminished force.  The dark branches swayed above them, intercepting the moonbeams.  In the open spaces between the trees they could see the ground strewn with white blossoms, and the air was heavy with their fragrance.  The grove was filled with voices new to the visitors from the north.  Through the, perfumed darkness came the rasping song of the cicada, the harsh croak of the tree-toad, and the whir of great insects that dashed at the lights with a sound like a released balance spring.  Gerald had grown accustomed to these noises and, wrapped in his own thoughts, was hardly conscious of them, when suddenly another tone--a strange tone, and yet one that seemed oddly familiar, mingled with the babble of the southern night.  Ffrench stopped abruptly and clutched Pat's arm.  The waiter had heard it too; all had heard it, and had halted instinctively.  The party was crossing a small opening and the young moon gave light enough to show the expression of doubt and disquietude on every face.</p>
				<p>Again that sound--a bubbling, gurgling groan--the voice of a man in agony, the cry of a drowning man, and yet, even in its indistinctness, there was something of the falsetto utterance which was the peculiarity of poor Graham Stokes's speech.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 91"/>Poor Graham Stokes!  It was thus that Gerald Ffrench thought of him already; it was thus that he thought of him when, five minutes later, sick with horror, he bent above the body lying dead at the foot of an orange tree, with a shower of the fragrant blossoms mingled snow-white and blood-red above and around it, and the crescent of the new moon dropping a pale shaft of light through the boughs on the white, silent face.</p>
				<p>Blood had flowed from the mouth and still hung there in bubbles; blood, but not so much, had flowed from the breast and stained the clothing around the deep dagger wound which had let the life out.</p>
				<p>"Is he dead?" asked Ffrench, breathlessly, and one of the Mexicans, raising the arm of the stiffening corpse, let it fall again as he answered:"Si, señor, he is dead more as an hour.""Impossible!" Hale broke in.  "We heard his groans as we were crossing that glade a moment ago."Pat, who had knelt by the body, shrank away from it.  "He's cowld already, sor; that must have been the banshee we heerd."A feeling of superstitious awe fell on the party.  The Mexicans drew away and huddled together<pb n="92 At the Town of the"/>like a flock of frightened sheep.  Evidently it would have required little to make them take to their heels.</p>
				<p>"Don't move," shouted Gerald, in a tone of command; "we must carry this back to the hotel.""I don't think we've any call to disturb it, sor," said Pat, "until the polis comes.  This is a murder."The Mexicans caught at the idea.  "Si, si, los alguazils!" they shouted and set off at full speed along the road they had come.</p>
				<p>"Here, come back, you cowardly greasers!" called Hale, and Gerald laid his hand on Pat, who seemed inclined to follow their example.  The swinging lanterns gleamed a moment among the orange trees like gigantic fire-flies, and then vanished.  The terrified waiter drew closer to the little band of journalists, and the dead man, looking straight up to heaven with his staring eyes, lay at their feet.</p>
				<p>"It's very strange, very!" murmured Murphy.</p>
				<p>"It's more nor strange, sor; it isn't right," cried Pat; and then he broke off abruptly and raised his hand.  "Hark!  Didn't ye hear something?"They had all heard it--a bubbling, gurgling moan, conveying in its agony an indefinable reminiscence of the dead man's voice.</p>
				<p>They looked at each other with blank, horror-<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 93"/>stricken faces.  No one could tell whence the sound came.  Gerald bent over the body again, but there was no change on that pale face, no light in those ghastly, open eyes.</p>
				<p>"Jintlemen, it isn't right, it isn't right!" screamed the poor waiter, in an agony of terror.  "There's sperrits about us!  For the love of the Lord, jintlemen, let us go home!""Nonsense!" said Ffrench, overcoming with a violent effort the strange sense of horror that seemed to chill his blood; "nonsense!  Someone must remain here till the police come.  They'll be along presently.  Those Mexicans will give the alarm.  It can't be far to the city.""All of two miles," whispered the waiter, faintly; and Ffrench recollected that the dead man had spoken of a similar distance when he received the summons after dinner.</p>
				<p>"He has been lured here on some pretence or other; this murder was a planned thing.  The note you brought him at the hotel, Pat---"He could go no further.  Again that groan of mortal anguish struck on their ears; they could not determine its direction.  It seemed to float down like the moonbeams through the blossomed boughs.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="94 At the Town of the"/>"This is past a joke," said Hale, in an awe-stricken whisper, falling back a step.  Pat was on his knees, crossing himself with trembling fingers, and calling in incoherent prayer on numberless saints and martyrs.</p>
				<p>"I--I think it must be fancy," hazarded Murphy, but his voice shook as he said it.</p>
				<p>"Fancy or no fancy, I'll not wait in it another minnit," shouted Pat, springing to his feet.</p>
				<p>"You can go if you want, Pat, but I think, boys, it's our duty to stay where we are," observed Gerald Ffrench, looking round the group.</p>
				<p>A murmur of assent showed that the journalistic spirit was staunch yet, and Pat, after taking a few steps, slunk back to the others.  He did not dare to face the horrors of the haunted grove alone.</p>
				<p>"Oh, wirra, wirra," he moaned, "that it should come to this!  I always towld him thim Mendozas was a bad lot, an' what did he want to make or meddle wid the likes o' them!  Maybe it's because I brought him the note that he's come back to hant me.""Do you know the man who gave you the note?" asked Gerald, eagerly, scenting a clew.</p>
				<p>"No, I niver seen him before," answered Pat;<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 95"/>"he was just a common ivery day greaser, an' I med no account of him.  How was I to misthrust that he--oh, wirra, wirra, that it should come to this!""Who's this Mendoza you were talking about?" pursued Gerald.</p>
				<p>"He's an ould greaser that had a bit of a ranch out San Pablo way; and he had a daughter that Mr. Stokes was said to be very swate on, but sure I dunno if there was anything in it?""Where is the daughter now?""Dead, rest her sowl, as dead as--as that wan there, rest his sowl, if it will rest.  She tuk her life, at laste that's what was said when they found her floating in the bay, about six months ago.""About six months ago!"  The men exchanged glances.  The date of the poor girl's suicide seemed to correspond with Graham's departure from Los Angeles.</p>
				<p>"Was this before or after Mr. Stokes left?" asked Ffrench.</p>
				<p>"Just afther!  They did say that he'd promised to marry Inez, and that it was because he went off that she done it--the Lord pardon her.""And the old man--the father?""He tuk on terrible, and said that he didn't give<pb n="96 At the Town of the"/>a trauneen for his life once his daughter was gone; but he had very hard feelins agin the man that druv her to it, an' swore he'd have his rivinge of him, if he'd to wait for it till the day o' judgment."The newspaper men consulted together.  Here was a clew, certainly.  If Stokes had attempted to play the Don Juan among these people--hot-blooded and hot-headed as everyone described them, the explanation of the crime became simple.  It was easy to conjure up the vision of a gray-haired father, living only in the happiness of a beloved and beautiful daughter.  And when her corpse floated in with the tide, and the evidence of her shame furnished reason for her death--a piteous picture--it was not hard to imagine the fiery old Spaniard nursing the thought of vengeance as his only solace.  This theory would explain everything except--Again that moan, awful, weird, almost supernatural in its resemblance to the voice of the dead man who lay at their feet voiceless.  The watchers drew together for a moment, and then, with one impulse, started in the direction of the sound, the trembling waiter crouching along at their heels like a whipped spaniel.  His lips were puckered to their<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 97"/>habitual whistle, and seemed to accentuate, in some grotesque way, the terror on his face.</p>
				<p>Before they had gone many yards they met the police, and hailed the approaching glimmer of the lights among the foliage as they might have welcomed the eyes of a friend.  All turned back together, and in a few words Gerald put Captain Strong, who had come in person, in possession of all he knew about the tragedy.  The captain heard him in silence.</p>
				<p>"He put the letter in his pocket, you say?" inquired the officer, when Gerald had concluded.</p>
				<p>"Yes," replied Hale, "he crumpled it up, and put it in his waistcoat pocket.  I saw him."The body had been lifted on a stretcher, and Captain Strong, bending over it, secured the paper.  Carefully smoothing out the creases, he read it by the light of a lantern which one of his men held for him.</p>
				<p>"It's written in Spanish," said the Captain; "a request for the deceased to meet the writer near the western edge of Jones's orange grove--this is the very spot--and it is signed 'Inez Mendoza!'  Inez Mendoza!  Why, that's the girl that drowned herself six months ago."<pb n="98 At the Town of the"/>"It's a decoy letter, Cap," suggested one of the officers.</p>
				<p>"That's plain enough!  But who wrote it?"  The Captain mused a moment, and then resumed.  "Harkins, go down to Mendoza's ranch--we're half way to it now, and bring the old man to town."The policeman withdrew, and the others, raising the stretcher, stepped out slowly with their ghastly burden.</p>
				<p>Pat had recovered some of his confidence with the arrival of the policemen and the lights.  He kept by Gerald's side when they started.</p>
				<p>"Aren't ye goin' to tell them anything about the sperrit groans, sor?" he asked.</p>
				<p>"I don't know," replied Gerald; "I'd like to find some explanation of them myself first."Suddenly the Captain halted, and raised his hand.  "Hark! what was that?"They all heard it, policemen, watchers, all!  It came from the grove in front of them, and sounded weird and awful amid the wonted sounds of the tropic night.</p>
				<p>"We've heard it several times," gasped Murphy, "and we can't make out what it is!  And it has a kind of uncanny likeness to poor Stokes's voice."<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 99"/>The Captain glanced sharply at the motionless figure on the stretcher, and then gave the signal to proceed.  The groans continued, always keeping a few paces in advance.</p>
				<p>The cold sweat ran down Pat's face, and his nervous fingers never ceased to make the sign of the cross above, around, on every side of him.  They all seemed uncomfortable--all but one old, grizzled policeman--and conversation sank to whispers, and then died out altogether.  But the moans continued, still in front, as if summoning them on.</p>
				<p>"Very strange, very strange!" said Captain Strong.  He was thinking aloud, but he was not left unanswered.</p>
				<p>"It is strange, Captain"--the speaker was the grizzled old officer who bore the feet of the corpse--"it is strange, but it's happened before!""Happened before!  That a dead man should send his dying groans on before his corpse," broke in Hale; "for that's Graham Stokes's voice, I'd swear to it.""You're right, an' you're wrong," said the old fellow, dogmatically.  "This here corpse, as we may call it, has died of a stab in the lungs, if I make bold to mention so much in advance of the medical examination."<pb n="100 At the Town of the"/>"I suppose so," admitted Ffrench, whose experience as a reporter had often taken him to the San Francisco morgue, and who could give a fairly expert opinion in cases of death by violence.</p>
				<p>"Very well!  How long does it take a man to die of a cut in the lung?""An hour, half an hour--I don't know," said Gerald.</p>
				<p>"Maybe--maybe two hours?  Ay, it may be three that this man has lain under that orange tree, waiting for his death to come to him, choking in his own blood and moaning in his agony."All shuddered at the horrible picture thus vividly presented.</p>
				<p>"Did anyone hear these groans?" went on the old policeman, who had by this time a breathlessly attentive audience.  "No one, at least so far as appears.""I beg your pardon," said Murphy; "we heard his groans for several minutes before we reached him.""Asking your pardon, young man, you lie," returned the old officer.  "He was stiff and cold before you got within a mile of him.  I say no one heard his groans, but I don't say no thing heard them."<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 101"/>"What has that to do with it, Pachett?" asked the Captain.  "Whoever, or whatever heard them, we hear them now," for at that moment the dismal sound was repeated.</p>
				<p>"Ay, and will hear them till somebody shoots that cat-bird," said Pachett, pointing to a dark object that flitted among the trees a few paces ahead of the party.  Ffrench recognized the flight of the California mocking-bird, called in local parlance the cat-bird, and as he realized the man's meaning a familiar verse of scripture came to his mind:"For a bird of the air shall carry the voice, and that which hath wings shall tell the matter.""Do you mean to say---?" began the Captain.</p>
				<p>"I mean to say, Cap," said the old policeman, that that there bird was likely sitting in one of them trees the whole time, and saw the meeting and saw the murder.  It's a pity we can't subpeny it as a witness, but we can't.  I likewise say that that there bird, sitting in one of them trees, listened to that man's groans for an hour or more--we've no way of being sure of the time--and is now repeating the new sound he has just learned, as is the nature of the beast.  And as the sounds are not very agreeable, I'll just take the liberty--" and the old<pb n="102 At the Town of the"/>man discharged his revolver in the direction of the mocking-bird, which flew away among the trees with a shrill scream that still carried with it some strange reminder of the haunting moan.</p>
				<p>The party exchanged glances; some of the younger men attempted to laugh, but without much success.  There was an effectual check to merriment in that silent figure on the stretcher, and though the mystery was dissolved, there was little comfort in the thought.  The bird had made them realize with horrible clearness the lonely and protracted death agony of the murdered man.</p>
				<p>Pat gave voice to the general feeling as he shook his fist at the tree behind which the bird had vanished, and exclaimed: "Bad cess to ye, then, for an onnatural, hathen fowl, an' may the first bit ye ate choke ye for puttin' the heart acrass in me wid fright, an' amin to ye."The journalists had arranged to return to their several papers on the following day, but the murder of Graham Stokes postponed their departure for twenty-four hours.  They were obliged to wait for the inquest.  Ffrench met Captain Strong the following morning, and asked if old Mendoza had been arrested.</p>
				<p>"No, Harkins was too late," replied the Captain.</p>
				<p>
					<pb n="Queen of the Angels. 103"/>"But there can be little doubt but that Mendoza was the guilty party.""Has he escaped, then?" asked Gerald.  "Have you any prospect of catching him?""None," answered the Captain, with a grim smile.  "Harkins found him lying dressed on his bed, with a pistol in his hand and a bullet through his heart.  The thing is plain enough.  He wrote to Stokes, whom he evidently knew to be ignorant of the daughter's death, and signed the letter with her name to make sure of the effect he wished.  Well, it worked, and Stokes went to his death.  No one knows what passed between the two men, but I think it is not difficult to guess.  Mendoza has been almost crazy since his daughter's death.""Then there is no doubt---" began Gerald.</p>
				<p>"That your friend deceived her, I think not.  It is a very sad story.  I always thought that Stokes was a bad egg.  Well, he's dead now, and his murderer must have gone straight to his lonely house, and saved the State of California the trouble of trying him.  The inquest will be at twelve.  So long," and Captain Strong strolled off down the street.</p>
				<p>Gerald Ffrench found more pity in his heart for the Spaniard he had never seen--murderer though he undoubtedly was--than for the American whom<pb n="104 At the Town of the"/>he had dined with the night before, and had met almost daily for six months.</p>
				<p>Not one of the journalists will admit that he was frightened that night, or that any thought of the supernatural ever crossed his mind, but it is remarkable, in the full reports of the tragedy which appeared in the California papers, that no mention was made of the "Wandering Voice." <pb n="105"/>
					<pb n="106"/>
					<pb n="107"/>AT five o'clock the harsh east wind, that bane of summer afternoons in San Francisco, had almost died away.  It had been blowing with more than ordinary force, and the air was still full of drifting particles from the sand-lots--pungent, intrusive atoms that made eyes smart and lips crack.  But the crowd, setting southward along Montgomery Street, was good-humored and jovial, for was not a great holiday in near prospect?  A few days more, and the sun of the centennial year would rise on Independence Day--the Fourth of July, 1876.</p>
				
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
