<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main Document Type//EN"
"http://infomotions.com/alex/dtd/tei2.dtd">
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hugh Quigley's The Irish Race in California, and on the Pacific Coast in electronic form</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Originally Prepared by</resp>
          <name>Erica Dillon</name>
        </respStmt>
        <principal>Matthew L. Jockers, Stanford University Department of English</principal>
        <sponsor>
          <name>Stanford University</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>Stanford, California 94305</addrLine>
          </address>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <name>Stanford Humanities Lab</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>Stanford University, Stanford, California 94305</addrLine>
          </address>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>
          <name>Distributed by The Irish-American West Project of the Stanford Humanities Lab</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>Stanford, California 94503</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <availability>
          <p>This e-text is freely available for non-commercial purposes</p>
        </availability>
        <date>2004</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Quigley, Hugh The Irish Race in California, and on the Pacific Coast. SAN FRANCISCO: A. ROMAN &amp; CO., PUBLISHERS, 1878.
        <note type="abstract" />
        <placeName>
          <name type="region">Pacific</name>
          <name type="country">United States</name>
          <name type="city">San Francisco</name>
          <name type="state">California</name>
          <name type="Demographic">Both</name>
        </placeName></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>This text was prepared for use in the Irish-American West project of the Stanford Humanities Lab at Stanford University. The two principal goals of this project are (A) to bring the wealth of western Irish--American literary and historical writing to the Internet in a scholarly project and (B) to counter the existing eastern bias in Irish-American scholarship, by providing an online collection of primary source material and scholarly articles devoted to exploring the works of western Irish-Americans.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Suspected errors in the text are marked with a "[sic]" but not corrected.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Hyphens that occur at the ends of lines have been removed, except in cases where it is possible the author intended the hyphen.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">The Irish Race in California, and on the Pacific Coast</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY</byline>
        <docAuthor>
          <name type="first">Hugh</name>
          <name type="last">Quigley</name>
        </docAuthor>
        <docImprint>
          <publisher>A. ROMAN &amp; CO., PUBLISHERS.</publisher>
          <pubPlace>SAN FRANCISCO:</pubPlace>
          <docDate>1878.</docDate>
        </docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="other">
        <p>WITH ANIntroductory Historical Dissertation on the principal Racesof Mankind, and a Vocabulary of Ancient andModern Irish Family Names,Author of the "CROSS AND THE SHAMROCK," "PROFIT AND LOSS," and other works.COPYRIGHT SECURED.FRANCIS &amp; VALENTINE, PRINTERS, 517 CLAY STREET, SAN FRANCISCO.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="preface">
        <p>PREFACE.We have concluded to publish this work, though it falls short of what it ought to be, and would have been, if circumstances had permitted us to devote more time to its composition. We are well aware of its imperfections and defects. But, with all its faults, we flatter ourselves that it contains much interesting and hitherto unpublished information, regarding the Irish race in the past and in the present. How singular the record of Erin, "the Island of destiny," and of her children, in the annals of mankind. As a country she stands one of the oldest on the globe, and her history was written before other nations were enumerated or enrolled among the brotherhood of nationalities; yet she is less known in the past and less honored in the present, than any other nation. Her annals are the most ancient and exact, and her fame was the most resplendent during the many centuries of her supremacy in Western Europe. Yet so completely obscured did she become during the few ages of her subjugation, that her very children became oblivious or indifferent to her ancient glories. It is now well known to thexxx Preface.investigators of the past, that there is no nation on the earth which has such minute, ancient and authentic records as Ireland. Leaving out what Diodorus Siculus, Tacitus, and Grecian historians say about Ireland and Ogygia, or the "Sacred Isle," what nation can boast of such a work as "The Annals of the Four Masters," compiled in the sixteenth century from the most authentic historic documents? Those invaluable annals give the history of Ireland and of the Irish people for a period of no less than four thousand years and more. There is nothing extant in the production of human genius, which equals these celebrated annals. The authors were well called the "Masters" or "Magistri" by Continental literary men, for their joint production masters anything ever before written in the line of historic records. There is not an event, or an occurrence, good, bad, or indifferent, worthy of notice, which took place in Ireland from its first colonization under Partholan or Caesair, up to the year 1616, which is not faithfully recorded in those "annals."But, although the Annals of the Four Masters have been published and procurable for years for a reasonable price, yet how few know of the rich historical treasures which these seven volumes enclose? There are but few who know of their ex-Preface. xxxiistence, and fewer still who read these important volumes. The author has read the Annals of the Four Masters over and over, but his gleanings from their rich fields of knowledge, he must confess, are but light and superficial, owing to the limits to which this volume had to be necessarily confined. His object has been to condense his matter within the smallest space, well knowing that, in this age of instantaneous electric communication, very few have the patience to read large volumes.If there ever was a time when the old proverb, that "brevity is the soul of wit," was universally admitted, it is now, when the substance of many a long period and tedious document is spread before a million readers by means of a few ticks of the telegraph. But, while studying brevity we must be careful not to fall into the grave error pointed out by the prince of critics in his rules for elegant composition, namely, "Brevis esse laboro obscurus fio." In endeavoring to make this book small and portable, we have tried also to keep the style plain, but perspicuous. We have followed no particular author, servilely, but formed our own conclusions by comparing the opinions of the different authors, more than one hundred in number, whom we have read and consulted before committing a line of this book to paper. Hence, it willxxxii Preface.be perceived by the attentive reader, that we do not follow, but reject, the theory of the descent of the Celtic or Irish race through the Scythians, though many respectable Celtic historians are of that opinion. We may have fallen into some mistakes regarding dates of events, or names of persons or parties, but such errors are hardly avoidable in a work of such a wide scope. Our preliminary or Introductory Dissertations will be found, we hope, interesting, if not new, to most of our readers; whilst our alphabetical list of ancient Irish names and their modern forms cannot fail to receive the approbation of all Irish-Americans. We acknowledge ourselves deeply indebted to the many gentlemen of the city press, and to others, for their courtesy and their readiness on all occasions to give us all the information which we sought and kindly received concerning the subject matter of our volume. The Alta, the Call, the Post and Chronicle officials, as well as the editors of the News Letter and the Mail, were most courteous and liberal in supplying us with the information we sought, gratuitously and promptly. But the Examiner and its conductors not only allowed us the use of their files, but supplied us with original and important information, not obtainable save through their kindness and courtesy. In fine,Preface. xxxiiiour book is the first of a series of publications which will, we hope, do justice to a subject so long and so unaccountably neglected as hitherto has been the "Irish race" on this Coast and Continent. The brief memoirs which we have given of individuals of our people, we trust, will be found correct, although they were taken substantially from published notices of the distinguished persons whose names are introduced, save in a few instances. The author has not received a dollar or a dime from anybody as a contribution toward the expenses of the publication of the work. Nor does he expect any reward, donation or profit, save whatever he may gain through the sale of the work to his subscribers. A love of the subject, as well a desire to have justice done to the "Irish race" in the past and the present, at home and abroad, has been his motive in this publication.THE AUTHOR.San Francisco, Dec. 8th, 1877.[xxxiv]&lt;illustration&gt;MILLER HALL, RESIDENCE OF JAMES MILLER, ESQ., SAN RAFAEL.&lt;/illustration&gt;</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="chapter" n="Hugh Quigley's The Irish Race in California, and on the Pacific Coast in electronic form">
        <p>
          <pb n="[i]" />
          <pb n="[ii]" />
          <pb n="[iii]" />
          <pb n="[35]" />
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER 1.">
        <p>THE UNITY OF THE HUMAN RACE. THE COINCIDENCE OFREVELATION AND NATURAL HISTORY ON THIS POINT.</p>
        <p>THE DISAGREEMENT OF THE SKEPTICAL ETHNOLOGISTSPRESUMPTIVE EVIDENCE OF THEIR ERROR. DIFFERENCEIN COLOR, HABITS, AND DEGREES OF CIVILIZATION ANDBARBARISM ACCOUNTED FOR BY NATURAL CAUSES. AB-SURDITY OF EVOLUTIONIST THEORIES.</p>
        <p>That "God created the whole human race of one flesh," was announced by St. Paul to the wise men of Greece, assembled in the Areopagus, without causing surprise among his hearers, because this was the doctrine of the wisest among their own philosophers. The oldest traditions even among the followers of the most corrupted mythol-
        <pb n="36 Introductory Dissertation." />ogies of paganism, agreed in regard to the unity of the human race, with the teachings of the inspired books, and the utterances of revelation. The Mosaic account of the creation of man, which the neo-atheists, with all their objections, have not been able to refute, says, that "God made man," not MEN, to His own image and likeness; and all the silly attempts to detect contradiction or error in the inspired narrative, fall to the ground, when we reflect that the account is merely a synopsis of the events related. Had the Book of Genesis given a full, complete, and accurate description of all the occurrences and terribly grand phenomena of the creation, when God rolled out the countless worlds into illimitable space to run their never-ending races within prescribed orbits; when He destroyed time reign of "chaos and eternal night" by the glorious illumination of the heavens and of boundless space; when He poised the stars in the palm of His all-embracing hand, and sent them rejoicing on their eternal courses without danger of collision or deviation; the book that could enclose within its covers all these descriptions should contain more pages than a million bibles of the present size. What a pity some of our neo-philosophers were not there when in virtue of "Fiat Lux," the light first dawned on the chaotic crea-
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 37" />tions; when the trees with their fruit, and flowers, and foliage sprung up from the earth; when the joyous birds sung their first chorus of praise to their Maker in the delightful groves; when the wild animals exercised themselves in coursing over the grassy plains; and when, even the fishes gamboled and disported in their aqueous element, and leaped high into the air to show their strength. Why do not our "philosophers" deny that these things happened, because there is no account of their occurrence in the bible? Instead of rational objections, the "new school" and their followers ask, where did Cain get his wife when he went into the "land of Nod," and what need was there for the Lord to mark Cain for fear some person or persons should kill him, when he and his father were the only two then in existence? An intelligent person needs hardly be told, that, before Cain took his journey eastward, there might have been many millions of people on the earth, all of his own race and kindred. It can be proved, that, before Adam died, he saw at least a thousand millions of his decendants [sic] on the earth, as it has been mathematically demonstrated that before the Deluge, there were at least fourteen billions of inhabitants living on the globe, because of the longevity and vigor of the antediluvian
        <pb n="38 Introductory Dissertation." />race. It is hard for men of the present day, especially if they are believers in the "evolution" theory of our neo-atheists, to conceive what progress learning, invention, and improvement, to which men reached who lived a thousand years! Can we suppose, that a student, say, who spent nine hundred years in search of knowledge could be ignorant of army science or art which a man who could devote only fifty years to study could master? Modern men are only pigmies when compared with those patriarchs of a thousand years! Hence, though we have no written records but such as are very scant regarding the affairs of those antediluvians, yet, there are traditions among most nations, of the giants or Titans, who made war on heaven, and hurled mountains in their gigantic slings against the very Lord of the Universe.</p>
        <p>But, though the human race is one, being one in its creation, and all men having the same constituent parts, yet there are many divisions and races of men having some peculiarities belonging to themselves, and distinguishable from one another. As there is but one body of water, for example, on the globe, whether fresh, saline, sweet, or bitter, yet this fluid body, though one, is divided into oceans, seas, rivers, lakes, creeks, springs, and rivu-
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 39" />lets. It is the same in the rational animal world. Many races, but one humanity.</p>
        <p>The divisions of men into race, it seems, took place before the Deluge, for it is recorded, that Cain and his people separated themselves from the descendants of Seth, and those who followed the primitive religious traditions of Paradise. It may be surmised, that Cain having been a prevaricator and a murderer with his mark of infamy on his person, did not care to encourage the religious spirit among his people, though industry and useful arts flourished among them. But, though he went out "a fugitive from the face of the Lord," he became the father of a numerous and powerful people, and his descendents were distinguished for their skill in the mechanical and fine arts; as Tubal Cain, who was a "hammerer and artificer of every work of brass and iron," and Jubal who was time father of those who played on the "harp and organ."The first grand division, therefore, of the human family appears to be founded on the distinction of the profane and godly, those who followed Cain and devoted themselves to material industry, and those who acknowledged Seth as their patriarch and followed Enos in "invoking the name of God." And as there was a separation of the good from the
        <pb n="40 Introductory Dissertation." />bad, of the profane and pious, soon after the creation, and the fall from the terrestrial paradise, so, at the end, the same revelation teaches us that there will be a grand separation of mankind into two great divisions, the elect and reprobate, before the final enjoyment of the heavenly paradise, of which the former one was, as it were, a mere figure. But as these things belong to the domain of the supernatural we shall not further discuss them, unless incidentally, while reviewing the different systems of the ethnologists.</p>
        <p>It appears that the first natural division of races after the Flood, is into WHITE, YELLOW and BLACK. The earliest ethnologists contented themselves with this three-fold enumeration, and among these Buffon stands conspicuous. Blumenback enumerates five divisions, namely, the Caucasian, Mongolian, Malayian, Ethiopian, and American, and the majority of modern writers on this subject have adopted this rather arbitrary division. Others, again, such as "Borey Saint Vincent," divide in mankind into fifteen different races, and another author, Des Moulin, not to be heat by his compatriot, St. Vincent, makes the number of races sixteen! Now, some of those authors believe in the unity of the human race, and others do not. These latter are called "Pollygenists," and rejecting the testi-
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 41" />mony of Revelation, and even of the pagan philosophers (as Lucretius De Natura Rerum), maintain that the different races were of separate and independent origin. Some of those assert that men grew up like mushrooms, from the soil, when it was warm and soft, just as the earth was cooling off from the red-hot state of its primitive condition! And that men grew white, black, red and yellow, and took all the sixteen shades, which they have preserved till now, from the color of the soil from which they sprung. Hence, the aborigines, in olden times, were called "Filii Terrae," sons of mother earth, before she cooled off, and grew too old to bring forth any new races !! The advocates of this theory of the "Pollygenists" adduce in proof of their fancies that in every large island and portion of the globe sufficiently extensive to support men, human beings have been found. But there is no place where men have been found that they could not have come there by traveling or navigation, either voluntarily undertaken or by force of storms. We know that all peoples living near seas or large bodies of water are accustomed to have recourse to fishing for food, and as there could be no successful fishing without some sort of vessels, and as those are frequently at the mercy of storms and waves--these timings will readily account for
        <pb n="42 Introductory Dissertation." />time dispersion and immigration of men to distant islands and coasts.* Other ethnologists and men of philosophic turn of mind distinguish the races by the languages which they speak, and their affinities as regards the construction of different tongues and dialects. For instance, the "monosyllabic" which prevails among vast nations, such as the Chinese; the compound or "agglutinative," and the "inflected" and the "reflected." Speech is, no doubt, one of the faculties which distinguishes man from all other animals, though Darwin pretends to demonstrate that some brutes, such as dogs, have it in as great perfection as man, and even superior to him, if the animals had one-half man's framing to make them perfect! How different Aristotle, the
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 43" />prince of philosophers, thinks from the neo-Atheist! "Animals have a voice," said the Stagerite, "but man alone speaks."And, in proportion as men become low and degraded, in the same does their language degenerate, as we find even in individual instances everyday. The agglutinative or compound, differing in termination, is an improvement on the monosyllabic, while the "reflective" excels this, and the reflective and the symbolical and abstractive, belongs only to the superior races, and can never be taught to animals, or with difficulty to perfection, even to lower races of Indians and negroes. This belongs to man in his highest type, and helps him to comprehend the good and true, the useful and beautiful, a compendium of all of which is religion, which raises man above the vicissitudes of life, strips death of its terrors and makes him immortal. We omit mentioning several other classifications, such as the dolychocephalous or "long-headed," and brachyocephalous or "short headed," which some recent writers introduce as distinctions of races, and will adopt the classification of Dr. Prichard, in his "Natural History of Man," 10 vols., who divides the human race into the "Aryan, Turanian, and Egyptian," and this is the least arbitrary, and among the most natural divisions of
        <pb n="44 Introductory Dissertation." />the human race, because it corresponds with the Japhetic, Semitic, and Hamite distinctions of sacred history.</p>
        <p>The neo-philosophers ask, were the three sons of Noah of the same color? And if they were, how came there black, red, and yellow men? Were the changes in complexion effected suddenly or gradually? If suddenly, what was the cause, or who the author of the change? If gradually, why has there been no evidence during ages of such changes taking place? We know from historic records, that black men existed thirty-five hundred years ago, and the same people are black still, and even when removed from the countries originally inhabited by them they don't change a shade in a thousand years. Hence, from these causes, they say, they and the white people are not of one flesh, of one blood, or of the same creation. All we have to say in answer is, that, the white and colored races are essentially the same. They have the same organs, the same number of bones, are alike in their arteries, veins, and nerves; are endowed with the same reason though limited in capacity, capable of the same culture, though of slower powers of comprehension, and every way like men of different colors, save in external appearance. If food and climate have not changed their skins, as we maintain that they
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 45" />have, then we can no more account for the dusky color of a native of Africa than we can for a colored animal, a black horse, a black sheep or cow. Some are born with red hair, some with raven black, some have a ruddy blond hue. Is not this as unaccountable as that a man should have a crop of curly hair like wool on his scalp? If you can't give credit to the agency of climate and food, don't fly to the conclusion that he grew up from the soft loamy soil of scorching Africa, like a blade of asparagus; or, that having descended from his first father, the gorilla or chimpanzee, after he got up from his "four alls," or quadrumanni condition, he remains a negro, because he is too lazy to scrub himself fair or to pluck out his wooly hair, as his white brothers before him succeeded in doing in the course of some two' hundred millions of years!</p>
        <p>Singular credulity of our evolutionists, who are willing, not only to believe, but to try to prove, that years and time have developed monkeys and lower quadrupeds into men, and cannot for a moment entertain the idea, that time, and food, and climate, can account for the most superficial change in man, namely, in changing the color of his epidermis, or in crisping his hair up into something like coarse wool!</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="46 Introductory Dissertation." />The advocates of the unity of the human race maintain the latter opinion, and they are ridiculed as credulous; but, when the "Pollygenists" maintain all the complicated theories of evolution requiring a greater stretch of credulity, they are regarded as the only philosophers, who take nothing on faith or revelation, but demonstrate everything. We are told that there are white settlements in Africa, the people of which have not changed their color for centuries, and that the colored, or negro races do not grow whiter in temperate or cold climates. These facts, if admitted, prove nothing, unless it can be shown that the white colonists under the equator relinquished their former habits as to food and clothing during their residence in temperate climates, and that the negroes are not by their condition now exposed to the same habits which they and their forefathers followed in the countries of their origin. It is a well-established fact, that a white person, especially if young, who chances to be brought up among the Indians, say for twenty-five years, will have very near the same color as the aborigines, and will prefer the savage to a civilized way of living. A celebrated French missionary among the Indians for over thirty years, assured the writer that some well-educated women who from choice married Indians, declared that
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 47" />they preferred the savage to their former life in society. "J'aime le [sic] vie sauvage," was the answer of one lady when he encouraged her to return to her relations in Canada. The evolution theory, now becoming popular, may be flattering to human pride; for a man's vanity may be tickled by the thought, that after having battled in his ancestors to obtain mastery by "natural selection" among gorillas, monkeys, and frogs, during millions of ages, he stands now, god-like, a full man, who owes his creation to no one but to his own good fortune as "being the fittest to survive." Even Darwin, the highest authority among those "Pollygenists," in the conclusion of one of his works, boasts that he has just traced the genealogy of man back through some two or three hundred millions of years, through quadrumani, quadrupeds and fishes, up to that mysterious but unexplored boundary which separates the animal and vegetable kingdoms; and surely, he says, this origin of man, even if descended from the lowest animal of creation, is far better than if, according to the Hebrew doctrine "he was made out of the dirt beneath our feet." This is the substance, if not in the very words, of the great evolutionist philosopher.</p>
        <p>Now, if Darwin was a natural philosopher or chemist, or if he was not off his guard, "Quadoque
        <pb n="48 Introductory Dissertation." />dormitat Homerus," he ought to know, that all those "noble" ancestors of man, monkeys, and reptiles, are made out of that same "dust under our feet," amid at dissolution return to that same "dust," at which Darwin sneers.</p>
        <p>Those artists who became famous in ancient or in modern times--Praxiteles, Canova, or the creator of the "&lt;ArtworkTitle&gt;Apollo Belvidere&lt;ArtworkTitle&gt;," did not construct their immortal images out of the borrowed bones of quadrupeds or other animals carefully joined together and shaped like man! No; but from shapeless blocks of marble, that is, from masses of cohesive "dust," they carved out, by their chisels, the immortal figures lying concealed in these blocks of "dust." And thus, these artists obtained the admiration, and almost the adoration of posterity. The "dust," then--for it contains all elements of matter--was the purest and the fittest material out of which man's body should be formed; and it was thus that he was formed, notwithstanding the opinions of the evolutionists and their innumerable array of dumb witnesses. The foundation of all the systems of those "Pollygenists" and evolutionists consists in doubt. "Doubt everything," they say, "that you cannot break with your geological hammer, bring within the focus of your great telescope, or see under your microscopic magnifier."
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 49" />This is the teaching of Huxley, Darwin and their associates. Now, if doubt be the key of knowledge and essential to its acquirement, we must be at present on the eve of a vast increase to our stock of science, for there are millions who do and ever will doubt the theories of the evolutionists. In fact, it would be expecting too much of human credulity to swallow one thousandth part of their nonsense about evolution and the origin of man. Only a few men who want notoriety follow their teachings, however novel. There were schools of so-called philosophers, who in the Augustan age of Roman literature, maintained some, but not all, of the theories of our neo-atheists. The atomists held, like the moderns, the eternity of matter; but the absurdity of their theories was exposed by the most noted of their own philosophers, such as Cicero; and even Lucretius, the poet, in his work, "De Natura Rerum," asks if the heavens and earth were eternal why have we no records of preceding events, such as we have of the destruction of Thebes or of Troy? Why are some of the arts now perfect while others are in their infancy, etc.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="50 Introductory Dissertation." />In other words, it may be asked, if the world is eternal and man struggled for about three hundred millions of years to become erect, and white, and hairless, why have we not any records of the thrilling events of his life till within about three thousand five hundred years ago? He took a wonderful leap, when he got off his "fouralls," to be able to build the Pyramids or the Parthenon, and erect the Colossus at Rhodes, not to speak of the Colosseum and the Temple of Solomon. What a wonderful development there must be of the primitive man when he could write Homer's &lt;poemTitle&gt;Iliad&lt;poemTitle&gt;, conduct the seige [sic] of Troy for ten years, build Nineveh and Babylon, and found the Grecian and Roman Republics!</p>
        <p>Galen, "the greatest of ancient physicians, and we may say, physiologists, though a pagan, explodes, and is indignant at this epicurean idea of the fortuitous creation of man, now revived by our 'progressive' philosophers. In his hook, "de Usu Partium," the father of medical science says: "Can we not treat with contempt the opinion of those philosophers who see in the human body merely the result of a fortuitous concurrence of atoms? Does not everything in our organization most clearly give the lie to this false doctrine (of the evolutionists)? Who will dare to invoke chance in explanation of this admirable disposition of parts? No; it
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 51" />is by no means a blind power which has given birth to all these wonders of the human organization. Do you know among men a genius capable of conceiving and executing such a grand work as the human body? There does not exist such an architect. This sublime organization of the human body is the creation of a SUPREME INTELLIGENCE, of which the intellect of' mail is but a poor reflection. Let others offer to the Deity reeking hecatombs; let them sing hymns in honor of the gods--my hymn of praise shall be the study and exposition of the marvels of the human frame."From this we can comprehend how degenerate our modern doctors of progressive science are when compared with their old master, Galen, concerning whom it has been written, that the healing art has not made much progress since his time. We can also understand that the theories and paradoxical systems of our modern evolutionists are not original, but were well known and completely refuted near two thousand years ago, by men who had not the light even of revelation to guide their intelligence.</p>
        <p>
          <pb n="52 Introductory Dissertation." />
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER II.">
        <p>THE SECOND GRAND DIVISION OF THE HUMAN RACE. THE HE-METIC, SEMETIC, AND JAPHETIC. THE RAPID SPREAD OF THERACES AND PEOPLES AFTER THE DELUGE. THE PERFECTIONOF NAVIGATION AT THAT EARLY DAY. THE THEORY OFTHE EVOLUTIONISTS REJECTED. THE HABITATION OFTHE ARYANS IN ASIA. THEY WERE THE LAST TO EMI-GRATE, AND WENT THE FARTHEST TO PEOPLE THE IS-LANDS. ERIN PEOPLED AT THE VERY DAWN OF HISTORY.</p>
        <p>The extant records of events before the Deluge are brief, and necessarily obscure and unsatisfactory, the occurrences of twenty centuries being recorded within the limits of a few short chapters of the Book of Genesis. But after the Flood, the annals of the human race are more explicit and exactly recorded.</p>
        <p>This is the era of the division of the grand family of Adam and his successive patriarchs into numerous races, peoples, and tribes. Had the condition of affairs during the antediluvian period continued, the earth would be soon too narrow and scant to sustain its billions of inhabitants, and their government would be impossible. Hence, without alluding to the Divine punishments incurred by
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 53" />their sins, by which "the earth was corrupted and filled with iniquity," or appealing to revelation, we can easily perceive the necessity of a division and diversity of races, even from a human standpoint.</p>
        <p>The three surviving sons of Noah, therefore, by divine Providence, as well as by natural right, became the fathers of the human race.</p>
        <p>They were well qualified to govern the whole earth. They belonged to both worlds--the one destroyed and the one renewed by its prolonged baptism under all the waters of the Deluge. They were familiar with the great events of creation and the fall, from a tradition come down to them through only two generations of men, for they spoke to those men who had seen and conversed with Adam. They heard, and perhaps witnessed many of the criminal actions of those who provoked the justice of Heaven to chastise them by the dreadful visitation of the Flood. They were educated and trained by their pious father, and thus were saved from the moral contagion that spread itself all over the earth. They were, therefore, by experience, education, natural right, and Divine appointment, qualified to be the wisest rulers that ever governed. Hence, they are regarded by all civilized peoples as the greatest of men, as well as the wisest of patriarchs. Such were the three men who divided the
        <pb n="54 Introductory Dissertation." />whole earth among themselves, in obedience to the primitive command, "go, increase and multiply; fill the earth and subdue it."There can be no doubt here. This division took place less than 4,000 years ago. No matter what silly theories men who call themselves wise and learned may promulgate about primitive man. Here we have monuments, genealogies, the building of cities, and history, to prove the descent of all mankind from time three sons of Noah----Shorn, Ham, and Japhet. The written record of the immediate descendants of those great fathers of the human family, are but the monuments which they left, and they are great and numerous. Acknowledging Ham as their father, we learn the names of those men renowned even in profane history. Thus, Nimrod, Mizraim, Ninus, Assur, and the cities of Babylon and Nineveh, Persepolis, Thebes, Memphis, attest their greatness. The race of Ham, notwithstanding that his impiety incurred the malediction of his father, and that he was the youngest son of Noah; made the greatest progress in material prosperity, for, besides the construction of large cities, we find that, especially in Egypt, most of the fine and industrial arts flourished under his descendants. From Egypt came astronomy and chronology, architecture, and agriculture, all
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 55" />which were necessarily connected with the periodical overflowing of the Nile. Alphabetic and symbolic writing originated in Egypt also, as well as sculpture and the plastic arts, as is proved by statutes, as the famous "&lt;ArtworkTitle&gt;Ghreffel&lt;ArtworkTitle&gt;," preserved to this very day, and at least 4,000 years since its execution, and according to some, it is an antediluvian work of art.</p>
        <p>That, the Babylonians, as well as Chaldeans, understood astronomy is proved by the registers of planets and their revolutions, brought by Alexander the Great to Greece, after his victorious campaigns, and these records and calculations were made and perfected two thousand years before our era. A nation which brought agriculture to such perfection as the ancient Egyptians did must be a highly civilized people; for the cultivation of the soil, while it gives competence and supersedes the precarious livelihoods obtained through hunting and fishing, gives also leisure to those who pursue this secure road to independence to cultivate the arts and sciences. But, while the race of Cham were so successful in the prosecution of material prosperity in Egypt, Babylon and Assyria, it was through that race that the primitive traditions were corrupted, especially in Egypt, and degraded into the lowest form of idolatry, which spread
        <pb n="56 Introductory Dissertation." />from there, as seeds from a hot-bed, to most of the surrounding nations of antiquity. Hence the Almighty, provoked by the abominations of those once mighty children of Cham, reduced this great people "to be the lowest among other kingdoms," and the land was "utterly desolated and wasted by the sword, from the Tower of Syene to the borders of Ethiopia."--Ezekiel xxix.</p>
        <p>The Semitic Race, descended from the eldest son of Noe, like the other races, before their dispersion, inhabited Asia. The primitive traditions regarding religion were longer preserved by this race than any other. The Semitic was divided, first, into three great branches--the Hebrews, the Arabians and Aramians. All religions, worthy of name, originated with the Semitic Race and its branches. The Jewish, the Christian, and even the Mahommedan systems were at first propagated through this enlightened race. They sent out colonies to Palestine, Tyre and Sidon, Arabia, Africa, one of which, Abyssinia, still exists. They also spread as far as Phoenicia, Suisiana, Cilicia, Cyprus, Mesopotamia, Lycia, Carthage, Spain, Cicily and Mauritania, or North Western Africa. After, Abraham, setting out from "Ur of Chaldea," reached Canaan, he found tribes of Semites, and this happened near two thousand years
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 57" />A. C. [sic] The student of history is surprised at the wonderful strides which these races made in the arts and sciences, as well as in aggrandisement and conquest, in the course of a few centuries, especially when contrasted with their present degeneracy. But his astonishment ceases when he remembers that much of the antediluvian knowledge, as well as traditions, were transmitted to those races, and that they had not yet entirely lost the longevity belonging to the patriarchal period. Abraham was one hundred and seventy-five years at his death ; and Sarah, his wife, had a son when she was ninety years of age. St. Augustine gravely remarks on this, in his work "De Civitate Dei," that Sarah must have been the most beautiful Woman in time world, since Abemelic, King of Cerara, in Egypt, "fell in love with her when she was ninety years old!" The wonderful rapidity with which these primitive races spread over the globe, and colonized the islands as well as the continents, upsets the favorite theory of the evolutionists, who assert that men at first ventured on the water on rafts, next they used the "dugout," like the modern Indian canoe. From the "dugout" they ventured on time two-oared boat, then on scows, then on vessels propelled by benches of oars, until finally they used canvas and sails, which
        <pb n="58 Introductory Dissertation." />are in a fair way of being superseded by steam, or safer systems of navigation, perhaps through the air. There can be nothing more improbable than this theory. It is certain that the three sons of Noe were in the ark, and that their children and immediate descendants were familiar with its history and the manner of its construction. Hence we must conclude that the remembrance of the recent events connected with the Deluge stimulated the art of navigation to a degree of great perfection. We know from experience, that when any remarkable calamity happens, that men begin to study how they may escape a recurrence of such calamities. Assuredly, then, after the Flood, and during many centuries down from that era, men must have devoted their best energies to the subject of navigation. Those who lived several months on board the ark, and their immediate offspring, could not but make little of a voyage over the deep of only a few days or a few weeks' duration. This is a reflection which the writer has never read a hint of in any author, but is no less on that account a very reasonable one. It is impossible to account for the rapid spread of the human race all over the globe, not only on the Eastern, but even in this Western Continent (as all the learned now acknowledge, was demonstrated
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 59" />from Mexican and Peruvian monuments), it is impossible to account for this universal spread of mankind, except on the supposition that navigation was very perfect immediately after, and for centuries after the Deluge!</p>
        <p>How on earth, for instance, could Ireland, a country so distant from Asia, the birth-place of the human race, be inhabited at, or immediately after the Flood, as it is now well-known that it was inhabited, if navigation was not a well-known science? And this, which we state regarding Ireland, is true of other nations and islands, which "the sons of Japhet divided among themselves."--Gen. x.</p>
        <p>The idea that any number of colonists, such as those which made Erin and the neighboring islands their homes, could arrive at their destination in "dugouts," or canoes, or rowboats, is not only absurd but really laughable. Nothing of the kind happened; on the contrary, large vessels, of which the "Argonaut" was the type, boldly traversed the seas, sailing along the center of the Mediterranean and entering the Atlantic Ocean through the "Pillars of Hercules," and never furled a sail till they landed in Bantry Bay in the County of Cork, as is proved by undeniable monuments, local and general. The predicted blessings that were pronounced on
        <pb n="60 Introductory Dissertation." />Japhet, whom "God was to enlarge," and whose descendants were to "divide the islands of the gentiles in their lands," as recorded in the ninth and tenth chapters of Genesis, were certainly soon fulfilled in the spread of the Japhetic or Aryan race, which supplied the roots, as it were, from which sprung the other great branches of the Celtic, Latin, Teutonic, Sclavonic, as well as the Medean and Persian races. The date of the emigration from Central Asia of the Aryan or "Indo-European," as the Japhetic have been called by late ethnologists, is of uncertain origin, and is supposed to be after the exodus of the Hamitic or Turanian and Semitic branches. Besides historic monuments and traditional accounts, the connections of this greatest division of the Noatic families are more certainly traced from the affinities of language in its derivation and roots, by which the Sanscrit, Greek, Celtic, Teutonic, and Sclavonic tongues are connected. Referring to the great dispersion, of which an account is given in the eleventh chapter of Genesis, it may be conjectured that the Japhetic families, as having received the "Islands of the gentiles" as their inheritance to occupy, moved off more slowly than the other divisions from the fertile plains of Asia, as being compelled by the necessary preparation for their distant des-
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 61" />tinations to be well provided with supplies. The first advance of the "Aryan" race was into India, and in that vast country they could have remained sufficiently long to have their common language moulded into a compact and connected system. And it is to this, probably, more than to any other cause, that most of our modern languages are traceable, in root, construction or derivation, to the Sanscrit dialects. As early as this period, that is, the emigration of the children of Japhet from Central Asia, whether before or after the Hamitic. and Semitic races, no matter, we find the first authentic account of that great branch of the human race, the Gomeranian or Celtic. All historians, .even the most prejudiced, whether English or French authors, agree, first, that the Celtic, or Keltic race was the most remarkable, and powerful, and durable known to history; and second, that the modern Irish are the most genuine, unmixed and unchanged Celtic people that exist on the globe. Even the most prejudiced writers against the Irish, such as Brace in his "History of the Races of the World," Figurier, Richard, Carl Voght, Fontaine, Lyell, and Rau and others, while they try to give the glory of the actions of the Celtic race to the Welch, Scotch and others, acknowledge that Ireland, to-day, is the land where that world-renowned race is to be found
        <pb n="62 Introductory Dissertation." />in its purity and in all its ancient characteristics! The Iranian plains in Asia, east of Armenia, from which the "Aryans" emigrated, was bounded on three sides by the Indies, Persia and Bellochistan, and from this stock sprung the primitive Indians of Hindostan, the Medes and the Persians, the Bactrians, the Aryans, as well as the Celtic and Teutonic families of nations. It is a strange coincidence that the name of Erin, though not spelled like "Aryan," has, in Celtic, the same sound as the latter word. The word is not "Erin," as it is considered refined to pronounce it, nor "Arin," but it is pronounced as if written "Aryan." Whether this is an accident or not, or that the first inhabitants bestowed their own name on the island towards the setting sun, which they made their home, the writer does not feel himself competent to decide, but will leave it to be settled by the Opinion of the learned *
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 63" />
        <pb n="64 Introductory Dissertation." /></p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER III.">
        <p>THE CELTIC RACE. ITS ANTIQUITY AND MIGRATIONS. CON-QUESTS AND INVASIONS. ITS MONUMENTS AND OTHEREVIDENCES OF ITS UNIVERSAL PRESENCE ALL OVER THEGLOBE. THE CELTIC TONGUE. ITS ELEGANCE ANDBEAUTY, AND UNCHANGEABLENESS. THE NEGLECT OF ITSCULTURE BLAMEABLE. ITS REVIVAL USEFUL, IF NOT NE-CESSARY, FOR THE NATIONAL INDEPENDENCE OF ERIN.</p>
        <p>As the "Aryan" or Japhetic race is the most celebrated of all the primitive divisions of mankind, so the Celtic race is the greatest and most renowned of history. Their language alone traces them more clearly than their architecture, and it is the opinion of the most learned philologists that the Celtic, or Gaelic tongue is as old, if not more ancient, than the Sanscrit. The Gomerians of the Bible and of Josephus (see Genesis and Ezekiel) are allowed to be the same people with the Celts, who were some of the first who emigrated from Central Asia and moved not only to the West, but penetrated to the extremity of India, as is proved by their monumental rocks, which are found to this day in the valleys of India, as well as on the mountains of Wales and green hills of Erin. The same style of "Druidical monuments," as they are called, proves
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 65." />beyond a doubt that this self-same race visited the coasts of China as well as the plains and valleys of North America; for the mounds and caves discovered in Ohio and in other western and central States, and the instruments and utensils therein found, prove them to be, beyond a doubt, of Celtic origin. This style of architecture was peculiar to the Celts, and consisted first of altars, tombs and monuments formed out of huge rocks erected on the surface or hidden in caves or mounds beneath the earth. And these evidences of the presence of the Celts are to be met with from the banks of the Oxus to Denmark, and from the coasts of China to the extremity of India. These monuments are not to be found isolated or erected at random, but are placed in lines, to mark the progress of those who left them behind, as evidences of their existence. One line of these Celtic monuments or trophies is found from Central Asia, running by the Oural mountains through the valley of the Oxus, and thence by Russian Poland, Scandinavia and Denmark, and all along to Belgium; while the other line of these singular monuments runs through the valley of the Indus, and here again divides, one chain of them going eastward, to China, and the other up by the Tigris and through Armenia, and, then along both shores of the Mediterranean till
        <pb n="66 Introductory Dissertation." />France and Spain are reached, and then the British Isles. No monuments of this class are attributable to any other save the Celtic races. But, besides these specimens of architecture so peculiar and unique, we have in all those nations the names of places which distinguish them as of Keltic nomenclature. Wherever we meet with the word "Gal" or "Bal" as forming names of places or peoples, we may be sure these designations were imposed by the Celts. Hence, we have the names "Galli," "Gahli-Comati," "Galli-Cisalpine" "Gallatia," "Gallia," "Gaul," "Celto-Scythae," "Celto-Cimmerians," "Cymri," and a thousand other names of places in Asia, Europe and Africa, of pure Celtic nomenclature. We have again Carura, Bellochistan, and other Celtic names of places in Asia; and Portugal, Iberia, Cumreag, Cymri, Cambria, and Cuma, as well as Gallipoli and Ballaclava in Europe.</p>
        <p>"[sic] Smith, in his "Natural History of Man," from which the above is principally abridged, remarks that the Celts must be experienced mariners, or they could not have spread so rapidly over the face of the earth, as is put beyond a doubt by the fact that their "crumlechs, raths, forths, cairns, uaghs, Celtic spear-heads and "Labha dia-mor-naguina," which are found in countless places all
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 67" />over the world. Besides their knowledge of navigation, the Celts were well versed in the arts of mining and smelting ores, as the tin mines of Cornwall and of Spain, and the silver and gold mines of Ireland, as well as the copper mines on the borders of Lake Superior, sufficiently attest. Doctor Mayers coincides with the statements of British ethnologists, and though by no means partial to the Irish, says that the stream of Celtic migration from Asia divided into three--one reaching Britain through Sweden, Germany and France, and another through Syria, Africa, France, Spain, and Britain; whilst a third, returning eastward, crossed the Danube, subdued the tribes bordering on the Black Sea, the Dardanelles and Constantinople, occupying the Crimea and Southern Russia, and finally returning through Wallachia, Illyria, Austria, Prussia and the Rhenish Provinces, joined the other branch of the race in Britain and Wales. What travelers they were, and yet we are told they had no ships! The very name of Britain, so long a mystery to English philologists, is a Celtic word--Brit-tannach*--and signifies, in its Celtic etymology,
        <pb n="68 Introductory Dissertation." />"The Land of Tin," which "sobriquet," if tin be understood as money, the modern British assuredly can lay claim to.</p>
        <p>Herodotus, 460 years before the Christian era, speaks of the Melesians, a tribe of Celtic origin, who penetrated to the Borysthenes, built the city of Olbio, famous for its fisheries and manufactures of fine linen--being the Belfast of that early day. Before this date, the Celts defeated the Etruscans, and established the kingdom of Cisalpine Gaul. They routed four great armies of the Romans, between the years 302 and 307, A. C. [sic], under the Consuls Papyrius, Silanius Cassius Longinus, and Caepio, and Manlius. And finally they took and burnt Rome herself, in the year 290, A. C. [sic], under the leadership of Brin, or Brennus of Livy. Afterwards they changed their course eastward, and joining their kinsmen, the Illyrians, they conquered Greece, Macedonia, and Thessaly, and founded Gallatia, in Asia Minor. Another detachment of these warlike people ravaged Hungary and Switzerland, which they permanently occupied. The Cimri, or Kymri, who ravaged Italy a century before the Christian era, were certainly a Celtic people. From these facts, we can understand the singular assertion of Diodorus Siculus, who states, after enumerating the many
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 69" />favorable features of the soil and climate of Ireland, as well as the skill of her harpers, and the commodiousness of her harbors, that the Greeks in former times visited Erin, and presented offerings or votive gifts at the shrines. These offerings were, probably, nothing but the payment of tribute by the Gallatians, who owed their independence and foundation as a nation to the Celts, who made their home in Erin. This great division of the human race has become amalgamated with other races. In Spain, with the Phoenicio-Semitic people; in Gaul, with the French; in Italy, with Goths, Vandals, and Lombards, and in Russia, Scandinavia, and Poland, with mixtures of the Turanian or Tartar races, and in Britain, with the Saxons and Normans. The only places where they are found in their purity, are, first, in Ireland and the highlands of Scotland, where the Gaelic or the larger branch of the race is found, and in Wales, the Basque provinces, and Brittany, in Spain and France, where the Cymric or mixed Celts are found. The Cymric branch of the Celts, though of the same features and physiognomy with the Irish Celts or Gaels, speak a language which is a compound of Finnic and Gothic words, added to the original Gaelic, which makes the orthography of the language difficult to any but natives of Wales.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="70 Introductory Dissertation." />Whereas, the Gaelic or Irish tongue is in its purity and as free from foreign mixtures as it was about four thousand years ago, when spoken by the children of Japhet, before they set out to people the islands of the ocean, and the continents of the globe. What a pity and shame, that this grand and musical old tongue in which the word of battle was given by Hannibal at Cannae, and by Brennus at Rome, and which was a classical language before Cadmus gave the alphabet to Greece--what a sad fact, that so few study this language to-day, at home or abroad!</p>
        <p>Nay, are there not men who are proud of belonging to this old Celtic race, who are not ashamed to confess that they are ignorant of the language of their native land? You are an Irishman and you don't know one word of Irish? Is there a country or people on earth of whom the same can be said? The Welsh cultivate their tongue, and all Welsh-men speak and read it. Was there ever an Italian, a Spaniard, a Frenchman, or a German who could not speak his national or mother tongue? Nay, even the savage Indian can never be got to forget his own uncouth dialect, and in the Lake Superior regions where Indians are half civilized, and in daily intercourse with white men, they never speak the language of the pale-face. On
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 71" />time contrary, all the whites there, who expect to do any business or trade with the "Red-skins," must learn their tongue as a preliminary to intercourse with them.</p>
        <p>What has preserved the Jews as a distinct race of people, next to the providence of God, but their language, the Hebrew, in which they worship Jehovah, and which they all speak? The Irish in Erin have lost their national independence, but a far greater loss was that of their old, noble, and expressive language. In fact, when they lost their native tongue, they lost the possibility of ever recovering their national independence, for the speech, the word, the "logos" of a man, is the next thing to his soul, for speech comes directly from the soul. Therefore, when a man loses his mother tongue, that mother no longer acknowledges him as her son. In a word, he ceases to be what he ought to belong to, and becomes identified in spite of himself, with the people or country whose language he speaks. Nor is the objection of some, who say the Irish tongue is out of date and sounds harshly, causing hearers to laugh at it, of any weight. For if the Hebrew or the Greek were spoken to those who do not understand these languages, or even the German, a harsher language still, those tongues would sound far more harshly in the
        <pb n="72 Introductory Dissertation." />ears of uneducated people, than the Celtic. We have been often shocked when quoting Greek and Hebrew texts in speaking, to observe fashionably dressed people smile and laugh. But their laughter arises from ignorance or want of cultivation of the mind, as it unquestionably does with those who cannot relish the elegance, flexibility, and sententiousness of the grand old Irish tongue.</p>
        <p>Even those old settlers of Norman and of English origin, who became "more Irish than the Irish themselves," "Hibernicis ipsis Hiberniores," in the reproachful language of their persecuting countrymen, the Geraldines, and all of the English Pale who intermarried with the native Irish, those had to learn and use the Celtic tongue before the fire of patriotism could be kindled in their bosoms. It is also remarkable, but no less true, that of all the modern Irishmen who became renowned for eloquence and literature, such as O'Connell, Curran, Burke, Davis, O'Brien, and Meagher, either spoke the Irish or used its idioms, and had their birth in localities of purely Celtic populations. Irish Nationalists, therefore, whether at home or in this country, should encourage their people to a study of the Celtic language, for it was while this tongue was the vernacular in Erin that all her great heroes, bards and professors flourished. This was
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 73" />the language of Owen Roe, Rory O'Donnell and Shawn O'Neil, as well as of Brian Boru and Saint Lawrence O'Toole, of the Bishop of Ross and of Donald O'Sullivan. And it is, to-day, the language of him who may be called "ultimus Romanorum," the last and the best of the Irish, John of Tuam.* The English Government, the most worldly-wise
        <pb n="74 Introductory Dissertation." />body of rulers in the world, perceiving that, while the Irish kept alive their national tongue, they could not be thoroughly subdued, first proscribed and then discouraged its use. Hence, for centuries, to speak or learn it was made a treasonable offence.</p>
        <p>"The Church by Law," also, declared that there could be no conversion of the Irish while the people made use of that vehicle to express their sentiments or say their prayers. And in this declaration, like the Jewish high priest, they unwittingly uttered a prediction--for it was in those provinces where the Celtic tongue was retained that the light of the faith never died out or could be extinguished. That battle is now over, and was won through, under Providence, the unconquerable influence of the old laconic, sententious and native elegance of the Celtic language. The battle for nationality is now preparing, and a large army of combatants and "skirmishers" are preparing for the fray. But we see the old enemy of Ireland and of the Celts making use of the same tactics as she did in the days of Elizabeth, Ann and William, only she is more chary of blood-letting. The Celtic tongue, and, consequently, Irish history, is still tabooed in all the schools and colleges under British rule, except in an instance or two where that language is studied as an antiquarian pas-
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 75" />time, as in Trinity College, Dublin; also, in the Catholic University, and elsewhere. Let the Irish tongue be but once again familiar to all Irishmen, and the renowned actions achieved while that tongue was dominant in Erin--let these things be popularly known and England's authority in Ireland would not last for a month. A want of unity is complained of as the great impediment in the way of Irish independence. But the greatest band of unity is wanting when the people you wish to unite speak not one but different tongues. In a word, there is a "Babel of confusion" in that nation where the people have no national language, as it is to-day in Ireland. Prof. Kavanagh says:"As to territory, the native tongue has, I regret to say, disappeared in Leinster, where, according to the census of 1871, only twelve in every thousand of the population are returned as speaking it. Yet, it still subsists in the south of Kilkenny, round the foot of Slieve Bloom, in the north of Louth, and in the north-west of Meath. The early plantation of the Pale seven centuries ago, proximity to the seat of Government, close intercourse with England and diffusion of education, account for its disappearance in Leinster.</p>
        <p>In the Province of Ulster there had been a succession of plantations and transportations, from the
        <pb n="76 Introductory Dissertation." />time of Elizabeth to the great plantation under James I. The natives and their tongue were banished, and Scotch and English adventurers obtained their lands. So that, in 1871, only 46 in every 1,000 of the people of Ulster are returned as speaking Irish. We must, however, distinguish between the eastern and the western counties in Ulster. In the former Irish has almost disappeared. Yet, we find it still spoken round the base of Slieve Donard, in Down; through some of the Glynnes, and in northern Antrim; sparingly in Fermanagh and Londonderry, and considerably in Armagh. Cavan yet clings to it; a still larger portion in Monaghan, and a very large number in Tyrone. When, however, we reach the western highlands of Ulster, ancient Tyrconnell, we find the native race have retained the faith and the tongue of St. Patrick and St. Columbkille. According to the census of 1871, no less, than 18,629 persons in Donegal are returned as speaking Irish only, and 44,505 as speaking both Irish and English; a total of 63,136, or twenty-nine per cent. of the whole population of the country.</p>
        <p>When we examine Connaught and Munster we find widely different results. In Connaught, in 1871, no less than 50,154 are returned as speaking Irish only, and 279,039 as speaking Irish and English:
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 77" />total 329,191, or more than 37 per cent. of the whole population of the province. The details of the five counties are instructive, as showing the relative strength of local influences in strengthening or weakening the use of the native tongue:Counties.</p>
        <p>Popula-tion.</p>
        <p>Speak Irish Only.</p>
        <p>Speak Irish and English.</p>
        <p>Total.</p>
        <p>Per ct. Speak Irish.</p>
        <p>Galway$$$248,45830,239109,444134,68356.2Leitrim$$$95,5623415,5155,8566.1Mayo$$$$246,03016,509122,453138,96256.1Roscommon140,67073717,36418,10112.8Sligo$$$$115,4932,32624,26326,58923.1 Totals$$846,21350,152279,039329,13137.4We see here the same plantation results as in Ulster, Leitrim, Roscommon and Sligo, adjoining the Leinster and Ulster settlements, which were occupied with alien adventurers, who almost stamped out the native tongue, while Mayo and Galway retained it.</p>
        <p>Permit me now, sir, to notice Munster. A succession of plantations, down to the Cromwellian Palatines, was settled there. Yet the native tongue subsists up to 1871, as follows:Counties.</p>
        <p>Popula-tion.</p>
        <p>Speak Irish Only.</p>
        <p>Speak Irish and English.</p>
        <p>Total.</p>
        <p>Per ct. Speak Irish.</p>
        <p>Clare $$$$147,8644,43253,71358,14538.6Cork $$$$$517,07011,628140,731152,35929.5Kerry $$$$196,58612,00970,01082,01941.7Limerick$$$191,9361,30223,36324,66912.9Tipperary$$216,71367521,24521,92010.1Waterford$$123,3103,82143,51647,33738.4 Totals$$1,393,48533,867352,578386,44527.7
        <pb n="78 Introductory Dissertation." />Thus, in the two provinces of Munster and Connaught, among a population of 2,239,698, we find 84,019 persons returned as speaking Irish only, and 631,617 as speaking Irish and English: total, 715,636, or nearly 32 per cent., speaking the Celtic--little short of one-third of the whole population of these two provinces.</p>
        <p>I venture to express a hope, sir, that I have proved, from official returns, that you were not correctly advised when you stated, as a Cabinet Minister charged with the representation of Irish affairs in the House of Commons, that "it is only in a comparatively small number of districts that the Celtic language is still spoken in Ireland."Ancient authors give the character of the Celts, which the reader will observe is as suitable to the remnants of the race to-day as it was over three thousand years ago. They were a people "brave and quick to resent injuries," which made them quarrelsome. They were fond of shows and displays, such as reviews and processions. They were capable of extraordinary efforts, either in war or peace, but of not much pertinacity or perseverance. Liable to spells of great excess of enjoyments, which generally ended in extreme depression. They preferred the life of large towns in consequence of their social habits to the occupation of lands. Fonder of seeking wealth
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 79" />by spoil and the chances of war or mining than of gradual accumulation, like the Teutonic races. They have filled the pages of history with the renown of their actions, but who had never long continued in authority, or founded but few permanent States. Though submitting to law, yet they were generally impatient under the authorities constituted over them. They were represented to be credulous and easily ruled and imposed upon by their Druidical teachers. In fine, from their war-like qualities, which were of the first order, they became, when scattered, the hireling soldiery of other nations, until, finally subdued and overcome by the steady discipline of Rome, they were ultimately, save in Ireland, absorbed by the Latin and Teutonic races. Individually, the Celts were tall and well-built, of florid complexion, and blue eyes, and dark hair. Their dress was that of the modern Highlander, and they generally fought with the sword or spear, and without armor. They wore ornaments of gold and silver on their persons, the coveting of one of which tempted Tarpeia, the Roman damsel, to open to them the gates of the city. Their architecture was peculiar, such as the round towers, which are to be found, not only in Ireland, but in Persia and in India. They possessed the art of writing, and from their alphabet,
        <pb n="80 Introductory Dissertation." />probably, the Greeks borrowed theirs, for they are almost identical in number and name, though of different characters. Their religion consisted in a worship of the powers of Nature, or of the planets, for there was only one idol in Erin at St. Patrick's arrival, and the Druids were their priests.["][sic]Such were the ancient Celts, and who can read this account of them, written by so many pens, without feeling convinced that the Irish of the present day, in Ireland and in America, are identical with the Celts of four thousand years ago? And yet how few of our countrymen have studied the annals of that proud and ancient race to which we belong? In our circular we said that the Jews were a more ancient people than the Irish; we were mistaken in that statement. The Jews, though favored by Providence as a peculiar people, and having written records of the most authentic character, yet as a race and as a people, and putting revelation out of sight, they occupy a very insignificant position when compared with the Celts, the descendants of Japhet, the colonizer of the greater part of the earth, and now, probably, the possessors of the lost inheritance of the Jews, even as regards religion. But this subject, which is the theme of Father Thebaud's book, shall be considered in another part of this volume.</p>
        <p>
          <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 81" />
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER IV.">
        <p>OTHER MODERN RACES. THE LATIN RACE SUCCEEDED THECELTS. THE LATIN THE FIRST RACE OF THE WORLD.</p>
        <p>THEIR JUSTICE AND DISCIPLINE. THEIR GENIUS ANDMILITARY SUCCESS. FAR SUPERIOR TO THE OTHERRACES. THE ANGLO-SAXON RACE A MYTH. THE CELTICTONGUE A LARGE INGREDIENT OF THE LANGUAGES OF THEEARTH, INCLUDING LATIN, GREEK AND ENGLISH. ITSNEGLECT A DISGRACE TO IRISHMEN AND A MARK OF SUB-JUGATION.</p>
        <p>Next to the Celtic race, which acted its part on the world's stage for almost four thousand years, we find the Roman or Latin race the most prominent. In fact, the Romans were only Celts under military discipline, and, like those from whom they sprung, became conquerors of all the civilized portions of the globe. The Romans were the greatest people that ever lived, and exercised their authority over the nations subdued by them with a justice and moderation unequalled before the founding of their government. All modern nations, even the most enlightened, can learn something in the art of government from the Romans. The Roman or Latin race gave to the world the most brave and accomplished generals, the most invincible soldiers,
        <pb n="82 Introductory Dissertation." />the wisest statesmen, and instances of the most incorruptible private virtue that we have any record of among mankind. It was among those people that the citizen was raised to the rank of a sovereign, in a republic that lasted hundreds of years. It was in Rome, even Pagan Rome, that the most important code of laws was enacted, from which all modern nations have copied. It was there that a Cato, a Cicero, a Regulus, a Scipio, a Virgil, a Horace, and a Seneca were born and educated. Greece, of course, founded republics before the Latins, and had her Demosthenes, her Codrus, and Solons, and Lycurgus; but their little republics were almost perpetually at war, either among themselves or with their neighbors, and when the Roman power became great the Grecian States dwindled into insignificance. For fifteen hundred years the Romans governed the world and effected more for the civilization of mankind than all previous governments. Rome fell, however, but even in its fall, like a mighty meteor, it cast rays of its light and vital vigor into all the surrounding nations which grew up like cions or buds from its roots. All the nations which acknowledged the sway of Rome and spoke her language are called the "Latin races," such as Spain, France, Italy, Portugal, and other peoples both at the east and west of the At-
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 83" />lantic. Modern civilization, science and art owe more to the Latin races than to any other race. Poetry, painting, statuary, inventions, science and literature, as well as law, morality, liberty and religion, have gone forth among mankind from the Latin races. As we are not writing controversy, it will not be deemed necessary that we should adduce proofs of our every statement.* We will merely refer to the defeat of the Saracens by Charles Martel, in France, and by John Sobieski, in Germany, and the expulsion of the Mohammedans from Spain after seven hundred years of "skir-
        <pb n="84 Introductory Dissertation." />mishing," and ask what would have become of European LIBERTY but for the valor of the LATIN RACES? How imprudent, not to say laughable, the boasting of those great orators on certain days of national festivity, who, in their highest enthusiasm, boast that they do not belong to the Latin races, but, thank God, that they can trace their genealogy to that now famous race called the "Anglo-Saxon." Nobody can blame men without a long line of ancestry--" Sine Majoribus," as the Romans expressed the condition of "new men"--if they tried to claim affinity with the most respectable races. But there is really no "Anglo-Saxon race" in existence, and there never was what could with propriety be called the Anglo-Saxon race. The modern English, a very wise and prosperous people and possessed of all the virtues of the most refined humanity, are certainly a very mixed people.</p>
        <p>"The stoutest asserter," as Donaldson says, "of our people being of a pure Anglo-Saxon, or Norman descent, is convicted, by the language of his daily life, of belonging to a race that partakes largely of Celtic origin." They are composed firstly of Celts--the old Brittons--which, probably, if not the first, were certainly the second people who held the island. Next came Romans, the the Saxons, the Angles and Jutes. Next the
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 85" />Frisians, Danes and Norwegians, then the Normans, and lastly the Fennic people, who, most likely, were the aboriginal inhabitants. That all those nations contributed their quota towards making up that paragon of perfection, in his own estimation, called the Englishman cannot, for a moment, be disputed or doubted. If history was silent in regard to these matters, which it is not, the language alone would establish the truth of the statement. As Donaldson remarks, "If I call for my coat before going out into the cold air, I don't reflect the word is from the Celtic 'cota.' If I give my servant a 'basket' to go to market, I forget that it comes from the Irish word 'busgead.' If I order a 'cart,' is it not evident it is from the Irish word 'cura?' If I send to get a 'cassock,' what is it but the Celtic word 'cassoge?' If I allude to the 'Swan of Avon,' what is this but the Irish word river without a change of a letter? If I order a 'pot of ale,' what is this but the Celtic word 'potha'?' from which, also, is derived the Latin word 'potus.</p>
        <p>'" Indeed, to count the number of Celtic and Irish words, and the roots of the English language, would be to write a vocabulary, so numerous are they. And strange, Webster, or rather Worcester, in his Dictionary, has the temerity, if it is not ignorance, to state in page xxv of
        <pb n="86 Introductory Dissertation." />his "Brief His. of E. L.," that "the Celtic words, in English, are altogether few in number!" Most of them, as bard, Druid, crowd, "cruid." And most of the words as "clan, shanty, whisky," of recent origin. This is certainly unworthy of the great lexicographer, and not at all correct. Neither "whisky," nor "shanty" are, as far as we know, Irish at all--whisky having been corrupted from "uiske," and, as for "shanty," it is most likely of Yankee origin.* The most learned philologists of the Continent, such as Zeus and others, allow that the Latin Classics cannot be understood without a knowledge of the Celtic tongue; and that there are, even in "Caesar's Commentaries," those works written during his Gallic campaigns, words such as
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 87" />"cingetorius," which are of purely Celtic orthography, and bearing no affinity whatever to the classical Latinity of Roman authors. We give, in the following, a list from memory alone, of Irish, Latin, Greek and English words, which will prove, so far, the antiquity of the first, that is, the Irish, over all the other tongues:IRISH.</p>
        <p>GREEK.</p>
        <p>LATIN.</p>
        <p>FRENCH.</p>
        <p>ENGLISH.</p>
        <p>Nanim,nomos,nomen,nom,name.</p>
        <p>Fion,dinos,vinum,vin,wine.</p>
        <p>Fir or fer,anhr,vir,verile,virile.</p>
        <p>Cree,kardios,cor,ceur,creed or cordial.</p>
        <p>Dioa,Deos,Deus,Dieu,Deity.</p>
        <p>Coppal,kaballus,cavallus,cheval,chivalry.</p>
        <p>Mathair,mhter,mater,mere,mother.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="88 Introductory Dissertation." />IRISH.</p>
        <p>GREEK.</p>
        <p>LATIN.</p>
        <p>FRENCH.</p>
        <p>ENGLISH.</p>
        <p>Athair,paihr,pater,pere,father or vater.</p>
        <p>Cuss,pons,pes,pie,foot.</p>
        <p>Cleave,cluphos,clypeus,----claymore.</p>
        <p>Milia,milion,millia,mille,millionNuct,nux,nox,nuit,night.</p>
        <p>Bie,bios,vita,le vie,life.</p>
        <p>Caen,kefhlh,caput,capille,capillary.</p>
        <p>Uaim,umnos,hymnus,----hymn.</p>
        <p>This list is far from being perfect, nor are these words, taken at random, by any means those which most clearly illustrate the matter. The numerals, and the days of the week and names of the months more plainly show the radical connection of the Celtic with most modern tongues, as well as the Greek and Latin, that one must be blind indeed who fails to perceive it. It is a pity that our immortal American Lexicographer allowed himself to express such a blunder as the one above referred to, for, if he has erred in regard to the Celtic tongue and its contribution to the AngloSaxon, will it not shake the confidence of men of learning, at least, in his derivations and interpretations of other languages? The Celtic tongue is, at present, almost a dead language, there being no more than about two millions of persons who speak it, and fewer still who study it. But, if all that, that
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 89" />old language contributed towards the composition of all, even the most ancient tongues of Europe, was withdrawn from them, their copiousness and beauty would be, if not totally destroyed, at least very munch impaired. The nations called the Latin, which, like the Gallic and Spanish races, fared better than the Irish, whom the Romans never subdued. Unlike the Irish, these were governed by rulers of their own race and blood. Hence their languages have been transmitted down to them, from their forefathers like their national characteristics and their blood. Hence the language of nations and their national independence go hand in hand. There is no instance where a free people exchanged their native tongue, however uncouth, for any other language.*&lt;horiztonal rule&gt;
        <pb n="90 Introductory Dissertation." /></p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER V.">
        <p>THE CELTS FAMOUS AT COLONIZATION. DISCOVERED AMERICAIN THE SIXTH CENTURY. THE TESTIMONY OF SCANDI-NAVIAN WRITERS, THOUGH PARTIAL, SUBSTANTIALLY COR-RECT. THEY SUPPRESS THE TRUTH FROM SELFISHMOTIVES. THEY MISREPRESENT THE STATE OF AFFAIRSIN IRELAND. THE IRISH MISSIONARIES WENT TO ICELANDIN THE SEVENTH AND EIGHTH CENTURIES. THE PROBABLECAUSES OF THE EXTINCTION OF THE IRISH COLONY. NOR-WEGIANS WERE PIRATES AND FREEBOOTERS, ETC., IN THESEAGES.</p>
        <p>That the Celts of the olden time were the most famous travelers, colonists and navigators that the world ever saw is now acknowledged by all having any claim to historic knowledge. It now remains to be seen how long they, as a people, preserved the leading traits of character which belonged to them during many centuries. Ireland was inhabited at a very early age of the world, and the same energy
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 91" />which enabled the Celts to make that island their home, certainly did not desert them after their settlements there, and must have remained with them for many centuries. Hence, we find them with the records of an independent people for a period of over three thousand years. There are authentic records of the existence of the Irish as an independent people from at least eighteen hundred years before the Christian era to the twelfth century. Not but that Erin was often invaded by Northmen, Danes, Scandinavians and Saxons; she certainly was, but none of the invaders ever succeeded in making a permanent subjugation of the people. This happened in England and in other neighboring countries, but Ireland never lost her independence till"Her faithless sons betrayed her."Hence, it is not surprising that with such antecedents in her history, her sons setting out on voyages of discovery and benevolence, were the first Europeans who landed in America. Even the Scandinavians themselves, though partaking of the almost universal prejudice against the Irish, on account of religious differences, allow that when their forefathers landed in America, in the tenth century, they found the Irish established there before them; hence, they called it "Ireland it
        <pb n="92 Introductory Dissertation." />Mickla," or Great Ireland. Whatever credit may be given to Scandinavian records, and they appear to be substantially authentic, probability is in favor of a preceding discovery by the Irish. There was an old tradition in Ireland that a great western island, that used to be seen by mariners in olden time, had been swallowed up in the ocean; but these stories were probably derived from Plato's narrative about the island "Atlantis" that was swallowed up in the waves. We have an account, also, in Strabo's Geography, of a Greek philosopher named Pytheas, who made, voyages into the Atlantic ocean 350 years before Christ, and astonished his cotemporaries [sic] by the account he gave of the length of the day in the northern latitudes which he traversed. It was he discovered the place which the Romans called, "Ultima Thule," which some took to be the Orkneys and some Iceland. But we have no need of these far-fetched, though probably true accounts. That there was a well-established belief in Western Europe about the discovery by the Irish missionaries of some western continent or large island, appears from the fact that the Atlantic was called the "Brandanic Ocean." It is not without cause that such a change in geographic nomenclature could take place. The nautical map which Columbus had to guide him
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 93" />was drawn up according to the traditions of Saint Brandan's voyage. St. Brandan, whom some say was a bishop and some an abbot of Clonfert, which means "The Valley of Wonders," departed on his western voyage about the year 540. He was accompanied by several of his disciples, among others St. Maclorius, or Maclut, St. Mernoc and St. Barrinthus. These two latter had been in the western country before, and it was at their solicitatation [sic] that the venerable Brandan set out in a large vessel containing provisions for at least fifty days. Before having set out he visited Saint Enda in the island of Arran.</p>
        <p>Saint Brandan returned back from his Transatlantic voyage, and used to entertain St. Ita, a celebrated nun and abbess, in Brittany, formerly his teacher when a child, with accounts of his travels in the newly-discovered country. These voyages, back and forth, continued for seven years, and Barrinthus, who wrote a description of the voyage and of the country, states that they sailed in the direction which was against the Summer solstice, "contra solstitium aestivale." And this point of the compass would certainly indicate the country of the "Whiteman's Land," in which the Scandinavians found the Irish colony. This western country, which was called, in the annals of Clonfert,
        <pb n="94 Introductory Dissertation." />extant in the eighth century, according to Colgan, "Terra repromissionis sanctorum, quam Dominus daturus est successoribas nostris in novissimo temporare." "This second land of promise of the saints, which the Lord will give to our successors in later ages." This was certainly written in the seventh century. What further proof do we want of our forefathers, both in race and creed, being the first settlers of this country? But, it will be asked, why had not Columbus access to those accounts, which were well known at Rome--for St. Brandan was a man who presided over a monastery of three thousand monks? No doubt, those records were extant in the eighth century, but were not most of the monuments and books of Ireland's glory destroyed by the Danes and Northmen pirates? and what the Danes spared the English completed the destruction of in the twelfth century. Hence these monuments were lost, save a few extracts in the works of contemporary hagiologists. Even Rome, in these years, was in trouble, too; and it appears that all memory, save what was saved under cover of misty traditions of these events, was lost. So that Columbus had to begin the work over again, which his predecessors securely accomplished. Had there been no printing presses in existence, and had the memory of
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 95" />his voyages been confined to the archives of monasteries, and had all his charts, maps and log-books been destroyed by war, perhaps Columbus' discovery might be disputed and doubted to-day as much as are the voyages of Saint Brandan, or of Are Marson, or Thorwald Ericson. Hence there is no need of accusing Columbus of being "an impostor," as one Aaron Goodrich does in his "History of the Character and Achievements of the So-called Christopher Columbus," written in bad English and worse taste. Columbus, most likely, never had any reliable account of the voyages of either Saint Brandan or of the Scandinavians, though one "Rasmus B. Anderson," of the University of Wisconsin, says that the Italian navigator sailed to Iceland in February, 1477, and must have learned all about previous Scandinavian voyages in conversation with the "Bishop and other learned men of Iceland." This by no means follows from Columbus having gone to Iceland in 1477. He might not have seen the Bishop or any of those learned men, which were probably scarce at that day in the freezing island. If they gave this information to Columbus, which enabled him to re-discover America, why did they not claim the honor of a previous discovery immediately after the glory of Columbus' achievement was being
        <pb n="96 Introductory Dissertation." />blazoned all ,over Europe? If they had the documents, these "learned, men," such as the "Codex Flateyensis," and the Sagas, why did they not bring them to light till about four hundred years after they were written? And, why was it not before 1837 that any steps were taken by Professor Rafn to bring these documents, eighteen in number, before the public, in his work "Antiquitates Americanae?" If it took from three to six hundred years for the Scandinavians to make good their claims to their having visited America, it is not at all wonderful that they communicated nothing to Columbus, if he went to look for information to Iceland, as it is stated that he did, in the year already named. Columbus, then, may be an honest man, without his being a saint. He may not have heard of the voyages from Iceland, and may have no data in regard to the voyages of Saint Brandan.. But as for what "Goodrich," and a long list of New England people say, this amounts to nothing but so much of what is called "Buncombe," whether coming from Bryant, Headly, Knowland or others, who write books to make money without much concern about the truth of what they state. Before the era of the invention of printing, when a book was written, there was often but one copy of it in existence. Hence, when that book was
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 97" />destroyed, the whole edition went out of existence, and if the author of the work was dead, who could attempt to re-write the lost work? This certainly was the fate of the written accounts of Saint Brandan's voyages and discoveries, for the Monastery of Clonfert was burned and ravaged by the Danes, in the ninth century, in or about A. D., 839.</p>
        <p>In confirmation of this fact that the Irish discovered and colonized America at an early age--not later than the seventh century--we have the Scandinavian records, which, while they establish as certain the discovery of Helluland, Markland, and Vineland, by their navigators, bear witness in favor of the former also. The following is taken in substance from the "Antiquitates Americanae," a copy of which the writer consulted, in the Sacramento Capital Library, and copied in substance:"In the year 983, Are Marson, a Prince of Reykjanes, in Iceland, was driven to Great Ireland (supposed to be south of the Chesapeake Bay), by adverse winds, and was there baptized by the Irish priests of the country. Rafn "the Limerick trader["][sic], was the first who gave circulation to this narrative. The Saga Land namabok, written by a descendant of Are Marson, states that "Great Ireland" lies south of Vineland, VI days' sail from
        <pb n="98 Introductory Dissertation." />Ireland, which is certainly an error, and instead of six according to Professor Rafn, should read XX or 26 days. But whatever the distance of Great Ireland from Old Ireland, it is stated again after this, in 999, that Bjorn Albrandson being obliged to fly Iceland to avoid the wrath of Snore Gode, found his way also to Great Ireland. A like adventure happened Guedleif Gudlaugson, who made a voyage to Dublin, but on returning home, he met with adverse winds, which drove his ship southwest, when late in the Summer he finally landed in an extensive country unknown to him. After having landed, they, the crew, were arrested by a band of men some three or four hundred in number, who bound them as prisoners, and threatened them with death. They did not know of what nationality they were, but it seemed to the Scandinavians that their language was Irish. While the master and crew of the vessel were bound, another party appeared, preceded by a banner, behind which rode a man of venerable appearance, and very old and grey. The treatment of the prisoners was at his decision. This man was no other than the outlawed Bjorn Albrandson.</p>
        <p>He caused Gudlaugson to be released and brought before him, and addressing him in the Norse tongue, asked him, whence came he? On
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 99" />his replying that he was an Icelander, and having been driven hither by adverse winds, the old sage Bjorn received him hospitally, making many enquiries about his acquaintances, particularly, "Thurid of Frod," on account of the illicit connection with whom he had been obliged to quit his country. The upshot of this deliberation, which reads like a fiction, was, that Gudlaugson and his countrymen were released, and advised to return to Iceland. Bjorn Albrandson, however, made them presents, and among other gifts, he sent a gold ring for "Thurid of Frod," and a sword to Kjarton, her son, illegitimate, Albrandson being his reputed father of said Kjarton, at that date, lord of the estate of Frod River. The lucky Gudlief returning again in safety to Dublin that Fall, and having wintered there--which then, by the way, his cousins, the Danes, had possession of--next Spring sailed for Iceland, and delivered his presents from Albrandson to his divorced wife and son. These accounts, and others of the same import, favor the certainty of the Irish colonization, and their testimony is more strong from the fact that the Irish did not seek those witnesses to confirm their claims, but came voluntarily from the Scandinavians themselves.</p>
        <p>There is one thing, however, which, the Norse
        <pb n="100 Introductory Dissertation." />historian narrates as singular, namely, that about three hundred of the people of "Ireland it Mickla," seized on Gudlaugson and his companions, and having bound them were about to execute them, until Albrandson, accompanied by a procession of venerable men moving after a flag, released the party. These were Irishmen, and why was it that they were so determined to use the Norsemen roughly, until they were restrained by the clergy, "venerable men marching behind a flag?" The fact was that these men who accompanied Gudlaugson were recognized as pirates, and in the opinion of the people of "Great Ireland," ought to suffer death. But Gudlaugson, who probably was a priest or bishop, restrained the laity from taking just vengeance on those barbarous pirate's, and hence, they were allowed to return to Dublin, under Danish rule at that time, though the season was far advanced for them to return. Limerick at that date also, was under sway of Scandinavians, and hence, Rafn "the Limerick trader," ought to have been called the "Limerick pirate," for these barbarous Northmen who now claim the honor of being a "powerful and distinguished nation," were nothing but tribes of pirates, who obtained a livelihood by plundering and devastating old and wealthy communities, like those of the Irish.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 101." />The Scandinavian accounts of the discovery of America may be, and probably are substantially true, but in all their narratives there certainly is manifest a suppression of the truth in regard to the history of Ireland, as well as what is related regarding the people of "Great Ireland." Why do not the Scandinavian historians mention the fact that Iceland, or Thule, Celtic "Inis Thyle," was visited by the Irish missionaries, some say, as early as the sixth century? but it is certain that Dicuill, who wrote a geography of Iceland, lived in the eighth century. His book was entitled "De Mensura Provinciarum Orbis Terrae." The Irish missionaries visited Iceland at an early date, say the sixth century; but when the Norwegians reached there they expelled the Irish, whom they called "Papas," who left behind them "Irish bells, books and staffs" and other sacred relics. These things are suppressed by the modern Scandinavian historians. Ara Multerius, in his "Schol. De Island and the Land-na-Mabok," gives the same account of the "Papas," alias Papists, who were found in Iceland before the Norwegian settlements in 874. Two Irishmen, Buo and Ernulph, were missionaries in Iceland after 874, and were probably captives by the Norwegians from Ireland. The latter had a church erected in honor of St. Columbanus in Eisen-
        <pb n="102 Introductory Dissertation." />berg. Dufflan McEathan and Magulmenen committed themselves to the waves in a boat of skins and wicker-work, and finally became Norwegian missionaries. All these facts regarding the intercourse between Ireland and the Scandinavians are suppressed by the modern writers of that race, as is also all mention of their ancestors, whom they call a "powerful nation" of being pirates and robbers, during three or four hundred years, of all the maritime borders of the European continent as well as the islands of Great Britain and Ireland. The testimony of the historians of such a piratical race should be received with doubt in all matters relating to their own self-aggrandisement, although in reference to what they adduce relative to the existence of an Irish colony in Whiteman's Land must be of great value. But, it may be asked, if such a colony existed in America during the ninth and tenth centuries, how has it been cut off, and why have we no monuments, historical at least, of its existence? This can be easily accounted for. It is most likely that the Irish settlement in "Whiteman's Land" was originally no more than a missionary station, consisting chiefly of priests and monks, but, after a time that persons of secular character were induced to emigrate. It is entirely consistent with the disturbed state of society from the eighth
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 103" />to the twelfth century--from 795 to 1100--that all emigration for the Western Brandanic colony ceased, and that from the wars of the aborigines and other causes, the white race, in the course of two or three centuries, either were cut off or became amalgamated with the natives. Hence, not only did the Irish pre-Columbian colony cease, but all knowledge of it was lost during a period of three or four hundred years.</p>
        <p>The celebrated linguist, Kast, says there are certain analogies, however, between certain dialects of the Indian language and the old Celtic, which cannot be accounted for save from the supposition of former Celtic amid Indian intercourse. For instance, when the Chippewa Indians express astonishment they ejaculate "O, yea, yea, yea," and the Irish express it in the same form. The names of several rivers have the prefix "onan," as "Onandaigua," the same as Irish "owe," or Avon. The word "uiske," Irish, is synonymous with the Indian word "iske." There is a town in Minnesota, near St. Paul, on the Mississippi, called "Miniske," or Smooth Water, and the Irish word "Meiniske" is the same. The name of Lake "Erie" is also Celtic, and is identical with "Erin" or "Erie," the old name of Ireland; "ogimah," a brave or chief. Irish, "oge-magh," brave and good.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="104 Introductory Dissertation." />In fact, so marked is the analogy between both tongues that some of the most learned philologists of modern times have remarked it.* Who knows but that those brave Indians of Florida, whom it was so hard to subdue, and who finally, rather than yield to the conqueror, buried themselves in the imperishable forests of the Everglades, had some Irish blood in their veins?</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 105" /></p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER IV.">
        <p>SAME SUBJECT CONTINUED. THE INSCRIPTIONS ON THE MAS-SACHUSETTS AND RHODE ISLAND ROCKS OF ROMAN ORIGIN.</p>
        <p>PRE-COLUMBIAN DISCOVERY CERTAIN, BUT ITSMEMORY LOST THROUGH WARS, AND PLAGUES, ANDCIVIL DISORDERS. COLUMBUS DESERVES HIS FAME.</p>
        <p>OBJECTIONS TO SCANDINAVIAN RECORDS, THOUGH SERI-OUS, YET NOT SUFFICIENT TO INVALIDATE THEM ALTO-GETHER. IRISH DISCOVERY OF AMERICA BEYOND ADOUBT.</p>
        <p>The "Antiquitates Americanae," make the following relation, in reference to the discovery of Greenland and America: "Eric the Red, in 986, went out from Norway, on account of manslaughter, and settled in Iceland, and from there he sailed to Greenland soon after, and planted a colony.</p>
        <p>Gardar became the capital of Greenland, which for 400 years was governed by Norway. Torfeus, a historian, gives a list of seventeen bishops of Greenland. Lief, son of Eric the Red, set out in search of land, said to be observed by one Bearne, who had lost his way, from sailing from Norway to Greenland.</p>
        <p>Lief had 35 men with him, besides a German named Tryker. They discovered lands they
        <pb n="106 Introductory Dissertation." />named Helluland, Marksland, and finally Vineland, in which they wintered. When Lief returned home, his brother Thorwald renewed the voyage in 1002, and having discovered a beautiful bay and promontory which he called "Kealarnes." But when preparing to return, he was killed by Indians or Skrellings, and was buried with a cross at his head and feet. Eric's third son, Thorstein, attempted a third voyage, but failed to discover land. A third expedition set out in 1006, consisting of three ships, one commanded by Thorsfinn Karlsefne, the other by Bearn Gremalsson, and the third by Thorwall Gonlason, names not very euphonic. They remained for a few years, and Gudrida Karlsefne's wife gave birth to a son, christened Snorre. If these annals are reliable, this was the first white child that we know of, born in North America.</p>
        <p>There were two Irishmen in this expedition, Haker and Hares; as we will find, also, in an account of Columbus' first voyage. Still another voyage was undertaken in 1012, in which Gudrida, Eric the Red's daughter, sailed. They returned, and had very rich cargoes of wood and other merchandise, one piece of timber called mazertin, selling for half a mark. This Lady Gudrida, afterwards made a pilgrimage to Rome, and
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 107" />built a church in Iceland, which became a bishopric. It was from this stock that Thorlack Runalfson was descended, who wrote the Ecclesiastical Code of Ireland in 1123, and was a learned bishop of that country.</p>
        <p>It is recorded, further, that Bishop Eric Upsi, who got his bulls from Pope Pascal II, made a voyage to Vineland, and most probably died there, though the authorities are silent on that event.</p>
        <p>There is an account, also, in these "saghas," of a voyage towards the northwest by clergymen, from the see of Garder in Greenland. No doubt, zeal for the conversion of Skrellings, induced them to make the voyage, as it did the Irish Priests and monks of the eighth and ninth centuries, to visit Iceland, before the Norwegians ever landed there.</p>
        <p>Adalbrand and Therwold were priests in 1282, who discovered what they called' "Fundu Nyza Land," supposed to be Newfoundland. Adam of Bremen published a book in 1373, confirming all the above accounts. There have been found inscriptions on rocks in New England, such as Assonet rock, and in or near Bristol, Massachusetts, which were certainly made before the Columbian discovery. But great doubt is cast on those inscriptions, as far as Norse discovery is concerned, from the fact, that the Roman characters are used instead of the Runic.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="108 Introductory Dissertation." />On one of these inscriptions, called the "Dighton Rock," there is the figure of a boat, with that of a "woman and child" and the letter S, which the modern wiseacres interpret as signifying the name of "Snorre," the first child born in America, whereas, most unquestionably, it refers to the "Virgin and Child," with S for Salvator. Most likely those rocks were once used in erecting churches, and that these inscriptions in Roman character had reference to religious subjects. But now-a-days the fashion is to ignore religion altogether, if possible. One thing is certain, however, that before the discovery of Columbus in 1492, there were people of European origin settled on this continent, though, from the effects of wars, revolutions and even plagues, as the Black Plague of 1347, which swept off the one half of the people in some nations--from these and like causes all reliable accounts of these settlements were totally lost and obliterated. Hence the immortal Columbus will ever have, and deserves to have, all the glory and fame of the Discoverer of the New World. Those who doubt the truth of the Scandinavian records base their objections on the following considerations: Firstly; it is evident that the climate and productions said to belong to the countries discovered do not correspond with what
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 109" />we know of these countries at present. Vinland, or Massachusetts, never produced grapes in such abundance as that a cargo of this fruit could be shipped to Iceland, or that "corn springs up there without being sown," as Adam of Bremen asserts; secondly; the voyages that took the Scandinavians but two or three and six days to make could hardly be made now, in sailing vessels, in as many weeks; thirdly, these descriptions of luscious grapes would indicate the latitude of Canaries or Azores rather than that of New England. When "the Pilgrim Fathers" landed in the same latitude, six hundred years after the Scandinavians, we do not read that they regaled themselves like the German "Tryker," with the juice of rich grapes, or that they reaped any crops of grain of spontaneous growth. However, the climate may have changed within a period of six hundred years, and allowance must be made for the disposition to amplify and exaggerate by old writers, who, like Adam, of Bremen were not eye-witnesses of what they relate, but took their information from the verbal narratives of exaggerating travelers. Another remarkable circumstance in connection with these Scandinavian accounts is, that they never afford the slightest allusion to the well-known historical fact that their ancestors, at the date of
        <pb n="110 Introductory Dissertation." />their discovery of America, were notorious pirates and plunderers, and that if their "powerful chief, Are Marson," as they call him, was detained a prisoner in "Ireland it Mickla," the reason was, that he was recognized as one of the barbarians who had plundered shrines in Ireland, as the menacing reception which Gudlaughson and crew met with arose from the same cause, namely, that they were recognized as pirates.</p>
        <p>These defects, however, though they weaken, are not sufficient to invalidate, altogether, the testimony of the Scandinavian records, especially in as far as they go to confirm the Irish accounts of transatlantic settlements. For those Irish missionaries, who in the sixth and seventh centuries sailed in their "Curraghs," eight hundred miles to Iceland, where several of them became martyrs for the faith of Christ--such men could not be deterred by a distance of double that of Ireland from Iceland, which would bring them to Newfoundland. Hence, the conclusion is clear, that the Irish were the first Europeans who established settlements on this continent of North America. Although the Irish cannot claim any credit from their connection with the great admiral's discoveries, the entire glory redounding to him and to Spain; yet Ireland was represented, though in an humble
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 111" />position, among his seamen on his first voyage. We are informed by the Count De Lorgue, in his celebrated history of Columbus, that there were two natives of Ireland among his crews, and that one of them was a native of Galway, whose name is registered in the log-book of the "Santa Maria," as Johannes Galviensis--in other words, John Galvin.</p>
        <p>In every important event having reference to the New World, it appears that Ireland and her sons act a conspicuous part. Whether as the Celts who built the round towers, crumlecks, and forts, in pre-historic times, and left their monuments on the banks of the Ohio; or the plains of Mexico and Peru, or as the first settlers of Whiteman's Land, or Great Ireland; or as immigrants and pioneers under our present government all over the land, from Maine to California, or from Florida to Minnesota, or Texas to Manitoba, the Irish are ever present to cut down the savage forests, to dig the mine, to bank the canal, to construct the railroad, to cultivate the soil, or to fight the battles of freedom, and do everything else necessary for the building up and perpetuation of the only free government on the globe. This is the boast and glory of the Irish-Americans, that, whatever else they may lack as compared with other races, they cannot be excelled, and but seldom equalled, in their en-
        <pb n="112 Introductory Dissertation." />thusiastic attachment to the Republic and all its institutions. They may be divided in local affairs and differ as to the best policy to pursue in regard to the independence of Ireland--an idea which they cling to with implicit faith--but there is no class of citizens, as even their enemies confess, so attached to the institutions of the Republic as the Irish race and their millions of descendants' in the United States. In the late unhappy war they did not wait to be drafted; they volunteered, and they constituted one-third of the army, to go to fight and to die in defense of the flag of our common country. Even in a certain district of New England, where before the war they were deprived of the arms of the State, no sooner were they tendered back the arms again by repentant, but prejudiced officials, than they grasped them and rushed into the breach to save the country. The public danger caused them, though sensitive to the most delicate point of honor, to forget their private feelings in their zeal for the common safety.</p>
        <p>
          <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 113" />
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER VII.">
        <p>THE IRISH IN THE UNITED STATES BEFORE AND DURING THEREVOLUTION. THE BRAVERY OF IRISH OFFICERS ON LANDAND ON SEA. THE DECLARATION OF INDEPENDENCE. THEIRISH AT HOME ALWAYS IN FAVOR OF AMERICAN LIBERTY.</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON'S REPLY TO THEIR ADDRESS. THEIR SUCCESSIN ALL WALKS OF LIFE.</p>
        <p>We have records to show that during the first half of the seventeenth century large bodies of Irishmen, driven from their native land by persecution, were obliged to seek their fortunes in the New World. Many were transported by decree of the sanguinary tyrant, Cromwell, while some, from choice, sought a home in the New World. After the Revolution of 1688 one hundred thousand operatives were compelled to quit Ireland on account of unjust laws placing restrictions on Irish manufacture, in the reign of William and Mary, and about three thousand of these exiles, principally from Ulster, came to the colonies.* The Irish were prominent in Pennsylvania from the founding of that colony by William Penn in 1699, James*We take the substance of this chapter from McGee's "Irish Settlers in America," a work of great merit, and written in a style which places the book among the English classics.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="114 Introductory Dissertation." />Logan accompanied Penn, and filled his place when absent, as well as succeeded him after his death. That, besides Logan and other prominent citizens, a large number of Irish of the humbler classes composed the immigration of 1699, is evident from the names of the townships called Donegal, Derry, Tyrone, and others, which certainly were settled by natives of Ireland. The colony of Maryland was settled in 1689, and though generally regarded as an English settlement, had certainly a large percentage, if not a majority, of colonists of Irish birth, such as the Carrolls, amongst them.</p>
        <p>Virginia, like Pennsylvania, from the names of her leading citizens as well as localities, such as Kinsale, Lynchburgh, Mayo, had certainly, as early as 1700, a respectable contingent of Irishmen among her colonists. The McGruders, McDuffies, McDowells, as well as Kennedys, Lynches and McFarlands will tell their own story in reference to genealogy and origin. To these we may add the celebrated names of Patrick Henry, Andrew Jackson and Calhoun, though belonging to a later date in our history. Some of the most celebrated men of American history, such as the Moores, the McClellans, the Butlers, and even Daniel Boone, belonged to the Irish race by birth or immediate descent. The McGradys, the Har-
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 115" />lans, McBrides, O'Sullivans, Croaghans, Moylans, and Waynes are unmistakably Celts, and of the southern stock also, beyond a doubt. That the Irish were a pretty important element in Massachusetts as early as 1720 is proved from the records of the "General Court" of the colony, which disgracefully resolved thus: "Whereas, it appears that certain families, recently arrived from Ireland, have presumed to make a settlement--that the said people be warned to move off within seven months, and if they fail to do so that they be prosecuted by the attorney-general," etc. The reason why this unjust legislation against the Irish settlers was enacted was most probably on account of "prejudices against them by their zeal in diffusing religious opinions." See Moore's Sketch of Concord and McGee's Irish Settlers. About this time we read that an Irish servant was sold like a slave at auction, for four years, in the godly city of Boston. In the year 1737 a charitable Irish society was formed in Boston by forty* Irish gentlemen, whose names, given in McGee's work, show that they were not only of Celtic origin, but that
        <pb n="116 Introductory Dissertation." />even to this day some of the leading "solid men of Boston" descended from the same old stock. In 1719 the flourishing colony of Londonderry was formed on the Merrimack, and from that settlement the Irish spread through the interior townships of Vermont, Massachusetts and New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>In 1723, the town of Belfast was laid out in Maine, by a number of families from the North of Ireland. Among these was a schoolmaster named Sullivan, whose sons, John and James, became leading men--one of them a general--at the time of the Revolution. The Higgins and the O'Reillys, as well as the Youngs, are recorded as among the earliest settlers in Massachusetts. Berkley, the celebrated Bishop of the Protestant Church, a native of Kilkenny, who was the founder of Yale Col-
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 117" />lege, came to America in 1729. He was the first who brought a large library with him to America, and devoted his fortune and many years of his life to the benevolent purpose of converting and educating the natives. He was, before he came out, Dean of Derry, which he resigned in order to carry out his benevolent project, and on his return, became Bishop of Cloyne. This Bishop Berkley was a singular genius, and his writings, especially his "Theory of Vision," are full of paradoxical propositions. But it is as an Irishman and a friend to education and learning, that we claim him as belonging to our race. It was from Ireland, and by an Irishman, that the first college or university was erected in America; the first church organ and library were also brought by the same famous prelate, and thus early were the first foundations laid of that system of education, which has been so successful ever since in all the States.</p>
        <p>A table of statistics from Watson's Annals, of Philadelphia, giving the arrivals at that port, for the year 1729, gives the numbers of the several nationalities, as follows:Arrivals.</p>
        <p>Persons.</p>
        <p>English and Welsh269Scotch43Germans343Irish5,655
        <pb n="118 Introductory Dissertation." />And ever since that day, to within a few years since, the Irish immigrants have not only equalled, but exceeded that of all other nationalities combined. And what is more remarkable still, most of the fighting, and it may be said without exaggeration, all the labor of the country, have been done by the Irish, from the era of the Revolution to the present time. And yet the stump orators, and the editors of money-making journals, and the compilers of "ring" school books, are ever harping in their canting organs, that we are of the Anglo-Saxon race! Before the era of the Revolution, from 1744 until 1776, the colonists had an opportunity of "seeing service" in the wars between the French and English, for the possession of the country from the mouth of the St. Lawrence to the Mississippi. Even in this war which formed a prelude to that of the Revolution, the Irish element was of consequence. In these campaigns McGinnis fell, after having taken Forts Crown Point and Stark, and Montgomery became familiar with the art of war. Not only were the colonial Irish engaged in these wars, but even the Irish in the service of France also participated in this warfare, under Montcalm. Those "Wild Geese"* were at*A name which Irish exiled soldiers, received when going into foreign service.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 119" />Oswego, which they captured, and also at the retaking from the British of Forts George and William and Henry. To these names already mentioned must be added those of Governor Moore, Colonels Lynch, Kearns, Marian, Conyers, Harvey, and McCauley, in the Carolinas; whilst the Rutledges, Carrolls and Charles Thompson were the forerunners of the Revolution in the very first battles and skirmishes between the British and the colonists. The Irish Parliament refused to vote money to put down the American Rebellion, and the Irish in England, headed by Edmund Burke, Sheridan and Barre, spoke and wrote against the oppression by "the mother country" of the colonists, while the Irish in the French service volunteered to fight their battles. Such were the Counts McMahon, Dillon, Conway, and Roche Fermoy. One of the first acts of importance to the cause of Freedom was successfully performed by two Irishmen of New Hampshire. John Sullivan, son of the Limerick schoolmaster, surprised, in company with John Langdon, the fort at Newcastle, taking all the men in possession of the fort and a large quantity of small arms, gunpowder and artillery. In the first battle of the war, at Lexington, out of eight hundred New Hampshire militia at least one hundred were Irish, of all ranks, from Col. Moore, Maj. Gaffe and Capt.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="120 Introductory Dissertation." />McLaughlin, down to privates John O'Neil, Patrick O'Murphy, and Patrick Flinn. When General Washington took command, in 1775, three of his generals, Sullivan, Richard Montgomery, and Knox, his master of artillery, were Irishmen. The colony of New York raised some regiments, and James and George Clinton were placed in command, with Colonel James McCleary. In Pennsylvania, where the Irish were most numerous, several regiments were raised in 1775, and Wayne, Irving, Thompson, Stewart, Moylan, and Butler got the command of these as colonels; and that celebrated division of the revolutionary army was afterwards known as "The Pennsylvania Line." But it is not only in action that the Irish distinguished themselves. In supplying the sinews of war, when the Continental army was on the verge of starvation and mutiny, twenty-four Irish merchants subscribed $442,500 to supply food and clothing to the starving veterans of "Valley Forge." We find among these twenty-four names those of Shiel, Murray, Kean, Delany, Meade, and others of unmistakable Irish origin. The founders of the American navy and its most distinguished commanders were Irishmen or of Irish descent. John Barry, called the "Father of the American Navy," was a native of Wexford, so fruitful in heroes.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 121" />McDonough, Porter and McGee were trained under Barry. Nor should history forget to mention five brothers named O'Brien,* who, in the port called Machias, in Maine, took the two first prizes from the British by their extraordinary valor and enterprize. One of the first acts of the Continental Congress was to adopt an address to the Irish people exempting them from all blame in the bring-&lt;/horiztonal rule&gt;
        <pb n="122 Introductory Dissertation." />ing on of the colonial oppression; and Franklin, who made a tour of Ireland in 1771, says, in a letter to a gentleman in Boston, "I found them disposed to be friends of America, in which I endeavored to confirm them, with the expectation that our growing weight might, in time, be thrown into their scale, and by joining our interest with theirs a more equitable treatment from this nation (Eng-
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 123" />land) might be obtained for them (the Irish), as well as for us." And so it happened, for the first relaxation of the Irish Penal Laws was obtained after the American Revolution began. Franklin also addressed a letter, in 1775, to the Irish people, from Paris, advising them to refuse to join in the war against the colonies. That Franklin's counsels to the Irish people were not disregarded, the history of the country from the date of the Declaration of Independence to the present abundantly proves.</p>
        <p>The Declaration of Independence, signed by 56 patriots, were nine of them Irishmen by birth or descent. These were 1, Matthew Thornton; 2, James Smith; 3, George Taylor; 4, George Read; 5, Chas. Carroll, of Carrollton; 6, Thomas Lynch; 7, Thomas McKean; 8, Edward Rutledge; 9, Charles Thompson, the Secretary of the Congress which adopted the immortal document. John Dunlap, a native of Strabane, was the first who printed the document, as was John Nixon the first who read it in public, from the window of Independence Hall, Philadelphia. In fine, after the war was over, and the Constitution adopted through the wisdom of Washington, Jefferson, Madison, Hamilton, and Rutledge, Daniel Carroll, a relative of Charles, freely presented to Washington a farm, which was the site of the city of Washington.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="124 Introductory Dissertation." />That the great and wise Father of his Country appreciated the services of the sons of Erin in the part they took in establishing the Republic, is evident from his reply to an address made to him by a body of men representing the Irish-American and Catholic element in the country, and signed by Chas. Carroll, of Carrollton, Daniel Carroll, Thomas Fitzsimons, Dominic Lynch, and Bishop Carroll. To this address, "claiming equal rights of citizenship as the price of our blood spilt under your eyes, and of our common exertions for her defence under your auspices," Washington replied, in language worthy of his wisdom:"As mankind become more liberal, they will be more apt to allow that all those who conduct themselves as worthy members of the community, are equally entitled to the protection of Civil Government. I hope to see America among the foremost of nations in examples of justice and liberality. I presume your fellow-citizens will not forget the patriotic part which you took in the accomplishment of their Revolution, and the establishment of their Government, or the important assistance which they received from a nation--the French--in which the Roman Catholic faith is professed."It seems, indeed, that before a hundred years
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 125" />revolved, and the Centennial was celebrated, that some of our "countrymen," contrary to the hopes of Washington, have tried to forget what Erin's sons contributed towards our national independence, and that in many instances those who came in at the eleventh hour, long after the battles of the Revolution were fought and won, claim and receive more consideration than those whose blood enriched every battlefield, from Lexington to Yorktown, and whose race, whether in war or in peace, or in literature and in art, have carved their names indelibly and high on the pillars of fame. In Darcy McGee's admirably written book, "Irish Settlers in America," will be found the names, hundreds in number, of those Irishmen who, from before the era of the Revolution up to the year 1850, distinguished themselves in all walks of life in the army, such as Wayne, Montgomery and Sullivan. In the navy, O'Briens, Barry, McDonogh, Murray, and Steward. In the legislative councils of the Republic, the Carrolls, Rutledges, McKeans, Butlers. In the legal profession, Butler, Emmett, O'Conor, Brady. In the church, Carroll, Kenrick, Hughes, England. In the medical profession, Allison, First Provost of Pennsylvania Medical College; McNevin, Reynolds, Dalton, Winters. Writers on
        <pb n="126 Introductory Dissertation." />political economy, Colles, who suggested to Clinton the construction of canals, Adrian, Carey, and McGee, himself one of the ablest of modern writers, orators and statesmen. Indeed, it would seem as if Ireland sent out her best sons to infuse new life and pure blood into the arteries of our young Republic, as the best security that those institutions which she helped to establish should continue and become permanent. What a fruitful mother of heroes was Ireland, which, by the bravery of her sons, not only helped to drive the English from our country, but also lent a hand to destroy the sway of the cruel Spaniards over the South American Republics! Bolliver, in Columbia, was aided by the Devereuxs, the Moores, the O'Learys, and Fergussons, always around him, and fighting his battles. The greater part of his staff was composed of Irishmen, who volunteered to give freedom to his countrymen and conquer their oppressors, or die.</p>
        <p>In Chili, Irishmen were in high repute. Don Ambrosio O'Higgins held the high position of Captain-General of the country, and his son, Don Bernardo O'Higgins, was the legitimate heir of his patriotism. Gen. McKenna was next to O'Higgins in bravery. Peruvian independence was aided by Generals O'Connor, O'Carroll, and Esmond. The
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 127" />cruel Spaniard, Benevides, heartless tyrant, when he captured O'Carroll, cut out his tongue before putting him to death, and the beastly Algorte would have executed Gen. Esmond in a like cruel manner but for the interposition on his behalf of an English officer in high command. Buenos Ayres, too, was aided in its Revolution by Irish Generals, the O'Briens and McKennas. Deprived of their liberty in their native land, they appreciated its value, and hence, wherever there was a chance of establishing it, they were ever ready to aid in its advancement by the sword, cannon, or bayonet.</p>
        <p>Ireland might well adopt as her motto the words of the foundress of Carthage:The following is extracted from an American work, "Heroes of the Revolution," by Magoon:"Ireland's poets are among the oldest and the best. Her literati shine brightly amid the chiefest luminaries of art and science. Her martial heroes have never been excelled by those of any other nation; and of her statesmen, it is enough to say, that for centuries they have been what they now are, the best debaters and orators. When Ireland had national councils of her own, she shone su-
        <pb n="128 Introductory Dissertation." />premely in legislative wisdom and justice, and when forced into allegiance with England, she eclipsed the splendors she encountered. The brightest names in English generalship, science, jurisprudence, as Wellington, Burke, and Sheridan, are Irish. But it is in eloquence, especially, that Ireland may challenge the most renowned nations of the earth. An unbroken series of consummate orators illuminated the dreary history of that abused and much injured land like so many pillars of fire!"Another author says: "I will venture the assertion, that one-half the writers on the American press are of Irish birth or descent, at the present time. Indeed, to give the names only of distinguished Irish and Irish-Americans who have, even in modern times, done honor to the Republic, would fill a large volume. In Alabama, there were the Butlers, Kings, Duffys, Phelans. In Tennessee, were Patricks, Sharkeys, Brandons, Jacksons, Carrolls, Coffies. In Missouri, Mullanphy, McDonough. Illinois, Shields, McClernand, Eagan, Ryan, Ford. In Michigan, Cass, O'Flynn, Fitzgerald. Indiana, Hannegan, Ryan, O'Gorman, Browns, O'Niels, Dowling. In Wisconsin, O'Byrne, O'Neil, Johnson, Furlong, Ryan. In Iowa, Jones, Quigley, Mahony. In a word, as a plain Irishman, Captain
        <pb n="Introductory Dissertation. 129" />Murphy of St. Paul once said to the writer: Pick out the Irish element, who seem to be the 'salt of the earth' here, from among our population, and what will remain?"The following table, published by Commissioners of Emigration, New York, for '49 and '50, will show the strength of our people in this country:Countries.</p>
        <p>No. ofArrivals.</p>
        <p>1848.</p>
        <p>No. ofArrivals.</p>
        <p>1849.</p>
        <p>No. ofArrivals at thePort of NewYork alone.</p>
        <p>1850.</p>
        <p>Ireland - - 98,061112,561111,738Germany -51,97355,70545,335England - - 23,06228,32128,163Scotland - - 6,4158,8406,773The other countries together, France, Holland, Wales, Norway, and Italy, sent about ten thousand during these three years! By adding the above figures it will be seen that during the years 1848, 1849 and 1850 the emigration from Ireland exceeded not only Germany, England and Scotland, but was more than 70,000 more than all these countries combined.</p>
        <p>
          <pb n="[130]" />
          <pb n="[131]" />
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER VIII.">
        <p>THE IRISH IN CALIFORNIA. ITS RESOURCES AND PRODUCTIONS,CLIMATE, FRUITS AND MINES. MISTAKES OF CERTAINWRITERS CORRECTED. THE IRISH FARMERS' SUCCESS.</p>
        <p>THE CITIES PREFERRED TO LAND BY THE IRISH. THEREASON WHY. ACCOMPLISHMENTS OF IRISH FARMERS'DAUGHTERS. IRISH PIONEERS DESERVING OF HONOR, ETC.</p>
        <p>There does not seem to be on the globe a country so situated with regard to climate and soil as California. In the area of the State, containing about 160,000 square miles, there is every variety of climate, from the Arctic severity of her snow-clad mountains to the intense tropical temperature of her valleys. And though the State is eight hundred miles long by about two hundred broad, there is no part of it that a man cannot, in the journey of a day, and often of an hour, reach the extremes of
        <pb n="132 The Irish Race in California." />heat and cold, from zero to 100 degrees in the shade. This pleasing variety of climate is what constitutes the charm of California and causes emigrants from the East to imagine that they have found a terrestrial paradise when they feel the agreeable sensations of the Pacific skies. For instance, the fatigued overland traveler, after having crossed the melancholy plains, notwithstanding their numerous evidences of a past world, becomes sad and taciturn as he ascends the Sierras, whose freezing atmosphere seems to chill the blood in his veins. But no sooner does he quit the "Mountain House," where he was obliged to take a stimulant to escape freezing, and take his seat in the fast-moving train, than in an hour or so aftewards [sic] everything is changed. His heart beats quicker, his spirit revives, his very clothing is a burthen to him; he wants ventilation and throws up the windows, and then he beholds the country, broken and rugged, indeed, but yet bathed in all the glory of a tropical sun and enriched by all kinds of luxuriant fruit, the production of his genial rays. This is California's Summer reception of her visitors. But even in Winter the surprise to the incoming stranger is not less agreeable. Then all her peaks and hills, and rugged mountains, and deep ravines, and valleys are clothed in the most beautiful verdure,
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 133" />while her plains and arable lands are enrobed in a vestiture of flowers of the most variegated colors and delightful fragrance. California, like a rich empress, has a magnificent reception at all seasons of the year for those who visit her charming borders. And in keeping with her pleasing climate are the richness and variety of the productions of her soil. Fruits of all varieties--oranges, lemons, apricots, olives, grapes, as well as peaches, apples, plums, cherries, etc., grow often in the same field, such as in the valley of the Sacramento; while there are counties and districts of the State peculiarly suited to each species, such as lemons, grapes and apricots. There is one species of fruit, the grape, which grows more productively and with less care in its cultivation than in any country in the world. The largest vine in the world, probably, is the one at Montecito, near Monterey, which was planted by a Spanish woman, from a cutting, in 1795, and the trunk of which is about fifty feet in circumference, and used to produce over four hundred gallons of wine. This famous vine is now decayed. There is seldom a failure of the grape crop. The vines that are cultivated were introduced by the Spanish or Mexican missionaries a little over one hundred years ago, though there certainly were wild grapes, indigenous to the soil,
        <pb n="134 The Irish Race in California." />before the introduction of the foreign varieties. The varieties that are cultivated now are very numerous, though the cultivation of the grape may be said to be, as yet, only in its infancy. The statistics of grape cultivation are not very reliable, from the fact that new vineyards are being yearly planted. There are several large vineyards, however, the most productive, probably, that at Buena Vista, near the village of Sonoma, containing about 500,000 vines, being the largest. There are also some at or near Los Angeles of as large area. Those of Mr. Wilson, at San Gabriel, and Mr. Rose, of the same place, approach near to the vineyard at Buena Vista, which is the property of an association. John O'Brien, of Sonoma, has a large vineyard, the produce of which, about one hundred acres, he makes into wine. Lynch, of Cherokee, also manufactures the very best article of that beverage.</p>
        <p>There are many distinguished Irishmen who own large vineyards in Los Angeles County, among others, Governor Downey; Matthew Keller, who owns an extensive vinyard; David W. Alexander, a soldier who fought in the conquest of California; Doctor Den, son of the late lamented Doctor Nicholas Den, and many others. There are many Irish farmers engaged in wine culture, stock and sheep-raising, in the county of Los Angeles, all well
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 135" />to do, and a credit to the land of their nativity and race. The Irish-American farmers and settlers in the southern tier of counties have had little or no difficulty in making settlements, from the fact that the Spanish always treated them with great hospitality and kindness on account of religion and ancient national affinities of the two races.</p>
        <p>The average quantity of grapes which an acre will produce is estimated at 8,000 pounds, which, at five cents a pound, yield, when the grapes are sold, $400 to the acre, and deducting expenses, leaves the cultivator at least $200 per acre. In France and other grape-producing countries the vines are supported by poles or stakes, whereas in this State the vines stand alone, without support, and the nearer the ground the grapes are allowed to mature the richer and better they yield. The greatest number of stocks or plants to an acre is 1,000, but 680 plants only are cultivated in Sonoma and in more northern parts of the State. It is remarkable that the fruit grows on the NEW twigs, or sprouts, in California, whereas in older countries, in Europe, the wood of last season only bears fruit on the next year. In round numbers, it may be said that California produces 10,000,000 gallons of wine at present, and the production is continually on the increase. It is strange that with this large pro-
        <pb n="136 The Irish Race in California." />duce of the "blood of the grape" annually, Californians, as a general rule, are not a wine-drinking people, and of those who do use wine at the table, foreign and French brands are preferred to the native article. Advocates of temperance in the old country recommend the use of wines in preference to that of malt or distilled liquors, and point to the natives of wine-growing countries as being little addicted to drunkenness. It is to be regretted that the people of California do not support such theories or give examples in favor of temperance. But the result is owing, probably, to the fact that wine is not a popular beverage here, and that, owing to the facilities enjoyed by men to adulterate liquors, even the native wines, from defective revenue regulations, that the evils of intemperance are so very lamentable in this glorious State. Even in some large country towns, if a man called for a bottle of wine to use at dinner he would get, instead of the native article, a villainous compound called "port wine," not one drop of which was ever expressed from the grape. Some of the wines, too, which are in the market, like the "Angelica," are manufactured and mixed with brandy and granulated sugars instead of owing their flavor to the glucose of the grape; and this "doctoring" of wines, otherwise pure and genuine,
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 137" />is what brings discredit on the California wines in eastern and foreign markets.*Next to the grape in importance are the pears and plums, which, as well as the grapes, attain extraordinary size and delicious flavor in California. These fruits when shipped to the Eastern States,
        <pb n="138 The Irish Race in California." />generally lose their flavor, and are in a damaged condition, from the fact that they are picked off the trees before being ripe, in order that they may stand the transportation without loss to the shipper. California orange culture is only in its infancy, and farmers do not like to invest in this business,
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 139" />for the reason that it takes from seven to ten years before they get a profitable return. But there can be no crop more profitable if properly cultivated. It is estimated that in the latitude of Los Angeles ten acres of oranges will yield $15,000 a year; whereas cultivation, irrigation and other labor, only costs about $3,000 per annum. Besides these and other tropical fruits, the strawberry yields very abundantly, and this delicious fruit ripens, under proper care and irrigation, all the year round. In a word, all the fruits of the earth, the pomegranate, even, seem to do well in California, and in all parts of the entire State. Indeed, it is no exaggeration to say that if all the land in California--not far from 100,000,000 of acres--should be cultivated, like France or Italy, or the German Rhenish Provinces, and irrigated, 20,000,000 of people could be supported from the produce of the soil; and yet, with far less than a million of inhabitants, there are at least to-day forty thousand people without employment or a certain means of obtaining a living. The emigrant, when he lands, gets nothing to do, and hence all the advantages of the State have no attractions for him.</p>
        <p>This is certainly an anomalous condition of affairs. The Golden State sends its wheat in millions of bushels to feed the poor half-starved operatives of
        <pb n="140 The Irish Race in California." />Great Britain. She allows as much of her fruit to rot as would support thousands; the people are generous, hospitable, and proud of their country, and of her wealth in mines, in treasure, in agriculture, and in undeveloped resources. All that she appears to need to make her greater than France or any of the older empires of Germany, is population. And yet, of those who come to make their home in this second Holy Land, if we regard her natural advantages, the one-third of the poor immigrants, if not more, return back again to the East to end their existence in the condition of poverty and misery, in which they were born, in the attics of tenement houses. This state of things cannot be denied, and certainly is not what one would expect in this land so rich in minerals, so luxuriant in soil, and so blessed by God, beyond almost any part of the globe. Whether our Irish race in California has been instrumental in bringing about this strange state of affairs, we shall enquire subsequently. For the present, we shall continue briefly to enumerate further some of the leading advantages and resources of the State, and what our countrymen have done to improve and develop them.</p>
        <p>The mining interests of California occupy a leading feature in the wealth, not only of the
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 141" />State, but of the country, and it may be said, of the whole civilized world.*It would be out of the question to enter into a detailed account of the mines of this State and
        <pb n="142 The Irish Race in California." />of Nevada since the discovery of gold in 1848, to the present time. But certainly, it is within the mark to state, that in the first quarter of century, since the first gold was found, California and&lt;/horizontalrule&gt;
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 143" />her dependencies--if we may use the expression--yielded over a thousand eight hundred millions of dollars. It may be that one-half that sum was expended in mining and preparing the treasure
        <pb n="144 The Irish Race in California." />for the market. But, making every allowance for the cost and labor of mining, it is certain that this was the principal attraction that brought population to the State. It was the discovery of gold that enticed people from all parts of the globe to steer for the shores of the Pacific and the "Golden State." The "Sacra auri fames"--this insatiable hunger for the precious metals, it was that brought us the stoutest men from the frozen North and the parched South; that brought thousands across oceans and continents, and from islands and mainlands, from Asia, Africa and Oceanica, as well as from refined Europe. Gold was the magnet that attracted them--the idol which they came to worship. This
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 145" />pursuit brought us population, to build our railroads, dig our acqueducts [sic], cut down our forests, drain our swamps, to man and manage our ships, to erect our cities, and cultivate and improve our "generous soil." All, all was a consequence of the discovery of gold and the precious metals in such abundance on the Pacific slope. It is true that gold was discovered in California by the pirate, Drake, in 1579, who reports that he "found the earth of the country to abound in rich veins of gold and silver;" but that buccaneer, licensed by Queen Elizabeth, did not delay to pick up much of the gold that abounded. He thought highway robbery or piracy a quicker road to wealth than mining. The first finding of gold, however, by Drake, like the discovery of the continent by the Irish and Scandinavians, was forgotten for about two centuries. Captain Smith, the first who came overland to California, discovered gold in the Sierra Nevadas in 1826. He exhibited the gold to the chief men of the American Fur Company, who ordered him back to prospect the country further, but as he was killed by the Indians the matter was not further prosecuted. Some of our progressive orators reproach the old padres with ignorance and blindness because they never saw the gold under their sandals. It is now well known that the missionaries did know of the
        <pb n="146. The Irish Race in California." />existence of gold in California; but they knew well, also, that if the presence of gold in the earth was generally known their missionary labors would be useless. Their mission was not to reap a harvest of gold, but to gain souls. Not only would their mission be barren had they made known the existence of gold, but even their lives would be endangered. They would have starved to death for the want of cultivators of the soil, hence they kept their knowledge secret. Beside, we know that Francisco Lopez discovered gold on Pine Creek, Ventura County, near Santa Barbara, in 1842. In November, same year, Abel Stearns sent twenty ounces of this gold to Philadelphia. The mint assay was returned in August, 1843, from Philadelphia, and that paper is now in possession of the Pioneer Association of San Francisco. The mine produced $8,000 a year, worked rudely by Lopez, a Frenchman named Baree, and Yaqui Indians.*
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 147" />Before I enter into the history of the Irish race in California in detail, it becomes a duty to refer to a statement or two made by John Francis McGuire, in his popular book, entitled, "The Irish in America," which are entirely at variance with the facts in reference to the Irish of this State. In the XIIIth chapter of this book, he states, that "one-fourth the farming land in this State is in the hands of Irishmen." This exaggeration is flat-
        <pb n="148 The Irish Race in California." />tering to the Irish in California, but it is entirely erroneous. The Irish in this State do not own one-twentieth of the land; and if we take the entire State, which contains not far from one hundred millions of acres, the Irish do not occupy the one-twentieth part of the land. It may be stated without fear of contradiction, that the average of Irishmen on the land in California, is not greater than in the Eastern States, and far less than in Iowa, Wisconsin, Minnesota or any of the Western States. Certainly, large tracts of land are owned by Irishmen or their descendants, such as the Murpheys, McLoughlins, Moors, Glenns, Montgomerys, Logans, and others. But these are all owned by individuals. If the land of the 455 proprietors who own from 5,000 acres up to as high as 500,000 acres, like Lux &amp; Miller, or 255,000 acres, like Charles McLoughlin, 44,000, Thomas Fowler, or 700,000 like E. T. Martin, was to be divided and sold to actual settlers, then would we see a large Irish agricultural population. As it is, however, many hundreds of Irish farmers own, not only 160 acres or even a thousand, but some of them--like James Miller Esq., of "Miller Hall," San Rafael, Mr. Lucas and Mr. Redmond, of the same neighborhood, and Alexander Logan, of Colusa, Montgomery; and others of the same county, Thos.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 149" />Fowler, of Tulare, 40,000--own from six, to 12 and 20,000 acres each. Another statement of the Member of Parliament's book is also objectionable, as it is devoid of correctness, namely, that a "township in Marin County is almost exclusively possessed by Irishmen, nearly all of whom a few years ago were laborers, working for monthly wages on the ranches of the old proprietors, or delving in the mines." If this were true, it would be no disgrace, but an honor to those who, by patient industry and honest labor advanced themselves to be owners of the soil. But it so happens that, a great many, if not most of the Irish-Americans of Marin County, purchased their lands from the old proprietors, or received them from the Mexican Government, in lieu of services rendered, like Don Timoteo Murphy, the Alcalde for some time of San Rafael. What is true of our countrymen in the Eastern States, and what has been characteristic of them for centuries, is, namely, that they prefer settling in cities rather than on land. This is the case also in California. There are more Irishmen in *San Francisco--three to
        <pb n="150 The Irish Race in California." />one--than there are in the rest of the State and in Nevada and Oregon added. Whether this happens from their social habits or family connections, or that they prefer the cities on account of the opportunities they afford for the education of their children, in science and in religion, people may differ in opinion, though we regard the last as the true cause of the love for the cities. But
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 151" />the fact remains, that the Irish race in America are generally located in cities and villages, notwithstanding all the advice they receive gratis, and efforts made by so-called emigration societies, to induce them to settle on lands. In their native land, no such disposition exists among the Irish. At home they prefer the country to the city, and cling to the land with the tenacity of the
        <pb n="152 The Irish Race in California." />ivy to the old ruined abbey wall. This is easily accounted for. At home they have the church and the school, now, thank God, at their very doors, even in the country, and the convent vesper bell is often heard by them from the neighboring cloister under the roof of their snug thatched cottages. Hence, they love to occupy and till the soil. But here, aye, even in California, the farmer is in most cases out on the plains, or in the secluded valleys, a mile or two, or even six from a school, and fifteen, twenty, or even forty miles from a church, which he can only visit once or twice in the year. His children grow up under a training he cannot approve. He may not be rich enough to send them into the cities to college, and even if he should do so a year or two, these make but a feeble impression, compared with the rough habits of a rude neighborhood. Perhaps, before his son or daughter is of age, he is disobeyed, or insulted and disgraced. Is it any wonder that the old man and his wife Mary try to sell out the place and come into the city to get a lot and a home, where he can be near the "House of God, anyhow ?" Of course, wealthy farmers, as we are happy to know many of the California Irishmen to be, have not these difficulties to contend with. There are many farmers in the vicinity of San Francisco,
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 153" />who, not content with sending their children to the excellent educational establishments of Santa Clara, under the Jesuits, and San Jose, under the pious and learned sisters of Notre Dame, but even send them all the way to Ireland to be educated. There is a gentleman in Oakland named Allen, who sent his daughter, after she graduated at the convent, all the way to Cork, to learn to read, write and speak the sweet old Irish tongue. And I am told she is prouder of her knowledge of the language of her forefathers, than of all her American accomplishments, and they are not a few. I met in farmers' houses in California young ladies, whose education could not be excelled, and who in their manners and accomplishments, such as music and singing, could rank with ladies of the highest class in Europe. But, no "160 acres, nor even 1,000 acres" of the best land could enable a farmer to give such a first-class education to his children. Those to whom I allude own from six to 12,000 acres of the best lands in the State.</p>
        <p>These lands were purchased by the pioneer Irishmen, who crossed the plains before the discovery of gold, and whose trials and sufferings, and perseverance--to be referred to hereafter--prepared them and pointed them out as men destined to succeed. The memories of such men deserve
        <pb n="154 The Irish Race in California." />to be handed down to posterity, and if they lived in the old classic days of Greece or Rome, they would have monuments erected in their honor, if for nothing but for having attempted to have crossed the plains, and thus individually to have earned a right to a higher niche in the temple of fame, by marching a distance greater than the ten thousand Greeks did under Zenophon, over the plains of Asia. We have never known an Irishman who crossed the plains, who was not, if not rich, at least in the possession of all the necessaries of life. The reason for this may be found in the fact, that none but those who have ability to succeed anywhere, would have risked the severe trial of travelling two thousand five hundred miles over a dreary desert, in order to found a homestead under the smiling skies of California. This has been done by many, and if we cannot give an account of them all in this book, it is not a lack of good will and intentions, but a lack of space that prevents us from doing so.</p>
        <p>
          <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 155" />
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER IX.">
        <p>THE FIRST SETTLERS OF THE IRISH RACE. HOW THEY ARRIVED,AND WHENCE AND WHEN THEY CAME. THE SMITHS,READS, MURPHYS, DENS, BURKES, MOORES AND OTHERS.</p>
        <p>THE LAW-ABIDING CHARACTER OF IRISH SETTLERS. THEIRSUCCESS AND INSTANCES OF THEIR HUMANITY AND CHARITY.</p>
        <p>THEIR HORROR OF MURDER AND RESISTANCE TO THE VIOLENT MEASURES OF "LYNCH LAW." FEWNESS OF THEIRISH IN VIGILANCE COMMITTEES. THOMAS FRANCISMEAGHER A VICTIM OF VIGILANCE COMMITTEES.</p>
        <p>The first Irish settlers in California are unknown, and will probably always remain in oblivion, with their names "unknown, unhonored and unsung," like those of their forefathers in "Ireland it Mickla," whose memory and history have perished from the records of history. It is certain that American whaling ships made voyages to the Pacific coast at an early date, after the Revolution, and as equally certain that many of the crews were Irishmen, not a few of whom deserted, especially when insulted, as was afterwards the case--then as well as now-- in reference to country or religion. A tradition exists, that a man named Logue, in 1800, was on board a whaler, who, on being offended by the mate for putting a piece of pork to his mouth on
        <pb n="156 The Irish Race in California." />Good Friday, stabbed the latter to the heart, and leaping overboard, escaped to the main land in the neighborhood of Mendocino. But the first record which we have of a man who made the overland trip, was of one Captain J. Smith, who reached this coast with a party of immigrants, or rather trappers, in 1826. Captain Smith's presence alarmed the Spanish inhabitants somewhat, seeing that himself and men were well armed, and hence, Father Zuran, of San Jose, sent an embassy to him to enquire of his prospects and intentions. Smith, who was a native of Kings County, Ireland, wrote to the missionary, stating that his object was trapping and his intentions pacific, and signing himself "your stranger but real friend and Christian Brother, J. Smith."This party, under Smith--forty in number--were mostly all murdered by Indians. Few only escaped, and among them, one Fallan--and two other Irishmen--a native of Galway, who settled in the country. Smith also escaped the massacre, and afterwards obtained a lucrative position as chief trader under the American Fur Company on the Green River. Having returned to California again a year or two afterwards, Smith was also killed by Indians.</p>
        <p>Though there were several other Irishmen, who, as
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 157" />officers on board sailing vessels, visited the coasts of California, and not a few of whom took up permanent residences here, yet, having married Spanish wives and learned to speak the "lingos di deos," they became completely Mexicanized, and have transmitted nothing save their names to prove their origin and descent. But, one of the most remarkable Irishman who came to California permanently to locate, at an early date, wasJOHN J. READ, ESQ.,Of Marin Co., who was among the first, if not the first Irishman who came to this coast to settle permanently. He was born in Dublin in the year 1805, and left Ireland in 1820. His uncle, it appears, was a seafaring man or in the English navy, and took young Read from home on a voyage to Mexico. From Mexico he came to California, in a Mexican national vessel sailing from Acapulco, and arrived here in 1826 just after reaching his majority. His first halt was at Los Angeles, but, after a short time, came he north and settled at Saucelito, Marin County, of which he was the first white or English-speaking resident. He was the first who erected a mill in the county, on the grant of land comprising one league and one-half which he received as early as 1834, from Governor
        <pb n="158 The Irish Race in California." />Figueroa. He was the first who surveyed and took soundings of the bay in the immediate vicinity of San Francisco and the neighboring islands, and probably established the first ferry boats across the bay from Saucelito to San Francisco. He made various improvements on his ranch, such as fencing, planting of orchards and fruit trees, and introducing some imported cattle.</p>
        <p>All this was accomplished by this energetic young Irishman when he was no more than 30 years of age, and while he was a single man. Finally, in 1836, the energetic young rancher got married at the Mission Dolores church to Hilarita, youngest daughter of Don Jose Antonio Sanchez, commander of the Presidio of San Francisco. This event took place on the 13th of October, '36. During all this time the young Leinsterman did not forget his widowed mother in Ireland, but kept up a regular correspondence with her, and got her blessings and counsel, accompanied by some presents to grace his nuptials with Miss Sanchez. On the year of his marriage be was appointed Commissioner of the Mission of San Rafael, a position he no doubt owed to his matrimonial alliance. His marriage was a happy one, and he had four children, named respectively, John, Hilarita, Ynes, and Richard. Mr. Read died young--
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 159" />38 years of age--in 1843, leaving the above named children survivors, who are all in prosperous circumstances. John Read, Esq., inherits the paternal ranch, and one of the daughters is wife of J. Boyle, Esq., another Irish-American of San Francisco. The remains of Mr. Read repose in San Rafael Cemetery where his surviving relations often visit to pay the tribute of prayerful commemoration to the memory of a worthy man.</p>
        <p>DON TIMOTEO MURPHY,Who came by sea from South America, as early as 1828, was born in 1800, in the town of Coolaneck, parish of Edermine, barony of Ballaghkee, the patrimony of the Wexford Murphys, in the County of Wexford. His mother's maiden name was Miss Stafford, a lady remarkable for comeliness and character. Young Tim, as he was called, got a good commercial education--his father being in comfortable circumstances--and after having completed his schooling, he got a position in a commercial firm in Dublin, but soon exchanged it for a better one in a large concern under English control, in Lima. He remained in Lima, however, not entire two years, because of a duel with some Englishmen, most likely, who are ever ready to taunt "Paddy" with some defect, especially if, by
        <pb n="160 The Irish Race in California." />his talents, he throws themselves into the shade. The young Wexford man was not dismissed [sic] the service of the English firm of Hartnell &amp; Co., but sent out to superintend an establishment of theirs in Monterey for packing and exporting beef. Accordingly, in 1828, he started for the land of flowers. Murphy was a man of commanding appearance, stood six feet two and one half inches high, muscular and straight, with a fair, florid complexion and an aquiline nose. He was a famous "shot." Even up to the day of his death, he could kill a deer or antelope at a distance of one-fourth of a mile, with his rifle. He also kept a large kennel of beagles and greyhounds, thirty-five of which he had at one time sent to him, by sea, by his cousins, the Conroys of Callao. Besides hunting for sport, he used to pursue other game, such as otters, which abounded in Marin County at that early time and whose pelts he used to sell for forty dollars each. He must have had letters of introduction to the governing Spanish authorities of Mexico, for, soon after his locating in California, he received from Don Micheltorena a grant of land of three leagues at "Point San Pedro," "Santa Margarita," and "Las Galinas," near San Rafael. After the plunder of the Missions and their secularization, Don Murphy was
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 161" />made Indian Agent and Commissioner of the Tribe of Nicassians. When Fremont invaded the State, with his Bear-flag followers, in 1846, on his way north, he paid Don Timoteo a sudden visit, and robbed him of some sixty animals, horses and mules. Don Timoteo lived and died a bachelor. He was of a very liberal mind, and his charitable donations were large. He donated some 1,000 or 1,200 acres to the orphan institution near San Rafael, and deeded large and valuable lots of ground, in the City of San Francisco, for church purposes. The site of the present Palace Hotel was once his property--a hundred vara lots of which he gave a free gift for a church. He died in 1853, in union with the Church, attended by Father Jno. Scanlon, after having devised his large estate to his nephews, Mathew Murphy's sons, and John Lucas, Esq.., also a nephew of his, who is at present proprietor of the splendid ranch Santa Margarita, near San Rafael. The old gentleman's remains lie interred in the San Rafael Catholic Cemetery. The memoirs of this representative of the Irish race are necessarily scant, from the fact that writers of books in California generally make it a point to ignore altogether, if they do not misrepresent, the lives and actions of distinguished Irishmen. If for instance, we peruse, from cover
        <pb n="162 The Irish Race in California." />to cover, that badly-written and notoriously-prejudiced book called "The History of California and Annals of San Francisco," we find no notice of Don Timothy Murphy, and those few Irish-Americans like Kearney, Riley, O'Farrell and Coppinger, whose names the editors could not well omit, are put down as English or British. But it is not only in the suppression of important facts regarding events in California that "The Annals" are defective, and unreliable. The writers, from the beginning, show their prejudice as well as ignorance by talking of a "priest-class, who rivetted the chains of Christianity on poor heathens." Who, "the sooner they are already weeded out, (viz., the aborigines) the better. Yet the fathers would retain them; then sweep the fathers away, too." These sentiments are ferocious and disgraceful. It is thus that these three editors, worthy to be disciples of Cromwell, coolly, in their "Annals," recommend wholesale massacre of the aboriginal race. Again, the "Annals" men, in page 70, call the fathers "ignorant and unlettered men, knowing little more than the mechanical rites of their church, though they seem to have been personally devout, self-denying and beneficent. They thought they did God a service in catching, taming and converting the Indians to Christianity," instead of hunt-
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 163" />ing them to death, starving and shooting them, as the authors of "The Annals" recommend as the most expeditious way to enlighten them. Do the "Society of California Pioneers," really approve of those "Annals," with all the prejudice, bigotry and bad taste they display? If they do not, as many of them cannot, then they should not accept the dedication made to them as a body, of a stupid book so unworthy of its title as "The Annals of San Francisco." In its report of immigrants for one year, when the arrivals were numerous, the Irish are omitted altogether, though Poles, Swedes, Welsh, and almost all other nationalities are mentioned. They give ample evidence of their prejudices against the Irish, yet the book is read by Irishmen! And where "The Annals" record the names of talented actors such as Kirby, McCloskey, Catherine Hayes, Matilda Heron, Dennin and others, they are recorded as English! In a word, it is to be regretted, that "The Annals of San Francisco" are of any authority, and it is certainly not an evidence of taste or judgment of those few Irish families, we hope, in whose book-shelves it is to be found. A more ignorant, unfair, or unreliable book was never written than these "Annals of San Francisco." Returning to the names of settlers of Irish birth
        <pb n="164 The Irish Race in California." />or origin under the old Spanish or the Mexican rule, the name of Daniel Hill, Esq., must not be omitted. He was probably an earlier settler than Don Murphy, having arrived by sea about the year 1823. He married with the Ortega family, of Castilian descent, and his children are thoroughly Spanish. One of Hill's daughters, Signora Donna Rosa, became the wife of the distinguished Dr. Nicholas Den, a native of Waterford, who made California his home long before Fremont and his followers raided, under the "Bear-flag," or scaled the Sierras. *Dr. Den owns a large quantity of land near Santa Barbara, and stands deservedly high in the community, both Spanish and American. He settled there, probably, in 1842, if not before, and is blessed with a charming family, all educated in first-class style. The doctor, from mere sympathy and compassion, interposed be-
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 165" />tween the famous Ned McGowan and his persecutors, by secreting the fugitive in his mansion for several weeks. It was finally through Dr. Den's influence and recommendation that McGowan surrendered himself when the reign of terror ceased, was tried and acquitted, and proved by law and public opinion, to have been entirely guiltless of the crimes laid to his charge, but, for which on mere suspicion, he would have been hanged, but for Providence, and the interference of such noble men as Dr. Nicholas Den, and his Spanish neighbors and connections.</p>
        <p>JAMES W. BURKE, ESQ.,Was another gentleman of our race, who has made California his home nearly fifty years, having arrived from Lima in 1830. He too formed marriage connections with the Spaniards, who, of all foreigners, come nearest the Irish in disposition. Capt. Burke was a seaman from his boyhood, and circumnavigated the globe, ere he settled down in Santa Barbara. He was native of Galway, Ireland, and has left a family, his offspring, in good circumstances. The jovial old sea-captain was hale and hearty at the age of 80 years. He died last Winter, universally regretted, 1877, and his remains were attended to their last resting-
        <pb n="166 The Irish Race in California." />place by all the citizens of Santa Barbara and vicinity.</p>
        <p>CAPT. MOOREIs another gallant Irishman, some time in the British naval service, who came to California in 1851. It was on the vessel commanded by him, that Thomas P. McGee escaped in 1848 to the United States. He got married soon after his arrival, and is located on a rancho called "Sal si puades," near Santa Barbara. Thomas Hope, a a [sic] native of Galway, came at an early day to the vicinity of Santa Barbara, where he resides.</p>
        <p>F. J. MAGUIRE, ESQ.,A brother to the late John Francis, of honorable memory, is one of the Irish-American hidalgos of Santa Barbara, and a Judge of the County Court. Mr. Maguire is nobly connected in Ireland with the Murphys of Cork, and others of the aristocracy, and though educated to one of the learned professions, preferred to follow for a time commercial pursuits, in which he was very successful. He became involved in the young Ireland politics of the year '48, and had to seek the protection of the "stars and stripes" against the convict's life which England had in store for those who are guilty of the crime of loving Ireland.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 167" />A gentleman named Reid also adds another name to this group of distinguished Irishmen who occupy an independent station in this fairest portion of California, and have occupied the same many years before the discovery of gold (except Mr. Maguire alone), or there was any talk or need of "vigilance committees," "hounds," "hoodlums" or halters, or other such kindred and constant accompaniments of Anglo-Saxon civilization. It is a fact remarkable and creditable to the humanity of the Irish race, and evidence of their love of law and order, that out of 200 names of vigilance committee-men there are not a dozen names of Irishmen among them. On the other hand, representative Irishmen, such as the Donahoes, the Casserlys, Sullivans, Downeys, Brodericks, Hayes, and others, kept clear of that organization, and used their influence to have the reign of law and order restored. Thomas Francis Meagher, of Montana, also set his face, like a globe of steel, against the vigilancemen of that Territory, having declared in public that, while he held supreme authority, no man should be condemned unheard or suffer death until after a legal trial. And for this plain but stern declaration his own life was threatened by a murderous banditti. And it is the general opinion now, formed from reliable data, that poor Meagher was dogged day and
        <pb n="168 The Irish Race in California." />night by the agents of the vigilants, who, in the dark hour of midnight, assissinated [sic] the hero of a score of battles by stabbing him and flinging his body into the muddy waters of the Missouri. The Irish, our countrymen, will kill a tyrant or shoot a landlord who has exterminated a people and depopulated a district (which some maintain they have a right to do), but they will not murder a man in cold blood or commit the outrage of taking the life of a human being for a violation of law, which, when compared with the acts of the vigilance people, cannot be regarded in any other light than as trivial or venial. And this is one of the proofs they give us of the superiority, forsooth, of the Anglo-Saxon race over the Spanish. No doubt the rope, the revolver and the mob are important factors in that civilization which is yclept Anglo-Saxon.*
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 169" />JOHN LUCAS, ESQ.,Of Santa Margarita ranch, near San Rafael, consisting of about 10,000 acres, inherited from his uncle Don Timoteo Murphy, came directly to this country from Ireland in 1852. He is a native of Wexford County, Ireland, and is the son of a hero of ninety-eight--Harry Lucas, who was born in 1775, and fought for his country in most of the actions between the military and peasantry in the county of Wexford. Young Lucas was as brave a young man as ever wielded a pike, and many a black-hearted militiaman bit the dust before the point of his weapon. He fought under Father Murphy at "Oulart Hill," and got severely wounded from a musket ball, which struck him on the jaw-bone, which was fractured, and severed the lower maxilary artery, from which he narrowly escaped bleeding to death. Having no surgical aid, his sufferings were intense,
        <pb n="170 The Irish Race in California." />and for three weeks he lay in a ditch under a covering of briars, which shielded him from the fury of the yeomanry, who gave no quarter, but murdered in cold blood all they suspected of disaffection or sympathy for the national cause. His food and drink were brought to him by night, by an old woman, who was so decrepid [sic] as not to attract the suspicion of the loyalists. He finally recovered his health and strength, and even his jaw-bone united naturally, without leaving but little signs of deformity. Harry Lucas lived to a ripe old age, leaving several children, the principal one of which is the subject of this brief sketch. John Lucas, Esq.., inherits no small share of the character of his ancesters [sic] on both sides, and is a most prosperous farmer. He is the father of an interesting family--three daughters and two boys--some of whom are married, and all educated in the very best schools in the State. His wife, however, not content with the home education of California, has sent one of her sons to Ireland to get him thoroughly instructed in the celebrated classical institutions of that country. Mrs. Lucas' family maiden name was Sweetman, and has exercised a marked influence in the refined manners which distinguish her children. Whether Lucas is derived from the old family name Lugardh, or of the English Lucas
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 171" />patromymic [sic], is not evident to the writer. Certain it is, however, that the proprietor of the Santa Margarita ranch is a genuine Irishman of no common stamp, distinguished by the prominent characteristics of his countrymen.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER X.">
        <p>LANDS AND FARMS, AND THE WAY TO OBTAIN THEM. MIS-REPRESENTATION OF RINGS AND CORPORATIONS INJURI-OUS TO IMMIGRANTS. DISAPPOINTMENT OF THOUSANDSAND INJURY TO THE STATE FROM THIS CAUSE. THEIRISH FARMERS ALWAYS SUCCESSFUL. THEIR PROSPERI-TY IN SANTA CLARA COUNTY. THE MURPHY FAMILY AMODEL FOR IMITATION FOR ALL. THEIR SUCCESS, VIR-TUE, PRUDENCE, PATRIOTISM. WEXFORD, THE MOTHER OFHEROES, ETC.</p>
        <p>There are at least four methods by which a man can get possession of land, ordinarily, in the United States; namely, by purchase from the Government of the lands in the market at $1.25 an acre; by title under the homestead law; by pre-emption, and by purchase from private individuals. In California all these ways to obtain title to lands prevail, but most, if not all, of the public lands are already taken up, those that remain unsold
        <pb n="172 The Irish Race in California." />being either arid deserts, parched mountains, out-of-the-way valleys, or swamps difficult of reclamation. Emigrants from the East in search of homes do not consider this distinction regarding lands, because the character or proper description of the lands are not explained to them. For instance, he reads in a book or pamphlet got up by some interested parties here--such as Nordhoff's book, written in the interest of rings and land-grabbers, railroad monopolists, or land speculators--that California, besides "27,000,000 of surveyed lands, has over 80,000,000 of un-surveyed lands." And thinking that all these lands are alike in fertility, he sells out his small farm in the East, packs up his goods, pays the price of a snug farm to the railroadmen for bringing him and his family to the Golden State. But, when he comes to San Francisco, he finds, when too late, that all the valuable lands are in the hands of great land-grabbers, who would not sell an acre of their princely domains for less than $200, and some of it would sell for $500 an acre. The immigrant becomes discouraged, packs up his things again after having travelled around for two months, his wife and children staying at a hotel in the mean time. He returns to the East "dead broke," dispirited and deceived, cursing his folly and his fate, and the soulless rail-
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 173" />road corporation, which, after having run him out very rapidly on first-class trains, now sends him back on emigrant cars, over the dreary, tedious, slow route to the East again, where he came from. This is an every-day occurrence of immigrant life among us, and such heartless treatment of that useful class of our population is doing more to retard the progress of California than any other circumstance. Our Irish race, however, though badly used by those corporations, manage to surmount all the obstacles thrown in their way toward advancement and success. The railroad monopolists seldom impose on them a second time. They seldom or never return to the East after having pitched their tents under the glorious skies of California. They do not all become millionaires, like the more fortunate of their countrymen, but if there is any life in the labor market, they are the soul of it. They succeed pretty well in the cities; where, unhappily for themselves, too many of them locate, notwithstanding the cosmopolitan competition which they have to encounter. But in the country, on the land, they never fail. There is scarcely an instance, either in the East or West, of an Irishman getting a farm of land ever becoming bankrupt. An Eastern example will illustrate what we here state. In Washington County, in the State of New York, there were two
        <pb n="174 The Irish Race in California." />or three poor Irish farmers, deeply in debt, about 25 years ago. But after the breaking out of the late war, many, if not most of the American farmers put all their property into Government bonds, purchased at 25 cents on the dollar, and paying no taxes. They sold their farms on time to Irish laborers, at an average of $100 an acre, thinking that the latter would not be able to pay the purchase money, for few of them could pay one-fourth down, and that they would have their farms back again. All predicted the ruin and the folly of the Irish farmers in purchasing the land at such high figures. But out of five hundred Irishmen who purchased such lands, not one of them but paid up the purchase money and interest. They are all now independent, among others, Patrick Buckly, Michael Conway, H. Duggan, Thomas McGowan, Daniel Deleury, the Bane Brothers, and five hundred others.</p>
        <p>They may talk of scientific farming and of the splendid farming of some of our great land-grabbers, but for successful farming, we maintain the Irish can't be beaten. Is it any wonder that those who made a living, aye, and made money, at farming in Ireland, under the most grasping landlords in the world, often, at a rent per acre sufficient to purchase forty acres in the United States, that is, $50
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 175" />a year per acre--is it any wonder that the Irish farmer, trained in this hard school of landlord tyrranny [sic], should succeed and get rich on a farm which is his own in fee simple forever? There are many localities in California where our Irish farmers have become independent and rich. Some in Colusa County, like the Logan Brothers, Pat. O'Brien, Peter Dolan, Mr. Walsh, Mr. Casey, John McConnell, P. Begley, Mrs. Campbell, etc. Some in Yuba and Sutter counties, as the O'Briens, Talant, Bunce, Corkeran, O'Connor, Slattery, etc. It is in Santa Clara County, however, that we find Irish farmers and Irishmen generally in the most prosperous condition. The actual number of Irish and Irish-Americans in Santa Clara County could not be easily obtained by the writer. But taking the number of voters as the basis of population, we may safely put down the number of our race as one in four, or at least one-fifth of the inhabitants. The number of registered voters is about nine thousand, and of these ten per cent., or nine hundred, are given as of Irish nativity. But upon counting over the names upon the great register we found many well-known Irishmen who are credited to Canada, Pennsylvania or other states, for the reason, perhaps, that, when asked where they came from, they mentioned the, places from
        <pb n="176 The Irish Race in California." />which they emigrated. We could not suppose that men whom we knew to be born in Ireland would call themselves Canadians or Pennslyvanians [sic] to avoid the odium and unpopularity of being considered Irishmen. This would be disgraceful; and there is not among the gallant and thriving Irish-Americans of Santa Clara one whom it would be possible to suspect of such meanness. Instead of only nine hundred voters' names on the great register of Santa Clara their number ought to be, including the sons of Irishmen, of course, two thousand four hundred, or about the one-fourth of the entire number. This is the result of a more careful study of the names of the voters on the great register, and certainly the one-fourth of them are of Irish origin. The same is true of the voters of San Francisco. It is a fair calculation that if there are 12,500 names whose native place is Ireland, there are at least one-half if not more, of persons of Irish descent who are credited, but do not really belong to, any other than the Irish race.</p>
        <p>Luckily for themselves, the Irish pioneers of Santa Clara settled in a most favorable situation for their previous education and customs. There the climate is healthy and delightful, while the soil is rich and suited to the production of the
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 177" />greatest variety of crops. Here, also, are located the colleges of the Jesuits and the academies of the "Sisters of Notre Dame," thus affording them every opportunity of having their children splendidly and safely educated. The Academy and University of Notre Dame in San Jose cannot be surpassed in America in all the appointments and conveniences of a first-class education. And as for the Jesuit colleges, to mention them is enough to recommend them. Many of our Irish people, no doubt, were attracted to this pleasant valley by the fame of those celebrated institutions of learning, and all their children have profited by the opportunities presented to them. This is, and was from the beginning, the home of the distinguished Murphy family, who were among the first, the most successful, and the most popular that ever crossed the Atlantic to ennoble the land of their adoption by their public and private virtues.</p>
        <p>Martin Murphy, the head of this distinguished family, was a native of the County of Wexford, Ireland, and emigrated from the land of his nativity with other members of his family, in or about 1820. Their destination was Canada, where the Murphys and their connections resided for several years, and prospered by farming on an extensive scale. In 1840, getting tired of the climate, or
        <pb n="178 The Irish Race in California." />possibly disgusted with British rule, Martin and his children immigrated to Missouri, where they settled on land also. Finding after a trial that the district in Missouri where they settled was plagued by malarious diseases of a malignant character, through which Mr. Murphy, Sen., lost his amiable wife--Mary Foley, aunt of Bishop Foley, now of Chicago--the old man, now about sixty years, determined "to pull up stakes" and steer for the far West, toward the setting sun. He had heard glowing accounts of the climate, soil and salubrity of the country from trappers and returning hunters, and he determined to reach it, though he knew it would take six months' continual travelling to do so. The old man's plan having been laid before his family and friends--consisting of about twenty-five individuals--they all assented to the seemingly desperate undertaking of crossing a desert 3,000 miles wide, infested with hostile Indians, in order to reach a country under a foreign government, and which looked with suspicion on immigrants from the United States. Such an undertaking, certainly, at that early day, when California was a Mexican Territory, required wonderful faith, energy, perseverance and resolution in no small scale, and point out the men who conceived and carried it out as heroes of no common
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 179" />stamp. Martin Murphy was accompanied by his five sons and four daughters. His oldest son, Martin "the II.," as he was called, was married, and was accompanied by his wife and children. James, also, his second son, was a married man, and was accompanied by his family. Daniel, John and Bryan--who afterwards perished on board the Jenny Lind steamer, on San Francisco Bay--were the three sons who were bachelors and were the least encumbered of the party. The daughters were all un-married but Mary, the wife of James Miller, Esq., one of the party. John Sullivan, Esq., at present a wealthy capitalist of San Francisco, formed one of the party. The party having provided themselves with the necessary outfit, in teams of horses, oxen, cows, and also with plenty of food in the shape of flour, meat and vegetables, crossed the Missouri River at Council Bluffs, in July, 1844. After having entered on the western Pilgrimage to the land of promise, and prayed devoutly to God to guide them, they started on their six months', but what they afterwards found to be eight months' journey. The incidents, accidents and providential escapes which the party experienced shall be omitted here, but described in the memoirs of James Miller, Esq., in the next chapter. Suffice it to say, here,
        <pb n="180 The Irish Race in California." />that Martin Murphy carried out successfully the enterprise he conceived and planned. He reached California in safety, without losing one of his party. Settled down in Santa Clara County. Purchased miles and leagues of land, and lived to a good old age, about twenty years, in his magnificent home-stead, Bay View ranch, near San Jose, where he saw his children, and I believe his great-grand-children, grow up around him, in honor, in virtue, and in health. The old patriarch's remains lie the Santa Clara Cemetery. His son and successor, Martin, owns the magnificent Bay View ranch, and his accomplished eldest son, Bernard, is at present Mayor of San Jose, for the third or fourth term in succession. The Mayor is a lawyer by profession, and a banker also, in which institution a younger brother represents him as cashier. All the Murphys were educated in Santa Clara, and unlike some degenerate Irishmen who try to change their names by cutting off some superfluous letter, or chiseling them to Anglo-Saxon euphony, the Murphys have not only preserved their old Irish names, handed down from Irish princes, but the younger members of the family have kept up their principles and traditional training, so as to equal if not excel the virtues of their ancestors. One of the family, Patrick, son of Martin the 2d, is
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 181" />settled near San Louis Obispo, on a ranch of some 60,000 acres or so. Bernard and Patrick W. were also for several years members of the Legislature and in the Convention which formed the State Constitution. The example of the Murphys of San Jose, and their connections, refutes the opinion of some obscure people, who imagine if they divest themselves of all sympathy for their native land, or that of their ancestors, that they will become popular and have better success, than if they retained all their Irish predilections. The very reverse is the case. Men who change their name or deny their country, will be apt to deny their God and become callous to all noble impulses. Whereas, the men who honestly confess their faith, and live up to the patriotic principles of their fathers, are generally honored and respected by honest men of all races and nationalities.</p>
        <p>The Murphys--and indeed most Wexford men--are distinguished by the same love of country which actuated their forefathers in '98, when, unaided and unarmed--save by rude weapons--they rose up against all the power of England and cut off 30,000 of her best soldiers. The cause of the patriots failed and the blood of the Sons of Wexford was shed without mercy or stint. Yet, from that crushed people who fought and fell, has
        <pb n="182 The Irish Race in California." />sprung up a race of the noblest peasantry in Europe. God seems to have blessed the sons of the patriots, to reward the bravery of their fathers, for in all Ireland, to-day, there is not to be found a more independent people than in Wexford.</p>
        <p>It was there that Father John Murphy died at the head of a column of Pikemen, assailing the hireling and ruffian soldiery of England. It was in Wexford, that Father Roche gained several pitched battles against the same hereditary foe. It is from Wexford that some of our earliest revolutionary heroes, such as Commodore Barry came. In a word, it was from Wexford that the Murphys of San Jose and San Rafael came, and this is saying a great deal for that small county, the mother of heroes and patriots, both in the old world and the new.*
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 183" /></p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XI.">
        <p>SANTA CLARA COUNTY. THE IRISHMEN WELL REPRESENTEDTHERE IN ALL THE PURSUITS OF LIFE. SUCCESSFUL ASFARMERS, MERCHANTS, PHYSICIANS, JOURNALISTS, CAPI-TALISTS, MINERS, ETC. "MOUNTAIN CHARLEY," JOHNCOONEY, AND OTHER SUCCESSFUL PIONEERS.</p>
        <p>It has been stated that land can be owned but by four methods, in the United States: 1st, by purchase from the Government, at $1.25 acre, without limit as to amount; 2d, by homestead title, which can be obtained by any citizen of the United States, or any foreigner, having declared his intentions to become a citizen, and only one hundred and sixty acres can be obtained in this way; 3d, by pre-emption, that is, by taking the land before it comes into the market, and improving the same, and this establishes the right of the
        <pb n="184 The Irish Race in California." />possessor to that land, by his paying the market price for it when it is advertised for sale; and 4th, by private purchase from an individual, which can be always done by a man who has plenty of money, in any part of the United States.</p>
        <p>In Santa Clara County, there can be no land acquired, of any account, except by this last manner, that is, private sale, so that any new-comers wishing to settle in that pleasant region, about 35 miles South from San Francisco, can get plenty of land, at from two hundred to five hundred dollars an acre. Events happen to develop, and changes take place pretty fast in California. Those who, ten or fifteen years ago, purchased their lands at from three to five dollars an acre, could now, if they were disposed, sell the same lands, for from one hundred and fifty to two hundred dollars an acre.</p>
        <p>More wonderful things than this have happened. In the vicinity of Oakland, on the San Pablo road, Irishmen, such as Mr. Matthews, who purchased their lands, hundreds of acres, for from ten to fifteen dollars an acre, in 1854, could now sell the same to-day for one thousand dollars an acre! And near San Jose, in its suburbs, Thomas Leahy, Esq., purchased a small tract of land for $4,000 within ten years. Already he sold $6,000 dollars&lt;illustration&gt;T. L. SMITH, ESQ., MILPITAS.&lt;/illustration&gt;
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 185" />worth of the property, and could sell the balance with improvements for $35,000 or $40,000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leahy is a Tipperary man, a cousin of the late Archbishop of Cashel, and became a capitalist in mining before he acquired real estate. A volume could not contain the records of such men as Mr. Leahy, who have become wealthy in Santa Clara County by their industry and good management.</p>
        <p>Thomas Leahy, Esq., has a large family of children, who have and are acquiring a first-class education at Santa Clara and San Jose.</p>
        <p>San Jose and Santa Clara were the sites of missions, the remains of which stand to this day, the one at Santa Clara being incorporated with the University there, under the care of the Jesuit Fathers; and the San Jose being situated about eighteen miles north of the city of San Jose, at present the parish church of the district and the residence of the clergymen in charge of the congregation.</p>
        <p>The climate of Santa Clara is healthy, whether in the valleys or the hills, and the atmosphere is clear and seldom burdened with the disagreeable fogs which prevail at San Francisco and in most towns situated near the ocean. The crops grow generally without irrigation, except, indeed, straw-
        <pb n="186 The Irish Race in California." />berries, which are produced all the year round, and some other small fruits, which must have irrigation to thrive well or become profitable to the cultivator. In most parts of the county, however, water can be procured in sufficient quanties [sic] for irrigation by artesian wells, which, when sunk two or three hundred feet, yield a most abundant supply of pure, clear water. On the farm of Thomas L. Smith, Esq., of the town of Milpitas, who has a ranch of about one thousand acres, there is an artesian well the water from which flows continually, and forms a little creek after it leaves the shaft near his farm-house; afterwards, dividing into little rivulets, it covers the entire of his pasture-land, which is always green, and on which his fine drove of dairy cattle feed and get fat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith, also, besides his dairy cattle of thoroughbreds, has several studs of fine horses and same full-blooded dogs and greyhounds, one of which is likely to become as noted for his speed as the famous "McGrath" was in Ireland.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith is a native of Mullingar, Westmeath, Ireland, and came to America in 1853, and to California about eighteen years ago. In the same town of Milpitas are several wealthy Irish farmers, some of whom, like the Synnotts and O'Tooles, enjoyed no small share of historic fame, even in Ireland.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 187" />John Synnott left gallant Wexford in 1831 and came to California in 1851. He is a native of Ballaghkeene, where his ancestors lived for centuries. He is at present seventy-seven years old, and is the father of a large and well-educated family. One of his relatives was for many years parish priest of Wexford town. Mr. Synnott's father, and all of his immediate relatives, took part in all the actions against the English in the rebellion of '98, where some of them sacrificed their lives and shed their blood for old Ireland.</p>
        <p>William O'Toole and his brother also own large tracts of land in Milpitas, and their brother, Lawrence O'Toole, in the township of Gilroy.</p>
        <p>This family came from one of the oldest and the noblest in Ireland, where they were princes and chiefs for centuries. The original Celtic form of spelling the name was "Ua Tuathail," anglicized O'Toole. The clan O'Toole were princes "in Mureadhaigh" (pronounced Murragha). St. Laurence was named Lorcan ua Tuathil, son of Murcherta, Lord of "in Murcherta," in Leinster, and died in 1180, in France. Some pro-English historians tried to make out that our St. Laurence was in favor of the Saxon domination in Ireland. But that is refuted by the actions of the Saint, as shown by the illustrious Dr. Lanigan, who, educated in
        <pb n="188 The Irish Race in California." />Italy and a professor of Pavia, condemned the unprecedented action of Pope Adrian IV. in consigning the government of Ireland to his countryman, King Henry II.</p>
        <p>All classes of Irishmen are well represented in Santa Clara County. Bankers, by McLaughlin and Murphy; physicians, by Abraham McMahon, Riley and others; journalists, by Judge Twohy, editor of the Herald; merchants, by Divine &amp; Lorigan, Captain Welsh, N. B. Edwards, Mark Bradley, Corkery and others; clergymen, by Father Dowling, a pious and popular young priest, Father Hudson, of Gilroy, a man of sterling worth, and the learned Dr. Cassidy, of Mission of San Jose; capitalists, James McMahon, Esq., C. W. Wilson, Esq., and several others. In fact, in all parts of the whole county Irishmen stand in the most prominent positions in society, finance, commerce and education, leaving religion out altogether, for that sacred topic does not come within the scope of the writer of this work in the present instance. It is true, the educational institution at Santa Clara was in existence before the Irish came to the State, and owes its foundation to the Spanish. But the college and the convents, too, are patronized and principally supported by the Irish people and their children. The Irish farmers of the county send their sons to Santa
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 189" />Clara and their daughters to San Jose to receive a thorough and finished education.</p>
        <p>Want of space will compel us to omit the names of hundreds of subscribers to this book in Santa Clara County and elsewhere, such as Michael Hughes, a Meath man, at Milpitas since '49, a large landowner; Mr. S. Scully, of Santa Clara, a pioneer of '49, too, a native of Borris in Ossory, Queen's County, and a Mr. Mullen, born in America, but of Irish parents, who owns a large sheep ranch south of San Jose.</p>
        <p>There are a few men, however, who, from peculiar circumstances, could not have their names omitted from these pages without detracting from the interest which the reader would expect to find in them.</p>
        <p>One of these is Edward Fox, Esq., a native of Dublin or its vicinity, who arrived in California in '52. Mr. Fox is one of the most extensive and best educated gardeners in the country. He has about 130 acres under young fruit and ornamental trees, and every variety of flowers. Mr. Fox exports his plants to all parts of the country, even to Europe, and has introduced several new varieties of seedling and grafted fruits and flowers by his scientific system of hybridization. Perhaps his countryman's great nursery of Barry &amp; Elwanger,
        <pb n="190 The Irish Race in California." />near Rochester, N. Y., is more famous than that of Mr. Fox. But most likely he stands at the head of the business in the United States, as he certainly does in California.</p>
        <p>William O'Donnell, Esq., too, is a professional gardener, but, of late years, has, we understand, paid more attention to landscape gardening than to the raising of fruits. His recreation gardens at San Jose are resorted to by the public on holidays and on occasions of excursions, and are kept under excellent management. Mr. O'Donnell, as he deserves, derives a large income from his popular place of amusement.</p>
        <p>The exploits of" Mountain Charley," or Charles McKernan, demand a limited notice in this place. Mr. McKernan is a native of the County of Leitrim, in Ireland, and emigrated from that country in '48. He came directly to California, without making unnecessary delays in the Eastern States, and at once took to mining and soon after to trapping or hunting, after securing a large tract of land on the elevated regions between San Jose and Santa Cruz, not far from Watsonville. Mr. McKernan had to fight, not only Indians, who once stampeded his cattle and horses, as he and party were crossing the Sierras, but he pursued and compelled the savages to return the plunder, after an
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 191" />engagement of some hours. After the defeat of the Indians he had to fight wild beasts, after he got settled on his ranch. One evening, on the Santa Cruz foothills, he saw a large grizzly bear across a small ravine from where he was about to encamp. "Charley," though he had only a single-barrel gun, could not resist the inclination to fire. He did accordingly fire, but the bear, instead of falling dead in the ravine, as "Charley" expected, leaped across it and in a few minutes attacked the hunter.</p>
        <p>Not having time to reload he had to club the gun, which, though it stunned the beast, left "Charley" without a weapon. The enraged animal soon had him under, and seizing him by the frontal bone of the skull, literally tore it out, from the eyes to the sutures, and crunched it beneath his teeth. As the bear was about to make a second mouthful of the remaining part of the skull, a companion of Mr. McKernan shot the brute dead. Of course "Mountain Charley" was given up for dead, even by the physician who attended him in a couple of days afterwards. But, contrary to all experience of surgery, "Charley" survived and still lives, without a forehead and with his eyes distorted and apparently out of their ordinary orbits. "Mountain Charley" lives in good
        <pb n="192 The Irish Race in California." />health, has a valuable cultivated ranch of over two thousand acres, and is the father of an interesting and large family. He has an elegant mansion in the city of San Jose, besides the residence on the farm, where his family rusticate during the "heated term."John Cooney, another Irishman farmer, in the vicinity of San Jose, is one of those men whose lives are considerably shaped and directed by adventure before they settle down to the quiet habits of a tiller of the soil. Mr. Cooney was born in Greenhall, in the County of Tipperary. He emigrated from the old country before '48, and having "come out West" to northern Illinois, commenced his career at mining, at Galena, a town which derives its name from the lead (or Galena, in Greek), found in that vicinity. Mr. Cooney was chiefly instrumental in 1849, in rescuing an Irishman named White, who was arrested by two Irish government detectives, and claimed under the Ashburton treaty. White was in Cooney's company when arrested by the "peelers," in colored clothes. It seems they had a wagon or carriage, and invited White and Cooney to take a ride into town, which the latter accepted. But, after proceeding about a mile, the detectives put White under arrest, and warned Cooney at the muzzle of the pistol to return
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 193" />home to the country. He did return home, but when he did, he mounted a horse and alarmed all the neighborhood, and caused them to go in pursuit of the "peelers" and their victim. The detectives thought they had their victim in safety when they reached the city, and securing him in irons, they were waiting for the next steamboat to carry him off. The crowd of Irishmen and sympathizers, however, grew from hundreds to thousands, and instantly an attack was made on the hotel where the "peelers" and their victim were lodged. They searched the whole edifice and could not find the prisoner, and such was the indignation at their conduct, that a Mrs. Ryan, whose property the hotel was, told them to burn it to ashes, rather than to allow an Irishman be taken back by the British Government, for the laudable action of defending his homestead against the tyrrany [sic] of landlords. Finally the "peelers" were seized on by the crowd, and told to prepare for instant death, if the prisoner was not produced. Whereupon, trembling and begging for their lives, they brought White forth from where they stowed him. And without any personal injury done to them, they were ordered out of town on foot, and the warrant of the British Government was torn into little bits before their faces. The Mayor of the city was afterward
        <pb n="194 The Irish Race in California." />tried for allowing this rescue to take place, at a time when he had one hundred men in arms at his command. But he was acquitted, when it was proved, that with one thousand men, it would be imprudent for him to act under the circumstances. The truth was, that the Mayor, like all true-hearted Americans, thought it beneath his dignity to risk his life or the lives of his men in carrying out the designs of the British Government. General Grant was then a resident of Galena, and luckily was not in power to aid his "mother country's" officials. The memory of the war of independence and the cruelties England inflicted on the colonists were too recent in the minds of the Eastern people to allow them to interest themselves much in maintaining the laws of that country, which called in the Indians to scalp their revolutionary fathers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cooney, himself perhaps the victim of landlord tyranny, retained a vivid recollection of the power of the "peelers" in Ireland, and on this account he exerted himself to save a fellow countryman from the clutches of the merciless landlord law. And he rejoices to reflect that his interference succeeded, and that he was instrumental in saving one more victim from the gallows. For, guilty or not guilty of the charge against him, poor White would surely hang but for the interfer-
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 195" />ence of John Cooney and his neighbors. John has a large ranch and a large family, and he expends a large amount of his income in keeping his children at Santa Clara College. For, like his countryman, Thomas Leahy, he believes that the best inheritance he can leave his sons is to give them a good education, a sentiment universal among Irish-Americans, and practically acted on by the Irish-American population of Santa Clara County.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XII.">
        <p>OVERLAND IMMIGRANTS. THE ADVENTURES AND TRIALS OF THECANADIAN-MISSOURI PARTY, UNDER MARTIN MURPHY ANDJAMES MILLER IN 1844. THE DANGERS THEY PROVIDEN-TIALLY SURMOUNTED. BIOGRAPHY OF JAMES MILLER, ESQ.,OF "MILLER HALL," NEAR SAN RAFAEL. HIS SUCCESS INLIFE. DESCRIPTION OF MILLER HALL. ACCOUNT OFAN EARTHQUAKE AND PROVIDENTIAL PRESERVATION FROMASSASSINATION.</p>
        <p>In this chapter, it is our pleasing duty to relate the incidents which the party under guidance of Martin Murphy and James Miller, his son-in-law, encountered in the hazardous undertaking of reaching California overland, as early as the year of grace, 1844. Three year afterward, the Donner
        <pb n="196 The Irish Race in California." />party attempted to accomplish what the Miller Murphy party did, and the most heartrending misfortunes befell them. In fact, one-half, or nearly one-half of them, perished by famine or canabalism![sic] But, by the Providence of God, and the resolution of the hardy Irish immigrants, the Murphy-Miller party reached their destination under similar difficulties, without the loss of a single soul. This wonderful success was due, under God, in a great measure, to the indomitable energy and prudence of James Miller. James Miller, like his relatives, the Murphys, is a Wexford man, and born in 1813, in the townland of Upton, Parish of Littermore, in the County of Wexford, and immigrated to Canada as early as 1821, in company with his parents, William Miller and Catherine Duff, his wife. He had six children, the old gentleman, all of whom are living in Canada, save the subject of this sketch and one who fled young. Mr. Miller married in 1837, his wife being the third daughter of Martin Murphy, Esq., and is at present in the enjoyment of good health. Mrs. Miller is a lady of the most amiable disposition, with a heart ever ready to sympathize with suffering, and the orphans and the poor have reason to bless her for her charities. In her countenance she exhibits the dignity of a Roman matron,
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 197" />inherited from her ancestors, mingled with the sweetness of a saint of the middle ages. And her children inherit her sterling virtues. This lady, being, as already stated, the daughter of Martin Murphy, projector of the expedition, and wife of the principal and most active member of the party, must have assuredly have borne more than her share of the cares and perils of the tedious journey. The other female members of the party must have looked up to her as to a mother, in their moments of trouble. Nor did they look to her in vain. She had that in her countenance which indicated great firmness, blended with kindness, and her cheerfulness and resignation encouraged the despondent and stimulated the courageous to new exertions, and cast a gleam of hope like a ray of light over the spirits of the entire party, consisting, in all, of about sixty individuals, one-half of whom were Americans who joined them on the way. Every day had its tedious routine of duties; to unharness and water the horses; to corral the vehicles for shelter and defense; to feed the animals and lead them to pasturage; to cook and prepare food for the party, and finally, to keep watch over the the [sic] camp and enjoy the rest of sleep.</p>
        <p>To be able to endure this routine of duties, not to speak of crossing rivers and mountains, and
        <pb n="198 The Irish Race in California." />sliding down the sides of precipices; to do these things for a week, or a month, would seem at present to be a most difficult undertaking. But, to continue a labor of which the above is only a brief and imperfect summary for six or eight, would seem to be a herculean task indeed. Yet this was accomplished without the loss of a man, or, as far as we could learn, of an animal, during eight dreary months, under the guidance, we may say, of James Miller, for he was younger than his father-in-law, and bore the heaviest duties on his shoulders. Let anybody think, who has ever crossed the plains, of having to face the red sun every day, whose rays were dazzling; of having to encounter the breath of these sometimes hot and sometimes cold, rainy winds; of having to suffer that almost continual thirst from the blinding alkali, drifting in ridges like snow-banks; of having to lay down under the poor shelter of a clumsy tent; of having to rise in the morning without fires to warm the numbed limbs; of having to go miles, perhaps, in search of chips, or the dried drippings of the buffalo, to burn for fuel; of having to endure heat, cold, hunger, fatigue and sadness every single day during the long, long period of eight months that it took to accomplish this terrible retreat through the wilderness, and that before the discov-
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 199" />ery of gold to elevate the spirit. Who can realize these, and a thousand other trials the overland passenger had to undergo, must acknowledge that the undertaking was truly heroic and sufficient to immortalize those who succeeded in its accomplishment? At length there is a change in the monotony of the dreary plains. The hill and snow-capped mountains are reached, which in their solemn grandeur inspire the mind by their sublimity, and by their friendly shadows protect the wayfarers from the scorching rays of the sun.</p>
        <p>For a few days the change of scene encourages the despairing and kindles within the sinking breast a hope that from the summit of the highest pass through the mountains all could get a view of the land which they were seeking to possess. But this brief imagination, inspired by hope, was soon dispelled when it was found that the mountains, if they cheered their spirits, also retarded their progress to their destination.</p>
        <p>There was a not unfounded fear, too, that at any moment, while defiling through the narrow passages of the mountains, they may be attacked and scalped by the savage tribes which made their homes in the sombre valleys of the "snowy range." But this danger the brave Wexford man Miller dissembled, for fear of alarming the women and the
        <pb n="200 The Irish Race in California." />weaker members of the party. But the Providence which protected them and almost miraculously saved them afterward, in the defiles of the snowy Sierras, shielded them, while passing at the base of the Rocky Mountains, from the attacks of hostile Indians. At length, after a tedious travel of about five months, the plains and mountains are passed and the "divide" reached, where the streams, rivers and creeks change their courses, all flowing toward the west and southwest, instead of the opposite direction, which they took in the East. This change of scene, too, had had a cheerful effect on the party, who began to imagine that, as the face of nature seemed to be turned smilingly toward the West, and as their journey henceforth would be on an inclined plane toward the Pacific, they would soon get a glimpse, if not a full view, of California.</p>
        <p>Here, then, by the banks of the Humboldt River, when they reached what is called "its Sink," on the 10th of November, '44, the party resolved to rest themselves for about ten days, to gather strength and provide for the remainder of the journey. The cattle were let out to grass, the horses unharnessed, while the men and women, too, busied themselves with repairing outfits, mending damaged vehicles, washing soiled clothing, and
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 201" />the younger members busied themselves in shooting game, which, in the shape of wild ducks, geese, sage hens, as well as antelopes and deer, were very abundant, and scarely [sic] heeded the presence of their pursuers.</p>
        <p>Refreshed and renewed though they all were, men and animals, after ten days' rest and recreation, yet this delay possibly occasioned most of the sufferings which the party were soon to undergo in the defiles of the Sierras, near Truckee Lake.</p>
        <p>The sun withdrew his pleasant face from where they camped a day or two, ere they renewed their journey. The sky became clouded, and the first fall of mountain snow warned them to make haste and depart. They did set out, but their progress was very much slower than before, through the alkaline and sandy drifts of the mountains. Before it was the glare of the red, angry sun that annoyed them, or the blowing blasts of the dusty plains that almost suffocated them. But now it was the snow, the snow that blew into their eyes, like fine sand, or gathered into high ridges to stop them, or treacherously filled deep ravines and pits, as it were, in order to lure them on to destruction. This was a dreadful journey to pursue for about a month, when, as the cattle and teams were on the point of starvation, and the entire party wearied
        <pb n="202 The Irish Race in California." />and almost frozen, they came to the resolution of building some cabins to protect the weaker members of the party from the weather, and thus save them from inevitable dustruction [sic].</p>
        <p>Accordingly, log-cabins were built, all of the cattle that was not needed for work around the camp or used by the men to go in search of relief were killed, and the flesh carefully preserved for the subsistence of those in camp. It was in December, '44, when the party was secure in their shelter of rude log houses, roofed by poles extended across the walls and covered by the hides of cattle that had been butchered, that the men were prepared to depart in search of some settlements.</p>
        <p>After having confided the women and children to the care of Mr. Miller, the brave men who volunteered to go in search of settlements or other evidence of civilization, departed. The men who departed, after many days' travel, reached "Fort Helvetia," the residence of Captain Sutter.</p>
        <p>When they reached Fort Helvetia, the residence of Captain Sutter, they found the country in a state of war, a rebellion having broken out against Micheltorena's authority, in which many of the Mexicans joined, and most of the Americans, aided by Captain McKenley. The party of emigrants joined in this uprising or were probably compelled to
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 203" />do so, as they marched as far as San Jose, as a part of the revolutionary forces. They were soon, however, allowed to return to the Sierras, but several weeks elapsed before they got back. In the mean time provisions were scarce among the inmates of the log cabins. All their flour, which consisted of only three barrels when they entered camp, was now consumed. And no wonder, when about fifty persons had to subsist on that limited supply. The starvation stage of their existence now commenced, and dire destruction began to stare them when they were obliged to cook and try to eat the hides that protected them from the weather, on the roofs of the cabins. And no doubt the fate of the Donner party would have been theirs, but for the presence of mind and cool deliberation of James Miller, the true guardian of the whole party, who, rather than see his people die of starvation, resolved himself to go in search of relief. Accordingly, with his gun, a blanket and an ax, and a small supply of meat, he started almost in spite of the advice of the inmates of the camp, who felt, when he was gone, that they had no protector. Accompanied by his little son William, a child of only a dozen years, he set out with the tardy consent of his affectionate wife, who, with the heroism worthy of epic renown, was satisfied
        <pb n="204 The Irish Race in California." />that her husband should sacrifice his life--like the good Shepherd--for the flock committed to his charge. He traveled on for four or five days with his son, like I$lus, following at a distance in his father's tracks. Finally, the little hero who volunteered to go with his father, became entirely exhausted, and lying down on the snow at the brow of a precipice, he flung the cup which he carried to drink out of and his blanket, over the cliff, after which he slept soundly. When he woke from his slumbers he felt thirsty, and finding he had not his cup, he seized on one of his father's boots, who also was taking a needed rest, and drank copiously from a snowy rivulet. Their small supply of food was already spent, and death by starvation should be their inevitable fate, had not the intrepid and active pioneer providentially encountered some game, which he shot, and had soon prepared for food. Supplying his empty haversack with some of this food, he was preparing to continue his journey toward the southwest, when the boy William, who was a little way ahead of his father, and whose hearing was most acute, ran back to report that he heard the jingling of bells. In a few moments afterward, horses appeared, and a party of men, whom the good man recognized as his companions who went in search of and brought relief. The
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 205" />journey back to the camp was made in the course of one day, where the famishing inmates of the cabins were soon rejoiced and refreshed by the plentiful supply of food sent by the benevolent Col. Sutter. The colonel was a native of Holland, who, after great trials and wandering, settled in California, and finally erected a fort and permanently settled down near the site of the present city of Sacramento, where he had received a grant of a large tract of land from the Mexican Government. His name has been historical, a synonym for kindness and benevolence to all, and they were thousands, who visited his place during the years of the coming of the emigrants, from '44 to '50, and before or afterward.</p>
        <p>Being a resident of Switzerland, though a Batavian by birth, and probably educated in the vicinity of the celebrated St. Bernard's Hospice, it was natural to him to know how to relieve the destitute, and save hundreds from perishing in the defiles of the rugged Sierras.</p>
        <p>James Miller, Esq., who is justly entitled to the merit of having saved what is called the Murphy immigration party, in '44, from the terrible fate of the Donner Lake party in '47, has resided near the village of San Rafael, Marin County, on his farm, formerly called Las Galinas, consisting of
        <pb n="206 The Irish Race in California." />several thousand acres, 10,000 or 12,000, at least, purchased by him from the Alcalde, Timothy Murphy, already mentioned in this work.</p>
        <p>The residence of Mr. Miller, known as "Miller Hall," occupies a most charming site, about four miles north of San Rafael, on the Petaluma mail road, about a quarter of a mile from the highway. The mansion is a square, massive edifice, with a veranda all around and an observatory on top, very commodiously divided into apartments, and tastefully, if not splendidly furnished. The house stands on a knoll in a pretty vale of about a mile in width, and surrounded on three sides by a ridge of hills, which, like walls, shelter it from the chilling blasts of the ocean, as well as protect it from the scorching sirocoes of the north. The building faces eastward, and there is a view in that direction of the bay and the ever-changing hue of its waters, disturbed almost continually by the paddles of steamers or keels of sailing vessels, interrupting the natural changes of its surface. In the same direction, but beyond the bay, stand Mount Diavolo and the bronzed and weather-beaten hills of Contra Costa, looking down upon the bay with heads parched and burned, reminding one of the Titans of mythology begging a drop of water to moisten their burning brows.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 207" />In a word, to complete the charms of this lovely spot where Miller Hall stands, there are several springs of water, having their sources in the surrounding hills, which is conveyed in pipes to the mansion and distributed in each of its many apartments through metallic tubes, and also supplying a pond and a "jette de l'eau" with refreshing showers of cooling water.</p>
        <p>This elegant mansion is the home of Mr. Miller and family, consisting of his faithful wife, with five accomplished daughters and two sons, three others, two daughters and a son, William Miller, Jr., having been married some years ago.</p>
        <p>The incidents herein recorded of the trials and sufferings of what we shall call the Murphy-Miller party of immigrants, are only few and unimportant compared with occurences [sic] such as the following, which were overlooked: After the departure of Mr. Miller from the log-camp in search of the party that left previously, a terrible earthquake occurred in the Sierras, which precipitated mountains into the valley, caused the very ground upon which the huts were erected to dance and reel, so that the inmates could hardly stand erect. The very logs in the fireplace were hurled against the sides of the huts, while immense rocks, trees and masses of frozen earth rushed down the sides of
        <pb n="208 The Irish Race in California." />precipices, like pebbles driven before a cataract. This was the condition of things around them on all sides, while overhead the lightning dazzled, the thunder roared with ten thousand reverberating echoes, the hail descended destructfully; torrents of water rushed down in streams from the black clouds, all presaging impending destruction. But nature soon, like a raving maniac, became exhausted, and the violence of the storm was succeeded by a delightful serenity.</p>
        <p>Even after having settled on land at that early day all danger to our farmer was not at an end. One day, while Mr. Miller and his hired help were preparing the soil for a crop, in the spring of '45, he was interrupted by a visit from band of irregular soldiers, under command of De La Torres, who was in pursuit of other marauders under De Castro and Micheltorena. The band of armed assassins, for they were no better, levelled their muskets at Mr. Miller and ordered him to prepare for instant death. He was stationed about twelve yards distance, and the whole troop ordered to prepare at the word of command to fire. Just as the word was about to be uttered two voices at once cried "hold, hold!" And then two young Frenchmen who had influence with the commander demanded that the man should be tried before
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 209" />execution--a thing which these Mexican ruffians thought too slow a process to go through. The trial was, of course, short, and led to the immediate release of the victim.</p>
        <p>From the above account of the difficulties which one party encountered in procuring themselves homes in California, an opinion may be formed of the courage and perseverence [sic] which were needed by others who successfully accomplished the journey across the plains at that early day. But, though multitudes succeeded in making the overland journey successfully, many failed in the attempt, and the many shallow graves all along from Omaha to Sacramento prove that hundreds, if not thousands, sacrificed their lives in their greed to grasp the golden sands of California.</p>
        <p>"The Mountain Meadow massacre" has horrified the civilized world by the atrocity of its perpetrators, and the "Donner Lake" horrors shock the feelings of our common humanity. No doubt there were several of our race murdered at Mountain Meadows, as there were many among the Dormer party of eighty individuals, nearly one-half of whom perished by hunger and cold, many of them having eaten the flesh of their nearest and dearest friends to save themselves from the horrors of starvation.</p>
        <p>
          <pb n="210 The Irish Race in California." />
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XIII.">
        <p>THE DONNER LAKE CATASTROPHE. MISTAKES MADE BYTHOSE UNDER WHOSE CONDUCT IT SET OUT. CANIBAL-ISM SUCCEEDS MURDER. SEVERAL SUCCESSIVE TRIPSACROSS THE PLAINS. INSTANCES OF IRISHMEN WHOMADE THE TRIP FREQUENTLY, ETC. APOCRYPHAL STORYABOUT AN IRISH CATHOLIC COLONY.</p>
        <p>Though it comes not within the scope which the writer of this volume proposed to himself in undertaking to relate any events not having any Connection with the Irish race in California, yet, because there were several Irish families among the sufferers at Donner Lake, and these the most deserving and undespairing of the whole party, it seems not to be out of place to give a brief account of that dreadful occurrence in this volume. The Donner party were principally from Tennessee, from counties bordering on the Cumberland River, and though ostensibly a party of native Americans, had at least one-third of its members of Irish birth or origin. For instance, there were the Murphys, most of whom who survived, and the Breens, the Dolans, Hallorins, who did most of the praying and kept the only daily journal of those terrible days, always ending his
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 211" />entries in his little log-book with a prayer that the merciful God would soon come to their relief. One of the Murphys--a Mary--who survived, gave the name Marysville to the metropolis of Yuba County, and her brother William is City Attorney, and a distinguished lawyer of said burgh. In the organization of the Donner party, a serious mistake was made in the election of a brute like Reed as captain, who was so unfeeling as to murder one of the party, named Snyder, for a slight disobedience of rules. After this instance of barbarous cruelty, the so-called captain ought either to have been executed as a murderer, or at least degraded from his position. He was driven off or left the party soon after the murder of Snyder. Then again, when the party ran short of food, the two Indian guides who volunteered to extricate them from their predicament, were murdered and devoured by the entire party. The survivors plundered their dead companions' property, and seemed more anxious to save it than their lives. So accustomed did the wretches become to the use of human flesh, that when relief came, they preferred the flesh of their fellowmen to that of beef or mutton. There was even one named Keisburgh, who, it was suspected, murdered several of his companions to devour them. For over three months the whole
        <pb n="212 The Irish Race in California." />party suffered from cold, and hunger, and sickness. When a death occurred, the flesh was instantly torn from the skeleton and devoured by the survivors.</p>
        <p>The following is an extract from one of the newspapers of that date, 10th April, 1847:"The bones of those who had died and been miserably devoured by those who survived were lying around their tents and cabins. The bodies of men, women and children, with one-half the flesh torn from them, lay on every side. A woman sat by the side of the body of her husband, who had just died, cutting out his tongue to eat it. The heart she had already cut out of his breast and broiled and eat it. The daughter was seen eating the flesh of her father, which she smoked to preserve it for future use; the mother that of her children; the children that of their parents. The emaciated, wild and ghastly appearance of the survivors added horror to the scene. Language cannot describe the awful change that a few weeks of dire suffering had wrought in the minds of the wretched beings. Those who but one month before, would have shuddered at the thought of eating human flesh or of killing their relatives or companions to preserve their own lives, now looked upon the opportunity by these acts afforded them of
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 213" />escaping the most dreadful of deaths as a Providential interference on their behalf! Calculations were coldly made, as they sat gloomily around their fires in camps, for the next meals of human flesh. Various expedients were devised to prevent the dreadful crime of murder, but they finally resolved to kill those who had the least claims to longer existence. * * * Some sunk into the arms of death cursing God for their miserable fate, brought on by themselves, while the last whisperings of others were prayers and praise to the Almighty. After the few first days but one, the all-absorbing thought prevailed of self-preservation. The fountains of all natural affection were dried up. Even the wild Indians, having visited their camp with hostile intentions, pitied them, and instead of destroying them, as they could have easily done, divided their own scanty food with them. When the party sent to relieve them with ordinary food arrived, so barbarous had those wretches become that they preferred the putrid human meat to that of cereals and animal food sent to relieve them. The day before relief arrived one of the Party took a child, four years old, to bed with him, and eat it before morning. The next day another child was devoured in the same manner."Some clung to their property till death, which,
        <pb n="214 The Irish Race in California." />it is thought, many of them could have escaped, had they not clung to it with desperation.</p>
        <p>Let us contrast the conduct of the Donner party with that of the Murphy-Miller party, caught in the selfsame predicament, three years before, and the reader will see how superior the organization, how indomitable the courage and how confiding and trustful in God's mercies was the character of the latter when compared with the former. Instead of cursing and blaspheming God's providence, as happened by the majority, but not all, in the Donner party, there was the most perfect resignation and confidence in the Divine assistance, that not one, for a moment, in the darkest hour, despaired. Instead of plotting the murder of their fellowmen, as was done in the instance of the two Indian guides, and most probably in several other instances, all the men of the Murphy-Miller party went off in search of supplies, exposing themselves to the danger of perishing of want in order that those in the camp should not run short of provisions. In a word, there was no discord, no idleness, no blasphemous reproaches among the Murphy-Miller party, as was evidently the case among the Donner immigrants. Hence, though situated in exactly the same circumstances, the former were saved and
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 215" />reached their destination in good order, while the latter were demoralized and well nigh entirely destroyed. After the Donner calamity became known and published it was feared that immigration to the country would be retarded at the recital of such unnatural occurrences. But no; for in less than a year after the discovery of gold in fabulous quantities in California was circulated on the wings of the press, from all parts of the United States, and, it may be said, from all over the civilized earth, a stream of immigration set in so continuous, so large , and so irresistible that not a hundred Donner Lake misfortunes could check its onward course. There were other accidents on a smaller scale than the Donner, many were massacred by Indians and disguised robbers, and along the whole route there were evidences of suffering, disease, murder and treachery. But such was the hurry people were in to reach the "gold diggings" and to become rich that they scarce looked at the horrors before their eyes, so blind were they to every other pursuit or dead to every feeling save that of getting gold. Soon the journey across the plains on foot or with cattle being an affair of some six months' travel lost all its dangers and adventures, and some men, like John McGrath, of Colusa, made the journey both
        <pb n="216 The Irish Race in California." />ways twice with large herds of cattle. And another man, Mr. Leyden, who afterwards settled in Marysville, traveled over the plains probably some fifteen to twenty times, for he followed the occupation of bringing parties and freight by contract across the plains. The good old man died about a year since, regretted by all who knew him during his honest career in business, and was followed to the grave by a large cortege of his townsmen in Marysville. He died in peace and happiness, and has left a large family of well-educated children to perpetuate his memory. His son, John F. Leyden, Esq., carries on his father's business in Marysville, and inherits all the virtues of his pious father. He is an instance of what a careful, pious education can effect with the youth of California.</p>
        <p>There is an account of one of our countrymen named Clark, who, in '49, crossed the plains alone; and though he carried no weapons, not even a shot-gun, reached the golden land in safety, carrying his supplies on a wheelbarrow and being protected from attacks by Indians simply by his being alone, the dusky Arabs of the wilderness thinking it dishonorable to attack a solitary individual. There were two other Irishmen, Kelly and Conway, who crossed the plains without even a wheelbarrow, and no more supplies than they carried in
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 217" />a haversack. They were armed, however, by means of which they secured themselves plenty of animal food. The only vegetables they had were berries and roots of herbs. They were healthy and vigorous, though they made the journey from Kansas to Sacramento in little over three months. We understand they are now settled in Oregon.</p>
        <p>In or about the year '46, we read in some of the veracious histories of California, which, though not old, are already to be found among dusty old books, that there was an Irish priest named McNamara, who got a grant of large tracts of land, in or near the San Joaquin Valley, which the Mexicans more readily granted him, the priest, because he engaged to settle Roman Catholic Irishmen on the lands granted. And that the plan would have succeeded, only that the priest died, and that the "Path-finder Fremont" and his fillibusters anticipated and frustrated the plans of the Irish priest.</p>
        <p>This story may be true in part at least. It may be true that McNamara made some such proposition to the Mexican authorities, and that they were willing to grant the lands. But it is not likely that the Mexican Government, which granted its lands so liberally to Col. Sutter, Jas. Black, of Marin County, and to numerous other men who were not Catholics, would concern itself about the
        <pb n="218 The Irish Race in California." />religion of the immigrants, whether they were Catholics, Protestants, or atheists. The Mexicans wanted but inhabitants for their lands, not enquiring about their religion. It is certain that before the revolution, or rather conquest, of California, by the United States, more grants of lands were made to Protestants than to Catholics, as it is equally well known that in Peru, and other South American republics who invite immigration, the vast majority of those who get the lands free, and other advantages, are German Protestants and atheists, who receive the same liberal treatment as if they were the most orthodox Catholics. And this is another evidence, is it not, of the illiberality of the Latin races? If a colony of Catholics applied for the like encouragement to any liberal Protestant government, would they be successful?</p>
        <p>The story of McNamara and his Irish colony, then, needs confirmation, for its narrators adduce no proof beyond rumor to corroborate their statements. It is certain, however, that England was negotiating for the possession of California, in lieu of heavy sums of money which Mexico owed her. It is known that an English fleet was on its way to take and keep forcible possession of the country and reached the port of Monterey a few hours after the territory was annexed by proclamation, by Com-
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 219" />modore Sloat. But if England had succeeded in planting the "union jack," where the stars and stripes then floated proudly, she could not have held the country for a month, for the veteran Kearney had arrived, and his 1,600 boys, mostly all Irishmen, together with Col. Stevenson's volunteers, 1,000 strong, would have had made short work of the "red-coats," had they succeeded in landing in California, with a view of conquests.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XIV.">
        <p>THE MILITARY MEN OF OUR RACE. COPPINGER AND GRAHAM,LEADERS IN REVOLUTION OF 1836. GRAHAM AND McGINLYREBEL AGAINST MEXICAN TYRANNY. COL. STEVENSON'SREGIMENT AND THE BRAVE IRISH OF HIS COMMAND.</p>
        <p>RESCUE OF PRISONERS AT SAN ANTONIO, AND RELIEFOF AMERICAN SOLDIERS AT LOS ANGELES. BRAVERYBELONGS TO NO CLASS, BUT FOUND MOST AMONG PEAS-ANTS.</p>
        <p>Though no great or brilliant battles decided the conquest of California from the Mexican Government, yet there was some fighting to be done under difficulties, and of this, no small share fell to the lot of our countrymen. The revolt of the people in 1836 against Gutierrez, was headed by two
        <pb n="220 The Irish Race in California." />Irishmen, Coppinger and Graham, the former of whom, by the way, the veracious compilers of the "Annals of San Francisco," call an Englishman. This Col. Coppinger was not only an Irishman, but a native of Cork, a near relative of a bishop of that name, of Cloyne diocese, and of the medical profession. Graham, also, though an American by choice, was of Irish birth or parentage. These men rallied all the American and foreign population, and by the co-operation of the most spirited of the Spanish and Mexicans, declared the country a free and independent republic. General Vallejo favored this revolution, and as the reward of what the Mexicans called his treachery, but what Americans named his patriotism, he was made commander of the army, and his nephew, Alvarado, Civil Governor. This state of things lasted for six years, until the arrival of Micheltorena, in 1842. Micheltorena, sent by Santa Anna, was no improvement in his manner of government on the system of his predecessors, who nine or ten in number, since the departure of the last Spanish Governor, Sola, in 1823, had all continued the same system of arbitrary rule and public plunder, which has been, from that day to this, the leading characteristics of their period in power. Bands of licensed plunderers scoured time country
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 221" />North and South, and under the pretense of detecting treasonable designs, or catering for the necessities of the State, pillaged the country without mercy, and frequently assassinated those who were tardy in yielding to their demands. Mr. Miller, of San Rafael, as already stated, had a most miraculous escape from a troop of those emissaries of Micheltorena, and was barely saved from instant murder by the interposition of some French gentlemen, who held command in the marauding party. But, as violence always produces revolution, and, in the government of the State or the Church has generally a reaction, the very reverse of what is expected by its blinded advocates, so Micheltorena lost his hold of the sword of State and was again in his turn compelled to give way, in 1846, the rebellion against his brief authority having been successful, through the bravery of Capt. McGinly, another Irish-American.</p>
        <p>Col. Fremont, too, when after having crossed over the plains and found the most accessible passes through the mountains, when he raised the "bear flag," had at least one-fourth, if not more, of his trusty sharpshooters to defend it--Irishmen. But if the conquest of California produced no generals to vie with Caesar or Napoleon, it produced men whose bravery the history of no country can
        <pb n="222 The Irish Race in California." />eclipse, from Horatius Cocles, Mucius Scevola, the Fabii, or the three hundred that guarded the pass of Thermopylae. Among Col. Stevenson's volunteers were men as brave as ever unsheathed a sword or fired a musket. A detachment of Stevenson's volunteers were at La Paz, a distance of sixty miles from San Antonio, the headquarters of the Mexicans.</p>
        <p>Finding that the enemy in his vicinity at La Paz was gone, Lieutenant-Colonel Burton, in command, ordered a detail of his men to go out in search of cattle or something that would supply them with fresh animal food, the men being threatened with scurvy from the use of inferior diet. They succeeded in driving some half-starved cattle into camp, but on their way back they encountered three American sailors, who had run away from a whaler ship in Magdalena Bay. The sailors informed the foraging party that they saw eight American prisoners in the Mexican camp at San Antonio, who expected to be shot every day. The prisoners, the major part of whom were Irish, as the sailors probably were, too, urged the latter to run with the news of their situation to La Paz, for that no time was to be lost, as every hour might be their last.</p>
        <p>Upon being interrogated as to the number of
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 223" />Mexican soldiers in San Antonio they answered that they did not know, but the town was full of them. Finally, the twenty men who brought in the cattle all volunteered to go to rescue the condemned Americans in San Antonio. They told Colonel Burton what the sailors said, but he would not listen to the mad undertaking, and ordered them back to their quarters. The matter was discussed all over the camp, and thirty men were determined to make the attempt. After using all the arguments be could to dissuade this small division from going on such a perilous undertaking, Colonel Burton said, "If you are determined on going, boys, you can go, though it leaves me in a bad fix, for one of you I never expect to see again alive. Observe great silence in your march, and if you meet any persons on the road drive them back of you, for your only chance of success is to surprise the enemy's garrison." On they marched until near daylight, when they surprised the guards at San Antonio, broke their arms, and forbid them, under pain of death, to move or speak. When the detachment rode into town they sounded their bugles and raised the wild Irish cheer, that woke up the Mexicans and sent their troops in double-quick out of town.</p>
        <p>In the dusk and twilight mist of the early dawn
        <pb n="224 The Irish Race in California." />the Mexicans imagined and magnified the thirty into a thousand men. In fine, the six hundred Mexicans took to the hills. The seven or eight prisoners, one of them named John Scollin and another Duncan, lieutenant of the navy, were rescued in safety, and all the volunteers, except one named Hipwood, who fell mortally wounded, returned back in safety to Colonel Burton, at La Paz, the next day after the victory! He was really astonished and delighted at the success of their apparently hopeless enterprise.</p>
        <p>There is not on record, we assert, anything that beats this in boldness, in valour, or in the singular exemption from casualties. The old Romans would have erected monuments to the memory of such heroes. For to save the life of one citizen deserved the public thanks of the Senate and a mural crown. And by whom were these deeds performed? The heroes who rescued those seven or eight citizens were one-third of them Irishmen, without including Dennison, who was certainly of Irish descent. This would give thirty per cent., or about three hundred of Colonel Stevenson's thousand men, as Irishmen.</p>
        <p>We here give a list of the names of the heroes:JOHN GALLAGHER, JOSEPH McDONAGH, PATRICK LYNCH, JAMES BRENNAN, MARTIN CAHILL, JOHN
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 225" />MURPHY, JAMES MELVIN and JAMES O'SULLIVAN. John Scollin and Lieutenant Duncan were among the rescued. When Colonel Stevenson enlisted his volunteers in New York he picked out the men himself, and it seems he made a good selection. The Colonel must have Irish blood in his veins,* if he was not born in Ireland, as most of his Irish troops regarded him as a countryman, for he was very kind and courteous to them, and always called them "his boys." Not a line records these events in the "complete" history of California and "Annals of San Francisco." Oh no, it would not do to give the Irish their proper place in a book written under the inspiration of Know-nothingism, and whose object appears to be to whitewash the worst doings of mobs and vigilantes, when they ruled the country by the worst sort of despotism--that of a mob.</p>
        <p>There is nothing in the whole book, or in the history of California, to compare with this episode
        <pb n="226 The Irish Race in California." />of the rescue of eight prisoners, guarded by six hundred soldiers, by a detachment of only 30 cavalrymen.</p>
        <p>We give a few paragraphs in reference to the nativity and history of these brave men:John Gallagher, born in Raphoe, Co. Donegal, Ireland, left home when 15 years, and landed in New York in 1840, where he learned the useful trade of blacksmithing. In '46, he laid dawn the hammer, relinquished the music of the anvil, and took up the sword and carbine in Colonel Stevenson's regiment, which got to San Francisco Feb. 5th, 1847. Served during the war, and was in many actions, until he was honorably discharged, in '48, since which time he has been a resident of California, except while he was going to see his parents, in 1852. He follows farming, including dairying and stock-raising, and lives at Sebastopol, in the county of Sonoma.</p>
        <p>Equally brilliant was the action of the other thirty men, who volunteered at Santa Barbara, in April, '47,
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 227" />to take ammunition to the American forces shut up within Los Angeles, and consisting of Kearney dragoons, mostly all wounded, and some Mormon soldiers.</p>
        <p>Colonel Burton, after parade, announced to his battalions at Santa Barbara, the desperate situation at Los Angeles. The colonel said he would not order any of his men to go, but if they volunteered, he would give his consent to their departure.</p>
        <p>Thirty men was all he could spare from his small force. The thirty men stood out to the front, and here again the Irishmen were among the first who volunteered. They were told it was a most perilous undertaking to travel 120 miles through the enemy's country, and carry relief to the beleagured. The ammunition was carefully stowed on a large cart, and the boys went into line in quick march, through a country where the sand was knee-deep, guided by two friendly Indians and a white teamster. The little forlorn hope was scarcely gone ten miles, when Col. Burton received a note from some officer whose name is not given, requesting him to recall the men, for none of them could ever reach their destination alive, and the ammunition should certainly be captured. Burton remarked to the courier that he would not recall the men, for he felt assured that they would not part with their
        <pb n="228 The Irish Race in California." />ammunition without a hard fight. On they went, the thirty heroes, through sandy deserts and parched plains, and on the second day after their departure they arrived at Los Angeles, relieved the beleaguered, and after driving the enemy to the hills, returned sorefooted and fatigued, but yet victorious, without the loss of a man, to Santa Barbara. The names of the Irishmen who participated in this remarkable action, were: 1st, Charles McMullen, James Lynch, Pat. Lynch, Joseph McDonagh and Nicholas McDonagh, brothers, John Brady, Michael Conolly, John Gallagher, Thomas Gorman and O'Grady.</p>
        <p>The particulars of this action is given in the following brief statement from one of the men engaged in it:"The march through the burning sands, knee-deep, was continued by our band of Spartan heroes for about twenty-four hours. At last the Mexicans appeared, stationed on a hill, determined to dispute the advance of such an insignificent [sic] body as the thirty United States soldiers who faced them. A halt was ordered, and it was proposed to the men either to retreat, after blowing up the ammunition, and return to Santa Barbara, or to advance and fight a body of men at least seven times their number. Every man of the ten
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 229" />Irishmen who formed the soul of that little army gave his voice to advance. 'It was better,' they remarked, 'to die fighting like men than to perish of thirst on the scorching plains.' The thirty advanced at a double-quick pace, and were soon face to face with at least three hundred of the enemy. Several volleys fired against them did not seem to obstruct their approach to the mountain's brow. Nicholas McDonough was the first who gained the crest of the hill, and being charged upon by a Mexican officer with a spear, he shot him dead and put his four companions to flight. Finally, turning round to his companions, whom he distanced in the race, he threw up his cap, raised the Irish cheer, well known on all the battle-fields of Europe, from Fontenoy to Ballaclava and Inkerman, and, as soon as his twenty-nine companions came up, having reached the hill, the Mexicans were retreating. The ammunition was safely delivered, and the beleaguered garrison of Los Angeles relieved!"Nor can it be objected to our history that the most remarkable of our heroes of Irish birth or descent are of humble origin. As the celebrated Dr. Brownson once objected to the author of the "Cross and the Shamrock," that all his characters were taken from the peasant class. And yet this
        <pb n="230 The Irish Race in California." />was the very circumstance that contributed to the immense popularity of that most popular of Irish-American tales. So here we give the history of men of our race, without distinction of position, origin or grade. No matter whether he crossed the plains behind a wheelbarrow, like Patrick Clark, or traveled in a silver-mounted parlor railroad carriage, like the modern Dives, all must stand on the same level and rise or fall beneath the searching scrutiny of history, in proportion as the merit they approbation or censure of posterity. Some of those men enumerated above in the first rank of Irish military glory have risen even in civil life to distinction, and all to comfort and competency.</p>
        <p>John Gallagher, as already stated, is a comfortable farmer in Sonoma. Nicholas McDonagh, the hero of "Todos Angeles," is a wholesale merchant in the city of San Francisco. He was also distinguished in the late war of the Rebellion as a captain or higher command in Meagher's Irish Brigade. It seems the McDonaghs came of an old brave stock of Irishmen remakable [sic] for valor and patriotism; and as blood is apt to tell, it is no wonder that the martial ardor of the race still glows, unaffected by distance or time. James Lynch, another of the heroes of Stevenson's Brigade, is engaged in sheep-farming on an exten-
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 231" />sive scale, in the vicinity of San Louis Obispo. Martin Cahill is in business in the city of Stockton, and all those brave men, if not millionaires, are at least in prosperous circumstances, and happy at the reflection, that by their bravery they helped to shape the destinies of this great country, freeing it of the harpies of Mexican cupidity, and opening it up to the enterprise and industry of the inhabitants of the whole globe.</p>
        <p>Men talk of great leaders, and look to persons of rank or fortune, as the most likely to lead nations to victory or glory. But we know from history that some of the greatest heroes rose from the rank of peasants. Caius Marius was a plebeian, Spartacus a slave, and several of the marshals of Napoleon--like Bernadotte, the King of Sweden--were taken from the ranks of private soldiers, and the bravest man in all the thousands engaged in the siege of Sebastopol, was a Sergeant Crowley, with whom Marshall Canrobert declared he would divide one-half of his honors, if he could exchange them for the moiety of the bravery which distinguished the brave Corkonian. Education, wealth, or aristocratic birth, do not confer bravery. No, it is a gift of Heaven impressed on the soul, and is inherited or conferred on the peasant class infinitely more oft than on any other class whatever of the people.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="232 The Irish Race in California." />We append the following eloquent remarks of Gen. Butler on the Irish soldier, and the sentiments, while they do but justice to the Irish soldiers, are most creditable to the head and heart of the general himself who is not unworthy of the noble race from which he is descended:"THE IRISH SOLDIER--GENERAL B. F. BUTLER'S LECTURE IN BOSTON ON THE "IRISH SOLDIER IN WAR AND PEACE--A THRILLING DESCRIPTION OF BATTLE SCENES AT MALVERN HILL.--General B. F. Butler delivered a lecture on Sunday evening last at the Boston Theatre, on 'The Irish soldier in War and Peace,' it being in aid of the family of the late Colonel B. F. Finan. In the course of it he said:While Irish names, great and illustrious, will maintain a large place in the history of our country, we must not forget that many, nay, most of them, won their laurels leading troops made up of officers and men of the same race with themselves, organized into distinctive bodies, known in our army as the Irish regiments and brigades, and how much of their success and honor is due to the fact that the men they commanded were so well fitted by nationality, aptness for discipline, capability of taking care of themselves, elasticity of temperament, capacity for endurance, carelessness of dan-
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 233" />ger, heedlessness of self-sacrifice, and courage in battle, that they soon became the finest soldiers the world ever saw.</p>
        <p>As a rule, an Irish regiment never breaks. They always stand or retreat together; therefore they seem to possess naturally the first element which it is the office of discipline to supply to the army. Whether it is that, finding themselves in foreign lands, either as exiles, enforced or voluntary, each man looks upon each comrade as a brother, yet true it is, whether in peace or war, they are rarely known to desert each other, but each gives to each of substance, of labor, of sympathy--all that a man can receive from brother man. This trait of character is nowhere more conspicuously displayed, and to the reflecting mind there can be no more touching sight, than when we see long lines of stalwart men leaving their occupations, laying aside all their business, to follow to their grave their dead, or the private grief of the majority of whom there is no other claim save that of nationality.</p>
        <p>A THRILLING BATTLE SCENE.</p>
        <p>After reciting the services of the Massachusetts Ninth in glowing terms, the General alluded to the scene at Malvern Hill in 1862, where Porter's Corps was acting as rear guard, as follows:It is wonderful, then, that men of the same re-
        <pb n="234 The Irish Race in California." />ligious faith, with such examples of heroism and self-sacrifice before them, went to do battle for their country, regardless of perils and dangers of the battle-field, and met death as calmly as they would lay down to a night's repose, like flowers at set of sun?</p>
        <p>The Ninth, with two supports of regiments, are ordered to take position to hold in check the advancing enemy and gain time for the rest of the army. The Ninth advance to their position as ordered. By some mistake or misconception of orders, the other two regiments do not go forward. It is now midday. The advance of Jackson's corps is seen winding out of the wood which had concealed his brigades. He turns the head of his column to 'sweep away,' as he sees the green flag which meets his eye as the noonday sun gilds the sunburst. Looking around them, the soldiers of the Ninth see the whole of our army in retreat, and they are consequently left alone, their support not having come up, to stand the shock of the fighting corps of Lee's army.</p>
        <p>Not a long time have they to wait. A volley pours into them from the advancing lines of the foe. That terrific yell we know so well follows. To retreat is capture to ourselves, with the destruction of our army. To stand, as we are under this
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 235" />plunging fire, will indeed sweep us from earth. They charge! Let us meet the enemy half way! Forward, now! Charge! with such a cheer as only Irishmen can give. The foe give back. That glistening line of steel, over which proudly floats the green flag of Erin, is too much for him. He seeks shelter in the wood from whence he came. Back, now, the Ninth. Give ground slowly, as if on parade. We must get a position where they cannot flank us, and where, if it is possible, our support may come up. Again the rebels charge. They think we are retreating, do they? They'll find out! About face, the Ninth! At them again! Another sight of the sunburst advancing, and they take to the woods again, but our loss of officers and men is fearful. Again and again was this repeated, from noon till four o'clock in the afternoon. Our commander now knows that he can rely on no support, and that the safety of the army depends upon his regiment alone. It is now four o'clock. The Confederate General Cobb takes the field, with his own legion at the head of Jackson's column, and with him the Nineteenth North Carolina and the Fourteenth Virginia, in the language of Count Estvan, a Prussian officer serving on his staff, 'foaming at the mouth' to see the best troops of the Confederate army foiled by a single
        <pb n="236 The Irish Race in California." />regiment. Cobb drives his brigade forward to crush that small line of blue over which waves in defiance, though torn with shot and shell, the green flag and the Stars and Stripes together. He comes out of the wood with his brigade deployed in two lines.</p>
        <p>COLONEL GUINEY AND HIS MEN.</p>
        <p>One would think the very appearance of those charging lines of gray would cause the blue to vanish from the field. Our Lieutenant-Colonel, the cool but daring Guiney, makes his disposition to meet them by a counter charge. 'Steady, now, boys!' he shouts. 'Color-bearers, forward! Men, follow your colors!'Now the cheer, and our blue line cuts through the charging column as if it were a Damascus blade of shining steel. The tide of battle is stayed--nay, is turned back. But what a loss of our officers and men! Our blue line is shorter now as we close our ranks. The flag of the golden harp is saved, but bathed in the blood of its heroic defenders. O God! the green is red now, as it will be again and again before dear old Ireland gets her place once more among the nations of the earth."The man that could give expression to such just sentiments, and that in a community where the
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 237" />subject of his oration created but little interest, must be a man of no ordinary ability and moral courage. General Butler, though of Irish origin himself, of which he is proud, yet living in a State where the old Anglo-Saxon prejudices against the Irish still lingers in a condition of vicious impotency, it would be no wonder, if like others of his race, he kept himself so far aloof from his kindred people as to escape the censure of his constituents and neighbors. But no; he has ever advocated boldly the cause of Ireland and the Irish race, and never shrinks from an opportunity to advocate their rights. He has been the subject of repeated censure and ridicule, during and since the late war. There can be but little doubt, however, that his advocacy of all measures tending to the amelioration of Irish interests, is the principal source of the assaults so persistently and undeservedly made on him by men who could never come up to him in genius, or rival him in statesmanship. He is deservedly popular, however, with the Irish-Americans, and that he is worthy of their admiration is proved by the extract given above.</p>
        <p>
          <pb n="238 The Irish Race in California." />
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XV.">
        <p>OUR MILITARY MEN CONTINUED. GEN. STEPHEN KEARNEY,GEN. PHILIP K., GEN. RILEY, GEN. CONNOR. THEIRISH-AMERICANS IN THE UNITED STATES ARMY. THESTATE NATIONAL GUARDS. THE IRISH IN OLD ANDMODERN TIMES. CULTIVATORS OF MILITARY SCIENCEAND DISCIPLINE.</p>
        <p>General Stephen Kearney was a native of Ireland, born in 1794, and entered the United States army in 1812. He soon became distinguished for his bravery in battle, and rose through the various grades of lieutenant, captain, colonel, until he became major-general in 1846, during the war with Mexico.</p>
        <p>He commanded the "Army of the West," as it was called, and made the celebrated march across the Continent, from the Missouri to the Pacific, an achievement which rivals the retreat of Zenophon, and eclipses, altogether, the march of Sherman from Tennessee to Charleston during the late Rebellion.</p>
        <p>Though Kearney's troops were only a few in number--1,600 men--in comparison with the legions of Sherman, and but scantily provided, he
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 239" />conquered New Mexico, and established a Civil Government, favorable to the United States, in Santa Fe. He fought the battle of San Pascual, with a small force of about 150 men, which was all he retained with him upon hearing that the conquest of California was completed. The principal part of his force he ordered back to New Mexico, to support the Civil Government established by him in Santa Fe.</p>
        <p>At San Pascual, therefore, he was in imminent danger of being cut to pieces with his small force, and received two severe wounds in action, in which he lost eighteen of his men. Comprehending his perilous situation, he retreated and took up his position on an eminence resembling a fort, and in the night time he dispatched a messenger to report his danger at the next American camp, at San Diego. Commodore Stockton dispatched one Lieut. Gray with 200 men to assist Kearney, but before their arrival, the wily old soldier managed to elude the forces of the enemy, and escaped without any greater loss than two field pieces, which he was obliged to abandon, but afterward recovered from the enemy.</p>
        <p>He also commanded the United States forces made up of marines and sailors from ship Congress, with a small force of cavalry, at San Gabriel,
        <pb n="240 The Irish Race in California." />where he subdued, the 29th of Jan., 1846, a force of 1,500 Mexicans, by his mixed army of about 500 men, though the enemy were strongly fortified on heights difficult of access.</p>
        <p>'Tis true that Commodore Stockton claimed that he was Commander-in-Chief, but Kearney, though with a self-denial uncommon among military men, while he acquiesced in Stockton's pretentions, did most of the fighting, and claimed his right to command ere the action began at San Gabriel.</p>
        <p>A Lieut. Rowan, another brave Irishman, commanded under Kearney. The battle was fought and won, and the enemy's forces completely scattered, two days afterward, on the plains of Mesa.</p>
        <p>Commodore Stockton soon after retired from the country, having been superceded or replaced by Commodore Shubrick; but before his departure, he appointed Fremont, Governor. Gen. Kearney protested againt [sic] this appointment, for he had instructions from Washington to conquer California, and set up a Civil Government therein, as he had done in New Mexico. Hence, he courtmartialed Fremont, and suspended him from time service--a proof that he understood the character of the Pathfinder. Gen. Kearney then became the first military Governor of California, which office he judiciously exercised for about four months, after which he re-
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 241" />turned to St. Louis, where he died calmly in 1848. Gen. Stephen Kearney, besides being a soldier of true valor, was endowed with no common civil administrative powers of mind. He published a work on the "Maneuvering of Dragoons," and a book of "Laws for the Government of New Mexico." It was in honor of him that our greatest thoroughfare, Kearny Street, was called.</p>
        <p>General Philip Kearney was a nephew of Stephen's. He was a graduate of West Point and of the Cavalry Military Academy of Saumeur, in France. He was in the Mexican war, where he displayed prodigious valor, and had many hairbreadth escapes from capture and death. It was in the Mexican war that he lost his arm, while leading a charge against a large force of Mexican cavalry. He was called the one-handed devil by the Mexicans, when he rode furiously against their ranks, with the reins in his mouth.</p>
        <p>After the restoration of his health and the end of the Mexican campaign he set out for France, and joined the French army in Algeria, as a captain of cavalry; and on the breaking out of the war between Austria and France and Italy he volunteered to fight against the former power. He fought at Solferino and Magenta.</p>
        <p>After the peace between Austria, Italy and
        <pb n="242 The Irish Race in California." />France, he traveled extensively on the Continent. But when the country was threatened with division and rebellion, he made no delay, but came home at the breaking out of the Rebellion, and distinguished himself, as he did in Mexico, at Manasses [sic], Fair Oaks, Yorktown, and other battlefields, at the head of a brigade raised at his own expense.</p>
        <p>He was finally killed at Chantilly, in Virginia, while leading a charge against the Confederates. There was no man in the army who could manage a horse with greater skill, though he had but one arm, in which he carried his naked sword, with the bridle in his mouth. Such were the men of our race, without stain or reproach, whose bravery and genius helped to create and mould our state into form. California and the United States, as well as Erin, must have a deep interest in handing down their memories to the latest generations for imitation for all who would aspire to military fame.</p>
        <p>General Riley succeeded Kearney as Governor of California. It was during his administration that the constitution of the state was formed, on the 13th of October, 1849, in the town of Monterey. It was he, the "Hero of Contreras," where he defeated the forces of Santa Anna, on August
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 243" />10th, 1847, who issued the proclamation, on June 3d, 1849, ordering an election of delegates to be held to frame a state constitution, afterwards to be submitted to the votes of the people for approval. Of the fifty delegates chosen about one-third were of our race, without including the General, who laid down his sceptre of authority as soon as the civil Governor, C. H. Burnett, was inaugurated, and finally took his farewell of the country and the coast in 1851, after a public reception and a gold medal presented to him by the people of Monterey.</p>
        <p>General Riley lived up to his income, and his hospitality kept him poor. The military men of his day, though well versed in the art of war, did not seem, like the modern heroes of the army, to know much about making money or getting rich. Hence, they were all poor, especially those of the Irish race--Jacksons, Kearneys, Rileys, Sheilds and others. And this unselfishness characterizes the bravery of the Irish soldier in humble as well as in higher rank. It has been remarked by General McClelland and others that, in the late war of the Rebellion, the Irish-American soldiers never plundered or took a dollar's worth of property from the people or country over which their valor triumphed.</p>
        <p>General Butler and all who commanded Irish
        <pb n="244 The Irish Race in California." />regiments declare that the Irish soldiers never "break" in retreating. No matter how few they are, they retire in order and together. It is no less honorable to say of them that they never plunder the conquered, as experience has proved in many hundreds of instances. This could not be said of the soldiers of any other nationality during the late Rebellion.</p>
        <p>GENERAL SHERMAN is of the Irish race, though of the second generation back. The Shermans were certainly numerous in the north of Ireland, and though probably of Norman descent, yet have been long enough in Ireland to make good their claim to be of Irish race. The General came here in 1853, after having resigned his position in the army. Be was a broker in San Francisco for some time after his arrival here. We next find him in Kansas, practising law. From that profession he passed again to the School of Military Science, and was president of the Military Academy of Louisiana. In 1861 he returned to the army, and now occupies the highest rank in the service.</p>
        <p>It is a singular fact that the two most successful generals which time late war developed--Grant and Sherman--resigned their positions in the service in disgust and rose into distinction and fame through the accident of the Rebellion. Grant
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 245" />might have continued a leather-currier and Sherman a schoolmaster to the end of their lives but for the secession debates of the Southern slave-holders. So much are some of the greatest men dependent on circumstances for their celebrity and fame!</p>
        <p>GEN. P. E. CONNER is also an Irishman. It was he who commanded the forces sent out in 1862 by the United States, to keep the Mormons in order when the the [sic] imposter, Brigham Young, threatened to make war on the "Gentiles," after having induced the various Indian tribes of the northwest to co-operate in conspiracy to drive them away from the limits of the Territory. Gen. Conner, after a severe march, retarded by early snows, pushed his columns over the desert, and never halted till he reached Salt Lake City, where ten thousand Mormons in arms were ready to give him battle. No way intimidated, however, the General sent his order to the Mormon Prophet, with the alternate to surrender or disperse his men, or to submit to the laws of the United States.</p>
        <p>The old sinner, finding that the Irish-American was not to be humbugged, bribed, or cajoled, gave in, and from that day to this the barbarous institution of polygamy retrogrades and de-
        <pb n="246 The Irish Race in California." />clines. Gen. Conner was backed by an army principally made up of his own countrymen, so that the glory belongs to them as the sons of Erin and Saint Patrick, of striking the first blow, and the most stunning, on this monstrous barbarism of Anglo-Saxon origin, which grew up in the midst of our luxuriant civilization, and of planting in its midst the seeds of the pure old Celtico-Roman morality.</p>
        <p>Gen. P. E. Conner has retired from the army since his bloodless victory over the Mormons, and practices the profession of law, we understand, in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>MAJOR COLLINS is a soldier of high character and tried bravery, and has chief command at Fort Boise, in Idaho. The Major has been a long time in the army, and was promoted from the ranks. He entered the army at an early day, and, having chosen it as a profession, has persevered and advanced himself to his present important position.</p>
        <p>LIEUT. RILEY, son of the second military Governor of California, "the hero of Contreras," is stationed at Fort Boise, also, and is a gentleman of high honor and dignified bearing.</p>
        <p>In looking over the army register for several years past, though a respectable minority of the officers of all ranks, from general to second lieuten-
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 247" />ant, are of our race, and are graduates of military academies, yet where it is stated that they were promoted from "the army" or the ranks, the vast majority are Irish.</p>
        <p>Out of one hundred and sixty who were promoted from the ranks, on looking over the register for one year, one hundred and twenty of them are Irish. And the same proportion holds good through the registers for the several years which we examined.</p>
        <p>We could here give along list of Irish officers who served on this coast, from the highest grade, from Gen. Phil Sheridan, down to the lowest grade of commissioned officers, such as Colonels Scully, Martin, Burns; Majors Tully, Hawkins, Sullivan, McGuire, Eagan, Gerin, Moylan, Doherty, Madden, Callinan, Hamilton, Nolan, Geary, O'Connell, and hundreds of others, distinguished for bravery, and belonging to the infantry.</p>
        <p>In the cavalry are Colonels Blake, Grier, Oaks, Greg, Graham, Devin, Duncan. Majors Morris, Lane, Telford, Brisbin, and a host of others, a barren list of whose names would not be interesting.</p>
        <p>Even in West Point Military Academy, the Irish race is well and favorably represented. Besides Gen. Smith, the hero of Fort Donaldson, who for twenty years occupied a leading position there, we
        <pb n="248 The Irish Race in California." />find at present Dennis Mahon, professor of civil and military engineering; John C. Molloy, assistant; James O'Hara and Major Dennison, teachers of theoretical and practical artillery; Carr and Griffiths, professors of mathematics, and McParlin, surgeon to the institution. So that in all branches of the service, men of the Irish race are distinguished, from the common soldier to the highest grade of scientific military science.</p>
        <p>Ed. J. Reynolds, now of this city, served five years in the United States cavalry, Third Regiment, under command of Captain Monahan, in New Mexico, Texas, Arizona and California. Mr. Reynolds is in business here and a leading officer in the Father Mathew Temperance Society.</p>
        <p>In this work we cannot give the exact numbers of the Irish-American element in the army of the United States, but it is estimated that at least one-third, if not one-half of the active force of the army are Irish-Americans--that is, of Irish birth or descent.</p>
        <p>THE STATE MILITIA of California, comprising the National Guard of California, three regiments of infantry, and several battalions of cavalry, shows that our race is also well represented. Out of twenty-one companies of infantry, ten of them, or
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 249" />about one-half, are Irish-Americans. The same is the case with the cavalry companies of this city.</p>
        <p>The Commander-in-Chief of the National Guard is his Excellency Governor Irwin, a gentleman universally esteemed by even his political opponents, and whose name will go down to posterity as one of the best men who ever occupied the highest office in the gift of the people.</p>
        <p>Brigadier General P. F. Walsh is Adjutant and Commissary-General and Chief of Staff under the Governor; Colonel Scott, Chief Engineer; Colonel Barney, Paymaster; Bernard D. Murphy, Judge-Advocate-General; Colonel Shorb, Surgeon; Lieutenant-Colonels Livermore, Travers, Smith, Newman, Budd, Logan, Aiken, Assistant Aids-de-Camp.</p>
        <p>On General Vernon's staff are Colonels Black, Division Inspector; John I. Tobin, Paymaster; Charles M. Gilmore, Judge Advocate, and J. Skelly and W. J. Chamberlain, Aids.</p>
        <p>Under General McComb are Major Smith, Dr. A. A. O'Neil, Surgeon; Major McLennen, Engineer, and Major Byrne.</p>
        <p>In First Regiment of Infantry, commanded by Colonel Grannis, are Rev. John Hemphill, Chaplain; Captains Thomas O'Keefe, Hughes, Henry Burns, Joseph Butler and others.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="250 The Irish Race in California." />In Union Guard are B. P. Quinlan, M. J. McDermott, Lieutenants.</p>
        <p>The Third Regiment is commanded by Colonel Wason, Bateman, Lieutenant-Colonel; J. J. Conlin, Major; John T. McGeogehan, Paymaster; J. C. McGuire, Commissary; Thomas Green, Surgeon; Rev. Thomas Larkin, Chaplain ; Cornelius Donahoe and Joseph Wallace, Lieutenants.</p>
        <p>Montgomery Guard--Captain, Charles Quin; John McCully and Jas. Pryor, Lieutenants.</p>
        <p>Shields Guard--M. J. Wren, Captain; Joseph Monaghan and P. McAleer, Lieutenants.</p>
        <p>Meagher Guard--Captain, D. J. Sullivan; T. Sullivan and Ed. Supple, Lieutenants.</p>
        <p>Emmet Guard--Robert Cleary, Captain; F. J. O'Keeffe and William Mannix, Lieutenants.</p>
        <p>McMahon Guard--John H. McMenomy, Captain; Edward F. Gleeson and J. H. Gilmore, Lieutenants.</p>
        <p>First Battalion of Cavalry--Major P. R. O'Brien, commanding; Lieutenants, William Corcoran, A. G. Fitzpatrick, J. W. Collins; Alexander Steward, Surgeon; Thomas McGinnis, Quartermaster.</p>
        <p>Jackson Dragoons--Captain Greany; Edward McPhillips, J. Kennelly, and P. F. McGrath, Lieutenants.</p>
        <p>Sarsfield Guard--Charles C. O'Donnell, Captain;
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 251" />J. C. Brown and Jas. J. Doyle, Lieutenants; Wm. Dolan, First Sergeant.</p>
        <p>Independent McMahon Guard--Thomas Bryan, Captain; John E. Green and J. J. Hughes, Lieutenants.</p>
        <p>Besides these companies--almost exclusively Irish-Americans--there are among the companies not here enumerated, a respectable minority of the officers and rank and file, who are of Irish birth or descent. From these brief memoirs it is evident that our countrymen, after their sacrifices and labors in other departments of life in this extreme but favorable region of the earth, have not neglected that noble profession of military science, which has been their distinguishing trait in all the nations of the earth in which their lot has been cast, from the earliest ages to the present time. In the words of Donatus, they are to-day as they were 3,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>"A race of men renowned in war, peace and faith."
        <pb n="252 The Irish Race in California." /></p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="CHAPTER XVI.">
        <p>SAN FRANCISCO. ITS GROWTH. ITS SITUATION AS A COM-MERCIAL CENTRE. ITS POPULATION, WEALTH, AND EN-TERPRISING INHABITANTS. ITS FUTURE PROSPECTS, ETC.</p>
        <p>CITY GOVERNMENT, INSTITUTIONS, ETC., ETC.</p>
        <p>San Francisco is one of the most remarkable cities on the globe. Thirty years ago, it was unknown on the map of the earth, and but a village of a few rude cabins, with little more than three hundred inhabitants, occupied a patch within a space which now contains 27,000 houses, inhabited by 300,000 people!</p>
        <p>We are told that poets have uttered imaginary descriptions which were afterwards found to be verified by discoveries, and Dante and Shakespeare are given as instances of such vaticinations. But no poet that ever lived could or did imagine anything like the wonders of "Yerba Buena," of 1847, developing into San Francisco of 1877. Even the prince of poets, Virgil, expressed astonishment at the growth of Carthage, but it took three centuries for the city of Dido to grow into an equal size with our city in thirty years! Chicago is
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 253" />the only city in modern times that approaches to anything like a comparison with San Francisco in the rapidity of her growth. But the forther never came up to the latter in increase of population or of wealth in a period of twenty years.</p>
        <p>Chicago is the great market of lumber and grain in the United States, but San Francisco, besides her grain which she exports to Europe, China, Australia and South America, sends her fruits and wines to the East, and the inexhaustible products of her gold and silver mines all over the world! New York, Boston, and the Atlantic cities control the commerce of Western Europe, and of the Southern Atlantic maritime States; but San Francisco makes tributary to her commerce, not only all of the United States West of the Missouri, but Mexico, Australia, South America, and the vast empires of China and Japan.</p>
        <p>Born in poverty, and covered with the swathing clothes of aboriginal indigence, like the monkish habit of the saint whose name she adopted, San Francisco has lifted her head so high above her sand-hills, as to astonish the world, and rival the oldest cities of the Continent, in her wealth, enterprise, and splendor. Her origin was nothing; her growth magical, her end, who can foretell? She may exceed Babylon, Rome, or London in popula-
        <pb n="254 The Irish Race in California." />tion, or any of the cities of the Middle Ages, in arts, and tastes, and luxury. Her splendid progress has not been the result of ages or years, but almost the spontaneous effect of her wonderful advantages from situation, climate, and the resources which surround her on every side.</p>
        <p>Her site was chosen and she received her name from men who profess to know nothing about the world, but to despise it. And in the absence of all human wisdom or sagacity we may fairly conclude that the name was providentially bestowed by the disciples of the poorest of men, who renounced even his paternal inheritance in order that he may be able more cordially to pray to his "Father in Heaven."*
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 255" />San Francisco holds the same relation to the State of California that Paris does to France. It forms the head and heart of, and is the miniature of, the commonwealth. The Romans had an expression which showed the importance of their city--" urbis et orbis "--implying that the world was ruled from Rome. The same may be said of San Francisco in regard to the State of California. The city rules the state; and though topographically its site is not pleasant, the uneven surface of the country being a succession of hills and valleys, swamps and sandy plains; yet geographically the site of San Francisco is unequalled in any part of the globe. The peninsula on the north end of which the city is built is about thirty miles long
        <pb n="256 The Irish Race in California." />by fifteen wide, and if the growth of the city continues at the same rate as since its incorporation, in 1850, in seventy-five years the city will embrace the entire peninsula.</p>
        <p>The assessed value of the real and personal property of the citizens of San Francisco is over three hundred millions of dollars. But no correct idea of the wealth of the city can be formed from the published reports of assessors, who can be influenced by various considerations to diminish or increase their estimates of the value of property.</p>
        <p>A man must visit this city and make his own calculations to obtain an idea of its wealth. A stranger coming to San Francisco will see more specie, money and bullion in a day than he could
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 257" />imagine to exist in the world. Not only are men in scores every day seen groaning under sacks of money carried as coal is carried in other countries, but he will see large four-horsed drays loaded with gold and silver bricks, moving along the streets without a guard or one to watch the treasure save the driver who guides the vehicle. This could not happen in any city of Europe, without a platoon of soldiers to intimidate robbers, and even in some Eastern cities, there would be some danger that some of the smaller bricks would be purloined. This speaks well for the honesty and honor of the majority of the people of San Francisco, notwithstanding their cosmopolitan character.</p>
        <p>Rome prided herself on her seven hills, which were all embraced within her walls. All those hills are now denuded of their grand architectural structures, except two, and those hills, the highest of them could not compare in altitude with any of the hills of San Francisco, which certainly are threefold more numerous than those of Rome, and ,which might, without impropriety, be called "the city of the many hills."Rincon Hill is as high, if not higher, than any of the hills of the Eternal City, while it would take three or four of such hills as the Quirinal, Viminal or Capitoline, heaped on top of one ano-
        <pb n="258 The Irish Race in California." />ther, to make such a hill as Telegraph, Russian or Nob hills.</p>
        <p>Situated as she is, with her back to the ocean and an inland sea at her feet, large enough to give room to all the navies of the world to shelter in, San Francisco seems certainly destined to become the mistress of the oceans. The salubrity of her atmosphere is wonderful, and she can accommodate the natives of all parts of the globe, by sending them a few hours' journey into the country, with the same climate they were used to at home, from ten degrees below zero to a temperature of one hundred degrees in the shade; and though the city is almost surrounded by water, which ensures her destined supremacy in commerce, the only fear she apprehends in the remote future, however, is a scarcity of water to drink! Such is San Francisco, a city built by the people, and not founded by kings or despotic rulers, and which rivals in her palaces of private citizens, in her broad streets and elegant stores, and splendid banks and depositories of treasure many of the oldest cities of the earth. She contains more inhabitants to-day, after only twenty-seven years of her existence, and ten times more wealth in money than Rome, a city of twenty-seven centuries existence. If we judge the future from the past, then
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 259" />what will San Francisco be in two hundred years from now? It may be thought extravagant to say that the Sierras and the ocean will form the eastern and western boundaries of this city of St. Francis.</p>
        <p>San Francisco has many public buildings, such as the Post Office, Custom House, Mint, and Sub-Treasury. But, except the Mint, where the money is coined, and the New City Hall and Custom House, they are not worthy of notice in these pages.</p>
        <p>There are some elegant bank buildings, such as the Nevada, and the Stock Exchange, on Pine St., California Bank Building on Sansome Street. But most of the banking business is carried on in plain buildings, such as the Hibernia, Donahoe &amp; Kelly's banking houses.</p>
        <p>The number of banks in the city is twenty-nine, with a capital of $34,000,000. In those banks are deposited 100,000,000 in specie! And the banking capital of the city is estimated--including savings, private institutions--at 150,000,000.</p>
        <p>The number of depositors in the Savings is about 71,000, averaging for each depositor $840; and dividing the entire sum of money in the banks among all the population, would give each individual in the city a sum of $500.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="260 The Irish Race in California." />At the head of all the banking institutions of the city and State, stands the Nevada Bank, which has a capital of $10,000,000, and has correspondents in all parts of the world. This bank belonging to Flood, O'Brien &amp; Co., is an evidence of the financial ability of the Irish race, which, in this difficult department of industry, has given birth to men of incorruptible integrity, and of the most sterling ability.</p>
        <p>The Hibernia Bank--among the savings institutions in the city--is classed deservedly as the first of its kind in the State, or even in the United States. This bank is conducted by men, plain and simple in their manners, but whom all the people regard as honest men, in whose guardianship the millions committed to their charge are as safe as it is possible for hnman [human] [sic] prudence to secure them. It is creditable to the managers of this institution to hear men say to those who were plundered by the fraudulent concerns--so many of which have lately burst--" oh, why did you not deposit your money in the Hibernia Bank? that's the only safe institution?"Our countrymen have been distinguished at home and abroad by many virtues and accomplishments in military, and civil, and domestic life. There is one thing in which they have made but
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 261" />poor progress, namely, the art of acquiring riches by fraud. Mooney, who left his creditors ninety cents on the dollar when he absconded, was only a bungler, when compared with the "smart" Duncan, who robbed his creditors of every cent of their deposits, and though he was a habitual perjurer and a forger, yet he managed to have himself regarded as a "pious Christian" during twenty years of his fraudulent existence.</p>
        <p>The bank of Donohoe, Kelly &amp; Co., a solid institution of many years standing, is controlled by men of our race.</p>
        <p>There are other smaller institutions, such as the Dime Savings Bank, under direction of W. McMahon O'Brien, Esq., which deserves notice, as having stood under a severe run in October, '77, after the failure of the Pioneer and other fraudulent concerns, too numerous to mention.</p>
        <p>San Francisco has twenty-two public parks, varying in size from a few hundred feet square to the great Ocean Park of one thousand and eighty acres. In the course of time this great park will be a delightful place for recreation. At present, however, it is too remote from the populous part of the city to be reached by any except those who can hire or drive their own vehicles to enjoy its scenery. The other smaller parks are not at all,
        <pb n="262 The Irish Race in California." />it seems, intended for the recreation of the people, for there are but few of them provided with benches to rest on or water to drink, and none of them with water-closets. It is strange that those who like to be dubbed "City Fathers" should neglect to provide for these and other necessary conveniences of those who visit the parks purchased by the people's money!</p>
        <p>The public schools of San Francisco are fifty-six in number, and are frequented by about thirty-four thousand pupils. Of these eighteen thousand are boys and sixteen thousand girls. The schools of San Francisco appear to be well conducted, and children are treated with perfect equality, no distinction being made for or against those of the different religious sects.</p>
        <p>Besides the public schools there are many flourishing schools connected with the churches and convents, in which many thousand children are taught, at least ten thousand, and also Episcopalian, Jewish, Lutheran, Methodist and Presbyterian, with private schools, all of which will aggregate nearly as many as the public schools, which cost the city about one million dollars annually, and the entire state $2,749,129.49--not far from three millions.</p>
        <p>There are several hospitals in the city, such as
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 263" />the German, French, Jewish, Episcopalian, Italian, the County Hospital and St. Mary's, conducted by the Sisters of Mercy. All these hospitals are conducted well; but it seems that most of them, except the County Hospital, are beyond the reach of the poor.</p>
        <p>In most of the denominational and national hospitals, like the French, twenty dollars a week is charged for the accommodation in a separate room. What chance has a poor laborer of getting into such hospitals? Could not an institution be made to pay expenses at twenty dollars a month, instead of eighty dollars, as is the case in all the eastern cities?</p>
        <p>It is to her Mining Stock Boards that San Francisco owes her commercial life and attracts the capital of the state and of the coast to her coffers. There are four of these boards, which, like the four chambers of the heart in the human body, propel the yellow stream of circulation through all her countless channels of trade. The miner, from his subterranean abyss, the sailor, from the ocean, the farmer, from his parched ranch, the laborer, from his pickax, the operative and mechanic, from their workshops--all come to this city in hopes, through the Stock Boards, to increase their wealth or savings.</p>
        <p>
        <pb n="264 The Irish Race in California." />Hence, over $500,000,000 of money annually passes through the four stock boards for investment. What matter to those noisy worshippers of Mammon, if most of the money invested is lost to the simple people who risk it in stocks? The city's trade is stimulated, the money is put into circulation, while those who were duped have either to bear their losses patiently or to commit suicide. In this business, even men of the Irish race have displayed the usual energy. Many of the brokers like E. Cahill &amp;. Co., men of standing and character, are Irish, as, are about 100 of the 450 mining stock brokers of the city.</p>
        <p>The City Municipal Government has a large number of its officials of the Irish race.</p>
        <p>The Board of Supervisors, consisting of twelve members, has eight members of them Irish-Americans, viz.: John Foley, Mangles, Roundtree, Smith, Farran, Hayes, Bryan and Shine.**There are no Aldermen in the City Government of San Francisco since '58, when a law was passed substituting Supervisors for Aldermen. This was done with a view to economy where all officers are paid high salaries, judges of Probate and County Courts getting $6,000 per annum, and District Judges $5,000 each. The whole amount paid in
        <pb n="The Irish Race in California. 265" />The Board of Education has two out of its four secretaries, namely: Charles A. Clinton, Esq., and James Duffv, Irishmen.</p>
        <p>In the Judiciary, we have McKee, Blake, Ferrall, Burnett, and Daniel J. Murphy, while the clerks of the Municipal Courts, including Thomas J. Reynolds, are mostly all Irish, such as Carroll, Quirk, Whalen, McCaulley, Barry, Loughlin, O'Neil, McGrath, Tracy, Farran, Devany, Harney, Stevenson, etc.</p>
        <p>The Sheriff Matthew Nunan, Esq., and his aids and assistants--about thirty in number-- are mostly all Irish, and the satisfactory manner in which Mr. Nunan has discharged his onerous duties has been the cause why he has been reelected by a handsome majority, notwithstanding a vigorous opposition to him from political opponents. Sheriff Nunan is a native of Limerick, of the same family with Hon. E. Nunan, State Sena-
        <pb n="266 The Irish Race in California." />tor, and a man whose sterling qualities of head and heart, could not fail to insure him popularity in any community. He gained the confidence of all parties during his first term in office, and hence occurred his re-nomination and re-election for a second term. Mr. Nunan, we believe, did not seek the office for the sake of its emoluments, for he is independent in circumstances; but when he saw that there was a principle at stake, and that he was put forward to represent that principle in opposition to a narrow-minded ring, he did not hesitate, but promptly responded to the call of his fellow-citizens, though it has involved him in great annoyance and no small expense.</p>
        <p>The Sheriff is one of those few men whom a long residence in the United States has not caused all traces of his native land to be ignored or obliterated.</p>
        <p>Though an American citizen from choice, he is as proud of his origin as if he still cultivated his father's farm at the foot of the sunny hills of Palasgrany or Caherconlish. He has several brothers, one a distinguished clergyman, who all retain the distinguishing characteristics of the family, namely, honesty, integrity, and a becoming modesty of conduct and deportment, together with sentiments of an enlightened liberality.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
